Validation of the i-STAT system for the analysis of blood gases and acid&ndash;base status in juvenile sandbar shark (<italic>Carcharhinus plumbeus</italic>)Evolution of oxygen secretion in fishes and the emergence of a complex physiological systemPhysicochemical parameters for use in fish respiratory physiologyThe linkage between oxygen and carbon dioxide transportThe interaction between O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> exchange in rainbow trout during graded sustained exerciseNon-linear release of Bohr protons with haemoglobin-oxygenation in the blood of two teleost fishes; carp (<italic>Cyprinus carpio</italic>) and tambaqui (<italic>Colossoma macropomum</italic>)Effects of anaerobic exercise accompanying catch-and-release fishing on blood-oxygen affinity of the sandbar shark (<italic>Carcharhinus plumbeus</italic>, Nardo)The stress physiology of extended duration tonic immobility in the juvenile lemon shark, <italic>Negaprion brevirostris</italic> (Poey 1868)The physiological response of the Caribbean reef shark (<italic>Carcharhinus perezi</italic>) to longline captureSeasonal variations in the physiological stress response to discrete bouts of aerial exposure in the little skate, <italic>Leucoraja erinacea</italic>Evaluation of a point-of-care blood analyzer for use in determination of select hematological indices in the seminole killifishImmediate and delayed effects of gill-net capture on acid&ndash;base balance and intramuscular lactate concentration of gummy sharks, <italic>Mustelus antarcticus</italic>Blood gas, oxygen saturation, pH, and lactate values in elasmobranch blood measured with a commercially available portable clinical analyzer and standard laboratory instrumentsEvaluation of a point-of-care blood analyzer and determination of reference ranges for blood parameters in rockfishValidation of the i-STAT system for the analysis of blood parameters in fishContribution of net ion transfer mechanisms to acid-base regulation after exhausting activity in the larger spotted dogfish (<italic>Scyliorhinus stellaris</italic>)Assessment of acid&ndash;base derangements among bonnethead (<italic>Sphyrna tiburo</italic>), bull (<italic>Carcharhinus leucas</italic>), and lemon (<italic>Negaprion brevirostris</italic>) sharks from gillnet and longline capture and handling methodsA critical evaluation of automated blood gas measurements in comparative respiratory physiologyThe estimated short-term discard mortality of a trawled elasmobranch, the spiny dogfish (<italic>Squalus acanthias</italic>)The physiological status and mortality associated with otter-trawl capture, transport, and captivity of an exploited elasmobranch, <italic>Squalus acanthias</italic>Differential sensitivity to capture stress assessed by blood acid&ndash;base status in five carcharhinid sharksEvaluation of critical care blood analytes assessed with a point-of-care portable blood analyzer in wild and aquarium-housed elasmobranchs and the influence of phlebotomy site on resultsHydrogen ion ballance in the elasmobranch <italic>Scyliorhinus stellaris</italic> after exhausting activityExercise and recovery metabolism in the pacific spiny dogfish (<italic>Squalus acanthias</italic>)The effect of temperature on the pH of blood and plasma <italic>in vitro</italic>Use of portable blood physiology point-of-care devices for basic and applied research on vertebrates: a reviewMethod for oxygen content and dissociation curves on microliter blood samplesPresent address: Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS), 1309 Greate Road, Gloucester Point, VA 23062, USA.<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We validated the i-STAT system for the analysis of blood parameters in sandbar shark. Results indicate that it is a useful tool for measuring blood pH and could be suitable for operation in most field settings. However, it is not recommended for the assessment of gas tensions in shark blood.Accurate measurements of blood gases and acid&ndash;base status require an array of sophisticated laboratory equipment that is typically not available during field research; such is the case for many studies on the stress physiology, ecology and conservation of elasmobranch fish species. Consequently, researchers have adopted portable clinical analysers that were developed for the analysis of human blood characteristics, but often without thoroughly validating these systems for their use on fish. The aim of our study was to test the suitability of the i-STAT system, the most commonly used portable clinical analyser in studies on fish, for analysing blood gases and acid&ndash;base status in elasmobranchs, over a broad range of conditions and using the sandbar shark (<italic>Carcharhinus plumbeus</italic>) as a model organism. Our results indicate that the i-STAT system can generate useful measurements of whole blood pH, and the use of appropriate correction factors may increase the accuracy of results. The i-STAT system was, however, unable to generate reliable results for measurements of partial pressure of oxygen (<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>) and the derived parameter of haemoglobin O<sub>2</sub> saturation. This is probably due to the effect of a closed-system temperature change on <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> within the i-STAT cartridge and the fact that the temperature correction algorithms used by i-STAT assume a human temperature dependency of haemoglobin&ndash;O<sub>2</sub> binding; in many ectotherms, this assumption will lead to equivocal i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> results. The <italic>in vivo</italic> partial pressure of CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>) in resting sandbar sharks is probably below the detection limit for <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> in the i-STAT system, and the measurement of higher <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tensions was associated with a large measurement error. In agreement with previous work, our results indicate that the i-STAT system can generate useful data on whole blood pH in fishes, but not blood gases.The i-STAT system<sup>&reg;</sup> (Abbot Point of Care Inc., Princeton, NJ, USA), a portable clinical analyser, is gaining acceptance as a means of blood analysis in biological studies on a variety of fish species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C28">Stoot <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). This is despite the fact that the i-STAT system was originally developed for the analysis of human blood, hence: (i) samples in the test cartridges are heated to 37&deg;C upon analysis; (ii) results are calculated based on algorithms derived for human blood characteristics (this includes temperature corrections); and (iii) the detection limits of the sensors within the cartridge are optimized for parameter ranges expected in air-breathing mammals. These potential sources of measurement bias require a thorough validation of the i-STAT system when used to analyse blood samples obtained from fishes, taking into account species and sampling conditions. While few studies have validated the i-STAT system for several fish species (seminole killifish, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C10">DiMaggio <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; sandbar shark and dusky smooth-hound, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C12">Gallagher <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; black and blue rockfish, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C13">Harrenstien <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>), only one validation study on rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) has assessed possible interaction effects from a broad range of conditions, by experimentally varying temperature, haematocrit and partial pressure of CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C14">Harter <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Results on rainbow trout indicated that the i-STAT was not appropriate for measuring blood parameters other than blood pH. Consequently, we see no justification for the use of the i-STAT system with rainbow trout in situations where more established analytical techniques are accessible. However, many studies on elasmobranch ecology, physiology and conservation rely on field measurement of blood parameters (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C21">Mandelman and Farrington, 2007a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C22">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C23">Mandelman and Skomal, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C7">Brooks <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C8">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C9">Cicia <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C11">Frick <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C16">Hyatt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), a situation where the i-STAT system may be the only available methodology. Nevertheless, the simple availability of a method cannot justify its implementation; the choice of a suitable method should depend on the quality of the produced data, in terms of precision and accuracy, and on the tolerance of the specific research question to variation in these quality criteria.Therefore, our aim was to validate the use of the i-STAT system for the analysis of blood gases and acid&ndash;base status in elasmobranchs over a range of temperatures, partial pressures of oxygen (<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>) and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>, using blood from sandbar shark (<italic>Carcharhinus plumbeus</italic>). In addition, we investigated the effects of heating blood samples in a closed system to 37&deg;C, to simulate the temperature changes that occur within i-STAT cartridges during measurements. Our goal was to provide guidelines for an appropriate implementation of the i-STAT system in future studies on elasmobranchs and, based on the results, allow researchers to make an informed decision on whether the i-STAT system is the right tool to answer their specific research questions.This study was carried out as part of a larger project on the effect of temperature on blood&ndash;O<sub>2</sub> binding characteristics in juvenile sandbar shark (P. R. Morrison, T. S. Harter, R. W. Brill and C. J. Brauner, unpublished data). During tonometry, subsamples of blood were also analysed with the i-STAT system, which allowed a direct comparison of the i-STAT system with measurements performed using conventional and proven laboratory techniques.Animal housing and all procedures were approved by the College of William and Mary Animal Care and Use Committee (protocol number: IACUC-2014-04-18-9548-rwbril). Sandbar sharks, <italic>Carcharhinus plumbeus</italic> Nardo 1827 (1.4&ndash;8.1&emsp14;kg), were caught using hook-and-line fishing gear in the tidal lagoon system surrounding the Virginia Institute of Marine Science Eastern Shore Laboratory in Wachapreague, VA, USA. All animals were held for several weeks in a shore-side circular tank (&sim;8&emsp14;m in diameter and 2&emsp14;m deep), supplied with flow-through sea water from the adjacent lagoon (25.7&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;1.2&deg;C, mean&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SD). Animals were held at a natural photoperiod (June&ndash;August), and the tank was shaded with black mesh for protection from direct sunlight. Fish were fed thrice a week with cut pieces of Atlantic menhaden (<italic>Brevoortia tyrannus</italic>), and feeding was suspended 24&emsp14;h before blood collection.After netting a shark out of the holding tank, a blood sample (10&ndash;20&emsp14;ml) was immediately collected into a heparinized syringe (sodium heparin; Sigma 84020) by caudal puncture and placed on ice. Blood samples were subsequently stored at 4&deg;C for several hours to avoid any confounding effects of possible red blood cell swelling immediately after sampling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C6">Brill <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Thereafter, 3&emsp14;ml aliquots of blood were loaded into six Eschweiler tonometers (5&emsp14;ml total volume), placed in a thermostated water bath and equilibrated with a water-saturated gas mixture (air, CO<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>). Gases were mixed daily, using mass flow controllers (MKS Instruments, Andover, MA, USA) and stored in automobile inner tubes. During mixing of gases, <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tensions were monitored using an infrared Capnometer HP 47210A (Hewlett-Packard, B&ouml;blingen, Germany). All tonometers were flushed with the respective gas mixture for 1&emsp14;h before loading the blood and allowed to equilibrate for another 1&emsp14;h before analysis.In order to validate the i-STAT system, temperature, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> were varied with three levels per factor: temperature 15, 20 or 25&deg;C; <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> 0.2 (&sim;1.52&emsp14;mmHg), 0.6 (&sim;4.56&emsp14;mmHg) or 1.5&percnt; (&sim;11.4&emsp14;mmHg); and <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> 10, 40 or 150&emsp14;mmHg (balance N<sub>2</sub>). Six replicate samples (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;6) were run for each combination of factors, and the experimental unit was a single tonometer containing blood from a single individual. A total of 171 samples were analysed, using blood from 14 donor fish.After equilibration, the six tonometers were sampled sequentially using heparinized, gas-tight Hamilton syringes. A 90&emsp14;&mu;l subsample was immediately loaded into an i-STAT cartridge; measurements were performed using the VetScan i-STAT 1 System (SN:704583-C; software version JAMS 137a/CLEW A28; Abaxis, Union City, CA, USA) with the i-STAT CG4&plus; cartridge test. Cartridges were stored in their original packaging at 4&deg;C in the dark and allowed to equilibrate to room temperature over night prior to experiments. All measurements were done within an air-conditioned laboratory and using the temperature correction function of the i-STAT system to account for differences between i-STAT measurements (37&deg;C) and treatment temperatures.Control measurements of blood parameters were carried out using established laboratory techniques. Haemoglobin (Hb) concentration was measured in triplicate with a Shimadzu UV-1800 spectrophotometer (Kyoto, Japan) using the cyanomethaemoglobin method. Hb concentrations were calculated based on absorption measurements at 540&emsp14;nm and using an extinction coefficient of 11. Whole blood pH and <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements were performed using two Radiometer BMS 3 Mk2 systems and Radiometer acid&ndash;base analysers PHM73 (Copenhagen, Denmark). One unit was thermostated at the respective treatment temperature (15, 20 or 25&deg;C) and the other at 37&deg;C, to simulate the closed-system temperature change that occurs to blood samples analysed within an i-STAT cartridge. Whole blood total O<sub>2</sub> content (TO<sub>2</sub>) was measured according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C29">Tucker (1967)</xref>. Hb&ndash;O<sub>2</sub> saturation (sO<sub>2</sub>) was calculated from TO<sub>2</sub> after subtracting physically dissolved O<sub>2</sub> according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C2">Boutilier <italic>et al</italic>. (1984)</xref> and dividing by the theoretical maximal carrying capacity of the rinsed red blood cells based upon the tetrameric Hb concentration obtained spectrophotometrically.All data were analysed with RStudio 0.98.1049 (RStudio Inc., Boston, MA, USA). The i-STAT values were compared with control measurements by regression analysis using the raw data. The measurement errors for the i-STAT values relative to control measurements were calculated as follows: &delta;&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;(i-STAT&emsp14;&minus;&emsp14;control)/control&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;100. The &delta; data were then compared with control measurements either by regression analysis or by fitting a non-linear model to the data. Linear, logarithmic and exponential models were compared using the Akaike information criterion (AIC), and the model with the best fit (i.e. with the lowest AIC value) was used as representative for the data. Normality of distribution was tested with the Shapiro&ndash;Wilk test (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05), and homogeneity of variances was tested with the Levene&apos;s test (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05). The effects of temperature, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta; were tested on the squared values of &delta; (i.e. all values were positive). In most cases, this transformation led to a significant deviation of the distribution from normality, which could not be remediated by data transformation. Therefore, the effects of temperature, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta; were tested with the Kruskal&ndash;Wallis rank sum test (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05, <italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;171; minus missing values as indicated in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV002TB2">2</xref>) and the Wilcoxon rank sum test (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05, <italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;108; minus missing values as indicated in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV002TB2">2</xref>) for the effect of <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta;<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>. All data are presented as means&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SEM.Parameter estimates (means&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SEM), <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>P</italic>-values for the relationships between i-STAT system vs. control measurements, i-STAT measurement errors, &delta;(<italic>x</italic>) (as &percnt;) vs. control measurements (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;171) and the effect of a closed-system temperature increase on pH and <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;54)Abbreviations: <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>, partial pressure of carbon dioxide; <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>, partial pressure of oxygen; sO<sub>2</sub>, haemoglobin O<sub>2</sub> saturation.Linear relationships according to: i-STAT(<italic>x</italic>)&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;<italic>a</italic>&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;<italic>b</italic>&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;control(<italic>x</italic>); and &delta;(<italic>x</italic>)&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;<italic>a</italic>&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;<italic>b</italic>&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;control(<italic>x</italic>).Exponential relationships according to: i-STAT(<italic>x</italic>)&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;<italic>a</italic>&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;<italic>b</italic><sup>control(<italic>x</italic>)</sup>&emsp14;&minus;&emsp14;<italic>c</italic>.Closed-system:Linear relationships according to: 37&deg;C(<italic>x</italic>)&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;<italic>a</italic>&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;<italic>b</italic>&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;treatment temperature(<italic>x</italic>).Exponential relationships according to: 37&deg;C(<italic>x</italic>)&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;<italic>a</italic>&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;<italic>b</italic><sup>treatment temperature(<italic>x</italic>)</sup>&emsp14;&minus;&emsp14;<italic>c</italic>.All parameter estimates in non-linear models were statistically significant (&apos;<italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001).(<bold>A</bold>) Sandbar shark whole blood pH measured with the i-STAT system (temperature-corrected values) vs. pH measured using a thermostated electrode (control). (<bold>B</bold>) The relative error of i-STAT pH measurements, &delta;pH [expressed as &percnt;; calculated as (i-STAT pH&emsp14;&minus;&emsp14;control pH)/control pH&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;100], vs. control pH. Continuous lines represent the fitted linear models (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV002TB1">1</xref> for parameter estimates) and dashed lines represent the lines of identity. (<bold>C</bold>) Effects of temperature (in &deg;C), partial pressures of oxygen (<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>) and carbon dioxide (<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>; in mmHg) on &delta;pH. Significant effects within treatments are indicated as &lsquo;&ast;&rsquo; at the <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05 level or NS for non-significant. Data are means&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SEM, and statistical analysis was performed on the squared &delta;pH values.(<bold>A</bold>) Sandbar shark whole blood <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measured with the i-STAT system (temperature-corrected values) vs. <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measured with a thermostated electrode (control). (<bold>B</bold>) The relative error of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements, &delta;<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> vs. control <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>. (<bold>C</bold>) Effects of temperature, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta;<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>. See legend to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F1">1</xref> for further information.(<bold>A</bold>) Sandbar shark whole blood <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> measured with the i-STAT system (temperature-corrected values) vs. set <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> in the tonometers (control). Mean values are indicated by the larger, open symbols. (<bold>B</bold>) The relative error of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> measurements, &delta;<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> vs. control <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>. The dotted line is the lowest reportable <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tension by the i-STAT system at 20&deg;C. (<bold>C</bold>) Effects of temperature, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta;<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>. See legend to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F1">1</xref> for further information.(<bold>A</bold>) Sandbar shark haemoglobin O<sub>2</sub> saturation (sO<sub>2</sub>) measured with the i-STAT system vs. control sO<sub>2</sub> measured according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C29">Tucker (1967)</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) The relative error of i-STAT sO<sub>2</sub> measurements, &delta;sO<sub>2</sub> vs. control sO<sub>2</sub>. (<bold>C</bold>) Effects of temperature, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta;sO<sub>2</sub>. See legend to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F1">1</xref> for further information.(<bold>A</bold>) Effect of a closed-system temperature increase (from treatment temperature to 37&deg;C) on pH of sandbar shark whole blood, equilibrated in tonometers at 15 (filled circles), 20 (open trianges) or 25&deg;C (inverted filled triangles). Measurements were performed simultaneously with two Radiometer BMS systems, one maintained at the respective treatment temperature and the other at 37&deg;C. The continuous (15&deg;C), dashed (20&deg;C) and dotted (25&deg;C) lines represent the fitted linear models, and the best model was determined by comparing the Akaike information criteria of linear, exponential and logarithmic models. (<bold>B</bold>) &Delta;pH per degree Celsius (means&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SEM) during a closed-system temperature increase from treatment temperature to 37&deg;C. Significant effects of temperature are indicated by &lsquo;&ast;&rsquo; at the <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05 level.Effect of a closed-system temperature increase (from treatment temperature to 37&deg;C) on <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> (in mmHg) of sandbar shark whole blood, equilibrated in tonometers at 15 (filled circles), 20 (open trianges) or 25&deg;C (inverted filled triangles). See legend to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F5">5</xref> for further information.Missing values as reported by the i-STAT system grouped by treatment (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;171)Certain combinations of experimental factors were more likely to cause faulty measurements. At the lowest <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tested (1.52&emsp14;mmHg), the i-STAT system was unable to report <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> in 93&percnt; of cases. This is not surprising, because the detection limit for <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> in the i-STAT system is 5&emsp14;mmHg, as specified by the manufacturer. Interestingly, at 1.52&emsp14;mmHg <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements failed in 25&percnt; of the samples, even though <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> was always within detection limits. Also, low <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> tensions (10&emsp14;mmHg) and high temperatures (25&deg;C) seemed to increase the occurrence of failed pH measurements with the i-STAT system in sandbar shark whole blood.Our results indicate that the i-STAT system is an appropriate tool for the measurement of whole blood pH in the sandbar shark. However, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> could not be measured accurately, and we cannot recommend the use of this instrument to assess blood gas tensions and any derived parameters in sandbar sharks under the tested range of conditions.In agreement with previous work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C14">Harter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), our results indicate that i-STAT measurements of sandbar shark whole blood pH were accurate, and on average only 1.65&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.07&percnt; lower than control pH measurements with a thermostated electrode. This is in line with previous studies on fish, which found similar measurement errors for pH (&delta;pH), as follows: &minus;3.8 for sandbar shark and &minus;4.4&percnt; for dusky smooth-hound (calculated from the data presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C12">Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>); &minus;5&percnt; for black rockfish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C13">Harrenstien <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>); and 2&percnt; for rainbow trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C14">Harter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Furthermore, we detected no significant effects of temperature or <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> on i-STAT &delta;pH, indicating that measurements will remain accurate even if these conditions vary. The significant effect of <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta;pH indicates that changes in blood <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> may affect the accuracy of i-STAT pH measurements. Even so, &delta;pH was within &lt;4&percnt; of control measurements for all pH measurements performed with the i-STAT system (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;156).We observed a high individual variation among i-STAT pH measurements, typically &sim;0.2&emsp14;pH units, which is perhaps a result of single-point measurements, whereas the BMS system allows the user to make continuous readings to reduce within-sample variation. Whether i-STAT pH measurements are suitable to answer certain research questions will depend on the tolerance for variation within the specific experiment; in any case, the expected variation needs to be considered in the experimental design (e.g. by increasing the number of replicates if greater accuracy of means is required).Given that the i-STAT system was developed for the analysis of human blood, samples in i-STAT cartridges are heated to 37&deg;C; these cartridges can be considered a closed system, because exchanges of protons, proton equivalents or O<sub>2</sub> with the environment are negligible. A closed-system temperature change, however, can have marked effects on whole blood pH and <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>, a phenomenon that we examined separately in order to further assess the suitability of the i-STAT system for the measurement of these blood parameters in ectothermic fish. In line with the theoretical considerations described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C20">Malte <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> underlying a closed-system temperature change, we found a decrease in blood pH when blood was heated to 37&deg;C (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F5">5</xref>A). As expected, the magnitude of this pH change was dependent on the temperature gradient (i.e. heating blood from 15 to 37&deg;C had a larger effect on pH than heating from 25 to 37&deg;C), but in a non-linear manner for sandbar shark blood (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F5">5</xref>B). The i-STAT system uses the pH-temperature dependency for human blood (&minus;0.0147 &Delta;pH/&deg;C, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C27">Rosenthal, 1948</xref>) to correct pH values from 37&deg;C to treatment temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C19">i-STAT Technical Bulletin, 2013b</xref>). The fact that the i-STAT system underestimated control pH by &sim;0.1 pH units may be indicative that, over the tested range of pH values and temperatures, the average pH temperature dependency of sandbar shark whole blood was greater than that used for human blood. Despite this bias, the temperature correction algorithm used by the i-STAT (see parameter estimates in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV002TB1">1</xref>) yielded better results compared with the temperature correction of i-STAT raw values proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C23">Mandelman and Skomal (2009)</xref>, although differences were small (0.835&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.023&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;control pH&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;1.087 &plusmn; 0.176, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.898). Therefore, the parameter estimates provided in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV002TB1">1</xref> and our results of closed-system heating on blood pH (i.e. the non-linearity of &Delta;pH per degree Celsius over the tested temperature range) can be used to correct i-STAT pH measurements and thereby increase their accuracy. It needs to be emphasized, however, that the presented linear relationships are likely to be species specific and are limited to the range of test conditions that have been examined (for comparison see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C12">Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).In contrast to our findings on pH, <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements on sandbar shark blood with the i-STAT were unreliable. The fitted linear relationship between i-STAT and control <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F2">2</xref>A) indicates that, at least at lower <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>, the i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> values were consistent with control measurements, but at higher <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> the variability of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements increased considerably. However, the calculated measurement errors (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F2">2</xref>B) indicate that at low <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>, the accuracy of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements was also poor, varying between &plus;50 and &minus;50&percnt;. At 150&emsp14;mmHg <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>, the i-STAT system on average underestimated control <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> by &minus;28&percnt;, which is reflected in a significant effect of <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> on &delta;<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F2">2</xref>C). The high variability of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements at 150&emsp14;mmHg <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> is not only indicative of an unreliable measurement, but also prohibits the use of linear equations to correct i-STAT results, because the assumption of homoscedasticity in linear regression analysis was violated. In addition, <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> had a significant effect on the i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurement error and therefore changes in <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> will affect the accuracy of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C12">Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>, who previously validated the i-STAT for blood gases in sandbar shark with the same BMS system, found a significant linear relationship between i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and control measurements, without the large variability that we observed. Underlying this difference between the two studies is undoubtedly the broader range of test conditions that were examined here. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C12">Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> analysed sandbar shark blood at one temperature (25&deg;C), while we tested <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> at three temperatures (15, 20 and 25&deg;C), discovering no significant effect of temperature on &delta;<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> for the temperature-corrected i-STAT values (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.062; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F2">2</xref>C). There was, however, a highly significant (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001) temperature effect on the &delta;<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> of the raw i-STAT data (i.e. without temperature correction; data not shown).In agreement with the results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C20">Malte <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>, the closed-system temperature increase that occurs in an i-STAT cartridge resulted in a dramatic increase in <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> of sandbar shark whole blood, nearly doubling the initial values (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F6">6</xref>). It is these high <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> tensions that will be analysed by the i-STAT and represent the basis for subsequent temperature correction of the results. According to the equations presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C20">Malte <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>, the measurement error for <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> after temperature correction will increase linearly with increasing initial <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and exponentially with increasing temperature gradient. These predictions are entirely in line with our results and may help to explain the increasing variability of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements with increasing initial <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F2">2</xref>A). Also, measurement errors are likely to be augmented by the differences in temperature dependency of Hb&ndash;O<sub>2</sub> binding between shark and human blood (P. R. Morrison, T. S. Harter, R. W. Brill and C. J. Brauner, unpublished data). The complexity of these interactions is further aggravated by the fact that pH and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> will also change during closed-system heating, and both of these factors typically alter Hb&ndash;O<sub>2</sub> binding properties in sandbar shark blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C6">Brill <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Collectively, these considerations raise general concerns about the accuracy of blood <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements for ectothermic species using any portable clinical analyser that operates at 37&deg;C. As indicated by our results, the closed-system temperature effects on <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> can be significant and may not be easily corrected over a wide range of species and conditions. Therefore, due to the high variability of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements and a significant effect of <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta;<italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>, we do not consider the i-STAT system an appropriate tool for measuring <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> in sandbar shark whole blood, or likely other fish species.In the i-STAT system, sO<sub>2</sub> is calculated from the measured values of <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and pH (for a summary of the methods used by the i-STAT system refer to Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV002TB2">2</xref> of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C14">Harter <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Control sO<sub>2</sub> values were varied experimentally from 20 to 100&percnt; (by changing tonometer <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>), and our results indicate that, over this range, the i-STAT system overestimated sO<sub>2</sub>. In a previous validation study on trout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C14">Harter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), the i-STAT system consistently reported 100&percnt; sO<sub>2</sub> over the entire range of control sO<sub>2</sub> values. For sandbar shark blood, there was some response of i-STAT sO<sub>2</sub> to the planned contrasts in sO<sub>2</sub> (which may reflect the absence of a strong Bohr&ndash;Root effect in sharks compared with trout; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C1">Berenbrink <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). However, control sO<sub>2</sub> values above &sim;60&percnt; were reported as full Hb saturation (i.e. 100&percnt;). In normoxic resting fish, sO<sub>2</sub> values typically range from 100&percnt; in the arterial system to 50&percnt; sO<sub>2</sub> in the venous system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C3">Brauner and Randall, 1998</xref>); over this range, the i-STAT was unable to detect relative differences by largely reporting 100&percnt; sO<sub>2</sub>. Venous sO<sub>2</sub> in fish will decrease below 50&percnt; during exercise and hypoxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C3">Brauner and Randall, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C4">Brauner <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>), while arterial sO<sub>2</sub> can be lower than 50&percnt; during severe hypoxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C5">Brauner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). However, i-STAT measurements of sO<sub>2</sub> over this range were associated with a measurement error ranging from 50 to 100&percnt;. Furthermore, the highly significant effects of <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> on &delta;sO<sub>2</sub> indicate that changes in these factors will affect the accuracy of sO<sub>2</sub> measurements with the i-STAT system. Sandbar shark have an exceptionally low <italic>P</italic><sub>50</sub> (the partial pressure of O<sub>2</sub> at which Hb is 50&percnt; saturated) of &lt;5&emsp14;mmHg at 15&deg;C (P. R. Morrison, T. S. Harter, R. W. Brill and C. J. Brauner, unpublished data), which indicates that their Hb will most likely be nearly fully saturated with O<sub>2</sub> in a broad range of environmental conditions. Consequently, it seems that the i-STAT system cannot generate accurate sO<sub>2</sub> readings on sandbar shark blood, and it seems unlikely that it would be able to detect relative differences in sO<sub>2</sub> occurring under most conditions <italic>in vivo</italic>.The three <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tensions (1.52, 4.56 and 11.40&emsp14;mmHg) that we used broadly cover the <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tensions expected in sandbar shark blood <italic>in vivo</italic>, from resting <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> to extreme hypercapnia during exhaustive exercise (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C25">Piiper <italic>et al.</italic>, 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C15">Holeton and Heisler, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C26">Richards <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Interestingly, studies that have assessed <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tensions in exhaustively exercised sharks using conventional <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> electrodes found no significant increase in arterial <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C26">Richards <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>) or only a moderate increase (5&emsp14;mmHg, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C15">Holeton and Heisler, 1983</xref>; 3&emsp14;mmHg, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C25">Piiper <italic>et al.</italic>, 1972</xref>), whereas i-STAT measurements generally report higher <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> values (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C23">Mandelman and Skomal, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C16">Hyatt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C24">Naples <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). We decided to validate the i-STAT system for the range of <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> values that are commonly reported in literature, including those values generated with the i-STAT system itself. Whether <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tensions as high as 11.4&emsp14;mmHg are representative of <italic>in vivo</italic> conditions in sharks was not the subject of this investigation, and to our knowledge this remains to be thoroughly assessed.The lower detection limit of the <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> electrode used in i-STAT cartridges is 5&emsp14;mmHg at 37&deg;C. However, the i-STAT will report temperature-corrected <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> values below this detection limit according to: min<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;5&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;10<sup>0.019</sup>(<italic>T</italic>&minus;37), where min<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> (in mmHg) is the detection limit of the i-STAT for <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> and <italic>T</italic> is the treatment temperature (in &deg;C; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C18">i-STAT Technical Bulletin, 2013a</xref>). For our test temperatures, the theoretical detection limit of the i-STAT for <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> is 1.9, 2.4 and 3.0&emsp14;mmHg at 15, 20 and 25&deg;C, respectively (see dotted line in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV002F3">3</xref>A). Consequently, our lowest test <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tension (1.52&emsp14;mmHg) was below the detection limit at every treatment temperature, and the i-STAT system reported values for only 7&percnt; of the 57 measurements (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV002TB2">2</xref>). We therefore excluded the lowest <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> from statistical analysis, and the linear relationships were based on the <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> values of 4.56 and 11.40&emsp14;mmHg only. Unlike the situation for rainbow trout (where <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> was overestimated by the i-STAT system), it appears that in sandbar shark blood the i-STAT underestimated <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> by &sim;20&percnt;. Yet, in both studies, &delta;<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> decreased at higher <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tensions and would be &lt;1&percnt; at a <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> of 19&emsp14;mmHg in rainbow trout and 50&emsp14;mmHg in sandbar shark. The &delta;<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> in rainbow trout scaled exponentially with control <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C14">Harter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), but the same could not be confirmed for sandbar shark blood after excluding our lowest <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> tension. The different outcomes of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> measurements in trout and sandbar sharks may be the result of differences in <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV002C14">Harter <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> nominally set <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> to 46&emsp14;mmHg, whereas we varied <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> over three levels and found a significant effect of <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> on &delta;<italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>. Therefore, changes in <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> will affect the accuracy of i-STAT <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> measurements, and overall, higher values of <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> will yield more accurate i-STAT <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> readings. We cannot recommend the use of the i-STAT system for measuring <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> in sandbar sharks because: (i) resting <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> values (of any water-breather) are typically below its detection limit; (ii) at those <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> values that can be expected in a highly stressed or maximally exercised shark, the measurement error of the i-STAT system is considerable and highly variable (ranging from &minus;5 to &minus;50&percnt;); and (iii) complex interactions between <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> and <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> measurements make the determination of a single correction factor for i-STAT <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> measurements unreliable, at best.Our results indicate that the i-STAT system with the CG4&plus; cartridge is a useful tool to measure pH in sandbar shark whole blood, but replicate measurements are recommended if accurate mean values are required. Although the i-STAT system underestimated pH by &sim;0.1 pH units, a correction for this bias seems possible with the linear equations we provide. In contrast, i-STAT <italic>P</italic>O<sub>2</sub> measurements on sandbar shark whole blood were associated with a high and variable measurement error, while measurements of <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> were likewise problematic, with resting <italic>in vivo</italic> values being below the detection limit. Therefore, we cannot recommend the i-STAT system for measuring blood gas tensions (and derived parameters) in sandbar shark or, presumably, other fishes.The limitations imposed by field research can make the accurate measurement of blood gases and pH difficult, if not impossible. With the i-STAT system, researchers have a reliable tool for measuring blood pH in fishes, with an exceptional ease of operation and portability. However, users should carefully evaluate whether the i-STAT system is the most cost-effective means to generate values for pH and any other validated blood parameters not examined in the present study (e.g. lactate), if other (validated) instruments or assays are available.This study was supported by a <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1">Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council (NSERC) of Canada Discovery Grant</grant-sponsor> to C.J.B. and A.P.F. and an NSERC Accelerator Supplement to C.J.B. A.P.F. holds a Canada Research Chair. This is contribution number <grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1">3433</grant-num> from the Virginia Institute of Marine Science, College of William &amp; Mary. Funding for some of the study supplies, including cartridges, was provided by an anonymous donor supporting J.W.M.&apos;s work.Thanks are due to Katy Bonaro for her help during experiments. The opinions expressed herein are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the US Department of Commerce, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) or any of its subagencies. Mention of trade names, products or commercial companies is for identification purposes only and likewise does not imply endorsement by NOAA or any of its subagencies.