Captivity results in disparate loss of gut microbial diversity in closely related hostsDevelopment of husbandry practices for the captive breeding of Key Largo woodrats (<italic>Neotoma floridana smalli</italic>)Co-evolution in context: the importance of studying gut microbiomes in wild animalsA molecular examination of relatedness, multiple paternity, and cohabitation of the Southern plains woodrat (<italic>Neotoma micropus</italic>)Packrat Middens: the Last 40,000 Years of Biotic ChangeWhat are the consequences of the disappearing human microbiota?PyNAST: a flexible tool for aligning sequences to a template alignmentQIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing dataUltra-high-throughput microbial community analysis on the Illumina HiSeq and MiSeq platformsDiet rapidly and reproducibly alters the human gut microbiomeDiet breadth of mammalian herbivores: nutrient versus detoxification constraintsGreengenes, a chimera-checked 16S rRNA gene database and workbench compatible with ARBThree sympatric species of <italic>Neotoma</italic>: dietary specialization and coexistenceDelivery mode shapes the acquisition and structure of the initial microbiota across multiple body habitats in newbornsSearch and clustering orders of magnitude faster than BLASTConservation evaluation and phylogenetic diversityStrategies in herbivory by mammals: the role of plant secondary compoundsMom knows best: the universality of maternal microbial transmissionFast UniFrac: facilitating high-throughput phylogenetic analysis of microbial communities including analysis of pyrosequencing and phylochip dataNormal gut microbiota modulates brain development and behaviorMetagenomic discovery of biomass-degrading genes and genomes from cow rumenExperience matters: prior exposure to plant toxins enhances diversity of gut microbes in herbivoresWild-caught rodents retain a majority of their natural gut microbiota upon entrance into captivityHerbivorous rodents (<italic>Neotoma</italic> spp.) harbour abundant and active foregut microbiotaEvolution of mammals and their gut microbesUniFrac: a new phylogenetic method for comparing microbial communitiesAre declines of an endangered mammal predation-driven, and can a captive-breeding and release program aid their recovery?Species differences in responses to captivity: stress, welfare, and the comparative methodDiet drives convergence in gut microbiome functions across mammalian phylogeny and within humansDevelopment of the human infant intestinal microbiotaFastTree: computing large minimum-evolution trees with profiles instead of a distance matrixConservation and the microbiomeThe Mathematical Theory of CommunicationRevisiting the dietary niche: when is a mammalian herbivore a specialist?Differential hepatic gene expression of a dietary specialist (<italic>Neotoma stephensi</italic>) and generalist (<italic>Neotoma albigula</italic>) in response to juniper (<italic>Juniperus monosperma</italic>) ingestionComparative Physiology of the Vertebrate Digestive SystemA core gut microbiome in obese and lean twinsThe effect of diet on the human gut microbiome: a metagenomic analysis in humanized gnotobiotic miceStephen's woodrat, a dietary specialistReproduction in Stephens' woodrat: the wages of folivoryDietary and digestive constraints on basal energy metabolism in a small herbivorous rodentEndosulfan degradation by a <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strain isolated from earthworm gutNaive Bayesian classifier for rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomyThe Analysis of Biological DataEvidence of cellulose metabolism by the giant panda gut microbiome<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We compared microbial community structure in two rodent species before and after captivity. One species lost a greater proportion of diversity in captivity, which was not rescued when they were returned to their natural diet. Mothers effectively transmitted microbiota to their offspring. These results have implications for captive breeding programs.The gastrointestinal tracts of animals contain diverse communities of microbes that provide a number of services to their hosts. There is recent concern that these communities may be lost as animals enter captive breeding programmes, due to changes in diet and/or exposure to environmental sources. However, empirical evidence documenting the effects of captivity and captive birth on gut communities is lacking. We conducted three studies to advance our knowledge in this area. First, we compared changes in microbial diversity of the gut communities of two species of woodrats (<italic>Neotoma albigula</italic>, a dietary generalist, and <italic>Neotoma stephensi</italic>, which specializes on juniper) before and after 6–9 months in captivity. Second, we investigated whether reintroduction of the natural diet of <italic>N. stephensi</italic> could restore microbial diversity. Third, we compared the microbial communities between offspring born in captivity and their mothers. We found that the dietary specialist, <italic>N. stephensi</italic>, lost a greater proportion of its native gut microbiota and overall diversity in response to captivity compared with <italic>N. albigula</italic>. Addition of the natural diet increased the proportion of the original microbiota but did not restore overall diversity in <italic>N. stephensi</italic>. Offspring of <italic>N. albigula</italic> more closely resembled their mothers compared with offspring–mother pairs of <italic>N. stephensi</italic>. This research suggests that the microbiota of dietary specialists may be more susceptible to captivity. Furthermore, this work highlights the need for further studies investigating the mechanisms underlying how loss of microbial diversity may vary between hosts and what an acceptable level of diversity loss may be to a host. This knowledge will aid conservation biologists in designing captive breeding programmes effective at maintaining microbial diversity.Sequence Accession Numbers: NCBI's Sequence Read Archive (SRA) – SRP033616The gut microbial communities of animals are hyperdiverse and influence many aspects of their physiology, such as nutrition, immune development and even behaviour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C2">Amato, 2013</xref>). The preservation of the microbial diversity present in the gut is thought to be critical to the success of their hosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C32">Redford <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). For instance, loss of microbial diversity may underlie increased disease prevalence in humans by resulting in microbial communities that are more susceptible to invasion or by altering host immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C5">Blaser and Falkow, 2009</xref>). Additionally, gut microbes serve as sources of novel gene products, such as enzymes for biomass degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C20">Hess <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) or bioremediation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C42">Verma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).There is concern that bringing animals into captivity for breeding programmes may result in a loss of microbial diversity, which may contribute to the failures of reintroduced individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C32">Redford <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). For instance, loss of the nutritional, immunological or behavioural functions provided by microbes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C2">Amato, 2013</xref>) may result in a reduction in host fitness. However, there have been few empirical studies tracking the loss of microbial diversity when animals are brought into captivity. Moreover, the transmission of microbes from mother to offspring for a wild species held in captivity has not been well characterized. The birthing process represents the greatest microbial acquisition event in the lives of many species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C30">Palmer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C13">Dominguez-Bello <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C17">Funkhouser and Bordenstein, 2013</xref>). It is currently unknown whether the uniform conditions of captivity tend to homogenize microbial gut communities among individuals or species.We addressed this gap in knowledge using woodrats (<italic>Neotoma</italic> spp.), which are small, herbivorous rodents that serve as a model system to study interactions between dietary plant toxins and the gut microbiota (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C10">Dearing <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Woodrats are interesting from a microbial perspective because they maintain dense microbial populations in the foregut of their stomach, as well as their caecum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C23">Kohl <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). We have previously demonstrated that the desert woodrat (<italic>Neotoma lepida</italic>) retained a majority of its gut microbes after 6 months in captivity and shared more microbial species with wild conspecifics than other studies on captive-bred species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C22">Kohl and Dearing, 2014</xref>). However, in that study, <italic>N. lepida</italic> exhibited a substantial loss in microbial diversity. It is unclear how consistent captivity-induced changes in microbial diversity are across host species. Furthermore, diet greatly influences microbial community diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C24">Ley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C38">Turnbaugh <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C21">Kohl and Dearing, 2012</xref>), and thus returning animals to their natural diet in captivity may rescue microbial diversity.Here, we compared the gut microbial diversity of two woodrat species, the white-throated woodrat (<italic>Neotoma albigula</italic>) and Stephens' woodrat (<italic>Neotoma stephensi</italic>), in the wild and in captivity. Both species were held in identical environmental conditions and fed the same diet, allowing us to determine whether species maintain unique microbial signatures in captivity. <italic>Neotoma albigula</italic> is a generalist species that feeds on a variety of plants across its range, such as <italic>Opuntia</italic> cactus, yucca, juniper, other shrubs and grasses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C27">Macedo and Mares, 1988</xref>). Conversely, <italic>N. stephensi</italic> is a dietary specialist that consumes a diet of 60–95% juniper (<italic>Juniperus monosperma</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C39">Vaughn, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C12">Dial, 1988</xref>). Given that diet influences microbial community composition over an evolutionary time scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C29">Muegge <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), we predicted that the specialist species would lose more microbial diversity due to the novel diet in captivity.The level of specialization exhibited by <italic>N. stephensi</italic> also permitted the recreation of its natural diet in captivity. In <italic>N. lepida</italic>, roughly a quarter of the bacterial species found in the gut are also found on plant surfaces, and so plants may represent a small microbial source to the gut community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C22">Kohl and Dearing, 2014</xref>). Additionally, diet is known to impact the microbial community structure of the gut (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C24">Ley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C38">Turnbaugh <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C21">Kohl and Dearing, 2012</xref>). Therefore, we predicted that feeding on juniper in captivity would restore microbial diversity to resemble more closely the gut microbiomes of woodrats in nature.We also investigated the transmission of gut microbes from mothers to offspring. Given that a large proportion of microbes are acquired from mothers through the birth process and milk feeding in mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C30">Palmer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C13">Dominguez-Bello <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C17">Funkhouser and Bordenstein, 2013</xref>), we predicted that offspring would resemble their own mothers and species, thus suggesting that captive breeding programmes may retain wild microbiomes.Finally, we compared food intakes between wild-caught and captive-born animals as an indicator of microbial function. Differences in food intake could be indicative of changes in fibre digestibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C41">Veloso and Bozinovic, 1993</xref>) or tolerance to the toxins present in juniper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C10">Dearing <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>); two functions provided by the gut microbiota (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C16">Freeland and Janzen, 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C36">Stevens and Hume, 2004</xref>). We predicted that captive-born animals would perform as well as wild-caught individuals due to effective microbial transmission.Details of trapping locations and time in captivityAfter 6 months in captivity, individuals of <italic>N. stephensi</italic> underwent a diet trial in which they were fed ground juniper (<italic>J. monosperma</italic>) to mimic their natural diet (4 days on 25%, 1 day on 50% and 4 days on 75%). Gut microbial communities respond rapidly to dietary changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C9">David <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), and this length of time is sufficient to induce changes in woodrat microbial communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C21">Kohl and Dearing, 2012</xref>). Diets were prepared using methods described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C35">Skopec <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Food intakes and body masses were recorded daily. Faeces were collected on the last day of this feeding trial and represent ‘juniper diet’ samples.Several animals (<italic>N. albigula</italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 2 and <italic>N. stephensi</italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 4) were pregnant when trapped and gave birth within 30 days of being brought into captivity. Offspring (<italic>N. albigula</italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 3 and <italic>N. stephensi</italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 5) were housed with their mothers until they were weaned at 2 months of age, placed in individual cages and fed rabbit chow. This time frame was similar to nature, where animals wean at 20–35 days old and first leave the den around 42 days old (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C40">Vaughn and Czaplewski, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C27">Macedo and Mares, 1988</xref>). Faeces were collected to inventory microbial communities of all offspring at least 4 months after weaning. Data from siblings were averaged to form one independent unit. Captive-born <italic>N. stephensi</italic> were subsequently fed a diet of 75% juniper to investigate whether they had the ability to consume this toxic, high-fibre diet (see details of feeding trial in the previous subsection).Whole DNA was isolated from faeces using a QIAamp DNA Stool Mini Kit (Qiagen, Germantown, MD, USA). Extracted DNA was sent to Argonne National Laboratory (Lemont, IL, USA) for sequencing. Bacterial inventories were conducted by amplifying the V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene using primers 515F and 806R, and paired-end sequencing on an Illumina MiSeq platform (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C8">Caporaso <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).Sequences were analysed using the QIIME software package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C7">Caporaso <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Sequences underwent standard quality control and were split into libraries using default parameters in QIIME. Sequences were grouped into <italic>de novo</italic> operational taxonomic units (OTUs) using UCLUST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C14">Edgar, 2010</xref>) with a minimal sequence identity of 97%. The most abundant sequences within each OTU were designated as a ‘representative sequence’ and then aligned against Greengenes 13_5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C11">DeSantis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) using PyNAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C6">Caporaso <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) with default parameters set by QIIME. A PH Lane mask supplied by QIIME was used to remove hypervariable regions from aligned sequences. FastTree (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C31">Price <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) was used to create a phylogenetic tree of representative sequences. The OTUs were classified using the Ribosomal Database Project classifier with a the standard minimal support threshold of 80% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C43">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Sequences identified as chloroplasts or mitochondria were removed from analysis.The number of OTUs that were shared between samples (wild and captive or wild and juniper diet) was determined within species to calculate the relative loss and retention of OTUs. For this analysis, samples were pooled within a condition (wild, captive, juniper diet) in order to maximize detection of microbial OTUs within a given condition. The proportion of OTUs retained was calculated as total OTUs shared between conditions divided by the total number of OTUs in both conditions. Differences in the relative loss and retention of OTUs between species as well as between diets in <italic>N. stephensi</italic> were compared using χ<sup>2</sup> analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C44">Whitlock and Schluter, 2009</xref>).Several α diversity measurements were calculated for each sample using QIIME. We calculated the Shannon diversity index (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C33">Shannon and Weaver, 1949</xref>), a biodiversity measure that incorporates both richness and evenness, and Faith's phylogenetic diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C15">Faith, 1992</xref>), which measures the cumulative branch lengths from randomly sampling OTUs from each sample. For each sample, we calculated the mean of 20 iterations for a subsampling of 12 400 sequences. Diversity measurements were compared between species using repeated-measures ANOVA with sample (wild or captive) as the repeated measure and species as the factor using JMP 10.0. Student's paired <italic>t</italic>-tests were used to compare between conditions (captive vs. juniper diet) in <italic>N. stephensi</italic>.We also compared community membership (presence or absence of bacterial lineages). We calculated unweighted UniFrac distances, which are the proportion of microbial OTUs that are specific to one sample or the other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C25">Lozupone and Knight, 2005</xref>). UniFrac distances were compared using a Student's unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test (between species) or a repeated-measures ANOVA. We also conducted principal coordinates analysis (PCoA) on UniFrac scores to visualize similarities in microbial communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C18">Hamady <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Clustering by treatment or individuals was determined using the analysis of similarity test (ANOSIM) within QIIME. Relative abundances of taxa were compared similar to α diversity measurements. All <italic>P</italic>-values were Bonferroni corrected, with α = 0.05 as a threshold for significance. All sequences were deposited in NCBI's Sequence Read Archive (SRA) under accession SRP033616.We compared body mass and food intake as indicators of tolerance to experimental diets. Data were compared between species with two-way ANOVAs, with either food intake or body mass as the dependent variable and species and status (wild caught or captive born) as the independent factors using JMP 10.0. Food intakes and body masses of <italic>N. stephensi</italic> fed rabbit chow or 75% juniper were compared with repeated-measures ANOVAs, with either food intake or body mass on the two different diets as the repeated measure and status (wild caught or born in captivity) as the factor.Shared microbial operational taxonomic units (OTUs) in the faeces of woodrats. (a) <italic>Neotoma albigula</italic> in the wild and after 6–9 months of captivity. (b) <italic>Neotoma stephensi</italic> in the wild, after 6 months in captivity fed rabbit chow diet, and fed a 75% juniper diet.Diversity metrics of microbial communities from woodrats from the wild, after 6–9 months in captivity fed rabbit chow diet, and fed a 75% juniper diet. (<bold>a</bold>) Shannon diversity index. (<bold>b</bold>) Faith's phylogenetic diversity.Changes in microbial communities between the wild and captivity. (<bold>a</bold>) Principal coordinates analysis. Lines connect an individual over time. (<bold>b</bold>) Unweighted UniFrac distances. Open bars represent mean distances between samples from the wild compared with animals in captivity. The hatched bar represents the distance between samples collected from animals in the wild to samples collected from animals fed the juniper diet. The asterisk denotes statistical significance between <italic>N. albigula</italic> and <italic>N. stephensi</italic>. The difference between <italic>N. stephensi</italic> fed commercial chow and 75% juniper was not significant (n.s.).Repeated-measures ANOVA results for relative abundances of bacterial phyla in faecal samples of two species of woodrats collected in the wild and captivity*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Relative abundances of microbial phyla in faecal samples of woodrats collected from the wild, after 6–9 months in captivity fed rabbit chow diet, and fed a 75% juniper diet.The addition of juniper to the diet of <italic>N. stephensi</italic> significantly increased the proportion of OTUs shared with samples collected in the wild to 58.2% (1372 of 2357 OTUs) from 51% before the diet amendment (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU009F1">1</xref>b; χ<sup>2</sup> = 27.9, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). <italic>Neotoma stephensi</italic> exhibited a slight decrease in the Shannon index after being fed the juniper diet (Student's paired <italic>t</italic>-test between 0 and 75% juniper samples, <italic>P</italic> = 0.06), but showed no difference in Faith's phylogenetic diversity (<italic>P</italic> = 0.15; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU009F2">2</xref>). Samples collected from individuals fed the juniper did not cluster differentially from ‘captivity’ samples collected when animals were fed rabbit chow (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU009F3">3</xref>a). <italic>Neotoma stephensi</italic> did not exhibit a significant decrease in UniFrac distance when fed juniper (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU009F3">3</xref>b).Statistics of pair-wise comparisons of relative abundances of various bacterial phyla in the faeces of <italic>N. stephensi</italic><italic>P</italic>-values have been Bonferroni corrected.*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; n.s., not significant.UniFrac distances between individuals born in captivity (BIC) and others. Open bars compare offspring with their mothers. Light grey bars compare offspring with adult members of the same species (excluding their mother). Dark grey bars compare offspring with adult members of the other species.Mean ± SEM body masses and food intake of wild-caught and captive-born woodrats<italic>Neotoma albigula</italic> were not fed a diet of 75% juniper.Conservation of gut microbial communities has been largely overlooked by conservation biologists, despite their importance in animal health and performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C32">Redford <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Here we show that captivity can have disparate effects on the microbiomes of closely related hosts. We discuss a number of potential mechanisms driving these results, which will require further research to understand the effects of captivity on the loss of microbial diversity.The loss of diversity in captivity may be driven partly by the loss of environmental sources of microbes. Both woodrat species exhibited a decrease in microbial diversity and a decrease in the relative abundance of the phylum Tenericutes. These trends have also been shown in <italic>N. lepida</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C22">Kohl and Dearing, 2014</xref>). Animals housed in captivity experience a much cleaner environment than in the wild. In nature, woodrats live in stick structures called middens that are passed on from generation to generation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C4">Betancourt <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>). While we did not inventory the microbial environment of middens, they are likely to be a rich source of microbes, given that unrelated individuals of woodrats and other species, such as mice, snakes and ground squirrels, may inhabit middens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C4">Betancourt <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C3">Baxter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Additionally, woodrats frequently collect and store scat from jackrabbits, coyotes and cows in or on their middens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C4">Betancourt <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>). Repeated exposure to faecal material from other individuals and species may increase the microbial diversity of woodrats in nature. Once in captivity, inter- and intraspecies inoculation no longer occurs (except for interactions with researchers), and woodrats receive very few microbes from environmental sources in captivity, such as food and bedding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C22">Kohl and Dearing, 2014</xref>). The removal from dense microbial sources may partly explain the observed loss of diversity, though does not explain species-specific differences.Captivity had a markedly different effect on the microbiomes of <italic>N. albigula</italic> and <italic>N. stephensi</italic>. Individuals of <italic>N. albigula</italic> retained a majority (64%) of their microbial OTUs after being held in captivity for 6–9 months. These results are similar to findings in captive <italic>N. lepida</italic>, which also shared 64% of their microbial OTUs with samples collected from free-ranging individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C22">Kohl and Dearing, 2014</xref>). However, <italic>N. stephensi</italic> shared only 50% of OTUs between samples taken before and after captivity. Likewise, both <italic>N. lepida</italic> and <italic>N. albigula</italic> exhibited a ∼7% decrease in Faith's phylogenetic diversity in captivity, while <italic>N. stephensi</italic> exhibited a 27% loss. These results are especially noteworthy given that some individuals of <italic>N. albigula</italic> had been in captivity for 3 months longer than <italic>N. stephensi</italic> (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU009TB1">1</xref>). Many closely related species exhibit different responses to captivity in terms of stress physiology and immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C28">Mason, 2010</xref>). These physiological responses to captivity may drive the differential retention or loss of microbes.Another factor that may underlie the differences between species is the high degree of dietary specialization exhibited by <italic>N. stephensi</italic>. There is strong coevolution between diet and gut microbial communities that seems to be driven by the relative amounts of various nutrients that animals consume (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C24">Ley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C29">Muegge <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Therefore, the microbes of dietary specialists may be especially reliant on the types of nutrients consumed by specialist hosts and more susceptible to perturbation by a novel diet. Specialist herbivores are often difficult to maintain in captivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C34">Shipley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), which may be due to loss of microbial diversity. Conversely, dietary specialists may not need to maintain as much microbial diversity as generalists in order to maintain function, due to the limited diversity in their diet. Indeed, one dietary specialist, the giant panda (<italic>Ailuropoda melanoleuca</italic>) exhibits the lowest amount of microbial diversity of any mammal studied to date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C45">Zhu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The <italic>N. stephensi</italic> in our study were still able to specialize on juniper despite reductions in diversity due to captivity. Future research on the microbial communities of dietary specialists in the wild and in captivity will uncover whether this is a general trend.Our results suggest that diet is not the sole driver of loss of microbial diversity in captivity. Both species in this study were placed on an identical diet of rabbit chow in captivity. If diet played a key role in sculpting microbial communities then it would be expected that the microbial communities of various woodrat species would converge with one another after being exposed to a similar diet and thus, unique species signatures would be lost. This outcome did not occur; the microbial signatures of woodrats in captivity continued to cluster together by species when measured by principal coordinate analysis. Moreover, returning <italic>N. stephensi</italic> to its natural diet did not fully restore microbial diversity to pre-captivity levels or cause shifts in the relative abundances of microbial taxa to match those of wild samples. However, the addition of juniper did result in the return of 299 OTUs found in the samples collected in the wild. These microbial OTUs may have come from juniper foliage or they may have been present in undetectable levels when animals were fed rabbit chow. Future studies could investigate whether microbial diversity is better retained when animals are fed a natural diet immediately when brought into captivity.The microbiota of offspring born in captivity closely resembled those of their mothers. Vertical transmission of microbes has been documented in a number of mammalian species, which acquire their microbes through contact with faecal and vaginal microbes during the birth process and also through milk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C30">Palmer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C13">Dominguez-Bello <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C17">Funkhouser and Bordenstein, 2013</xref>). We compared vertical transmission across species born in the same captive environment. We found that offspring of <italic>N. albigula</italic> more closely resemble their mothers compared with <italic>N. stephensi</italic>; this result suggests enhanced vertical transmission for <italic>N. albigula</italic>. The mechanisms and limitations of vertical transmission of the microbiota in mammals are poorly understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C30">Palmer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C13">Dominguez-Bello <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C17">Funkhouser and Bordenstein, 2013</xref>), and thus future research is required to determine what drives species-specific transmission.Despite losses of diversity in captivity and between generations, woodrats nonetheless maintained a high proportion of their natural microbiota. Although the offspring of <italic>N. albigula</italic> and <italic>N. stephensi</italic> in this study were born and housed in the same room, they retained the unique microbial signatures characteristic of their species. For example, all <italic>N. albigula</italic> (born in captivity and wild caught) lacked the phylum Verrucomicrobia. These results demonstrate that captivity does not homogenize microbial communities between species.It is worth noting that this study only monitored losses in taxonomic diversity and did not investigate functional diversity of the microbiota. In humans, despite high variability in taxonomic diversity of microbes among individuals, there is high redundancy in functional gene content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C37">Turnbaugh <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009a</xref>). Captive <italic>N. stephensi</italic> were able to ingest high levels of toxic, fibre-rich food and maintain mass in captivity, suggesting that the microbiota is still functional. Furthermore, captive-born <italic>N. stephensi</italic> still inherited a high tolerance for juniper and consumed similar amounts of the 75% juniper diet to the wild-caught <italic>N. stephensi</italic>. Thus, loss of microbial diversity in captivity may not necessarily result in a measureable loss of function.Our results may have relevance for another species of woodrat, the Key Largo woodrat (<italic>Neotoma floridana smalli</italic>), which is federally endangered and has undergone a captive breeding programme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C1">Alligood <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). This programme was unsuccessful due to high predation rates on reintroduced individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C26">McCleery <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Microbial diversity has been implicated in the movement patterns of laboratory rodents. For example, germ-free mice (those lacking a gut microbiota) voluntarily cover more area in an open arena, engage in more risky behaviours and exhibit lower indicators of anxiety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU009C19">Heijtz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). It is possible that captive-bred Key Largo woodrats harbour lower microbial diversity, which may cause them to engage in more risky behaviours and experience higher rates of predation. However, this connection is largely speculative at this time.Collaborations with zoos or wildlife refuges may be necessary to investigate how conditions in captivity impact the loss of gut microbial diversity and how this loss affects animal performance. Identification of the physiological or ecological mechanisms that drive differential loss of diversity between host species will inform conservation biologists about how best to design captive breeding programmes. Additionally, it would be ideal to compare microbial diversity of native and captive-bred individuals after being released into the wild. These studies will better inform scientists how to conserve taxonomic and functional diversity of the gut microbiome.We thank T. Bakke, Z. Cambell, C. Dalton, T. Edwards and B. Jessen for assistance with animal care, and A. Stengel for assistance with DNA extraction. We also thank S. Owens of Argonne National Laboratory for assistance with 16S rRNA amplification and sequencing. This work was supported by Weber State University and the National Science Foundation [Graduate Research Fellowship to K.D.K., Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant, DEB 1210094, to M.D.D. and K.D.K., and DEB 1342615 to M.D.D.].