 Fibre wall and lumen fractions drive wood density variation across 24 Australian angiosperms  Functional strategies of chaparral shrubs in relation to seasonal water deficit and disturbance  The role of wood mass density and mechanical constraints in the economy of tree architecture  Pathogen mortality of tropical tree seedlings: experimental studies of the effects of dispersal distance, seedling density, and light conditions  Wood specific gravity in species from two tropical forests in Mexico  Radial variation in wood properties of naturally and plantation grown light red meranti ( Shorea , Dipterocarpaceae)  Functional convergence in hydraulic architecture and water relations of tropical savanna trees: from leaf to whole plant  Safety and streamlining of woody shoots in wind: an empirical study across 39 species in tropical Australia  Towards a worldwide wood economics spectrum  Cell wall and lumen percentages in relation to wood density of  Nothofagus nervosa   Allometric scaling of production and life-history variation in vascular plants  Variation of cellular proportions in sweetgum and their relation to other wood properties  Hydraulic conductivity traits predict growth rates and adult stature of 40 Asian tropical tree species better than wood density  Wood anatomical variables in tropical trees and their relation to site conditions and individual tree morphology  Preparation of thin sections of synthetic resins and wood-resin composites, and a new macerating method for wood  Anatomy and properties of Japanese hardwoods II. Variation of dimensions of ray cells and their relation to basic density  Anatomy and properties of Japanese hardwoods. I. Variation of fibre dimensions and tissue proportions and their relation to basic density  Juvenile wood of hardwoods judged by density variation  Stem xylem conductivity is key to plant water balance across Australian angiosperm species  Allocation to leaf area and sapwood area affects water relations of co-occurring savanna and forest trees  Interprétation anatomique des composantes d'un modèle mixte de densité du bois chez le Chêne sessile ( Quercus petraea  Liebl.): âge du cerne compté depuis la moelle, largeur de cerne, arbre, variabilité interannuelle et duraminisation  Trends in wood density and structure are linked to prevention of xylem implosion by negative pressure  IAWA list of microscopic features for hardwood identification  Do xylem fibers affect vessel cavitation resistance?  Xylem density, biomechanics and anatomical traits correlate with water stress in 17 evergreen shrub species of the Mediterranean-type climate region of South Africa  Cavitation resistance among 26 chaparral species of Southern California  Comparative community physiology: nonconvergence in water relations among three semi-arid shrub communities  The relationship between wood density and mortality in a global tropical forest data set  Rethinking the value of high wood density  Between- and within-tree variation in the anatomy and specific gravity of wood in Oregon white oak ( Quercus garryana  Dougl.)  Testing hypotheses that link wood anatomy to cavitation resistance and hydraulic conductivity in the genus  Acer   Wood anatomy and wood density in shrubs: responses to varying aridity along transcontinental transects  Wood specific gravity and anatomy in  Helicarpus appendiculatus  (Tiliaceae)  Whole-tree water transport scales with sapwood capacitance in tropical forest canopy trees  Constraints on physiological function associated with branch architecture and wood density in tropical forest trees  Using multiple trait asociations to define hydraulic functional types in plant communities of south-western Australia  Interspecific and inter-site variation in wood specific gravity of tropical trees  Are functional traits good predictors of demographic rates? Evidence from five Neotropical forests  The importance of wood traits and hydraulic conductance for the performance and life history strategies of 42 rainforest tree species  Relationships among xylem transport, biomechanics and storage in stems and roots of nine Rhamnaceae species of the California chaparral  Wood density and vessel traits as distinct correlates of ecological strategy in 51 California coast range angiosperms  Uprooting and snapping of trees: structural determinants and ecological consequences  Functional anatomy of five endangered tropical timber wood species of the family Dipterocarpaceae  Effects of stem anatomical and structural traits on responses to stem damage: an experimental study in the Bolivian Amazon  Anatomical features associated with water transport in imperforate tracheary elements of vessel-bearing angiosperms  Leaf photosynthetic traits scale with hydraulic conductivity and wood density in Panamanian forest canopy trees  Biophysical properties and functional significance of stem water storage tissues in Neotropical savanna trees  Der Anteil der einzelnen Zellarten an dem Holz der Rotbuche  Character convergence, diversity, and disturbance in tropical rain forest in Guyana  Proportions of wood elements in stem, branch, and root wood of black oak ( Quercus velutina )  Stem water storage capacity and efficiency of water transport: their functional significance in a Hawaiian dry forest  Ecological and evolutionary determinants of a key plant functional trait: wood density and its community-wide variation across latitude and elevation  The effect of ray tissue on the specific gravity of wood  Wood property variation of Mississippi delta hardwoods  Proportions and types of cells in stems, branches, and roots of European black alder ( Alnus glutinosa  L. Gaertn.)  Plant ecological strategies: some leading dimensions of variation between species  Geographic variation in wood specific gravity: effects of latitude, temperature, and precipitation  A more rational climatic moisture index  The worldwide leaf economics spectrum  Functional traits and the growth-mortality trade-off in tropical trees  Angiosperm wood structure: global patterns in vessel anatomy and their relation to wood density and potential conductivity  Spatial patterns of wood traits in China are controlled by phylogeny and the environment  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Wood density is often considered to be a key plant functional trait. But it is not clear what actually wood density is? We rigorously quantified anatomical underpinnings of wood density variation. We found that density was mainly driven by properties of mechanical tissue such as fibre wall fraction and fibre lumen fraction. However, there was also a substantial anatomical variation independent of density. This variation suggests that different plant ecological strategies may be available to woods with the same density. Our results imply that density is a complex characteristic of wood rather than a straightforward indicator of plant ecological strategies.  Wood density is considered a key plant trait, affecting mechanical and physiological performance, yet its biological meaning is still rather unclear. Accordingly we investigated the anatomical underpinnings of wood density in trees and shrubs. We measured wood density and anatomical traits in distal stems 4–10 mm diameter under bark in 24 Australian species. Proportions of wood components that are functionally distinct were analysed, including fibre wall and lumen, vessel wall and lumen, and axial and ray parenchyma. Wood density was mainly driven by the density of wood outside vessel lumens (density NV ) rather than by vessel lumen fraction. In turn, density NV  variation was chiefly affected by fibre wall and lumen fractions. Considerable anatomical variation was observed at a given density NV , especially among medium-density NV  species (0.60–0.85 g cm −3 ); this range of medium density NV  roughly translates to 0.50–0.75 g cm −3  of overall density. The anatomy of these species formed a continuum from low fibre lumen and medium parenchyma fractions to medium fibre lumen and low parenchyma fractions. Our data suggest that wood density is an emergent property influenced by a complex anatomy rather than an unambiguous functional trait, particularly in medium-density species. With much anatomical variation, they likely represent a wide range of ecological strategies.  Plants vary significantly in their ecological, physiological and mechanical properties or ‘traits’ both across climate and even within a site ( Westoby  et al.  2002 ;  Wright  et al.  2004 ;  Chave  et al.  2009 ). This indicates that there are multiple solutions to the problem of how to be a successful plant and maintain species continuity. Different solutions can be called plant ecological strategies ( Westoby  et al.  2002 ).  Wood density has been suggested as a key player in plant ecological strategies ( Chave  et al.  2009 ). Firstly, wood density has been linked with hydraulic strategies. Denser woods tend to operate at more negative water potentials ( Ackerly 2004 ;  Bucci  et al.  2004 ;  Santiago  et al.  2004 ;  Jacobsen  et al.  2007 b  ,  2008 ;  Gotsch  et al.  2010 ) and to have greater cavitation resistance than low-density woods ( Hacke  et al . 2001 ;  Jacobsen  et al . 2005 ;  Pratt  et al . 2007 ;  Lens  et al . 2011 ). Wood density has been studied in relation to hydraulic conductivity but the results are inconclusive, showing either a negative relationship between the two traits (measured conductivity,  Stratton  et al . 2000 ;  Bucci  et al . 2004 ;  Santiago  et al . 2004 ) or no relationship (theoretical conductivity,  Poorter  et al . 2010 ;  Fan  et al . 2012 ). Also, density has been found to correlate negatively with capacitance ( Meinzer  et al.  2003 ,  2008 ;  Pratt  et al.  2007 ;  Scholz  et al.  2007 ). Secondly, wood density has been associated with plant mechanical strategies where denser woods tend to be stiffer and more resistant to breakage at a given wood diameter ( Chave  et al.  2009 ). However, it has also been suggested that plants can build thicker stems to compensate for their lower density ( Anten and Schieving 2010 ;  Larjavaara and Muller-Landau 2010 ;  Butler  et al.  2011 ). Thirdly, denser woods might be more resistant to pathogen attacks ( Augspurger and Kelly 1984 ;  Romero and Bolker 2008 ). Wood density has also been widely discussed in relation to life-history strategies. For example, species with denser wood tend to experience lower stem mortality rates ( Putz  et al.  1983 ;  Kraft  et al.  2010 ;  Poorter  et al.  2010 ). Growth rate is another important component of life history. Growth rate can be expected to negatively relate to wood density on the basis that higher investment in mass per volume should slow down growth ( Enquist  et al.  1999 ) and, while generally true, the correlation is not always strong ( Poorter  et al.  2008 ,  2010 ;  Chave  et al.  2009 ;  Wright  et al.  2010 ;  Fan  et al.  2012 ). Across species, wood density can vary with environmental factors such as temperature ( Wiemann and Williamson 2002 ;  Swenson and Enquist 2007 ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ) and precipitation ( Barajas-Morales 1985 ;  Wiemann and Williamson 2002 ;  Swenson and Enquist 2007 ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ;  Zhang  et al.  2011 ), although not in all studies ( Ter Steege and Hammond 2001 ;  Wiemann and Williamson 2002 ;  Muller-Landau 2004 ). Despite this broad climate-related patterning, wood density also tends to vary quite widely among co-occurring species ( Wiemann and Williamson 2002 ;  Muller-Landau 2004 ).  Thus there are many potential functional roles for wood density but also a number of unresolved questions about each potential role.  Larjavaara and Muller-Landau (2010)  argued that some observed correlations may not be causal, but rather may reflect correlated selection on other traits. Further, if wood density has multiple functions, then it might not be a very good predictor of any one of them. In any event, a useful step towards resolving this problem is to ask what are the structural underpinnings of wood density variation. The premise of the work reported here was that if structural underpinnings of wood density variation were rigorously quantified and better understood, this might help to explain complexities in the functional implications of wood density.  Most studies of anatomical components of angiosperm wood density span only one or a few species ( Schulz 1957 ;  Taylor 1971 ;  Taylor and Wooten 1973 ;  Ezell 1979 ;  Vurdu and Bensend 1980 ;  Fukuzawa 1984 ;  Bosman  et al.  1994 ;  Stokke and Manwiller 1994 ;  McDonald  et al . 1995 ;  Lei  et al . 1996 ;  Denne and Hale 1999 ;  Rana  et al.  2009 ) or focus on commercial woods ( French 1923  as cited in  Panshin and de Zeeuw 1980 ;  Manwiller 1973  as cited in  Koch 1985 ). Fewer studies make comparisons across a broad number of species ( Fujiwara  et al.  1991 ;  Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al . 2009 ;  Poorter  et al.  2010 ;  Fichtler and Worbes 2012 ).  Wood is a complex tissue composed of three main cell types: vessels that transport water, fibres responsible for mechanical strength, and parenchyma that stores and transports nutrients. These tissues have different structural characteristics and their relative proportions within wood influence wood density. Vessel lumens have essentially zero density; fibre and vessel walls and parenchyma have positive density. Vessel fraction has variously shown either negative or no correlation with wood density ( Preston  et al . 2006 ;  Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ;  Mitchell  et al . 2008 ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ;  Poorter  et al.  2010 ;  Zanne  et al.  2010 ;  Gleason  et al.  2012 ). Parenchyma is another commonly occurring tissue, which has been reported to have positive, negative or no relationship with density ( Taylor 1969 ;  Fujiwara 1992 ;  Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ;  Rana  et al . 2009 ;  Poorter  et al.  2010 ). Wood density is generally well correlated with fibre properties, especially fibre wall fraction ( Fujiwara  et al.  1991 ;  Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al . 2009 ). However, it is unclear how these different fibre traits are interrelated with each other and consequently how these interrelations influence wood density.  Most previous work linking anatomy with density has concentrated on vessels with relatively little attention given to the other tissues. Furthermore, among the studies investigating all the major tissues (vessels, parenchyma and fibres) only one focused on the wood of twigs in 17 species studied by  Jacobsen  et al . (2007 a ) . Twigs are important, being in direct spatial and functional contact with leaves and having been commonly subjected to physiological and ecological measurements. In this paper, we investigate wood from twigs from a wide range of angiosperm tree and shrub species growing in various environments (24 species from four sites in eastern Australia). We address two main unresolved issues: (i) Which fibre properties have the most decisive effect on wood density and how are those properties interrelated with each other? (ii) How do vessel and parenchyma proportions influence wood density?  Four sites were chosen that spanned a wide range of temperature and aridity in eastern Australia  [see    Supporting Information   ] . The objective of site selection was to generate a broad range of trait values rather than to enable site comparisons. All carried natural, undisturbed vegetation growing on oligotrophic soils on flat to slightly sloping terrain. Two locations in Tasmania, at ∼43°S, represented low mean annual temperature (MAT; 10.6 °C), and two locations in Queensland near 18°S represented higher MAT ( c . 22.5 °C). Within each latitude, two locations were chosen so as to differ markedly in aridity index (AI;  Willmott and Feddema 1992 ), the ratio of mean annual precipitation (MAP) to potential evapotranspiration (PET). In both Queensland and Tasmania the wetter site had an AI  c . 1.0 and the drier site  c . 0.6. MAP, MAT and PET were obtained from GIS (geographic information system) layers from the Australian Bureau of Meteorology.  Sampled sites, species names and families.  Wood density was measured on segments 3–5 cm long for each twig sample. Bark and pith were removed and measurements were carried out on xylem only. In this paper we refer to xylem as ‘wood’. After removing bark and pith, wood pieces were soaked in water for at least 48 h prior to volume measurement. Then a beaker filled with water was placed on a balance (0.0001 g, Mettler AE 160). A thin wire platform was suspended in water so that it did not touch the side or bottom of the beaker. The balance was tared before each measurement and a sample was gently placed on the platform. The mass of displaced water was read from the balance. From standard water density of 1 g cm −3  and knowing the mass of displaced water, we calculated sample volumes applying Archimedes' buoyancy principle (e.g. 1 g of displaced water equals 1 cm 3  volume). Samples were then placed in paper envelopes and dried at 70 °C for at least 72 h. Wood density was calculated as the dry mass divided by water saturated volume (g cm −3 ).  To obtain anatomical cross-sections the material was first fixed in formalin–acetic acid–alcohol (FAA) for 4 weeks. The FAA was prepared in proportions of 5 : 5 : 90 (formalin : glacial acetic acid : 70 % ethanol;  Gerlach 1972 ). After 4 weeks, the fixative was replaced with 70 % ethanol. This 70 % ethanol was then replaced two more times within 10 days to further wash the fixative out. Final replacement of alcohol was used as a long-term storage medium. Segments for image analysis were rehydrated by immersion in 50 % ethanol and after 2–5 days in 30 % ethanol. Cross-sections were cut with a sledge microtome (Reichert, Vienna, Austria) at 10–20 µm thickness using disposable blades (Model A35, Feather Safety Razor Co. Ltd, Japan). For better contrast and tissue identification, sections were stained with safranin O (Gurr Microscopy Materials, BDH Chemicals Ltd, UK) for lignified cell walls (10 min) and with Janus green B (Gurr's, London, UK) for cytoplasm (10 min). Safranin O solution used 2 g of stain in 100 mL of distilled water ( Ruzin 1999 ) and Janus green B used 0.1 g of stain and 1 mL of glacial acetic acid in 100 mL of distilled water ( Conn  et al.  1960 ). Sections were rinsed in distilled water after each staining session. Afterwards, they were mounted in glycerol on a slide, covered with a cover slip and sealed with nail polish. Measurements were made only on cross-sections, but to assist in interpreting and identifying cell types, longitudinal tangential and radial sections and macerations were also made. For macerations, small shavings were placed in vials filled with Franklin's solution: glacial acetic acid and 6 % hydrogen peroxide in proportions of 1 : 1 ( Franklin 1945 ). These vials were loosely covered with Parafilm tape and heated in the oven at 60 °C for 1–2 days. Tissues were then rinsed with distilled water, stained with safranin O (10 min) and gently squashed onto a microscope slide.  A twig cross-section of  Grevillea parallela , Proteaceae. The radial sector of the stained section is shown on the left side and the processed image on the right. Colours in the processed image denote different tissue types: blue, vessel lumen; purple, vessel wall; green, rays; orange, axial parenchyma; brown, fibres. The scale bar corresponds to 100 µm.  Proportions of all major wood cell types (vessel wall and lumen, fibre wall and lumen, axial parenchyma, rays and tracheids) and their properties (mean vessel lumen area and mean fibre lumen and wall area) were quantified. Here, mean vessel lumen area is also called ‘mean vessel area’ for brevity. Mean vessel area, fibre lumen area and wall area were calculated as the arithmetic mean across all relevant cells (vessels or fibres) measured within a given radial sector of a sample. In addition to these traits we calculated theoretical maximum hydraulic conductivity (called here ‘theoretical conductivity’; also known as ‘potential conductivity’). Conductivity for the lumen of each conduit was calculated from the Hagen–Poiseuille expression (π r  4 )/(8 µ ), where  r  represents mean vessel lumen radius and  µ  represents water dynamic viscosity (assuming a standard viscosity value of 1 at 20 °C). The sum of all vessel lumen conductivities per unit cross-section is theoretical conductivity. This quantity expresses conductivity variation across species due to conduit diameters, but it should be thought of as the  theoretical  maximum since it does not capture effects of end-wall resistances, blockage by tyloses, effects of emboli, etc.  Traditionally, wood is considered a complex tissue composed of several cell types ( Evert 2006 ). However, we refer to those cell types as ‘tissues’ for brevity and also because they perform distinctly different functions. Anatomical terminology follows the ‘IAWA list of microscopic features for hardwood identification’ ( IAWA Committee 1989 ). Vascular and/or vasicentric tracheids occurred in 13 species and are referred to hereafter as tracheids. Tracheids were first determined in macerated wood and then identified on a cross-section on the basis of the number of pits and size of the pit border (both resembling that of vessel pits) and cell size ( IAWA Committee 1989 ;  Sano  et al.  2011 ). Axial apotracheal and paratracheal parenchyma were collectively measured as axial parenchyma. None of the species studied here had storied rays. Tissue types were expressed as the fraction of a tissue per cross-sectional area (Fig.  1 ). Tissue fractions of the area outside vessel lumen (non-vessel area) were calculated as tissue fraction multiplied by non-vessel area fraction. The term ‘non-vessel’ area is used for brevity and it includes vessel walls, fibre walls and lumens, axial and ray parenchyma, and tracheids. Non-vessel-lumen quantities are hereafter denoted by subscript ‘NV’, e.g. fibre wall fraction NV , wood density NV , etc. Fibre wall proportion in a given fibre was expressed as a proportion of the total fibre area. Fibre wall fraction was obtained by multiplying mean fibre wall proportion in a fibre by the fibre fraction per cross-section. Fibre lumen fraction was similarly calculated from mean fibre lumen proportion in a fibre multiplied by fibre fraction.  We collected measurements for 23 species, one of which occurred at two sites and was considered as two entities, giving a total of 24 data points analysed. Measurements were carried out on three replicate individuals per species and the trait values were averaged for comparisons across species. Wood density, vessel lumen, sum of ray and axial parenchyma, ray parenchyma and fibre wall fractions of total wood area as well as non-vessel wood area were all approximately normally distributed (Shapiro–Wilk test,  P  &lt; 0.05). Vessel wall, axial parenchyma, tracheids and fibre lumen fractions of total wood area as well as of non-vessel wood area were right-skewed and were transformed to generate approximately normally distributed variables. Log 10  transformations normalized all distributions with the exception of tracheid fraction and tracheid non-vessel fraction. We used ordinary least-squares regression to assess bivariate relationships (SigmaPlot, Systat, San Jose, CA, USA).  Tissue fractions for 24 species arranged in order of increasing wood density (from bottom to top). Large wood density numbers indicate total wood density whereas small numbers indicate non-vessel density (density NV ). Mean tissue fractions across all species are shown in the bar at the top of the figure.  Leucopogon ericoides  occurred in two sites and is treated here as two separate entities. An asterisk denotes  L. ericoides  from the cold-wet site as opposed to  L. ericoides  from the cold-dry site with no indicator.  Relationship between fraction of wood outside vessel lumens (fraction NV ) and the density of that non-vessel fraction (wood density NV ) among 24 Australian species. Fraction NV  = 1−vessel fraction. Each circle represents a different species (mean value from three replicates). Diagonal isolines represent contours of overall wood density, which increases towards the upper right. All axes are log scaled.  Relationship between non-vessel density (wood density NV ) and fibre fraction in non-vessel fraction (fibre fraction NV ). Each ‘donut’ circle symbolizes one species. The width of the donut border (black) represents fibre wall proportion within an individual fibre and the width of the hole (white) represents fibre lumen proportion. These proportions were estimated from individual fibres (as fibre wall area—or lumen area—divided by total fibre area), for 75–314 fibres per replicate (mean 170), and then across three replicates per species.  Relationships between non-vessel density (wood density NV ) and (A) fibre wall fraction in non-vessel fraction (fibre wall fraction NV ) and (B) fibre lumen fraction in non-vessel fraction (fibre lumen fraction NV ). Each circle represents a different species (mean value from three replicates). *** P  &lt; 0.001.  Relationship between the fraction of the non-vessel fraction that is fibre wall or is fibre lumen. Each symbol represents a different species (mean value from three replicates). Symbol diameter is proportional to non-vessel wood density (wood density NV ), with the biggest symbol indicating highest density NV  (0.92 g cm −3 ) and the smallest symbol indicating lowest density NV  (0.44 g cm −3 ).  The second most abundant tissue, parenchyma, was not correlated with density NV  nor were its components, rays and axial parenchyma (all  P &gt; 0.7). Similarly, vessel wall fraction NV  was unrelated to density NV . Nevertheless, both parenchyma and vessel wall fractions NV  indirectly affected density NV . Figure  6  illustrates that there was considerable variation in density NV  (indicated by symbol size) at a given fibre wall fraction NV , especially at lower wall fraction NV  (lower half of the graph), and considerable variation in density NV  at a given fibre lumen fraction NV , especially at lower lumen fraction NV  (left half of the graph). These variations in density NV  could be partially explained by parenchyma and vessel wall fractions NV . At a given fibre wall fraction NV , density NV  was positively correlated with parenchyma and vessel wall fractions NV  ( r  2  = 0.15,  P  = 0.064 and  r  2  = 0.29,  P  = 0.007, respectively) and negatively with fibre lumen fraction NV  ( r  2  = 0.45,  P  &lt; 0.001; all relationships tested against residuals from a regression of wood density NV  on fibre wall fraction NV ). Conversely at a given fibre lumen fraction NV  (i.e. tested against residuals from a regression of wood density NV  on fibre lumen fraction NV ), wood density NV  was negatively correlated with parenchyma fraction NV  ( r  2  = 0.28,  P  = 0.008), not correlated with vessel wall fraction NV  ( P  = 0.29) and positively correlated with fibre wall fraction NV  ( r  2  = 0.40,  P  &lt; 0.001). Additionally, parenchyma fraction NV  was tightly negatively correlated with total fibre fraction NV  ( r  2  = 0.74,  P  &lt; 0.001). The only remaining tissue, tracheids, occupied on average a very small fraction NV  and was not subjected to detailed analysis.  Relationships between wood density and (A) mean vessel area and (B) theoretical conductivity. Each circle represents a different species (mean value from three replicates). * P  &lt; 0.05, ** P  &lt; 0.01.  This study aimed to describe the anatomical components of wood density in twigs of 24 Australian tree and shrub species. Properties of fibres, the most abundant tissue, had the strongest effect on wood density variation, as has been shown in some previous studies ( Fujiwara  et al.  1991 ;  Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al . 2009 ). However, our results contribute to a more comprehensive understanding of wood structure and its influence on density in twigs. Here, we discuss in detail the properties of fibres and other tissues as components of density.  Density of tissue outside vessel lumens (density NV ), rather than vessel lumen fraction, was the main driver of overall wood density variation. This result agrees with a comparison made across 584 species that considered main stem wood ( Zanne  et al . 2010 ), implying that density NV  determines overall density in both twigs (this study) and main stems similarly. Accordingly, the discussion here is directed towards density NV  and individual tissue fractions within the non-vessel part of the wood (indicated by subscript ‘NV’, e.g. fibre wall fraction NV ). We compare these results with the results for overall wood density reported by other studies, on the basis that overall wood density and density NV  are closely correlated ( r  2  = 0.95,  P  &lt; 0.001, this study).  All tissue fractions NV  influence density NV  but fibre wall and lumen fractions NV  are the most important. The strong influence of fibre wall fraction NV  was due both to its high proportion and its variability, while the influence of fibre lumen fraction NV  was associated chiefly with its high variability ( c . 60-fold). Other studies have consistently found a positive relationship between fibre wall fraction and density: in trunk wood among 50 Japanese trees ( Fujiwara  et al.  1991 ) and 61 North and South American shrubs ( Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ); and in twig wood of 17 South African shrubs ( Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ). Fibre lumen fraction has received less attention but has also been shown (in concordance with our study) to have a negative relationship with wood density ( Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ;  Rana  et al.  2009 ). The second most abundant tissue, parenchyma, did not correlate with density NV  in our study nor in tree and shrub trunks ( Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ;  Poorter  et al.  2010 ;  Fichtler and Worbes 2012 ) but correlated negatively with twig wood density across 17 species ( Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ). These discrepancies might be caused by variable densities of parenchyma tissue itself ( Taylor 1969 ;  Fujiwara 1992 ;  Guilley and Nepveu 2003 ) or by varied correlations between parenchyma and fibre wall and lumen fractions (see below). Plausibly, these discrepancies could also stem from different relationships between ray and axial parenchyma. We did not find any cross-correlation between those two components of parenchyma nor were they individually related to density. In contrast,  Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  (2009)  reported that ray and axial parenchyma were negatively correlated with each other and individually correlated with density (axial parenchyma positively correlated, rays—negatively). In that study these links were strongly associated with environmental variables (MAP, MAT and AI). These findings imply that different functional trade-offs can be related to ray and axial parenchyma individually and also that their link is affected by climate. Possibly these trade-offs may be more pronounced in trunk wood, as opposed to the twig wood studied here.  We did not find a direct relationship between parenchyma and density NV . Nevertheless, our results imply that parenchyma together with fibre lumens can influence density NV  variation in a less direct way. At a given fibre wall fraction NV , density NV  depended on the parenchyma fraction NV  relative to fibre lumen fraction NV . Density NV  was marginally positively correlated with parenchyma fraction NV  and negatively with fibre lumen fraction NV . Parenchyma has higher density than fibre lumen, which has zero density. Therefore, higher parenchyma fraction NV  relative to fibre lumen fraction NV  increases density NV , and conversely higher fibre lumen fraction NV  decreases density NV . We note that parenchyma fraction NV  was only weakly correlated with density NV  at a given fibre wall fraction NV . This weak correlation possibly stems from variable parenchyma tissue densities ( Taylor 1969 ;  Fujiwara 1992 ;  Guilley and Nepveu 2003 ).  Fibre fraction NV  (sum of fibre wall and lumen fractions NV ) was not associated with density NV  because of wide variation in wall proportion within a fibre (top right to low right in Fig.  4 ).  Poorter  et al.  (2010)  suggested a similar explanation, but as far as we are aware, this issue has not been quantitatively clarified until now.  Anatomical traits that are not expressed as fractions of wood volume have less direct effects on density. We found that density NV  was correlated with fibre wall proportion within a fibre. Previous studies have also shown that density can be related to fibre lumen diameter ( Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al . 2009 ), fibre wall thickness ( Fujiwara  et al.  1991 ;  Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ) and fibre wall to lumen ratio ( Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ). We believe those traits would deliver a more insightful understanding of wood density when combined with information about fractions, e.g. the relationship among density NV , fibre fraction NV  and fibre wall proportion in a fibre, as described above. Similarly for mean vessel area, which in this study was weakly negatively correlated with wood density. Mean vessel area  per se  should not affect wood density. Rather, vessel fraction (vessel area multiplied by vessel number per area) should be causally linked with density variation.  A schematic representation of the graph in Fig.  6  flipped clockwise by 45°. The actual graph from Fig.  6  is repeated here in an inset and also flipped 45° clockwise. The diagram represents four cross-sections of potential anatomical structures in low-, medium- and high-density species. Each hexagon within the three squares indicates a fibre cell consisting of dark fibre wall and bright fibre lumen. The green area on the right of each square indicates parenchyma. Wood density NV  increases towards the top of the diagram.  Cross-sections through twigs of four species. The triangle arrangement corresponds to the one in Fig.  8  and so the cross-sections are examples of respective anatomies drawn in that figure. (A)  Bossiaea cinerea  (Fabaceae, wood density NV  0.92 g cm −3 ), (B)  Grevillea parallela  (Proteaceae, wood density NV  0.74 g cm −3 ), (C)  Corymbia intermedia  (Myrtaceae, wood density NV  0.78 g cm −3 ), (D)  Alphitonia excelsa  (Rhamnaceae, wood density NV  0.44 g cm −3 ). V, vessel; FW, fibre wall; FL, fibre lumen; A, axial parenchyma; R, ray parenchyma. Fibre lumens are indistinct in (A) due to their small sizes.  It has been shown that denser woods tend to operate at more negative minimum water potentials ( Ackerly 2004 ;  Bucci  et al.  2004 ;  Santiago  et al.  2004 ;  Jacobsen  et al.  2007 b  ,  2008 ;  Gotsch  et al.  2010 ) and have higher cavitation resistance ( Hacke  et al . 2001 ;  Jacobsen  et al . 2005 ;  Pratt  et al . 2007 ;  Lens  et al . 2011 ). However, we and previous literature have shown that wood density is most strongly related to fibre properties, not vessel properties. Thus, the relationship among wood density, minimum water potential and cavitation resistance does not appear to be directly influenced by wood density, but rather by a third, unexplained factor. Another element of hydraulic strategies is capacitance, which tends to be negatively correlated with wood density ( Meinzer  et al.  2003 ,  2008 ;  Pratt  et al.  2007 ;  Scholz  et al.  2007 ). Our results imply that capacitance water could be stored in fibre lumen or in parenchyma but the exact mechanism of this water storage and release is not known, nor is it clear what might be the advantage or disadvantage of fibre lumen capacitance compared with parenchyma capacitance. Density also plays a role in the mechanical behaviour of wood. It is a good predictor of mechanical strength and elasticity at a given wood diameter ( Chave  et al.  2009 ). However, it has also been shown that plants can compensate for mechanically weak wood by building thicker stems ( Anten and Schieving 2010 ;  Larjavaara and Muller-Landau 2010 ;  Butler  et al.  2011 ). Thick, low-density stems could be mechanically strong but their maintenance costs would be higher due to large surface area ( Larjavaara and Muller-Landau 2010 ). Additionally, our results suggest that in similar density woods maintenance costs per sapwood cross-sectional area could vary depending on wood anatomical structure. Namely, woods with high fraction of living parenchyma would presumably incur higher maintenance costs than woods with high fraction of non-living fibres. What then would be the advantage of high parenchyma fraction? Hypothetically, high parenchyma fraction could ensure high nutrient storage capacity, which may be beneficial in some ecological strategies. This issue and other questions about causal links between wood anatomical structure and ecological strategies require further investigation and open interesting pathways for future research.  Caution is needed when comparing results from twigs with results from main trunks. It is not proven that the relationships of wood density and anatomy are the same at the twig level as at the trunk level.  Taylor and Wooten (1973)  found that in five species vessel and fibre fractions shifted in the same direction with plant height, but this was not the case for ray fraction. Other studies examining association between vessel lumen fraction and wood density across a large number of species showed no relationship in the main trunks ( Martínez-Cabrera  et al.  2009 ;  Poorter  et al.  2010 ;  Zanne  et al.  2010 ) but a negative relationship in twigs ( Preston  et al.  2006 ;  Jacobsen  et al.  2007 a  ;  Mitchell  et al . 2008 ;  Gleason  et al.  2012 ). Such disparities indicate that the relationship between wood density and tissue fractions may conceivably be different in main trunks than in twigs, yet it is unclear how generally this is so.  Wood density has been proposed as a key plant functional trait and is related to ecological strategies ( Chave  et al.  2009 ) but relatively little is known about the underpinnings of these relationships. This study clarifies the anatomical basis for wood density variation across species. It shows that wood density depends on anatomical structure, but also that a range of very different structures can result in very similar wood density, especially among species with medium density NV  (here, 0.60–0.85 g cm −3 ). This conclusion suggests that there may be a wider range of ecological strategies among such species. Taken together, these findings imply that twig wood density should not be considered as an unambiguous indicator of plant ecological strategies. We hope this research will enhance the interpretation and design of ecological studies related to wood density.  This work has been supported by the Macquarie University Research Excellence Scholarship (Australia) and the Australian Research Council Discovery Project grant  DP0877064  awarded, respectively, to K.Z. and M.W.  All authors contributed to the analysis of the results, writing and editing of the manuscript. D.W.B devised site selection. K.Z., D.W.B and S.M.G. carried out fieldwork. K.Z. performed anatomical work.  None declared.   The following Supporting Information is available in the online version of this article –    File 1.  Table. Details of the four sites sampled in this study.   File 2.  Table. Species traits: wood density and tissue fractions.   File 3.  Table. Species traits: wood density and tissue fractions of non-vessel fraction.   File 4.  Table. Species traits: mean vessel area and theoretical conductivity.  We thank Judy and Eddie Howitt, John and Jill Bignell, and National Parks and State Forests staff in Queensland and Tasmania for their hospitality and sites access. Parks and Wildlife Service of Tasmania and Queensland gave permission for plant material collection. Macquarie University Microscopy Unit kindly provided facilities to carry out anatomical work. Many thanks to Steven Jansen, editor Tim Brodribb and two anonymous reviewers for constructive comments on earlier versions of this manuscript. Wendy Noble and Luen-Hsien Chang also provided useful feedback on earlier versions of this manuscript. We are grateful to Comparative Ecology Lab members for constructive conversations about the research presented here. 