Development of expressed sequence tag and expressed sequence tag–simple sequence repeat marker resources for <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>Artificial inoculation on plants and banana leaf pieces with <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic> spp., responsible for Sigatoka leaf spot diseasesClass III peroxidases in plant defence reactionsGapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programsReactive oxygen species intermediates mediate a systemic signal network in the establishment of plant immunityCaracterização agronômica e molecular de genótipos diplóides melhorados de bananeiraQuality improvement of cultivated MusaGene ontology: tool for the unification of biologyGenomes, diversity and resistance gene analogues in <italic>Musa</italic> speciesTransposable element contributions to plant genome evolutionTransgenic potato plants expressing soybean β-1,3-endoglucanase gene exhibit an increased resistance to <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> RPM1 disease resistance gene product is a peripheral plasma membrane protein that is degraded coincident with the hypersensitive responseIsolation and characterization of microsatellite markers from <italic>Musa balbisiana</italic>Reactive oxygen species and cellular interactions between <italic>Mycosphaerella fijiensis</italic> and bananaA BAC end view of the <italic>Musa accuminata</italic> genomeMolecular cloning of a metallothionein-like gene from <italic>Nicotiana glutinosa</italic> L. and its induction by wounding and tobacco mosaic virus infectionDNA sequence quality trimming and vector removalA platform for efficient genotyping in <italic>Musa</italic> using microsatellite markers<italic>Mycosphaerella fijiensis</italic>, the black leaf streak pathogen of banana: progress towards understanding pathogen biology and detection, disease development, and the challenges of controlBlast2GO: a comprehensive suite for functional analysis in plant genomicsDetection of single sequence repeats polymorphisms in denaturing polyacrylamide sequencing gel by silver stainingGenetic characterization of banana cultivars (<italic>Musa</italic> spp.) from Brazil using microsatellite markersIsolation and characterization of microsatellite loci from a commercial cultivar of <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>Utilization of molecular genetic techniques in support of plantain and banana improvementGermins: a diverse protein family important for crop improvementThe phenylpropanoid pathway and plant defence—a genomics perspectiveHost plant resistance to <italic>Radopholus similis</italic> in a diploid banana hybrid populationProteomic analysis of pathogenesis-related proteins (PRs) induced by compatible and incompatible interactions of pepper mild mottle virus (PMMoV) in <italic>Capsicum chinense</italic> L3 plantsIsolation of EST-derived microsatellite markers for genotyping the A and B genomes of wheatBase-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred II. Error probabilitiesPlant transposable elements: where genetics meets genomicsA modified CTAB DNA extraction procedure for <italic>Musa</italic> and <italic>Ipomoea</italic>The Gene Ontology project in 2008The hypersensitive response facilitates plant infection by the necrotrophic pathogen <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>Strategies for development of fungus-resistant transgenic plantsTransferable EST-SSR markers for the study of polymorphism and genetic diversity in bread wheatMetallothioneinPlant disease resistance genesCharacteristics, development and mapping of <italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> derived EST-SSRs in allotetraploid cottonGlutathione and glutathione-dependent enzymes represent a co-ordinately regulated defence against oxidative stressDomestication, genomics and the future for bananaA saturated SSR/DArT linkage map of <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> addressing genome rearrangements among bananasRepetitive part of the banana (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic>) genome investigated by low-depth 454 sequencingA novel stress-inducible metallothionein-like gene from riceThe plant immune systemMolecular breeding in genus <italic>Musa</italic>: a strong case for SSR marker technologyThe KEGG resource for deciphering the genomeGeneration and comparison of EST-derived SSRs and SNPs in barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.)Nonrandom distribution and frequencies of genomic and EST-derived microsatellite markers in rice, wheat, and barleySequence tagged microsatellite site (STMS) markers in the MusaceaeInsights into the <italic>Musa</italic> genome: syntenic relationships to rice and between <italic>Musa</italic> speciesDifferential expression and characterization of three metallothionein-like genes in Cavendish banana (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic>)Use of molecular markers in banana and plantain improvementGlutathione and a UV light-induced glutathione S transferase are involved in signaling to chalcone synthase in cell culturesRIN4 interacts with <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> type III effector molecules and is required for RPM1-mediated resistance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RIN4 is a target of the type III virulence effector AvrRpt2 and modulates RPS2-mediated resistanceIdentification of genes differentially expressed during ripening of bananaMap-based cloning of a protein kinase gene conferring disease resistance in tomatoDifferential induction of distinct glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferases of wheat by xenobiotics and by pathogen attackPlant NBS-LRR proteins: adaptable guardsAnalysis of non-TIR NBS-LRR resistance gene analogs in <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> Colla: isolation, RFLP marker development, and physical mappingCharacterization of novel microsatellite markers in <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> subsp. <italic>burmannicoides</italic>, var. Calcutta 4Candidate resistance gene discovery: resistance gene analog characterization and differential gene expression analysis in <italic>Musa</italic>-<italic>Mycosphaerella</italic> host-pathogen interactionsGenomes, diversity and resistance gene analogs in <italic>Musa</italic> speciesGenome-wide analysis of phenylpropanoid defence pathwaysPAMP-triggered basal immunity in plantsSecondary polyploids, heterosis, and evolutionary crop breeding for further improvement of the plantain and banana (<italic>Musa</italic> spp. L.) genomeTIGR gene indices clustering tools (TGICL): a software system for fast clustering of large EST datasetsAnalysis of expressed sequence tags derived from a compatible <italic>Mycosphaerella fijiensis</italic>-banana interactionThe first set of EST resource for gene discovery and marker development in pigeonpea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> L.)Barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) oxalate oxidase is a manganese-containing enzymePlant metallothioneinsGenomics of banana and plantain (<italic>Musa</italic> spp.), major staple crops in the tropicsPRIMER 3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmersAnalysis of expressed sequence tags from <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> ssp. <italic>burmannicoides</italic>, var. Calcutta 4 (AA) leaves submitted to temperature stressesReceptor-like kinases from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> form a monophyletic gene family related to animal receptor kinasesA receptor kinase-like protein encoded by the rice disease resistance gene, <italic>Xa21</italic>MIPSPlantsDB–plant database resource for integrative and comparative plant genome researchMapping and analysis of simple sequence repeats in the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> genomeComparing signaling mechanisms engaged in pattern-triggered and effector-triggered immunityHigh-throughput screening of suppression subtractive hybridisation cDNA libraries using DNA microarray analysisSignificance of inducible defense related proteins in infected plantsGenic microsatellite markers in plants: features and applicationsAn epidermis/papilla-specific oxalate oxidase-like protein in the defence response of barley attacked by the powdery mildew fungusExpression of β-1,3-glucanase in flax causes increased resistance to fungiAssociation between molecular markers and blast resistance in an advanced backcross population of riceMolecular characterization of the oxalate oxidase involved in the response of barley to the powdery mildew fungusThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Many varieties of banana (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic>) lack resistance to biotic stresses. An EST collection was developed, including transcripts expressed in banana-<italic>Mycosphaerella fijiensis</italic> interactions. Developed polymorphic gene-derived SSR markers are applicable for genetic mapping, diversity characterization and marker assisted breeding.Banana (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic>) is a crop contributing to global food security. Many varieties lack resistance to biotic stresses, due to sterility and narrow genetic background. The objective of this study was to develop an expressed sequence tag (EST) database of transcripts expressed during compatible and incompatible banana–<italic>Mycosphaerella fijiensis</italic> (<italic>Mf</italic>) interactions. Black leaf streak disease (BLSD), caused by <italic>Mf</italic>, is a destructive disease of banana. Microsatellite markers were developed as a resource for crop improvement.cDNA libraries were constructed from <italic>in vitro</italic>-infected leaves from BLSD-resistant <italic>M. acuminata</italic> ssp. <italic>burmaniccoides</italic> Calcutta 4 (MAC4) and susceptible <italic>M. acuminata</italic> cv. Cavendish Grande Naine (MACV). Clones were 5′-end Sanger sequenced, ESTs assembled with TGICL and unigenes annotated using BLAST, Blast2GO and InterProScan. Mreps was used to screen for simple sequence repeats (SSRs), with markers evaluated for polymorphism using 20 diploid (AA) <italic>M. acuminata</italic> accessions contrasting in resistance to <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic> leaf spot diseases.A total of 9333 high-quality ESTs were obtained for MAC4 and 3964 for MACV, which assembled into 3995 unigenes. Of these, 2592 displayed homology to genes encoding proteins with known or putative function, and 266 to genes encoding proteins with unknown function. Gene ontology (GO) classification identified 543 GO terms, 2300 unigenes were assigned to EuKaryotic orthologous group categories and 312 mapped to Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes pathways. A total of 624 SSR loci were identified, with trinucleotide repeat motifs the most abundant in MAC4 (54.1 %) and MACV (57.6 %). Polymorphism across <italic>M. acuminata</italic> accessions was observed with 75 markers. Alleles per polymorphic locus ranged from 2 to 8, totalling 289. The polymorphism information content ranged from 0.08 to 0.81.This EST collection offers a resource for studying functional genes, including transcripts expressed in banana–<italic>Mf</italic> interactions. Markers are applicable for genetic mapping, diversity characterization and marker-assisted breeding.Commercially cultivated varieties of banana and plantains are derived from the progenitors <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> Colla (AA) and <italic>Musa balbisiana</italic> Colla (BB). These crops are of extreme importance across the world's tropical and sub-tropical regions, contributing to both food security and export commodity revenue, with a global annual production in excess of 97 million tonnes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C31">FAOSTAT 2009</xref>).Cultivated bananas have evolved from hybridization of wild species of <italic>M. acuminata</italic> (A genome) and <italic>M. balbisiana</italic> (B genome). In contrast to fertility in wild species, many of today's commercial cultivars are sterile triploids or diploids, with fruit development via parthenocarpy. Together with female sterility, this results in either seedless fruits or non-viable seeds. Consequential asexually driven evolution has resulted in a narrow genetic base, with the crop often lacking resistance to pests and diseases. For this reason, the industry has witnessed numerous pathogen and pest outbreaks. Of the &gt;40 fungal diseases affecting banana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C45">Jones 1999</xref>), the foliar pathogen <italic>Mycosphaerella fijiensis</italic> (<italic>Mf</italic>) is today one of the most threatening. Responsible for black leaf streak disease (BLSD) in banana, commonly known as black Sigatoka, yield losses range from 20 to 80 % (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C17">Churchill 2011</xref>), with premature fruit ripening also affecting export markets. Although cultural practices contribute to disease control, without the integrated use of chemicals their impact is insufficient. Commercial banana plantations are therefore dependent upon long-term use of agrochemicals, which implies a constant threat for the emergence of fungicide-tolerant or -resistant <italic>Mf</italic> strains. The development of disease-resistant genotypes is today therefore regarded as the most cost-effective long-term control strategy available for the <italic>Musa</italic> industry.Current breeding strategies for <italic>Musa</italic> rely upon sexually active wild or improved fertile <italic>M. acuminata</italic> diploids, which, in contrast to most commercial <italic>Musa</italic> varieties, where genetic diversity is fixed by vegetative propagation, serve as sources of resistance to biotic and abiotic stresses for transfer across varieties. Programmes for the development of tetraploid hybrids, for example, are typically generated via crosses between semi-fertile established triploids and wild or improved fertile diploid parents with agronomic traits of interest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C68">Ortiz 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C6">Amorim <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Such breeding strategies can, however, have only limited success, given low numbers or absence of seeds. Complementary strategies for resolving these constraints for perennial crop breeding are therefore required.Isolation of candidate genes of agronomic interest and development of specific molecular markers for application in molecular genotyping and marker-assisted selection (MAS) allow for both accelerated conventional breeding and gene-transfer programmes as strategies for genetic improvement. Expressed sequence tags (ESTs) are 5′- or 3′-end single-pass-sequenced portions of randomly isolated cDNA clones, which as such represent part of the transcribed region of the genome in given conditions. As a rapid approach for gene discovery and analysis of gene expression and regulation, data can also be exploited for the development of functional genetic markers. For <italic>Musa</italic>, a total of only 15 464 ESTs in <italic>M. acuminata</italic> and 5289 in <italic>M. balbisiana</italic> are currently publically available in GenBank (accessed March 2012). These datasets have been generated from a number of cultivars, plant tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C74">Roux <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), during abiotic stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C76">Santos <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>) and post-harvest ripening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C58">Manrique-Trujillo <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). Only limited analysis of gene expression in response to biotic stresses has been reported (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C88">Van den Berg <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C70">Portal <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).Highly variable microsatellites or simple sequence repeats (SSRs) are abundant in eukaryotic genomes, and may occur in both coding and non-coding regions (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C80">Tamana and Khan 2005</xref>). Typically they are reproducible, somatically stable, highly polymorphic, co-dominant, multi-allelic markers, with application in population genetics, genetic mapping and molecular breeding. Locus-by-locus <italic>de novo</italic> development is costly and time consuming, in contrast to mining from EST sequence databases. As EST–SSR markers originate from transcribed genes, they offer potential for analysis of functional diversity in populations and application in MAS, through utilization of markers that either originate from a gene responsible for a desirable phenotypic trait, or that co-localize with a particular quantitative trait locus (QTL) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C90">Varshney <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). Applications of SSR markers in <italic>Musa</italic> have focused on evolution and taxonomy (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C51">Lagoda <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>), genotyping (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C24">Crouch <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C21">Creste <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C23">Christelová <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), and, more recently, linkage map saturation (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C42">Hippolyte <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). In comparison with other important crops, however, still relatively few SSR markers have been developed for <italic>M. acuminata</italic> and <italic>M. balbisiana</italic> material (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C47">Kaemmer <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C51">Lagoda <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C24">Crouch <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C12">Buhariwalla <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C22">Creste <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C14">Cheung and Town 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C63">Miller <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). Considering that alleles can be monomorphic or even absent when applied across cultivars, the number of useful SSR loci available remains limited.This work describes the generation of an EST resource for <italic>M. acuminata</italic> and its mining for gene-derived SSR markers. The annotated ESTs were generated from two cDNA libraries constructed from BLSD-resistant <italic>M. acuminata</italic> ssp. <italic>burmannicoides</italic> var. Calcutta 4 (MAC4) and BLSD-susceptible <italic>M. acuminata</italic> subgroup Cavendish cv. Grande Naine (MACV) leaves <italic>in vitro</italic> infected with <italic>Mf</italic>. The wild diploid cultivar Calcutta 4 is widely employed in breeding programmes as a source of resistance to fungal pathogens and nematodes. It has also been used as a model for comparative genomics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C14">Cheung and Town 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C52">Lescot <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), functional genomics (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C76">Santos <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>) and candidate resistance gene discovery (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C8">Azhar and Heslop-Harrison 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C62">Miller <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). A subset of the EST–SSR marker loci was screened for polymorphism across <italic>M. acuminata</italic> accessions contrasting in resistance to <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic> leaf spot diseases.<italic>In vitro</italic>-derived, 6-month-old whole plants of <italic>M. acuminata</italic> Calcutta 4 (BLSD resistant) and Cavendish Grande Naine (BLSD susceptible) (<italic>Musa</italic> International Transit Centre accessions ITC0249 and ITC0654, respectively) were maintained in a greenhouse under a 12-h light/12-h dark photoperiod at 25 °C and 85 % relative humidity. Leaf disc materials (squares of 36 cm<sup>2</sup>) for the two contrasting <italic>M. acuminata</italic> cultivars were collected from the two youngest leaves and spray inoculated on the adaxial surface using conidiospore suspensions (3 × 10<sup>3</sup> mL<sup>−1</sup>) of the <italic>Mf</italic> strain CIRAD89. Inoculated leaf discs were incubated in a climatic chamber at 25 °C, again under a 12-h light/12-h dark photoperiod. Calcutta 4 was shown to be highly resistant, with a typical incompatible response, whereas Cavendish was found to be highly susceptible, displaying symptoms of a compatible interaction. Seven replicate leaf discs were prepared to ensure sufficient material for RNA purification and microscopic examination following infection. The <italic>in vitro</italic>-infected leaf disc tissues were maintained for extended periods in a green, non-senescent state, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C1">Abadie <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref>.Two cDNA libraries were constructed, the first from a pool of RNA samples isolated from infected leaf discs at early time points in the incompatible interaction [4, 6, 7, 10, 12, 14 days after inoculation (DAI)] [<italic>M. acuminata</italic> ssp. <italic>burmaniccoides</italic> Calcutta 4 (MAC4)] and the second from pooled late time points in the compatible interaction (19, 25, 31, 39 DAI) [<italic>M. acuminata</italic> cv. Cavendish Grande Naine (MACV)]. This approach was adopted not only to generate EST resources, but also to potentially enrich the unigene set for genes involved in defence responses during this host–pathogen interaction. Collected leaf material was flash frozen in liquid nitrogen to prevent RNA degradation and stored at −80 °C. Total RNA was extracted from leaf tissue using the Trizol kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), according to the manufacturer's instructions. Total RNA quantification and quality analyses were conducted on an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA). Poly A<sup>+</sup> RNA was isolated from total RNA using a MicroPoly(A)Purist™ mRNA Isolation Kit (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA), according to the manufacturer's instructions. Full-length cDNA libraries were constructed using the Creator SMART cDNA Library Construction kit (Clontech, Palo Alto, CA, USA). Poly A<sup>+</sup> RNA quality was compared with an in-house control, and cDNA synthesized by reverse transcriptase, via long-distance polymerase chain reaction (PCR). High-quality cDNA was isolated via fractioning, digested with SfI and ligated to the plasmid cloning vector pDRN-LIB (Clontech). Transformation into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and recombinant selection on selection medium followed the manufacturer's protocols. Library qualities were examined by colony PCR and PCR amplification of plasmid inserts from randomly selected cDNA clones, with over 90 % showing inserts &gt;400 bp. A total of 27 648 clones were prepared for each cDNA library and preserved as glycerol cultures.Randomly selected clones from each cDNA library were 5′-end single-pass di-deoxy-based Sanger sequenced in Brazil at the Universidade Católica de Brasília, Embrapa Recursos Genéticos e Biotecnologia and in Japan at the National Institute of Agrobiological Resources using BigDye chemistry (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). A total of 14 272 sequences were generated from the MAC4 library and 7623 from the MACV library. Sequence analysis began with base calling and quality assignment using the program Phred and a <italic>Q</italic> &lt; 16 quality score (<italic>Q</italic>) threshold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C30">Ewing and Green 1998</xref>). Low-quality sequences were removed using the program Lucy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C16">Chou and Holmes 2001</xref>) and vectors were masked using Cross_Match (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C30">Ewing and Green 1998</xref>). Sequences were screened for contaminant <italic>E. coli</italic>, chloroplast and mitochondrial DNAs utilizing the SSAHA package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C82">Website 1</xref>, <bold><uri xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/analysis/SSAHA/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/analysis/SSAHA/</uri></bold>). The processed sequences were assembled into sequence consensi with the program TGICL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C69">Pertea <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>).To annotate unique transcripts (unigenes) and identify putative functions, similarity searches were performed on assembled sequences using the Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) suite of programs, version 2.2.24+ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C3">Altschul <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>), against distinct databases to identify protein functional categories [NCBI non-redundant sequence database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C83">Website 2</xref>, <bold><uri xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/COG/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/COG/</uri></bold>); The Swiss-Prot Database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C84">Website 3</xref>, <bold><uri xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/downloads" xlink:type="simple">http://www.uniprot.org/downloads</uri></bold>, uniprot_sprot_ release of 2010 04 23); The TAIR Database: The Arabidopsis Information Resource (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C85">Website 4</xref>, <bold><uri xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.arabidopsis.org/</uri></bold>, Tair_9_pep_ release 2009 06 19); KOG (clusters of eukaryotic orthologous proteins from complete eukaryotic genomes); LSE (lineage specific expansions); and TWOG (clusters for two species)]. BLASTX criteria accounting for identity significance were that the alignment length should be &gt;100 amino acids and the expected value (<italic>E</italic>) ≤ 1<italic>E</italic><sup>−10</sup>. Species distribution for <italic>Musa</italic> unigenes was calculated via homology searches against all plant proteins in the NCBI NR database, based upon best hit for each analysed sequence. An <italic>E</italic>-value ≤ 1<italic>E</italic><sup>−3</sup> was set as the threshold to consider a BLAST hit significant. Unigene annotation based on protein domain comparisons with InterPro, Pfam and COG databases was conducted using InterProScan (version 4.5, <bold><uri xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/software/unix/iprscan/" xlink:type="simple">ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/software/unix/iprscan/</uri></bold>), HMMER3 (<bold><uri xlink:href="http://hmmer.janelia.org" xlink:type="simple">http://hmmer.janelia.org</uri></bold>) and BLAST analyses. Gene placement prediction was performed using Metabolic pathway annotation against the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C48">Kanehisa <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Functional classification of annotated unigenes according to the categories of molecular function, biological process and cellular component was conducted using Blast2GO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C18">Conesa and Götz 2008</xref>), following the gene ontology (GO) scheme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C19">Consortium 2008</xref>).Transposable elements (TEs) were identified during EST pre-processing steps using RepeatMasker Open-3.0 (<bold><uri xlink:href="http://www.repeatmasker.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.repeatmasker.org</uri></bold>) with the MIPS Repeat Element Database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C78">Spannagl <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Repeats were classified into superfamily, family and class according to version 4.3 of mips-REdat.The isolated RNA samples used for cDNA library construction were normalized and 10 µg of each size separated via agarose gel electrophoresis (1.2 %) under denaturing conditions. Northern blot analyses of candidate gene expression at different time points during <italic>Musa</italic>–<italic>Mf</italic> interactions in the contrasting cultivars were carried out using Nylon Hybond N+ membranes according to the manufacturer's instructions. Polymerase chain reaction fragments of three selected cDNA clones of interest (GenBank accession numbers JK533438, JK545622 and JK535529) were labelled with α-<sup>32</sup>P dCTP via random hexanucleotide-primed DNA synthesis using the Megaprime<sup>TM</sup> DNA Labelling System RPN 1607 (Amersham Biosciences, Piscataway, NJ, USA). Membrane hybridization signals were observed after exposure on an autoradiography Storm 820 imaging system (Amersham Biosciences, Piscataway, NJ, USA).A computational search using the program Mreps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C86">Website 5</xref>, <bold><uri xlink:href="http://bioinfo.lifl.fr/mreps/" xlink:type="simple">http://bioinfo.lifl.fr/mreps/</uri></bold>) was used to locate perfect SSRs across EST subsets (2186 ESTs from the MAC4 library and 2363 from the MACV library). Microsatellite detection required the presence of at least two repeating units (e.g. GC) spanning &gt;10 bp. Flanking forward and reverse primers were designed using the program Primer 3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C75">Rozen and Skaletsky 2000</xref>).<bold>Diploid (AA)</bold> <italic>M. acuminata</italic> <bold>accessions contrasting in resistance to</bold> <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic> <bold>leaf spot diseases selected for use in SSR marker validation</bold>.<sup>a</sup>Not defined.<bold>Macroscopic and microscopic observation of infected tissues during the time course interaction with <italic>Mf</italic>.</bold> Symptoms of apoptosis were apparent only in Calcutta 4 (19–31 DAI), while cell death attributed to necrotic disease stages was restricted to Cavendish Grande Naine (DAI31). DAI, days after inoculation; magn, magnified.For the development of an EST dataset for <italic>M. acuminata</italic>, two full-length cDNA libraries were constructed, from MAC4 and MACV leaf tissue samples, both <italic>in vitro</italic> infected with <italic>Mf</italic>. The estimation of insert size via both restriction digestion with SfI and PCR amplification revealed averages in excess of 400 bp, showing that both cDNA libraries were of high quality.From a total of 10 995 single-pass 5′-sequenced clones in the MAC4 cDNA library, vector trimming and quality analyses resulted in 9333 high-quality reads. In the case of the MACV cDNA library, from an initial 4157 clones, a total of 3962 high-quality reads were generated. Size distribution analysis revealed a mean length of ESTs following quality filtering and vector trimming of 370 bp for MAC4-derived ESTs and 494 bp for MACV-derived ESTs. The most common length distribution categories were between 201 and 500 bp for MAC4 ESTs, and between 401 and 500 bp in the case of MACV ESTs. All high-quality sequences were deposited in NCBI with GenBank accession numbers JK531581–JK540913 (MAC4) and JK542313–JK546274 (MACV).<bold>Summary of EST quality and sequence assembly from combined MAC4 and MACV datasets.</bold> (A) Length distribution of the <italic>M. acuminata</italic> ESTs; (B) length distribution of the assembled <italic>M. acuminata</italic> unigene contigs; (C) length distribution of the <italic>M. acuminata</italic> unigene singletons; (D) frequency and distribution of ESTs in assembled <italic>M. acuminata</italic> unigene contigs.<bold>Species distribution of <italic>M. acuminata</italic> unigenes shown as the percentage of the total homologous monocotyledon plant sequences.</bold> The best BLAST hits of each sequence were analysed.<bold>Representation of <italic>M. acuminata</italic> unigenes classified in functional groups.</bold> The GO hits were assigned to categories (A) molecular function, (B) biological process and (C) cellular component.A total of 2300 unigenes were assigned to KOG categories: amino acid transport and metabolism (72/1.8 %), carbohydrate transport and metabolism (110/2.8 %), cell cycle control, cell division, chromosome partitioning (28/0.7 %), cell motility, lipid transport and metabolism (1/0.02 %), cell wall/membrane/envelope biogenesis (28/0.7 %), chromatin structure and dynamics (23/0.5 %), coenzyme transport and metabolism (19/0.4 %), cytoskeleton (49/1.2 %), defence mechanisms (26/0.6 %), energy production and conversion (127/3 %), extracellular structures (8/0.2 %), function unknown (160/4 %), general function prediction (319/7.9 %), inorganic ion transport and metabolism (67/1.6 %), intracellular trafficking, secretion and vesicular transport (119/2.9 %), lipid transport and metabolism (56/1.4 %), nucleotide transport and metabolism (21/0.5 %), post-translational modification, protein turnover, chaperones (320/8 %), replication, recombination and repair (15/0.3 %), RNA processing and modification (89/2.2 %), secondary metabolite biosynthesis, transport and catabolism (53/1.3 %), signal transduction mechanisms (172/4.3 %), transcription (109/2.7 %), translation, ribosomal structure and biogenesis (289/7 %), and no hits (1696/42.5 %) [see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/pls030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">ADDITIONAL INFORMATION 1 and 2</ext-link>].Defence-related transcript functions identified according to the KOG classification across the unigenes comprised nine germin/oxalate oxidases (OXOs), three regulators of pathogen resistance responses of RPS2 and RPM1 genes, two dual-specificity phosphatases, two flavonol reductase/cinnamoyl-CoA reductases, two HVA22/DP1 gene product-related proteins, two macrophage migration inhibitory factors, a drought-induced protein, a bax-mediated apoptosis inhibitor TEGT/BI-1, a BPI/LBP/CETP family protein, a mercaptopyruvate sulfurtransferase/thiosulfate sulfurtransferase, a predicted protein tyrosine phosphatase, and a protein involved in the control of unknown local host defence mechanisms to pathogens.From a total of 172 predicted unigenes classified to the KOG category of signal transduction, a number are typically associated with plant immunity mechanisms. These included 20 unigenes characterized as ‘Receptor protein kinase containing LRR repeats’. Other significant findings were 20 serine/threonine protein kinases, two mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase (MAP2K) and five WRKY superfamily transcription factors. Further manual mining also revealed predicted unigenes typically associated with defence responses in plants: five isoflavone reductase/pinoresinol-lariciresinol reductase/phenylcoumaran benzylic ether reductases (phenylpropanoid/flavonoid pathway); 14 glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferases (GSTs), two metallothioneins, three superoxide dismutases (SOD) (plant detoxification); one 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase (ethylene biosynthesis); three β-1,3 glucanases (PR 2 proteins); one transcription factor containing NAC and TS-N domains (plant defence); one cysteine proteinase inhibitor B (cystatin B) (plant defence); and six glycolate oxidases [production of reactive oxygen species (ROS)].<bold>Northern blot analysis of expression of selected defence-related <italic>M. acuminata</italic> unigenes during the time course interaction with <italic>Mf</italic>.</bold> Arrows show differential gene expression between the tested cultivars for each gene probe.<bold>Summary of</bold> <italic>M. acuminata</italic> <bold>unigenes mapped in KEGG pathways</bold>.<bold>Abundance and diversity of expressed TEs in</bold> <italic>M. acuminata</italic> <bold>EST datasets</bold>.<bold>Overview of SSR repeat abundance in</bold> <italic>M. acuminata</italic> <bold>ESTs and primer design statistics</bold>.<bold>Characteristics of polymorphic microsatellite loci isolated from</bold> <italic>M. acuminata</italic> <bold>Calcutta 4 and Cavendish Grande Naine EST data</bold>.Polymorphism was evaluated across 20 <italic>M. acuminata</italic> accessions.HE, expected heterozygosity under Hardy–Weinberg expectations; HO, observed heterozygosity; PIC, polymorphism information content.The objectives of this work were to generate an EST resource for studying functional genes in <italic>M. acuminata</italic>, which also included transcripts expressed in banana–<italic>Mf</italic> interactions during compatible and incompatible reactions. We also pursued the development of gene-based microsatellite markers as a resource for genetic mapping, diversity characterization and MAS of specific traits in conventional breeding populations.In total, 9333 high-quality ESTs were generated from MAC4 and 3964 from MACV. At the time of analysis in December 2011, only 15 464 ESTs were publically available for <italic>M. acuminata</italic>. This study therefore contributes almost a two-fold increase in EST resources for this species. BLASTX homology searches of the 3995 <italic>M. acuminata</italic> unigenes against monocotyledonous plant proteins in the NCBI NR database revealed 28.4 % of unigenes as potentially novel and exclusive to <italic>M. acuminata</italic>, with only 4.1 % of BLAST hits to existing <italic>Musa</italic> NR database proteins. This dataset therefore provided a significant contribution of value for gene discovery and validation of function for the genus.Functional categorization assigned a large number of unigenes to involvement in intracellular cell components, membranes, organelles, metabolic processes, translation, transport, oxidation and reduction processes, enzyme activity, binding, structural molecule activity and catalytic activity. Given the still limited characterization of gene expression during banana–<italic>Mf</italic> interactions (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C70">Portal <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), a strategy for potential enrichment of <italic>Musa</italic> EST resources to also include genes involved in defence responses was employed. Given that defence responses typically occur earlier in incompatible rather than compatible interactions, distinct time points for cDNA library preparation were chosen to reflect such expected differences. Although the sequences encoding activities related to response to stress, defence response and signal transduction were less represented, numerous unigene sequences potentially involved in plant effector-triggered immunity (ETI) and pathogen-associated molecular pattern (PAMP)-triggered immunity (PTI) were characterized. Pathogen-associated molecular pattern-triggered immunity is considered to be based upon interactions between host pattern recognition receptor-like kinases and conserved PAMPs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C67">Nürnberger and Kemmerling 2009</xref>), conserved across a microbial class and essential in fitness. Pathogen-associated molecular pattern-triggered immunity involves activation of a mitogen-associated protein kinase cascade and WRKY transcription factors (TFs), conferring resistance to the majority of potential pathogens. Effector-triggered immunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C46">Jones and Dangl 2006</xref>) is based upon co-evolution of plant resistance R-protein receptors and specific pathogen effector molecules, conferring resistance at the intra-specific level. Many downstream signal transduction components are shared between PTI and ETI, including an oxidative burst via the production of ROS and changes in plant hormone levels. Mitogen-activated protein kinase signalling cascades also occur in both PTI and ETI, with variations in duration probably responsible for differential downstream responses in the two immunity branches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C81">Tsuda and Katagiri 2010</xref>). Overall, a number of expressed genes potentially involved in different pathways in PTI or ETI were identified, the most abundant of which included host receptor genes involved in PAMP or pathogen effector recognition, unigenes involved in signalling mechanisms, phenylpropanoid/flavonoid pathway genes, phytohormone biosynthesis genes, pathogenesis-related protein coding unigenes and genes involved in plant detoxification.Distinct plant <italic>R</italic>-gene families are recognized as involved in ETI, based upon protein domain structure and biochemical function. The most abundant class encodes cytoplasmic receptor proteins containing nucleotide binding site-leucine-rich repeat (NBS-LRR) domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C38">Hammond-Kosack and Jones 1997</xref>). In rice, ∼400 NBS-LRR genes have been characterized, with around 150 present in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C61">McHale <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Conservation of motifs within <italic>R</italic>-genes, such as those present within NBS-LRR domains, have facilitated amplification in diverse plant taxa. Such work has been reported in <italic>Musa</italic>, with large-scale analyses of NBS-LRR <italic>R</italic>-gene family RGA diversity across the genus (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C62">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C65">Mohamad and Heslop-Harrison 2008</xref>). In the current study, three regulators of pathogen resistance responses of NBS-LRR <italic>R-</italic>genes RPS2 and RPM1 genes were identified in the transcribed unigene dataset. The RPM1 protein is known to be associated with the host plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C11">Boyes <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>), as is RPS2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C57">Mackey <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>), where they recognize modification in the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>negative regulator RPM1 interacting protein 4 (RIN4), target of <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> type III bacterial effector proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C56">Mackey <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>), triggering the hypersensitive response (HR) or programmed cell death of infected cells, characterized by the appearance of small necrotic lesions at infection sites. Other known plant <italic>R</italic>-gene classes include extracellular LRRs anchored by transmembrane domains (receptor-like proteins), extracellular LRRs linked to cytoplasmic serine–threonine kinase domains, intracellular serine–threonine kinases and proteins with a coiled-coil domain anchored to the cell membrane. EuKaryotic orthologous group-based analysis predicted a total of 20 unigenes with function assigned as ‘Receptor protein kinase containing LRR repeats’. Over 600 such receptor-like kinases (RLKs) have been characterized in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C77">Shiu and Bleecker 2001</xref>), with the disease ETI resistance gene <italic>Xa21</italic> being one of the earliest examples from this class, conferring durable resistance to <italic>Xanthomonas oryzae</italic> pv. <italic>oryzae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C79">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>). In a previous study in <italic>M. acuminata</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C64">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), sequence similarity analysis of amplification products generated using degenerate primers for RLKs identified numerous sequences with significant similarity to <italic>R</italic>-gene and RGA sequences for this class. A total of 20 serine/threonine protein kinases were also identified on the basis of KOG function assignment. Examples of such kinases include the intracellular cytoplasmic <italic>R</italic>-gene <italic>Pto</italic>, which was the first <italic>R</italic>-gene in tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) proved to confer resistance to <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. <italic>tomato</italic> strains that express the <italic>AvrPto</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C59">Martin <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>). Defence reactions associated with HR and programmed cell death are considered to be induced following <italic>AvrPto</italic> recognition in the presence of an NBS-LRR protein known as <italic>Prf</italic>, which is present in the <italic>Pto</italic> kinase gene cluster. Other significant findings in relation to unigenes typically involved in signal transduction from pathogen recognition to defence gene expression included two MAP2K and five WRKY superfamily transcription factors.Phenylpropanoids in plants are involved in a number of defence responses, acting as antimicrobial compounds (phytoanticipins and phytoalexins) and molecules involved in signalling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C26">Dixon <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C66">Naoumkina <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). EuKaryotic orthologous group classification revealed five isoflavone reductase/pinoresinol-lariciresinol reductase/phenylcoumaran benzylic ether reductases. Isoflavone reductase is an enzyme required for biosynthesis of the phytoalexin pterocarpan. Monolignols serve as precursors of plant lignins and lignans, which are composed of phenolic compounds and are involved in physical and chemical plant defence mechanisms. Cinnamoyl-CoA reductase is the first enzyme specific for monolignol synthesis. EuKaryotic orthologous group data identified two unigenes encoding this enzyme.Pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins were initially observed in tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>) and are now known to accumulate in diverse plant hosts when under pathogen attack. These structurally and functionally diverse proteins have been classified into 17 families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C89">van Loon <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Given that both HR observed in incompatible plant–pathogen interactions and subsequent systemic acquired resistance (SAR) to diverse pathogens are associated with accumulation of PR proteins in local and systemic tissues, such proteins are believed to contribute to resistance. Our unigene set included three β-1,3 glucanases, which are recognized as PR-2 family members. This widely studied family has been reported to limit activity in diverse fungal pathogens, through degradation of the cell wall component β-1,3 glucan. Up-regulation of β-1,3 glucanases in incompatible interactions has been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C28">Elvira <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), and over-expression analyses have confirmed involvement in resistance. For example, PR2 genes from soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic>) have been shown to confer resistance in potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>) to <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C10">Borkowska <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>) and in kiwi (<italic>Actinidea deliciosa</italic>) to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C35">Grover and Gowthaman 2003</xref>). Similarly, a PR2 gene from potato increased resistance to both <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> and <italic>Fusarium culmorum</italic> in flax (<italic>Linum usitatissimum</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C92">Wróbel-Kwiatkowska <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>).Numerous germin OXOs were encountered in the unigene sets. Within the germin protein family, OXOs have been reported to play roles in calcium regulation, oxalate metabolism and response to pathogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C25">Davidson <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Evidence for the latter includes up-regulation in cereals in response to powdery mildew (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C94">Zhou <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>) and co-segregation of markers for OXO genes and with rice blast resistance QTLs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C93">Wu <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Oxalate oxidases can catalyse the conversion of ROS to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C72">Requena and Bornemann 1999</xref>), important components of HR in plants. Hydrogen peroxide is involved in cell wall cross-linking and messenger activity for activation of defence genes, triggering SAR. Also reported as a molecule necessary for phytoalexin biosynthesis, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> has been shown to have direct antimicrobial activity, causing oxidation of invading pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C91">Wei <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>). Our northern blot data revealed early increased expression (4–6 DAI) of OXO in resistant Calcutta 4 only, suggesting a possible involvement in ROS and associated HR components.EuKaryotic orthologous group-derived mining revealed 14 GSTs in the unigene sets. Glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferases appear to be ubiquitous in plants, with a function in endogenous and xenobiotic compound detoxification, such as herbicides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C40">Hayes and McLellan 1999</xref>). Up-regulation has been shown in individual GSTs during pathogen attack in numerous plant species (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C60">Mauch and Dudler 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C4">Alvarez <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>), with likely involvement in detoxification of products of oxidative stress during HR, thus limiting both cell damage and the extent of cell death. Expression in <italic>Mf–M. acuminata</italic> compatible interactions has recently been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C70">Portal <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). The potential role of GSTs in cell signalling pathways has also been suggested, with a GST from parsley involved in UV-dependent signal transduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C55">Loyall <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>).Metallothioneins are low-molecular-weight polypeptides rich in cysteine residues. Present across prokaryotes and eukaryotes, they play a role in detoxification and homeostasis, sequestering metal ions such as Cu<sup>2</sup>, Zn<sup>2</sup> and Cd<sup>2</sup>, and preventing mutations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C37">Hamer 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C73">Robinson <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>). Up-regulation has been observed in plants in response to increased metal concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C44">Hsieh <italic>et al</italic>. 1995</xref>). Since plants experience oxidative stresses following pathogen infection, it has also been argued that this protein family might be associated with regulation of intracellular redox potential and oxygen detoxification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C37">Hamer 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C15">Choi <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>), protecting cells from damaging effects of ROS. Previous reports also indicate differential regulation of metallothioneins after viral infection in tobacco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C15">Choi <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>), temperature stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C44">Hsieh <italic>et al</italic>. 1995</xref>) and foliar senescence. Four distinct types (MT1–MT4) have been described in plants, according to distribution of cysteine residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C73">Robinson <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>). Expression of MT1 is generally more associated with vascular tissues and roots, MT2 with shoots and leaves, MT3 with leaves and mature fruits, and MT4 with seed tissues. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C53">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. (2002)</xref> reported isolation of MT2 and MT3 in banana, with expression influenced in response to ethylene and metals. More recent examination of transcripts has reported that metallothionein-like genes are abundant in <italic>M. acuminata</italic> Calcutta 4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C76">Santos <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). Our study confirmed this, with isolation of MT2 and MT3 unigene sequences derived from contigs with considerable numbers of EST members. Northern blot data showing early expression of type 2 metallothionein-like proteins only in Calcutta 4 suggest involvement in cell protection ROS-scavenging during HR responses. By contrast, it is possible that late expression in Cavendish Grande Naine may indirectly reflect increased ROS during the fungal necrotrophic disease phase. Necrotrophs have been reported to induce ROS accumulation in plant hosts as a mechanism for promoting pathogen access to nutrients through triggering host programmed cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C34">Govrin and Levine 2000</xref>).A number of peroxidases were also observed in the unigene sets. In addition to auxin metabolism, cell wall reinforcement and phytoalexin synthesis, such enzymes are also typically involved in ROS metabolism during defence responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C2">Almagro <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Recent histochemical analysis of peroxidase and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation during <italic>Mf</italic>–<italic>M. acuminata</italic> interactions reported a peaked accumulation of both in resistant <italic>M. acuminata</italic> Calcutta 4 at 10 days after conidial inoculation of detached leaf material, with no accumulation in susceptible Cavendish Grande Naine and partially susceptible Pisang Madu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C13">Cavalcante <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). The marked early peroxidase gene expression induction 6 DAI observed only in resistant Calcutta 4 is in agreement with these previous findings, and again correlates with HR-like responses observed in this genotype.Transposable elements are known to occur in all living organisms, and can occupy over 50 % of nuclear DNA. Given that these elements display mobility, they are important in plant evolution, through creation of novel genes or modifying gene function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C9">Bennetzen 2000</xref>). In the case of vegetatively propagated crops such as banana, it is therefore likely that some somaclonal variation events can be due to such TE activity. Classification of eukaryotic TEs is based on the mode of transposition, with RNA-mediated TEs (Class I) and DNA TEs (Class II). Class I TEs can be divided into subclasses: long terminal repeats (LTRs), retroelements without LTRs (the long interspersed nuclear elements (LINEs) and the small interspersed nuclear elements (SINEs)) and TRIMs (Terminal-repeat Retrotransposons In Miniature). Class II TEs include the MITEs (Miniature Inverted-repeat Transposable Elements) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C32">Feschotte <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). Our results revealed a predominance of retrotransposons to transposons. Similar distributions of DNA repeats have recently been reported in <italic>M. acuminata</italic> Calcutta 4, based on low-depth 454 sequencing of genomic DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C43">Hribová <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).The development of genomic libraries enriched for SSRs is typically expensive and labour intensive, in contrast to data mining in ESTs. Expressed sequence tag-derived SSR markers enable enrichment of genetic maps with gene-based markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C49">Kota <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>), as opposed to anonymous genomic DNA-derived SSRs which are predominantly derived from intergenic regions. Given that markers are isolated from coding regions, conservation is expected to be high, such that these EST–SSR markers are generally also transferable to related species (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C36">Gupta <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>). The gene-based marker tools developed in this study for <italic>Musa</italic> also serve as a resource for diversity characterization and downstream marker-assisted breeding using markers for traits. Work is ongoing in the research community for the development of suitable segregant populations for traits of interest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C5">Amorim <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C27">Dochez <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C54">Lorenzen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Linkage disequilibrium mapping is a potential alternative route for identifying genes for traits of interest in <italic>Musa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C41">Heslop-Harrison and Schwarzacher 2007</xref>), which, while not dependent upon crosses and progeny maintenance, requires hundreds of plant accessions and thousands of genetic markers. The SSR markers designed in our work are also applicable for such a study. In general, the frequency and distribution of SSRs in ESTs and in genomic sequences differ, with dinucleotides typically more abundant in genomic survey sequences and trinucleotides more common in ESTs (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C50">La Rota <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C90">Varshney <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C63">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). In our study, tri-nucleotide repeat motifs (an average of 55.8 % across both EST datasets) were indeed more abundant than di-nucleotide motifs (average of 28.4 %). All other motifs, from tetra- to hendeca-repeats, were only poorly represented. Such a predominance of trinucleotides probably reflects the fact that such motifs in gene regions will avoid frameshift mutations which would cause changes at the protein level. Simple sequence repeat mining criteria in software may also distort real differences in motif abundance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C90">Varshney <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). A total of 75 out of 303 tested SSR marker primer pairs were reproducibly polymorphic when tested across <italic>M. acuminata</italic> accessions contrasting in resistance to Sigatoka diseases, complementing the previous work by our group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C63">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Similar polymorphism rates have been observed in other crop species such as wheat and cotton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C29">Eujayl <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C39">Han <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Polymerase chain reaction amplification failed, however, for 106 primer pairs. Possible reasons include SSR extension across splice sites, poor sequence quality or chimeric DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C90">Varshney <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). It has been reported that EST-derived SSR markers show less polymorphism than genomic sequence-derived SSRs, as a result of conservation in gene regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS030C71">Raju <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Indeed, from a total of 75 loci, only 289 alleles were observed, with an average of 3.8 alleles per locus and an average PIC of 0.5. Considering that a total of 303 potentially functional SSR markers were identified from a subset of 4549 ESTs in the present study, it is possible to estimate approximately a further 1000 markers that could be derived from the 15 464 publically available <italic>M. acuminata</italic> ESTs. Given the advent of next-generation sequencing-derived gene expression sequence data, however, this number looks set to increase considerably.This study contributes considerably to publically available EST resources for <italic>M. acuminata</italic>, providing a unigene set of 3995 sequences derived from accessions Calcutta 4 and Cavendish Grande Naine during incompatible and compatible interactions with <italic>Mf</italic>. Genes was characterized according to the KOG-based classification, Interpro-based domain identification and GO category assignment. A large set of genic-SSR markers was developed, with polymorphic markers applicable for genetic map enrichment, diversity characterization and downstream marker-assisted breeding. In summary, it is anticipated that this dataset contributes to genomic resources for <italic>Musa</italic>, with downstream application in genetic improvement. Ongoing next-generation sequencing-based investigation of gene expression (including transcription profiling) in <italic>Musa</italic>–pathogen interactions by our group will offer potential for further elucidation of gene expression during plant immune responses, and will contribute to validating annotated gene models in the <italic>Musa</italic> whole-genome sequencing project.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/pls030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">The following additional information is available in the online version of this article –</ext-link>File 1: <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> unigene assignment to KOG categories.File 2: EuKaryotic orthologous group category abundance of <italic>M. acuminata</italic> unigenes.File 3: Details of 303 <italic>M. acuminata</italic> genic-SSR markers, validated for polymorphism across 20 diploid accessions.High-quality 5′ single-pass ESTs for 9333 cDNA clones from the MAC4 library and 3962 from the MACV library have been deposited in the GenBank database (<bold><uri xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/dbEST/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/dbEST/</uri></bold>) [accession numbers: JK531581–JK540913 (MAC4); JK542313–JK546274 (MACV)].This work was funded by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">IAEA, Austria</grant-sponsor> (Project <grant-num xlink:type="simple">13187</grant-num>), <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">FINEP, Brazil</grant-sponsor> (Project <grant-num xlink:type="simple">0107060900/0842/07</grant-num>), <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">CNPq, Brazil</grant-sponsor> (Projects <grant-num xlink:type="simple">680.398/01-5</grant-num> and <grant-num xlink:type="simple">506165/2004-3</grant-num>). M.A.N.P. was supported by a fellowship from the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">CNPq</grant-sponsor>.M.A.N.P. participated in EST sequencing, microsatellite marker validation and data analysis. V.O.C. participated in microsatellite marker validation and data analysis. F.L.E. participated in EST sequencing and data analysis. C.C.T. participated in EST sequencing. M.T.S.J. conceived the study and participated in EST sequencing. T.M. participated in EST sequencing. V.C.R.A. participated in microsatellite marker validation and data analysis. C.F.F. participated in microsatellite marker validation and data analysis. E.P.A. participated in microsatellite marker validation and data analysis. L.F.A.F. participated in EST sequence data analysis. N.F.M. participated in EST sequence data analysis. M.J.B.C. participated in northern blot analyses. F.C.B. conceived the study and participated in northern blot analyses. O.S. supervised and participated in EST sequence data analysis and computational searches for microsatellite identification and primer design. G.J.P.J. supervised and participated in EST sequence data analysis and computational searches for microsatellite identification and primer design, and editing of the manuscript. L.P. conducted <italic>in vitro</italic> bioassays. C.A. conceived the study and conducted <italic>in vitro</italic> bioassays. A.Y.C. conceived the study, prepared cDNA libraries and supervised microsatellite marker validation and data analysis. P.P. conceived the study, prepared cDNA libraries, participated in northern blot analysis and edited the manuscript. R.N.G.M. conceived the study, participated in EST sequencing and data analysis, and drafted the manuscript. All authors have contributed to, read and approved the final manuscript.None declared.R.N.G.M. acknowledges the financial support from IAEA (13187). The work from all authors was in the context of IAEA Coordinated Research Project ‘Molecular Tools for Quality Improvement in Vegetatively Propagated Crops Including Banana and Cassava (D23027)’ and the FAO/IAEA Joint Programme. We thank anonymous reviewers for their useful comments on the manuscript.