 Growth of  in vitro Oncidesa  plantlets cultured under cold cathode fluorescent lamps with super-elevated CO 2  enrichment  Efficient plant regeneration through somatic embryogenesis from callus cultures of  Oncidium  (Orchidaceae)  Tissue culture advances for mass propagation of  Oncidium  mericlones  Effects of long-term elevated CO 2  from natural CO 2  springs on  Nardus stricta : photosynthesis, biochemistry, growth and phenology  Effects of elevated CO 2  on growth and morphological characteristics of ornamental bromeliads  Effects of a new light source (cold cathode fluorescent lamps) on the growth of tree peony plantlets  in vitro   More efficient plants: a consequence of rising atmospheric CO 2 ?  The effects of increased atmospheric carbon dioxide and temperature on carbon partitioning, source–sink relations and respiration  The propagation of  Oncidium papilio  by shoot tip culture and a discussion of some nutrient media  Photoautotrophic micropropagation of  Epidendrum  (Orchidaceae) using disposable, gas permeable film vessel  Effects of super-elevated CO 2  on the growth and carboxylating enzymes in an epiphytic CAM orchid plantlet  Photosynthetic acclimation in trees to rising atmospheric CO 2 : a broader perspective  Inoculation of  in vitro  shoots of  Oncidium  in film culture vessels under open condition and CO 2  enrichment condition  Changes in mineral and carbohydrate content in pseudobulbs of the C 3  epiphytic orchid hybrid  Oncidium  Goldiana at different growth stages   In vitro  CO 2  enrichment of CAM orchid plantlets  The application of biotechnology to orchids  Enhancement of growth and regeneration efficiency from embryogenic callus cultures of  Oncidium  ‘Gower Ramsey’ by adjusting carbohydrate sources  Effects of basal medium composition on the growth of carnation plantlets in auto- and mixo-trophic tissue culture  Growth and stomatal behavior of hydroponically cultured potato ( Solanum tuberosum  L.) at elevated and super-elevated CO 2   Review: CO 2  enrichment in greenhouses. Crop responses.  The growth response of  Phalaenopsis  plantlets cultured under cold cathode fluorescent lamps (CCFL) and high CO 2  enrichment   In vitro  growth and single-leaf photosynthetic response of  Cymbidium  plantlets to super-elevated CO 2  under cold cathode fluorescent lamps  Acclimation of photosynthesis to increasing atmospheric CO 2 : the gas exchange perspective  Yellowing and photosynthetic decline of barley primary leaves in response to atmospheric CO 2  enrichment  Effects of CO 2  enrichment on soluble amino acids and organic acids in barley primary leaves as a function of age, photoperiod and chlorosis  Disposable film culture vessels  Morphological observation on vegetative growth and flower bud formation in  Oncidium  Boissiense  Growth of tissue cultured  Spathiphyllum  on rockwool in a novel film culture vessel under high CO 2   Micropropagation of  Phalaenopsis  by using synthetic seeds in film culture vessels  The physiology of  Cymbidium  plantlets cultured  in vitro  under conditions of high carbon dioxide and low photosynthetic photon flux density  Cold cathode fluorescent lamps (CCFL): revolutionary light source for plant micropropagation  Orchids: advances in tissue culture, genetics, phytochemistry and transgenic biotechnology  Establishment of optimum nutrient media for  in vitro  propagation of  Cymbidium  Sw. (Orchidaceae) using protocorm-like body segments  Priming abiotic factors for optimal hybrid  Cymbidium  (Orchidaceae) PLB and callus induction, plantlet formation, and their subsequent cytogenetic stability analysis  The influence of different carbon sources, photohetero-, photoauto- and photomixotrophic conditions on protocorm-like body organogenesis and callus formation in thin cell layer culture of hybrid  Cymbidium  (Orchidaceae)  Instant media for orchid seed germination  Some pH changes in nutrient solutions  Effect of cold cathode fluorescent lamps on growth of  Gerbera jamesonii  plantlets  in vit ro  Supraoptimal carbon dioxide effects on growth of soybean [ Glycine max  (L.) Merr.]  Population dynamics of epiphytic orchids in a metapopulation context  Development and application of photoautotrophic micropropagation plant system  Ionic composition and strength of culture medium affect photoautotrophic growth, transpiration and net photosynthetic rates of strawberry plantlets  in vit ro  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  How can one increase the biomass of plants, particularly orchids, in an effective way? Photoautotrophic micropropagation is an effective means of increasing the biomass of  Oncidesa  orchids. Using 10,000 µmol mol −1  CO 2  and a photosynthetic photon flux density of 60 µmol m −2  s −1 , the number of leaves and roots and shoot and root fresh and dry weights could be considerably increased, but only when cultured on Kyoto medium rather than Vacin and Went medium. Super-elevated CO 2  enrichment and growth under cold cathode fluorescent lamps can positively affect the efficiency and quality of commercial production of clonal  Oncidesa  plantlets.  As interest in how to increase biomass production through biotechnological means gains traction, focus is turning towards the use of photoautotrophic micropropagation under elevated levels of carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) to maximize plant growth and productivity. The effect of super-elevated CO 2  with cold cathode fluorescent lamps (CCFLs) on the photoautotrophic growth of  Oncidesa in vitro  has been studied using a gas-permeable film culture vessel, the ‘Vitron’. The growth of  Oncidesa  (formerly  Oncidesa  Gower Ramsey ‘U-1’) plantlets on Vacin and Went (VW) medium was stimulated by 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2 . In particular, increasing the photosynthetic photon flux density (PPFD) from 45 to 60 μmol m −2  s −1  under 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  in the growth chamber remarkably increased the number of leaves and roots, and shoot and root fresh and dry weights compared with plantlets under the same level of CO 2  under low PPFD (45 μmol m −2  s −1 ). However, there was a remarkable decrease in photosynthetic capacity, and chlorosis and browning of leaves. In stark contrast, plantlets grown on Kyoto medium at 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  under high PPFD had a higher photosynthetic rate than plantlets grown on VW medium, and no chlorosis or browning was observed. Furthermore, shoot growth was remarkably enhanced. Therefore, super-elevated CO 2  (10 000 μmol mol −1 ) enrichment and growth under CCFLs can positively affect the efficiency and quality of commercial production of clonal  Oncidesa  plantlets.  The use of plant tissue culture as a way to increase plant biomass in a short span of time is an attractive application of biotechnology practised by many plant scientists. The ability to induce greater biomass by increasing the carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) concentration through photoautotrophic micropropagation—which has proven benefits in terms of productivity ( Kozai  et al.  2005 )—has wide practical applications for ornamental and other horticultural crops.   Oncidium  is an epiphytic and terrestrial orchid. This genus comprises about 400 species distributed mainly in tropical and subtropical South and Central America ( Endress 1996 ). Many hybrid  Oncidium  have been produced, the most attractive having become commercially important as potted plants and cut flowers.  Fast (1973)  first reported that  Oncidium  plantlets could be induced by shoot tips, and several effective protocols for clonal propagation have been developed since then ( Arditti 2008 ) and are now used for commercial micropropagation. However, relatively high production costs continue to hamper the expansion of hybrid  Oncidium  production since it may take almost one year for plantlets to reach the acclimatization stage. Since orchids such as  Oncidium  are inherently slow growers, there are considerable energy costs spent on controlling air temperature and lighting in the culture room. To overcome these limitations, despite several studies existing on efficient multiplication and regeneration of  Oncidium  plantlets (e.g.  Chen and Chang 2000 ;  Chen  et al.  2001 ;  Jheng  et al.  2006 ), it is also important to enhance the growth of plantlets regenerated  in vitro .  Over two decades, many studies have been conducted on photoautotrophic culture in various species, including  Oncidium  hybrids ( He  et al.  2003 ), which has several advantages over photomixotrophic culture: promotion of growth and photosynthesis, high survival percentage  ex vitro , elimination of physiological and morphological disorders, and less microbial contamination (reviewed in  Xiao  et al.  2011 ). Under photoautotrophic culture, CO 2  is one of the most important factors directly affecting the growth and photosynthesis of plantlets because they should produce complex organic compounds from CO 2  as a carbon source using energy from light. Therefore, it is necessary for enhancing photoautotrophic growth to provide a sufficient optimal concentration of CO 2 .  Tanaka (1991)  developed several film culture vessels that had high gas and light permeability. The photoautotrophic growth of several orchid plantlets was stimulated using 3000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment: C 3   Cymbidium  ( Tanaka  et al.  1999 ;  Teixeira da Silva  et al.  2007 ), C 3   Epidendrum  ( Giang and Tanaka 2004 ), CAM  Phalaenopsis  ( Tanaka  et al.  1993 ) and C 3   Oncidium  ( He  et al.  2003 ). It was previously demonstrated in CAM  Phalaenopsis  that an increase in CO 2  concentration from 3000 to 5000 μmol mol −1  remarkably enhanced the photoautotrophic growth of plantlets in film culture vessels ( Norikane and Tanaka 2010 ), implying that higher CO 2  enrichment (&gt;3000 μmol mol −1 ) could have a positive effect on the photoautotrophic growth of orchid plantlets.   Hew  et al.  (1995)  and  Gouk  et al.  (1997)  conducted detailed plant physiological studies on the effect of super-elevated CO 2  levels (10 000 μmol mol −1 ) on the  in vitro  growth of CAM orchids Mokara White and Mokara Yellow, concluding that these levels were able to stimulate the growth of plantlets on sugar-added medium (i.e. photomixotrophic conditions). A similar trend was noticed for the  Cymbidium  hybrid but at a lower CO 2  level (3000 μmol mol −1 ) ( Teixeira da Silva  et al.  2007 ). In the photoautotrophic culture of  Cymbidium , 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment remarkably enhanced the growth of plantlets in a conventional glass bottle with a TPX cap having a hole covered with a gas-permeable membrane ( Norikane  et al.  2010 ). However, beyond these studies, little is known about the effect of super-elevated CO 2  enrichment on the photoautotrophic growth of orchid plantlets (or any other crop for that matter) in film culture vessels. Thus, one key objective of our study was to ascertain whether super-elevated CO 2  would have further positive effects on the photoautotrophic growth of  Oncidesa  plantlets in film culture vessels.  Light is also an essential factor for plant growth and development. Recently, the use of cold cathode fluorescent lamps (CCFLs) as a radiation source for plants has been attempted because of their attractive features, including their small diameter (1.6–3.0 mm), long life (50 000 h) and low heat generation, with an estimated 40 % reduction in electric energy consumption used for lighting and air conditioners during micropropagation ( Tanaka  et al.  2009 ;  Norikane and Tanaka 2010 ). Those studies demonstrated that  Cymbidium  and  Phalaenopsis in vitro  plantlets cultured under CCFLs showed enhanced photoautotrophic growth compared with plantlets cultured under conventional heat fluorescent lamps.  Ding  et al.  (2010)  and  Wang  et al.  (2011)  also reported the usefulness of CCFLs as a lighting source for the micropropagation of tree peony and  Gerbera . Our present study is the first report on the use of CCFLs as a radiation source for  Oncidesa  plantlet growth  in vitro .  The aim of the present study was to achieve more efficient and higher-quality commercial clonal orchid plantlets, in this case, an  Oncidium  hybrid ( Oncidesa ), by super-elevated CO 2  enrichment under CCFLs on two different media.  The explants used in this study were shoots with 2–3 leaves obtained from a mass of protocorm-like bodies of  Oncidesa  (formerly  Oncidesa  Gower Ramsey ‘U-1’;  Royal Horticultural Society (RHS) 2013 ) derived from shoot-tip culture. This is a sympodial orchid hybrid, thin-leaved and with a C 3  mode of photosynthesis ( Hew and Yong 1997 ). Twenty-five shoots were cultured in each culture vessel for 3 months, and two culture vessels were used for each treatment.  Vacin and Went (VW) ( Vacin and Went 1949 ) sugar-free liquid medium was used as the basal medium. To examine the effect of basal medium under super-elevated CO 2  enrichment, Kyoto ( Tsukamoto  et al.  1963 ) sugar-free liquid medium was also used. VW and Kyoto media are two of the most commonly used media in orchid biotechnology ( Teixeira da Silva  et al.  2005 ). The pH of the media was adjusted to 5.3 with 1 N NaOH or HCl before autoclaving at 121 °C for 17 min.  The film culture vessel ‘Vitron’ (122 mm × 122 mm × 140 mm) consists of a three-dimensional injection-moulded polypropylene frame covered by a heat-sealed OTP film (Otsuka Techno Co. Ltd, Tokushima, Japan) on all sides, except the top ( Giang and Tanaka 2004 ). OTP is a multi-layer film consisting of three layers: the outer layer of TPX (4-methyl-1-pentane polymer) and the inner layer of CPP (a polypropylene) which are bonded together by a middle layer of polyolefin resins. The top seal film (OTP) is affixed to the top of the vessel after removing the paper backing to expose the adhesive. The medium substrate was rockwool (a 25 joined block, 5 × 5, of Grodan ®  Rockwool Multiblock™ AO 18/30, Grodania A/S, Denmark) with 180 mL of liquid medium. The rockwool was previously sterilized in a dry sterilizer (150 °C, 1 h), and placed in the ‘Vitron’. Then, sterilized liquid medium was poured evenly over the rockwool.  CO 2  enrichment system under a CCFL light source.  The photosynthetic light response curve and net photosynthetic rate were measured in the second leaf, counting from the top downwards, of plantlets, in which a pseudobulb was not formed, after culturing for 90 days. It was measured in at least five plants using a portable infrared gas analyser (LI-6400, Li-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA). For obtaining the photosynthetic light response curve, the photon flux density that was provided from a red LED light source built into the top of the leaf chamber was changed from 300 to 0 μmol m −2  s −1 . The net photosynthetic rate was measured at 300 μmol m −2  s −1  (saturating or near-saturating PPFD). The CO 2  concentration and temperature in the leaf chamber were adjusted to maintain 400 μmol mol −1  and 25 °C, respectively. The relative humidity in the leaf chamber was kept as close to 65–70 % as possible. The air flow rate was 200 mL min −1 .  Means were separated by ANOVA and significant differences were assessed by Tukey's multiple range test and a Student's  t -test at  P  = 0.05.  Effects of CO 2  concentration and PPFD on the  in vitro  growth of  Oncidesa  plantlets under CCFL.  x Chlorophyll content in the second leaf, counted from the top downwards, of the plantlets.  y Different letters within a column indicate significant differences at  P  ≤ 0.05 by Tukey's multiple range test.  n  = 50.  z Non-CO 2  enrichment.  In  Cymbidium , an increase in PPFD (using CCFLs) under 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment further enhanced the  in vitro  growth of both shoots and roots ( Norikane  et al.  2010 ). A similar trend was observed in  Oncidesa  plantlets in the present study; the number of leaves and roots, and shoot and root fresh and dry weights of the plantlets grown at 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  under high PPFD increased remarkably, although plant height, root length, and pseudobulb volume, fresh and dry weights and formation frequency did not differ between both PPFD levels under 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  (Table  1 ). Thus, we concluded that super-elevated CO 2  enrichment (10 000 μmol mol −1  in the ‘Vitron’) with high PPFD (provided by CCFLs) also has a positive effect on the growth of both shoots and roots in  Oncidesa .  Effects of CO 2  concentration and PPFD on the  in vitro  growth of  Oncidesa  plantlets under CCFLs. (A) Low PPFD (from left to right: ambient, 3000, 5000 and 10 000 μmol mol −1 ). (B) High PPFD (from left to right: ambient, 3000, 5000 and 10 000 μmol mol −1 ). (A) and (B) are at the same scale.  Photosynthetic light–response curve for single  Oncidesa  plantlet leaves grown at 0, 3000, 5000 and 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under low and high PPFD. Open diamonds: non-CO 2  enrichment under low PPFD; closed diamonds: non-CO 2  enrichment under high PPFD; open circles: 3000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under low PPFD; closed circles: 3000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under high PPFD; open triangles: 5000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under low PPFD; closed triangles: 5000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under high PPFD; open squares: 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under low PPFD; closed squares: 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under high PPFD.  Effect of media composition on the  in vitro  growth of Oncidesa plantlets at 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under high PPFD (60 μmol m −2  s −1 ).  y Chlorophyll content in the second leaf, counted from the top downwards, of the plantlets.  z Different letters within a column indicate significant differences at  P  ≤ 0.05 by Student's  t -test.  n  = 50.  Net photosynthetic rate for single  Oncidesa  plantlet leaves grown on Vacin and Went and Kyoto media at 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under high PPFD. Significant differences according to Tukey's test ( P  &lt; 0.05) are indicated by different letters.  Effect of media composition on the  in vitro  growth of  Oncidesa  plantlets at 10 000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under high PPFD. Left: Vacin and Went medium; right: Kyoto medium. Significant differences according to Tukey's test ( P  &lt; 0.05) are indicated by different letters.  We have shown in this study that super-elevated CO 2  (10 000 μmol mol −1 ) under high PPFD emitted by CCFLs enhanced the photoautotrophic growth of  Oncidesa  plantlets in the ‘Vitron’, although the upper ‘threshold limit’ would be 5000 μmol mol −1  CO 2  enrichment under high PPFD before a negative impact on photosynthesis would occur. This would help to maximize the productivity and quality of  Oncidesa  plantlets cultured  in vitro . In addition, CCFLs have several advantages over existing lighting systems used for plant tissue culture ( Tanaka  et al.  2009 ). In particular, CCFLs emit much less heat through their unique properties, allowing plants or cultures (culture vessels) to be placed very close to the light source, making more efficient use of the culture room and intensifying the efficiency of CO 2  enrichment. Our results indicate that there is great hope for using super-elevated CO 2  enrichment under CCFLs for more efficient and higher-quality commercial production of clonal orchid plantlets, which is a key objective of orchid biotechnology ( Hossain  et al.  2013 ;  Teixeira da Silva 2013 ).  All authors have made a substantial contribution to the manuscript and the research presented. M.T. and A.N. co-designed the experiment. M.T. and J.A.T.d.S. oversaw the experimental execution. A.N. conducted all research. A.N. and J.A.T.d.S. drafted the paper and made all edits for the revisions. All authors have seen and agreed to the submitted manuscript.  None declared. 