Influence of halophytic hosts on their parasites—the case of <italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic>HalophytenDas Physiokonzept—ein Modell zur Erklärung ökophysiologischer Anpassungen?Water and nutrient status of the mistletoe <italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic> parasitic on isolated Negev Desert populations of <italic>Acacia raddiana</italic> differing in level of mortalityWasser- und Salzverhältnisse bei Halophyten der Salzsteppe in Utah/USAZur Ökologie und den Mineralstoffverhältnissen absalzender und nicht-absalzender XerohalophytenSalinity tolerance of different halophyte typesWann ist eine Pflanze ein Halophyt? Untersuchungen an Salzpflanzen in Zentralasien und anderen SalzwüstenSalinity, halophytes and salt affected natural ecosystemsSalinity tolerance in halophytesImportance of bladder hairs for salt tolerance of field-grown <italic>Atriplex</italic>-species from a Portuguese salt marshMineral nutrition of mistletoes: general conceptsMistletoe ecophysiology: host–parasite interactionsGas exchange and water balance of a mistletoe species and its mangrove hostsDirected dispersal of mistletoe (<italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic>) by yellow-vented bulbuls (<italic>Pycnonotus xanthopygos</italic>)Saltcedar (<italic>Tamarix ramosissima</italic>) an uncommon host for desert mistletoe (<italic>Phoradendron californicum</italic>)Umriß von Südpalästina im Kleide der FrühlingsfloraMineral nutrition of mistletoes<italic>Acacia</italic> trees as keystone species in the Negev desert ecosystemsMistletoes as parasites: host specifity and speciationHost specifity in parasitic mistletoes (Loranthaceae) in New ZealandOsmotica in <italic>Amyema miquelli</italic> (Lehm. Ex. Mig) Tieghem. and <italic>Amyema pendulum</italic> (Sieber ex. Sprengel) Tieghem. (Loranthaceae) on different hostsCompatible solutes in different organs of mangrove treesEcophysiology of xylem-tapping mistletoesSolutes and succulence in southern African mistletoesAn updated inventory of mistletoe (<italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic> and <italic>Viscum cruciatum</italic>) distribution in Jordan, hosts, and severity of infestationParasitic flowering plants of woody species in JordanSodium relations in Chenopodiaceae, a comparative approachHost recognition in a desert mistletoe: early stages of development are influenced by substrate and host originThe role of bladders for salt removal in some Chenopodiaceae (mainly <italic>Atriplex</italic> species)The mistletoe <italic>Loranthus acaciae</italic> (Loranthaceae) on halophytic and non-halophytic hosts in the southern Arava-Valley (Israel)Diurnal courses of leaf conductance and transpiration of mistletoes and their hosts in Central AustraliaFlowering seasonality and flower characteristics of <italic>Loranthus acaciae</italic> (Loranthaceae): implications for advertisement and bird-pollinationZonobiom III: Sinai-Halbinsel und Negev-WüsteDer Salzhaushalt der SukkulentenParasitic flowering plants on <italic>Euphorbia</italic> in South Africa and NamibiaWater relations and mineral content of the mistletoe <italic>Loranthus acaciae</italic> on halophytic and non-halophytic hostsIonen- und Wasserhaushalt von <italic>Anabasis articulata</italic> in Sanddünen der nördlichen Negev-Sinai-WüsteIonen- und Wasserhaushalt von <italic>Brownanthus pseudoschlichtianus</italic> (Aizoaceae) im Richtersveld (Südafrika)Die Ökologie der ostafrikanischen MangrovenCompatible and counteracting solutes<bold>Guest Editor:</bold> Tim J. FlowersThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Parasitic plants obtain nutrients, carbohydrates, ions and water from their host plants and develop special morphological features to survive on the living tissue of other plants. We investigated the mistletoe <italic>Psilocephalus acaciae</italic> on halophytic and non-halophytic hosts in the Arava Valley. When <italic>P. acaciae</italic> was parasitic on halophytic hosts, ions were transported by the transpiration stream in the parasite. Chloride and sodium induced the development of leaf succulence in the parasite. Increasing succulence is a morphological adaptation by the mistletoe to the increasing salt stress on halophytic hosts.Halophytes develop various morphological and physiological traits that enable them to grow successfully on saline substrates. Parasitic plants on halophytic hosts may also encounter salt stress. We investigated the mistletoe <italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic> (syn: <italic>Loranthus acacia</italic>; Loranthaceae), which occurs on 5 halophytic and at least 10 non-halophytic hosts in the Southern Arava Valley (Israel). <italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic> is a common parasite north of Eilat to the Dead Sea area and in the Jordan Valley. Morphological and physiological responses of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> to salinity were investigated by comparison of plants on halophytic with those on non-halophytic hosts. Ion patterns of different host–parasite associations were determined as was the development of leaf succulence at different growth stages. The leaf water content of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> increased and leaves developed succulence when growing on halophytic hosts, especially on <italic>Tamarix</italic> species, where leaf water content was three times higher than that on non-halophytic hosts and the leaf volume increased four to five times. The reason for increased succulence was a higher ion concentration of, and osmotic adjustment with, Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup>. <italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic> showed a high morphological and ecophysiological plasticity, enabling it to cope with salt stress, and can be classified as a facultative eu-halophyte, which increases its halo-succulence according to the host. Host–parasite associations are a model system for the investigation of halophytes under different salt stress conditions.Halophytes develop various physiological and morphological adaptations to cope with high salt concentrations in soil and water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C47">Waisel 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C8">Breckle 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C10">Flowers and Colmer 2008</xref>), and the regulation of uptake of Na<sup>+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> and transportation and storage of these ions in plant organs are key issues to understand life strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C6">Breckle 1990</xref>). In combination with the physiological processes, morphological adaptations like leaf bladders, salt glands and succulence develop to mitigate the effects of high salt concentrations in the photosynthesizing tissue by desalinization of leaves or dilution or compartmentalization within leaf tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C4">Breckle 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C8">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C34">Schirmer and Breckle 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C11">Freitas and Breckle 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C41">Veste 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>). Furthermore, the ion pattern and chemical composition of terrestrial halophytes are often characteristic of the species and family and only partly influenced by soil conditions (‘physiotype concept’; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C1">Albert 1982</xref>). For example, some desert halophytic members of the Aizoaceae are characterized by a selective hyper-accumulation of Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> in their leaves even on soils with low salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C45">Veste <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C41">Veste 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>) as is also the case with the members of Amaranthaceae (Chenopodiaceae: see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C44">Veste and Breckle 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C2">Albert 2005</xref>). On the other hand, members of the Poaceae are able to limit the uptake of Na<sup>+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C1">Albert 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C2">2005</xref>). This emphasizes the importance of active ion regulation and selective transportation of ions already in the root system.An interesting question is what happens if the root system for such ion selection is missing, as in the case with parasitic plants? Is the pattern of ion accumulation between host and parasite mirrored to some extent? In this context, xylem-tapping mistletoes are a perfect model lacking a root system for selective ion uptake. Water and nutrient uptake is directly linked to their hosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C13">Glatzel and Geils 2009</xref>) through a haustorium, which connects the parasite with its host and allows the transportation of water, inorganic and organic compounds from the host’s transpiration stream directly into the parasite. While there has been considerable attention to nutrient exchange between the parasite and the host (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C20">Lamont 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C12">Glatzel and Balasubramaniam 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C25">Popp 1987</xref>), only little attention has been given to mistletoes growing on halophytic hosts and the influence of the salinity experienced by the host on the parasite. There are several reports from mistletoes on mangroves: <italic>Phthirusa maritima</italic> (Loranthaceae) on <italic>Conocarpus erectus</italic> and <italic>Coccoloba uvifera</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C14">Goldstein <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>); <italic>Lysiana subfalcata</italic> on <italic>Ceriops tagal</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C38">Ullmann <italic>et al.</italic> 1985</xref>), <italic>Loranthus rhamnifolius</italic> on <italic>Sonneratia alba</italic> and <italic>Loranthus sansibarensis</italic> and <italic>L. dregei</italic> on <italic>Lumnitzera racemosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C48">Walter and Steiner 1936</xref>) and <italic>Loranthus capitellatus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C17">Holtermann 1907</xref>). In these cases, the mistletoes on mangroves have a 0.2- to 3.5-fold higher Na<sup>+</sup> concentration than their hosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C20">Lamont 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C14">Goldstein <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>). In South Africa and Namibia, of 19 mistletoes only <italic>Tapinanthus oleifolius</italic> (Loranthaceae) occurs on the halophytes <italic>Tamarix usneoides</italic> and <italic>Salvadora persica</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C46">Visser 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C28">Popp <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>), where it has a higher salt concentration in its xylem sap than the host. <italic>Tapinanthus oleifolius</italic> also increases its leaf succulence on the halophytic <italic>T. usneoides</italic> as well as on non-halophytic <italic>Euphorbia virosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C42">Veste 2007<italic>b</italic></xref>), which is strongly correlated with the accumulation of inorganic ions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C28">Popp <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>). <italic>Tamarix ramosissima</italic> is an uncommon host for <italic>Phoradendron californicum</italic> (Loranthaceae) in North America, but the mistletoe is able to grow on the halophyte (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C16">Haigh 1996</xref>).Another example for such a host–mistletoe association is <italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic> (syn: <italic>Loranthus acaciae</italic>; Loranthaceae) with an east-Sudanian distribution. The mistletoe occurs along the Arava Valley and some adjacent wadi systems north to the Jordan Valley and in some parts of Jordan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C35">Shmida and Darom 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C30">Qasem 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C31">2011</xref>). Within the Arava Valley, the highest density of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> can be found close to Yotvata (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C37">Todt <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>), where most of the trees are parasitized by <italic>P. acaciae</italic>. The number of parasites decreases strongly a few kilometres north and south of Yotvata, and the movement pattern of the bird bulbul (<italic>Pycnonotus xanthopygos</italic>), as the main disperser of the red berries with sticky seeds, can explain the distribution of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> in the Arava Valley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C15">Green <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The most common hosts are Acacia trees because of their wide distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C22">Munzbergova and Ward 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C3">Bowie and Ward 2004</xref>). Other hosts for <italic>P. acaciae</italic> in the southern Arava Valley are trees and shrubs (<italic>Atriplex</italic>, <italic>Nitraria</italic> and <italic>Tamarix</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C37">Todt <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). On these hosts the parasite shows morphological and physiological plasticity as known for other halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C8">Breckle 2002</xref>) growing under different salt conditions. This high flexibility makes the different host–parasite associations of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> an interesting model system to understand adaptive plasticity to salt stress. We wanted to check how the parasite is able to cope with halophytic hosts growing under high salinity stress and the ecophysiological plasticity of ion accumulation that is involved. A special focus is given to ion uptake and its link with the development of leaf succulence at different growth stages on different hosts. We also compiled an updated checklist of the known host–parasite associations.Climatic diagram of Yotvata (southern Arava, Israel) indicating the 12-months arid season.Ion content was determined in hot water extracts with an atomic absorption spectrometer (AAS 2280, Perkin-Elmer, Waltham, MA, USA) with a C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>2</sub> flame. Cl was determined with a micro-chlorocounter (Marius, Utrecht, NL). In all analytic determinations, there were three repetitions. If the relative standard deviation was &gt;2 %, then additional checks were made.Statistical analyses were performed with SPSS package 7.5.1. We checked the normality of distributions and variance of all samples with the Kolgomorov–Smirnow test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C18">Köhler <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C21">Lozán and Kausch 1998</xref>). For correlation analysis we used Spearman's rank correlation coefficient (<italic>r</italic>’s). Significance of differences between samples fixed at the 0.05 probability level for all statistical tests was checked with the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test.Checklist of non-halophytic and halophytic hosts of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> in the Arava Valley (Israel and Jordan). Hosts in Yotvata (Israel) are marked with YOT. W, species growing in natural habitas; Cv, cultivated species. Data source: (1) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C29">Post (1932)</xref>, (2) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C50">Zohary (1966)</xref>, (3) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C36">Täckholm (1974)</xref>, (4) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C9">Feinbrun-Dothan <italic>et al.</italic> (1991)</xref>, (5) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C35">Shmida and Darom (1992)</xref>, (6) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C43">Veste and Breckle (1995)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C37">Todt <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref>, (7) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C39">Vaknin <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref>, (8) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C19">Kotschy (1861)</xref>, (9) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C30">Qasem (2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C31">2011</xref>).Leaf area (cm<sup>2</sup>) of young and old leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> parasitic on non-halophytic (light grey) and halophytic (dark grey) hosts. Box plots indicate interquartile range, median (thick line) and total variation.Leaf thickness (mm) of young and old leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> parasitic on non-halophytic (light grey) and halophytic (dark grey) hosts. Box plots indicate interquartile range, median (thick line) and total variation.Volume (cm<sup>3</sup>) of young and old leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> parasitic on non-halophytic (light grey) and halophytic (dark grey) hosts. Box plots indicate interquartile range, median (thick line) and total variation.Succulence (g H<sub>2</sub>O g<sup>−1</sup> d.m. org.) of young and old leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> parasitic on non-halophytic (light grey) and halophytic (dark grey) hosts, with standard deviation.Ash content of old leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> parasitic on non-halophytic (light grey) and halophytic (dark grey) hosts. Box plots indicate interquartile range, median (thick line) and total variation for <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2.Correlation between Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> concentration (mmol kg<sup>−1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>O) in leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> growing on non-halophytic and halophytic hosts.Correlation between Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> concentration (mmol kg<sup>−1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>O) in leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> growing on non-halophytic and halophytic hosts.Correlation between K<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> concentration (mmol kg<sup>−1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>O) in leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> growing on non-halophytic and halophytic hosts.Correlation between succulence (g H<sub>2</sub>O g<sup>−1</sup> d.m. org.) and Na<sup>+</sup> concentration (dots: mmol kg<sup>−1</sup> d.m.; crosses: mmol kg<sup>−1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>O) in leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> growing on non-halophytic and halophytic hosts.Correlation between succulence (g H<sub>2</sub>O g<sup>−1</sup> d.m. org.) and the ion sum (Na<sup>+</sup> + K<sup>+</sup> + Ca<sup>2+</sup> + Mg<sup>2+</sup> + Cl<sup>−</sup>, mmol kg<sup>−1</sup> d.m.) in leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> growing on non-halophytic and halophytic hosts.Sodium–potassium ratio (derived from H<sub>2</sub>O values, mmol kg<sup>−1</sup>) in leaves of the non-halophytic hosts <italic>A. tortilis, C. comosum</italic> and <italic>H. persicum</italic> the halophytic hosts <italic>T. nilotica, A. halimus</italic> and <italic>N. retusa</italic> and the respective <italic>P. acaciae</italic> hemi-parasites on them.Ion contents of old leaves of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> on various hosts (± standard deviation) and corresponding ionic contents of host plants [in each cell: upper figure, mmol kg<sup>−1</sup> d.m.; lower figure, mmol kg<sup>−1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>O].Ion ratio (mmol-paras/mmol-host) calculated from H<sub>2</sub>O values (mmol kg<sup>−1</sup>) for the checked parasite/host pairs.Ratio of ion concentration parasite/host for the five ions, calculated from the H<sub>2</sub>O values (mmol kg<sup>−1</sup>). The values for <italic>A. halimus</italic> are beyond the graph (Na<sup>+</sup> = 479/1955; Cl<sup>−</sup> = 552/2084).Previously published information on hosts of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C50">Zohary 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C9">Feinbrun-Dothan <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C35">Shmida and Darom 1992</xref>) mentioned <italic>Atriplex</italic> and <italic>Tamarix</italic> but no particular species. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C30">Qasem (2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C31">2011</xref>) updated the list of hosts of <italic>P. acaciae</italic> in Jordan to 26 species from 12 families (included in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU084TB1">1</xref>). In total, there are now 37 non- and 6 halophytic hosts known. Similar to other halophytes, the succulence observed for <italic>P. acaciae</italic> growing on halophytic hosts showed a morphological adaptation of the mistletoe to salt stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C6">Breckle 1990</xref>). The increased succulence presumably resulted from absorption of Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> ions from the host and osmotic adjustment by the parasite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C43">Veste and Breckle 1995</xref>). There was a highly significant correlation between the succulence and Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> accumulation, which is in accordance with observations made by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C28">Popp <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref> for <italic>T. oleifolius</italic> growing on <italic>Tamarix usnoides</italic> in Namibia. An increase of Na<sup>+</sup> can also be deduced from the higher Na/K ratio on halophytic than non-halophytic hosts (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU084TB2">2</xref>), a very general rule for many other non-parasitic halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C1">Albert 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C32">Reimann and Breckle 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C8">Breckle 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C27">Popp and Richter (1998)</xref> also reported an increase in Na/K ratios for <italic>T. oleifolius</italic> growing on <italic>T. usneoides</italic> from 1.58 to 13.21 with increasing leaf age.The concentrations of osmotically active ions were not strongly correlated with those of the parasite. This may easily be explained by the fact that the samples of leaves from the parasite and of the corresponding young host stems or host leaves were not directly osmotically dependent. Similarly, the Na/K ratios did not reflect the relation between the host and the parasite (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU084TB2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU084TB4">4</xref>).It is difficult to be certain about the concentrations of ions available to the haustoria of the parasite, as obtaining xylem sap (the presumed source) is in itself difficult. However, the concentrations of monovalent ions in the leaves of the host are unlikely to provide a good indication of the xylem concentrations due to the presence of salt bladders (<italic>Atriplex</italic> species) or salt glands (<italic>Tamarix</italic> species). Additionally osmotic adjustment may involve compatible solutes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C49">Yancey 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C10">Flowers and Colmer 2008</xref>), which we did not investigate; they are, however, found in other mistletoes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C26">Popp and Polania 1989</xref>), although in the more succulent leaves of <italic>T. oleifolius</italic> they are of minor importance for osmotic adjustment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C28">Popp <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>).Various definitions and classifications of halophytes have been proposed over the past decades, but following the classification of halophytes by Breckle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C6">1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C7">2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C8">2002</xref>), which includes the mechanisms for controlling the NaCl concentration in plants, <italic>P. acaciae</italic> is a facultative eu-halophyte. <italic>Plicosepalus acaciae</italic> increases its halo-succulence according to the host, which is in this respect comparable with soil substrates. In any case, the water and nutrient status of the host plants, especially under desert conditions has a strong influence on the equilibrium of host and parasite and thus may mutually influence mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C3">Bowie and Ward 2004</xref>). Surface structure, size and indirectly host origin influence the success of germination and of seedling establishment of parasite on host twigs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C33">Rödl and Ward 2002</xref>): whether, during these early stages of development, the halophytic character of the host plant and salinity plays a role is still unclear. Host specificity seems to be rather low in mistletoes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C23">Norton and Carpenter 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU084C24">Norton and de Lange 1999</xref>) since seeds germinate readily in almost all situations, whereas other parasitic plants germinate only in response to chemical signals from the host plants. In future a more detailed analysis of xylem concentrations and ion patterns of host and parasite is a strong necessity for a better understanding of ecophysiological behaviour and the differing infestation rates of the parasite on different species of the host. But our results show that the ion pattern of substrate (host) and plant (parasite) is, to some extent, mirrored, but that haustoria of the parasite (similar to roots in soil) have only a limited capacity for ion selectivity. Thus, we can conclude that the mistletoe we studied exhibited an adaptive plasticity depending on substrate conditions offered by the host, reflecting the xylem sap concentrations of Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup>. Basically this host–parasite association is an excellent model system and could be used for future ecophysiological research on halophytes.The research was funded by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">DAAD—Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst</grant-sponsor>, Bonn, Germany, and the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">BMBF—Federal Ministry of Science and Education</grant-sponsor>, Bonn, Germany.All authors have contributed substantially to this manuscript. M.V. was involved in planning, data analyses and manuscript writing. H.T. conducted the field investigations, and was involved in the data analysis and manuscript writing. S-W.B. was involved in the planning and supervision of all the experimental work and in writing the manuscript.None declared.Thanks to the Arava Research and Development Station Yotvata and Tel Aviv University for their kind logistic support of this investigation and to Liat Mizrahi-Todt for translating Hebrew literature. The authors also thank Yiftach Vaknin for his information on the northern Arava Valley. Thanks are due to COST Action FA0901 ‘Putting Halophytes to Work—From Genes to Ecosystems’ for their support, as well as to suggested improvements by reviewers and by Tim Flowers.