 Moving house: long-term dynamics of corticosterone secretion are unaltered in translocated populations of a rare reptile (the tuatara,  Sphenodon punctatus )  Inter-island differences in the corticosterone responses of North Island Saddlebacks ( Philesturnus rufusater ) in New Zealand do not suggest selective effects of translocation  Corticosterone shifts reproductive behaviour towards self-maintenance in the barn owl and is linked to melanin-based coloration in females  Modulation of corticosterone secretion in tuatara ( Sphenodon punctatus ): evidence of a dampened stress response in gravid females  Directions in reintroduction biology  Review of factors influencing stress hormones in fish and wildlife  Habitat type influences endocrine stress response in the degu ( Octodon degus )  Behavioral and physiological adjustments to new predators in an endemic island species, the Galapagos marine iguana  The effects of repeated handling and corticosterone treatment on behavior in an amphibian (Ocoee salamander:  Desmognathus ocoee )  Do baseline glucocorticoids predict fitness?  Thirsty sea snakes forsake refuge during rainfall  Assessing the impact of live-capture, confinement, and translocation on stress and fate in Eastern gray squirrels  Diel rhythms of basal and stress-induced corticosterone in a wild, seasonal vertebrate, Gambel&apos;s white-crowned sparrow  Stress and reproductive hormones reflect inter-specific social and nutritional conditions mediated by resource availability in a bear&ndash;salmon system  Translocation statistics (2002&ndash;2010), and the revised Department of Conservation translocation process  Geographic variation in corticosterone response to chronic predator stress in tadpoles  Water supplementation affects the behavioral and physiological ecology of Gila monsters ( Heloderma suspectum ) in the Sonoran desert  Seasonal patterns of body condition, hydration state, and activity of Gila monsters ( Heloderma suspectum ) at a Sonoran desert site  Stress and translocation: alterations in the stress physiology of translocated birds  Stress: an inevitable component of animal translocation  Does translocation influence physiological stress in the desert tortoise?  Hormonal and behavioral responses to food and water deprivation in a lizard ( Sceloporus occidentalis ): implications for assessing stress in a natural population  Effect of water deprivation on baseline and stress-induced corticosterone levels in the Children&apos;s python ( Antaresia childreni )  Variation in testosterone and corticosterone in amphibians and reptiles: relationships with latitude, elevation, and breeding season length  Evaluation of stress during transport  Do handling and transport stress influence adrenocortical response in tortoises ( Testudo hermanni )?  Fecal glucocorticoid metabolite analysis as an indicator of stress during translocation and acclimation in an endangered large mammal, the Grevy&apos;s zebra  Variation in stress and innate immunity in the tree lizard ( Urosaurus ornatus ) across an urban-rural gradient  Human disturbance alters endocrine and immune responses in the Galapagos marine iguana ( Amblyrhynchus cristatus )  Measuring animal welfare within a reintroduction: an assessment of different indices of stress in water voles  Arvicola amphibius   Suitability of amphibians and reptiles for translocation  Conflicting and complementary ethics of animal welfare considerations in reintroductions  Fecal corticoid monitoring in whooping cranes ( Grus americana ) undergoing reintroduction  The behavioral and physiological effects of long-distance translocation on Western rattlesnakes ( Crotalus oreganus )  Physiological and behavioral effects of repeated handling and short-distance translocations on free-ranging Northern Pacific rattlesnakes ( Crotalus oreganus oreganus )  Delayed physiological acclimatization by African elephants following reintroduction  Behavioural and physiological stress responses to transportation in a group of Przewalski&apos;s horses ( Equus ferus prezwalskii )  Tuatara  Plasma corticosterone concentrations in males of the skink  Egernia whitii  during acute and chronic confinement, and over a diel period  Stress hormones link food availability and population processes in seabirds  The effects of Hurricane Rita and subsequent drought on alligators in southwest Louisiana  How much stress do researchers inflict on their study animals? A case study using a scincid lizard,  Eulamprus heatwolei   A comparison of the adrenocortical responses to acute stress in cardueline finches from the Tibetan Plateau, Arctic Alaska and lowland Western North America  Dehydration and drinking behavior of the marine file snake  Acrochordus granulatus   Securing the demographic and genetic future of tuatara through assisted colonization  Urinary corticosterone responses and haematological stress indicators in the endangered Fijian ground frog ( Platymantis vitiana ) during transportation and captivity  Egg production by tuatara on Lady Alice and Stephens Island, New Zealand  Baseline corticosterone and stress response in the Thorn-tailed Rayadito ( Aphrastura spinicauda ) along a latitudinal &shy;gradient  Adrenocortical involvement during diverse stress in soft-shelled turtle  Lissemys p. punctata Bonnoterre   Thyroidal inhibition following diverse stress in soft-shelled turtles,  Lissemys punctata punctata   Effects of storage times and temperatures on T3, T4, LH, prolactin, insulin, cortisol and progesterone concentrations in blood samples from cows  Tameness and stress physiology in a predator-naive island species confronted with novel predation threat  Seasonal changes in plasma glucocorticoid concentrations in free-living vertebrates  How do glucocorticoids influence stress responses? Integrating permissive, suppressive, stimulatory, and preparative actions  Restitution of mass-size residuals: validating body condition indices  Reversing defaunation: restoring species in a changing world  Measuring stress in wildlife: techniques for quantifying glucocorticoids  The adrenocortical responses to stress in breeding Willow Warblers  Phylloscopus trochilus  in Sweden: effects of latitude and gender  Chronic low humidity-stress in the lizard  Anolis carolinensis : changes in diurnal corticosterone rhythyms  Physiology in conservation translocations  Effects of anthropogenic and environmental stress on the &shy;corticosterone levels of wintering Northern Pintails ( Anas acuta )  Revisiting translocation and reintroduction programmes: the importance of considering stress  Protocols for translocation of organisms to islands  Relationships between corticosterone concentration and season, time of day and confinement in a wild reptile (tuatara,  Sphenodon punctatus )  Post-emergence handling of green turtle hatchlings: improving hatchery management worldwide  Conservation physiology  Water balance in neonate and juvenile desert tortoises,  Gopherus agassizii   Reproduction and resistance to stress: when and how  Ecological bases of hormone&ndash;behavior interactions: the &ldquo;emergency life history stage&rdquo;  Effect of tidal cycle and food intake on the baseline plasma corticosterone rhythm in intertidally foraging marine iguanas  Variation in baseline corticosterone levels of Tree Sparrow ( Passer montanus ) populations along an urban gradient in Beijing, China  Behavioral changes, stress, and survival following reintroduction of Persian Fallow deer from two breeding facilities   Editor:  Steven Cooke  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Translocations are an important conservation tool; however, the process is a potential stressor for most species. We evaluated effects of translocation on plasma corticosterone in a rare reptile (the tuatara). We found that translocated tuatara are resistant to cumulative stressors and show no hormonal sign of chronic stress.  Translocations are an important conservation tool used to restore at-risk species to their historical range. Unavoidable procedures during translocations, such as habitat disturbance, capture, handling, processing, captivity, transport and release to a novel environment, have the potential to be stressful for most species. In this study, we examined acute and chronic stress (through the measurement of the glucocorticoid corticosterone) in a rare reptile (the tuatara,  Sphenodon punctatus ). We found that: (i) the acute corticosterone response remains elevated during the initial translocation process but is not amplified by cumulative stressors; and (ii) the long-term dynamics of corticosterone secretion are similar in translocated and source populations. Taken together, our results show that translocated tuatara are generally resistant to cumulative acute stressors and show no hormonal sign of chronic stress. Translocation efforts in tuatara afford the potential to reduce extinction risk and restore natural ecosystems.  Translocations are human-assisted movements of living organisms from one area to another and are an important tool for conservation efforts and population restoration of species at risk ( Armstrong and Seddon, 2008 ;  Ewen  et al ., 2012 ;  Seddon  et al ., 2014 ). The International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) recognizes two types of conservation translocation to restore populations, namely (i) reinforcements, in which individuals are released into an existing population of conspecifics to enhance the sustainability of populations, and (ii) reintroductions, in which individuals are released in a historically occupied area in order to re-establish a population after extirpation. Although these types of movements are ultimately aimed at helping species, the translocation process is inherently stressful, because associated procedures, such as habitat disturbance, capture, handling, processing, captivity, transport and release to a novel environment, are necessary and unavoidable ( Germano and Bishop, 2009 ;  Dickens  et al ., 2010 ;  Parker  et al ., 2012 ). In a recent review,  Tarszisz  et al . (2014)  identified physiology as a key disciplinary area that is lacking attention in conservation translocations and also highlighted how physiological data can improve short- and long-term translocation success.  In vertebrates, the acute stress response produces a rapid increase in glucocorticoid hormone secretion [corticosterone (CORT) or cortisol] to help individuals cope with immediate stressors ( Wingfield  et al ., 1998 ); consequently, non-essential processes (such as reproduction and growth) are suspended until homeostasis returns. Although the stress response serves to promote immediate survival, prolonged or sustained CORT secretion (typically expected during translocations) can manifest as &lsquo;chronic stress&rsquo; and is generally considered detrimental to overall health and fitness (i.e. the CORT-Fitness Hypothesis;  Sapolsky  et al ., 2000 ;  Wingfield and Sapolsky, 2003 ;  Bonier  et al ., 2009 ;  Parker  et al ., 2012 ;  Almasi  et al ., 2013 ). In a recent review of the associations between stress and movement of animals,  Teixeira  et al . (2007)  concluded that stress is a contributing factor to the success or failure of a translocation project. Stress induced by the initial translocation process and relocation to a novel environment increases the vulnerability of individuals to reproductive failure, disease, starvation, predation and long-range dispersal, thereby decreasing the chance that individuals will survive and that a self-sustaining population will result ( Teixeira  et al ., 2007 ;  Dickens  et al ., 2009 ,  2010 ;  Parker  et al ., 2012 ).  Measuring and monitoring CORT secretion is the most widely used method for assessing stress in vertebrates ( Wikelski and Cooke, 2006 ;  Dickens  et al ., 2010 ;  Sheriff  et al ., 2011 ). Although several factors relevant to translocation efforts influence CORT secretion, studies that assess and monitor stress (by way of CORT secretion) throughout and after the translocation process are limited ( Germano and Bishop, 2009 ;  Harrington  et al ., 2013 ;  Tarszisz  et al ., 2014 ). Numerous studies have shown that associated procedures commonly applied in translocation programmes (such as capture, handling and transport) stimulate a significant stress response and influence CORT secretion ( Fazio and Ferlazzo, 2003 ;  Langkilde and Shine, 2006 ;  Narayan and Hero, 2011 ;  Bliley and Woodley, 2012 ;  Baker  et al ., 2013 ;  Fazio  et al ., 2014 ). Likewise, altered CORT secretion has been associated with variation of environmental factors, such as exposure to humans ( French  et al ., 2010 ;  Taylor  et al ., 2014 ) and novel predators ( Berger  et al ., 2007 ;  R&ouml;dl  et al ., 2007 ), change in food availability ( Woodley  et al ., 2003 ;  Kitaysky  et al ., 2007 ;  Bryan  et al ., 2014 ), latitudinal differences ( Silverin  et al ., 1997 ;  Dahl  et al ., 2012 ;  Eikenaar  et al ., 2012 ;  Quirici  et al ., 2014 ) and habitat type ( French  et al ., 2008 ;  Zhang  et al ., 2011 ;  Li  et al ., 2012 ;  Bauer  et al ., 2013 ). In addition to experiencing acute stressors during the initial translocation process, translocated individuals released into new environments are faced with several survival challenges (such as finding food and shelter and avoiding predators); therefore, physiological stress is inevitable ( Teixeira  et al ., 2007 ).  Here, we examine the acute CORT response and long-term dynamics of CORT secretion through the translocation process in a rare reptile, the tuatara ( Sphenodon punctatus ). The tuatara is a protected reptile endemic to New Zealand and is the only living representative of the reptilian order Rhynchocephalia ( Jones and Cree, 2012 ). Although the tuatara is now considered non-threatened but &lsquo;at-risk &ndash; relict&rsquo; ( Hitchmough  et al ., 2013 ), translocations contribute to conservation and ecological restoration efforts and serve to re-&shy;establish tuatara within their pre-human range ( Hitchmough  et al ., 2013 ;  Cree, 2014 ). In addition to easing extinction pressure, translocations also offer a chance to examine and address relevant research questions ( Germano and Bishop, 2009 ;  Miller  et al ., 2012 ;  Cree, 2014 ). In 2012, wild tuatara were translocated to six island and mainland sanctuaries from two source populations (Lady Alice Island and Stephens Island/Takapourewa, New Zealand;  Cree, 2014 ), which presented an excellent opportunity to examine the CORT response to translocation in multiple populations. Previous studies have examined patterns of CORT secretion in tuatara; in general, baseline CORT in tuatara is fairly low (with plasma concentrations typically 2&ndash;5&emsp14;ng/ml), a significant CORT response to capture restraint is observed, and female reproductive condition, body temperature and season (but not time of day) are influential factors ( Tyrrell and Cree, 1998 ;  Tyrrell  et al ., 2000 ;  Anderson  et al ., 2014 ). In a recent study examining CORT secretion in four populations of tuatara, we found that baseline CORT was similar among all populations; however, the CORT response varied with latitude, seabird density, sex ratio and genetic diversity (L. Anderson, N. Nelson, D. Towns and A. Cree, unpublished data). Although translocations of tuatara continue to take place, CORT secretion (as an indicator of stress) during and after the translocation process has not been examined. Comparing CORT secretion simultaneously in translocated and source populations of tuatara would allow detection of altered CORT secretion that is correlated with environmental and/or habitat change and that would be an indication of chronic stress.  This study had two aims. First, we examined the acute CORT response in tuatara at different stages of the initial translocation process and tested the prediction that the acute CORT response would be amplified with cumulative stressors. Second, we tested whether long-term changes in CORT secretion provide evidence of &lsquo;chronic stress&rsquo; in three translocated populations (compared with the corresponding source populations as control animals). We made the following predictions: (i) baseline CORT (post-translocation) would be similar among all populations; and (ii) the CORT response (post-translocation) would be amplified in translocated populations that experienced a marked environmental and/or habitat change (e.g. a greater latitudinal shift). Moreover, body condition indices (mass relative to snout&ndash;vent length) in translocated populations (along with source populations as control animals) were examined, because chronic stress can influence energy expenditure ( Romero, 2002 ).  Populations involved in short- and long-term monitoring of physiological data (corticosterone) throughout a conservation translocation programme in New Zealand. Source populations (open circles) and translocated populations (filled circles) are shown.  Schematic diagram of short-term (upper panel) and long-term monitoring (lower panel) during the translocations to Motuihe Island from Lady Alice Island in March 2012 (translocation &lsquo;A&rsquo;) and to Cape Kidnappers and Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari from Stephens Island in October 2012 (translocation &lsquo;B&rsquo;). Short-term monitoring was carried out during translocation A only. Comparisons for long-term monitoring were made between source (dark grey) and translocated populations (light grey). The sex ratio (M:F) for each population is shown.  In translocation A only, we examined the acute CORT response (i.e. CORT secretion above baseline) through all stages of the initial translocation process, during which standard translocation protocols were followed ( Towns  et al ., 1990 ;  Cromarty and Alderson, 2013 ). In summary, adult tuatara (snout&ndash;vent length &ge;170&emsp14;mm) that had emerged from their underground burrows were captured by hand (between 20.00 and 04.00&emsp14;h), and sex was identified by examining secondary sex characteristics, such as head size/shape, body shape, spine shape and crest development ( Cree, 2014 ).  All individuals in the translocation programme were subjected to a capture-restraint &lsquo;hold&rsquo; [which involved capture of individuals and initial holding (between 40 and 60&emsp14;h) in cloth capture bags], processing (which involved handling, weighing, measuring and implantation of a passive integrated transponder tag) and transfer to the release site [which involved holding (between 6 and 10&emsp14;h) in perforated cardboard postal tubes (10&emsp14;cm&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;50&emsp14;cm), movement by foot to the helicopter pick-up site, a 30&emsp14;min helicopter flight, unloading and a 30&emsp14;min &shy;handing-over ceremony upon arrival at Motuihe Island].  To determine the acute CORT response at different stages of the translocation programme, we collected baseline CORT samples (following the blood sampling protocol described below in the &lsquo; Sampling protocol &rsquo; section) from tuatara at capture (0&emsp14;h;  n &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;54) and collected a second sample after one of the following: (i) an 18&emsp14;h hold ( n &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;15); (ii) a 42&emsp14;h hold ( n &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;14); (iii) a 42&emsp14;h hold&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;process&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;transfer ( n &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;11); or (iv) a 66&emsp14;h hold&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;process&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;transfer ( n &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;14). Tuatara do not show significant daily variation in baseline CORT ( Tyrrell and Cree, 1998 ); therefore, the time of day at sampling is unlikely to contribute to variation in CORT secretion in this study.  Figure  2  presents a schematic diagram of samples obtained during translocations A and B and displays sex ratios (M:F) for each population. For all samples, adult tuatara (both sexes) were captured at night by hand (between 20.00 and 04.00&emsp14;h). Upon capture, a baseline CORT sample was obtained, and after 3&emsp14;h capture restraint in a cloth bag, a second sample was obtained to determine the CORT response. In translocation A, we collected samples from the source population (Lady Alice Island; LA) before translocation (March 2012) and from the source (LA) and translocated (Motuihe Island; Mot) populations at 12&emsp14;months post-translocation (March 2013). In translocation B, we collected samples from the source population (Stephens Island; ST) before translocation (October 2012) and from the source (ST) and translocated [Cape Kidnappers (CK) or Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari (MT)] populations at 6&emsp14;months post-translocation (March 2013). Given that significant seasonal variation in CORT secretion has been observed between the breeding (March) and non-breeding (October) seasons in tuatara (L. Anderson, N. Nelson, D. Towns and A. Cree, unpublished data), we also analysed samples from the ST source population (obtained in a previous study; March 2012) for annual comparison. In order to determine whether the release site (within a translocated population) had a significant effect on CORT secretion, we collected post-&shy;translocation samples from two separate release-site locations on Mot (site 1&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;Orchards Bush and site 2&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;Von Luckner&apos;s Bush) and at MT (site 1&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;Tuatarium and site 2&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;Northern Enclosure).  Depending on field conditions (i.e. electricity available or not), blood samples were separated either by centrifuge (5&emsp14;min at 480  g ) or under normal gravity for 6&ndash;8&emsp14;h at 4&deg;C ( Reimers  et al ., 1983 ;  Sheriff  et al ., 2011 ;  Anderson  et al ., 2014 ). Plasma was transferred into cryogenic vials with a micropipette, stored in a cryogenic dry shipper (Thermo ScientificTM, Arctic ExpressTM Dual 10) or in a freezer at &minus;20&deg;C until return to the laboratory, and then stored at &minus;80&deg;C until assayed. Corticosterone was analysed with commercial enzyme immunoassay kits (Cayman Chemical Co., Ann Arbor, MI, USA) using a previously described method validated for tuatara ( Anderson  et al ., 2014 ). Briefly, CORT was extracted from plasma samples with redistilled dichloromethane, and each sample was assayed in duplicate. For each extraction, a subset of tritiated CORT samples were analysed to measure extraction recovery. Extraction recovery was 106&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;8&percnt; (mean&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SD) with an overall coefficient of variation of 7&percnt;. Intra-assay and interassay coefficients of variation were 9.9 and 14.2&percnt;, respectively.  Data analyses were carried out using R v3.2.0 statistical software (R Development Core, 2013) and Prism 6 (Graphpad Software Inc., La Jolla, CA, USA). All data were checked for assumptions of normality and were transformed if necessary. Linear mixed effects regression (LMER) models were fitted using the &lsquo;lme4&rsquo; package ( Bates, 2013 ) in R to analyse the following: (i) the acute CORT response during the initial translocation process; and (ii) the long-term dynamics of CORT secretion in translocated populations. Models were constructed through forward/backward stepwise regression procedures ( Field  et al ., 2012 ). In all LMER models, a random effect of tuatara identity was included to account for repeat sampling of individuals. The &lsquo;lmerTest&rsquo; package ( Kuznetsova, 2013 ) was used to compute  P -values for coefficients in final models, and significance was assumed at  P &emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05.  In analysis 1 (short-term monitoring), log-transformed CORT was the response variable, and sample (baseline, 18&emsp14;h hold, 42&emsp14;h hold, 42&emsp14;h hold&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;processing&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;transfer or 66&emsp14;h hold&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;processing&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;transfer) was the input variable. In analysis 2 (long-term monitoring), we first examined whether CORT secretion varied by release site within translocated populations, with log-transformed CORT the response variable and input variables of hour (0 or 3&emsp14;h), site (site 1 or site 2) and an interaction term of hour&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;site. Models were fitted to data from Motuihe Island and Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari, because these translocated populations had two separate release locations. Then, we compared CORT secretion between translocated and source (control) populations, with log-transformed CORT the response variable and input variables of hour (0 or 3&emsp14;h), sample (source pre-, source post-, translocated pre- or translocated post-) and an interaction term of hour&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;sample. Lastly, we compared body condition pre- and post-&shy;translocation, with body condition score (log mass/log snout&ndash;vent length) the response variable and sample (source pre-, source post-, translocated pre- or translocated post-) the input variable. Models were fitted to data from translocation A and B.  Results from a linear mixed-effects regression model examining corticosterone secretion (in nanograms per millilitre) during different stages of the translocation process  Coefficient estimates (positive or negative) are shown and indicate the &shy;direction of the linear regression from the intercept (baseline corticosterone 0&emsp14;h). Standard errors (SE),  t -values and  P -values are shown.  Short-term monitoring. The corticosterone response (in nanograms per millilitre) of tuatara ( Sphenodon punctatus ) at different stages of the translocation process during translocation A to Motuihe Island from Lady Alice Island in March 2012. Sample size ( n ) is indicated by the number at the base of each bar. Bars that share identical letters are not significantly different ( P &emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;0.05).  Results from linear mixed effects regression models examining dynamics of corticosterone secretion (in nanograms per millilitre) pre- and post-translocation to Motuihe Island from Lady Alice Island (source population; a) and to Cape Kidnappers and Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari from Stephens Island (source population; b)  Coefficient estimates (positive or negative) are shown and indicate the direction of the linear regression from the intercept (baseline corticosterone 0&emsp14;h). Standard error (SE),  t -values and  P -values are shown. Abbreviations: CK, Cape Kidnappers; LA, Lady Alice Island; MT, Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari; ST, Stephens Island.  Long-term monitoring. Dynamics of corticosterone (CORT) secretion (shown as means&emsp14;&plus;&emsp14;SEM) in populations of tuatara ( S. punctatus ) translocated to: ( a ) Motuihe Island from Lady Alice Island (LA); and ( b ) Cape Kidnappers Sanctuary (CK) and Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari (MT) from Stephens Island (ST). Sample size ( n ) is indicated by the number at the base of each bar and represents a paired sampled of baseline CORT (black bars) and the CORT response (3&emsp14;h minus 0&emsp14;h; grey bars) taken from all individuals. Bars that share identical letters are not significantly different ( P &emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;0.05).  In translocation B, CORT secretion varied between translocated (CK and MT) and source (ST) populations at 6&emsp14;months post-translocation. Baseline CORT was significantly lower in one translocated population (CK; LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;&minus;2.345,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.020), but was similar in the other translocated population (MT; LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;&minus;0.925,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.356) compared with the source (ST) population (Fig.  4 b). The CORT response was similar in one translocated population (CK; LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;&minus;1.247,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.213), but was significantly higher in the other translocated population (MT; LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;1.991,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.048) compared with the source (ST) population (Fig.  4 b). Corticosterone secretion (both baseline CORT and the CORT response) was similar between the two translocated populations (CK and MT; baseline CORT, LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;1.210,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.227; and CORT response, LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.745,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.457; Fig.  4 b). Corticosterone secretion in the source (ST) population was similar between both pre-translocation samples (March 2012 vs. October 2012; Table  2 b and Fig.  4 b). In all populations, baseline CORT was significantly higher at 6&emsp14;months post-translocation (March 2013) compared with both pre-translocation samples (March 2012 and October 2012; Table  2 b and Fig.  4 b). The CORT response was similar pre- and post-translocation in the two translocated populations (CK and MT), but was significantly lower post-translocation in the source (ST) population (Table  2 b and Fig.  4 b).  Body condition scores (log mass/log snout&ndash;vent length) in populations of tuatara ( S. punctatus ) translocated to: ( a ) Motuihe Island from Lady Alice Island (LA); and ( b ) Cape Kidnappers Sanctuary (CK) and Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari (MT) from Stephens Island (ST). Data points (means&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;SEM) that share identical letters are not significantly different ( P &emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;0.05).  In translocation B, body condition at 6&emsp14;months post-translocation was similar in one translocated population (CK; LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;&minus;1.351,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.179) but was significantly lower in the other translocated population (MT; LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;&minus;3.058,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.003) compared with the source (ST) population (Fig.  5 b). Furthermore, body condition in the translocated populations (CK and MT) varied, because body condition was significantly lower in the MT population compared with the CK population (LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;&minus;4.022,  P &emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001; Fig.  5 b). Body condition was similar post-translocation (March 2013) compared with pre-translocation (March 2012 and October 2012) in the translocated (CK) and source (ST) populations, but was significantly lower in the translocated (MT) population (CK, LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;1.261,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.210; and MT, LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;&minus;3.083,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.003; ST: LMER,  t &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;&minus;0.077,  P &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.938, Fig.  5 b).  Here, for the first time, we examined CORT secretion throughout the entire translocation process in a rare reptile (the tuatara,  S. punctatus ). Our findings were as follows: (i) plasma CORT concentrations remain elevated throughout the initial translocation process (short-term monitoring between 18 and 66&emsp14;h) but are not amplified by cumulative stressors; and (ii) the long-term dynamics of CORT secretion are similar in translocated and source populations. Taken together, our results show that tuatara are generally resilient to cumulative acute stressors and to chronic translocation stress.  To our knowledge, this is the first study to quantify the effect of cumulative stressors (routinely experienced in a translocation) on the acute CORT response in a reptile. We expected to see an effect of additive stressors on the acute CORT response, but this was not the case. The CORT response peaked at 18&emsp14;h of holding/captivity restraint, and additional processing procedures of measurements, microchip insertion and air transfer did not increase CORT secretion further, suggesting resistance to cumulative stressors in this species. Some species show diel variation of CORT secretion ( Breuner  et al ., 1999 ;  Jones and Bell, 2004 ), which can confound interpretation of results if samples are not taken at 24&emsp14;h intervals; however, no evidence of a diel cycle has been found in the tuatara ( Tyrrell and Cree, 1998 ). Nevertheless, a significant CORT response was observed throughout all stages of the translocation process, and at no point did CORT returned to baseline concentrations. This observation is consistent with results from our previous study examining the acute CORT response to capture restraint in tuatara, in which a return to baseline CORT concentrations was not observed over 24&emsp14;h ( Anderson  et al ., 2014 ). Therefore, we recommend that animal disturbance, holding time, transport duration and post-translocation disturbance be minimized in tuatara to mitigate potentially harmful effects of sustained CORT secretion in individuals directly following translocation.  In the present study, we did not examine patterns of CORT secretion in the immediate weeks following translocation (our first follow-up sampling occurred at 6&emsp14;months post-translocation). Consequently, we are lacking information on the speed of recovery to baseline CORT secretion levels.  Langkilde and Shine (2006)  found that CORT secretion in male and female lizards ( Eulamprus heatwolei ) subjected to microchip &shy;implantation remained elevated at 14&emsp14;days (post-treatment) and &shy;subsequently increased in response to additional stressors at that time. Likewise, tortoises ( Testudo hermanni ) that experienced handling plus ground transport had increased baseline CORT at 4&emsp14;weeks (post-stressor), compared with a control group that experienced handling only ( Fazio  et al ., 2014 ). These studies have shown that short-term CORT secretion dynamics are significantly altered by processes experienced during a translocation; therefore, obtaining supplementary information on short-term patterns (within 4&emsp14;weeks post-translocation) of CORT secretion in tuatara would shed light on the presence of a sustained CORT response and speed of recovery/negative feedback dynamics following translocation.  Summary of long-term dynamics of baseline CORT, the 3&emsp14;h CORT response and body condition at 12&emsp14;months post-translocation in source (Lady Alice Island or Stephens Island) and translocated populations (Motuihe Island, Cape Kidnappers or Sanctuary Mountain)  Arrows indicate direction of change and asterisks denote level of significance (&ast;&ast; P &emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.01 and &ast;&ast;&ast; P &emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001). Abbreviation: CORT, corticosterone.  Unexpectedly, through long-term monitoring in this study, we observed a significant annual increase in baseline CORT among all source and translocated populations (Table  3  and Fig.  4 ), probably indicating a ubiquitous environmental effect. The CORT response was unaltered in all populations, with the exception of the Stephens Island source population, where the CORT response was reduced at 12&emsp14;months post-&shy;translocation (Table  3 ). Body condition declined in the Lady Alice source population and the Motuihe Island and Cape Kidnappers translocated populations. Moreover, these results highlight the importance of collecting information simultaneously from source populations (as a control), because without this our results of increased baseline CORT in all translocated populations and reduced body condition in two out of three translocated populations could have been erroneously interpreted as an indication of chronic stress.  It is probable that we detected an unplanned/unexpected effect of drought on baseline CORT secretion in tuatara. In 2012&ndash;2013, New Zealand experienced its worst drought in 40&emsp14;years, with the North Island affected more severely ( Porteous and Mullan, 2013 ).  Lance  et al . (2010)  observed increased plasma CORT in alligators ( Alligator mississippiensis ) experiencing a severe drought, and recovery of CORT concentrations (to within normal limits) was observed after substantial rainfall. Although dehydration stress was not directly measured (by way of CORT secretion),  Davis and DeNardo (2009)  found that water supplementation in a long-lived desert lizard (the Gila monster,  Heloderma suspectum ) led to greater hydration, tail-fat reserves and surface activity. In a recent experimental study,  Dupoue  et al . (2014)  examined CORT secretion in water-deprived snakes ( Antaresia childreni ) and found that the CORT response, but not baseline CORT, was significantly higher in dehydrated snakes, and the loss of body mass was two to four times greater, compared with controls. The authors suggest that baseline CORT in snakes may respond only to a more severe degree of dehydration and that reduced locomotion (to reduce levels of dehydration) may explain the amplified CORT response in water-deprived snakes ( Dupoue  et al ., 2014 ).  Reptiles, including tuatara, can moderate water loss through behavioural adaptations, such as limiting movement/locomotion and retreating to (or not emerging from) burrows, caves, fallen logs or undersides of rocks, where humidity is higher ( Wilson  et al ., 2001 ;  Bonnet and Brischoux, 2008 ;  Davis and DeNardo, 2009 ;  Cree, 2014 ).  Dunlap (1995)  found that lizards ( Sceloporus occidentalis ) that were more active (compared with less active) during a drought experienced greater changes in physiological measures (e.g. CORT, weight loss, haematocrit and osmolality). Moreover,  Dunlap (1995)  suggested that individual variation in behavioural responses of reptiles (e.g. remaining active during drought) can lead to biased analysis of stress in natural populations. Burrowing in tuatara reduces water loss by up to three times the rate experienced when emerged ( Cree, 2014 ). Thus, it is possible that the increased baseline CORT observed in our study is influenced by sampling bias (capturing active individuals out of burrows rather than inactive individuals remaining in burrows).  Contrary to our prediction, an amplified CORT response (post-translocation) was not observed in translocated populations experiencing a shift to warmer climates/lower latitudes, specifically the Cape Kidnappers and Sanctuary Mountain translocated populations. In previous studies, we observed an amplified CORT response in tuatara at higher temperatures (L. Anderson, N. Nelson and A. Cree, unpublished data) and at lower latitudes (L. Anderson, N. Nelson, D. Towns and A. Cree, unpublished data). The Stephens Island (40&deg; 40&prime; S) source population showed a reduced CORT response (from pre-translocation to post-translocation), which was not observed in the Cape Kidnappers (39&deg; 64&prime; S) and Sanctuary Mountain (38&deg; 30&prime; S) translocated populations (in which the CORT response was unaltered). Likewise, individuals translocated to Motuihe Island (35&deg; 58&prime; S) from Lady Alice Island (35&deg; 53&prime; S) did not show an altered CORT response. It is possible that the individuals translocated from Stephens Island (to Cape Kidnappers and Sanctuary Mountain) would have shown a dampened CORT response (at 12&emsp14;months) if they remained on Stephens Island or were translocated to equal or higher latitudes. Examining CORT secretion in tuatara populations translocated to equal/higher latitudes [e.g. to Orokonui Ecosanctuary (45&deg; 77&prime; S) from Stephens Island;  Cree, 2014 ], might clarify the effects of latitudinal/climate change on the CORT response.  Although body condition did not statistically influence CORT secretion in our study, the sustained body condition in the Cape Kidnappers translocated population and in the Stephens Island source population suggests better hydration at these sites in the midst of a drought.  Porteous and Mullan (2013)  report that New Zealand&apos;s South Island (close to where Stephens Island is located) was not affected as severely as the North Island, and better hydration in the Cape Kidnappers population was probably achieved through provision of supplementary water sources (L. Anderson, personal observation). Reduced body condition has been observed in dehydrated/water-restricted reptiles, including snakes ( Dupoue  et al ., 2014 ;  Lillywhite  et al ., 2014 ), lizards ( Summers and Norman, 1988 ;  Dunlap, 1995 ;  Davis and DeNardo, 2009 ,  2010 ), alligators ( Lance  et al ., 2010 ) and turtles ( Ray  et al ., 2004 ,  2008 ;  van de Merwe  et al ., 2013 ). Clearly, information on relationships among water availability/dehydration, body condition, stress and CORT secretion is lacking and should be considered in light of imminent &shy;climate change.  This work was supported by  Victoria University of Wellington , the  Allan Wilson Centre for Molecular Ecology and Evolution , the  Centre for Biodiversity and Restoration Ecology  and the  San Diego Zoo .  We would like to thank Ng&#x0101;ti K&#x014D;ata iwi, Ng&#x0101;ti wai iwi, Te &#x0100;ti Awa iwi, Ngai Tai Ki Tamaki iwi, Ngati Paoa iwi, the New Zealand Department of Conservation (DOC) and the Natural Heritage Management Committee (Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari) for permission to carry out this research. We would also like to thank Tonkin &amp; Taylor Ltd, Motuihe Restoration Trust, Auckland Zoo, Cape Kidnappers Sanctuary and Sanctuary Mountain Maungatautari for assistance with this study. We also thank the numerous field volunteers involved with data collection and thank the staff of the Department of Zoology, University of Otago for supporting laboratory work. This work was carried out in accordance with the animal ethics committee of Victoria University of Wellington under AEC protocol no. 2009R12. 