 High water-use efficiency and growth contribute to success of non-native  Erodium cicutarium  in a Sonoran Desert winter annual community  Enemy release? An experiment with congeneric plant pairs and diverse above- and belowground enemies  Tradeoffs and adaptive negative correlations in evolutionary ecology  Linking growth strategies to long-term population dynamics in a guild of desert annuals  Functional tradeoffs determine species coexistence via the storage effect  Measuring plant interactions: a new comparative index  Leaf construction cost, nutrient concentration, and net CO 2  assimilation of native and invasive species in Hawaii  The evolution of an invasive plant: an experimental study with  Silene latifolia   Evolution of increased competitive ability in invasive nonindigenous plants: a hypothesis  Ecology. Interrelated causes of plant invasion  Interactions between resource availability and enemy release in plant invasion  Pracma: Practical numerical math functions R package version 1.5.0  Phenotypic and genetic differentiation between native and introduced plant populations  Competition between alien annual grasses and native annual plants in the Mojave Desert  Peak fire temperatures and effects on annual plants in the Mojave Desert  Effects of increased soil nitrogen on the dominance of alien annual plants in the Mojave Desert  Competition between native perennial and exotic annual grasses: implications for an historical invasion  Performance comparisons of co-occurring native and alien invasive plants: implications for conservation and restoration  Fluctuating resources in plant communities: a general theory of invasibility  Carbon isotope discrimination and photosynthesis  Nitrogen allocation, partitioning and use efficiency in three invasive plant species in comparison with their native congeners  Specific leaf area relates to the differences in leaf construction cost, photosynthesis, nitrogen allocation, and use efficiencies between invasive and noninvasive alien congeners  Resource-use efficiency and plant invasion in low-resource systems  Competitive effect and response in four annual plants  Variation in photosynthetic response to temperature in a guild of winter annual plants  Water-use efficiency and relative growth rate mediate competitive interactions in Sonoran Desert winter annual plants  Competition among old-field perennials at different levels of soil fertility and available space  Testing the evolution of increased competitive ability (EICA) hypothesis in a novel framework  Photosynthetic resource-use efficiency and demographic variability in desert winter annual plants  Understanding past, contemporary, and future dynamics of plants, populations, and communities using Sonoran Desert winter annuals  Suitability of stressed and vigorous plants to various insect herbivores  Interactions among unrelated species: granivorous rodents, a parasitic fungus, and a shared prey species  Effects of predation and competition on survivorship, fecundity, and community structure of desert annuals  Exotic plant invasions and the enemy release hypothesis  Differing effects of cattle grazing on native and alien plants  Contemporary climate change in the Sonoran Desert favors cold-adapted species  Differences in the timing of germination and reproduction relate to growth physiology and population dynamics of Sonoran Desert winter annuals  Fitness and physiology in a variable environment  Phenotypic selection favors missing trait combinations in coexisting annual plants  Trade-offs in community ecology: linking spatial scales and species coexistence  Progress in invasion biology: predicting invaders  Invasive California poppies ( Eschscholzia californica  Cham.) grow larger than native individuals under reduced competition  Leaf trait relationships of native and invasive plants: community- and global-scale comparisons  Native and exotic invasive plants have fundamentally similar carbon capture strategies  Mechanisms underlying the impacts of exotic plant invasions  Pre-mission invasion of  Erodium cicutarium  in California  Fire season and mulch reduction in a California grassland: a comparison of restoration strategies  Release of invasive plants from fungal and viral pathogens  Invasions: the trail behind, the path ahead, and a test of a disturbing idea  Can a breakdown in competition–colonization tradeoffs help explain the success of exotic species in the California flora?  Growth, biomass allocation and photosynthesis of invasive and native Hawaiian rainforest species  A theory of seed plant invasiveness: the first sketch  What attributes make some plant species more invasive?  Plant invasions: merging the concepts of species invasiveness and community invasibility  The population biology of invasive species.  Annu Rev Ecol Syst   Positive and negative effects of exotic  Erodium cicutarium  on an arid ecosystem  Out of the quagmire of plant defense hypotheses  Are plants really larger in their introduced ranges?  Seed mass and the competition/colonization trade-off: a sowing experiment  Bet hedging in a guild of desert annuals  Population and Community Dynamics in Variable Environments: The Desert Annual System, Environmental Fluctuation, Temporal Dynamics and Ecological Process  Are competitive effect and response two sides of the same coin, or fundamentally different?   Editor:  Lawren Sack  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Erodium cicutarium, an invasive plant, has recently increased in abundance in the Sonoran Desert. We tested hypotheses for its success, and found no evidence for a release from natural enemies. Instead, E. cicutarium was able to achieve higher growth rates while controlling leaf-level water loss, allowing it to out-compete natives.  The success of non-native, invasive species may be due to release from natural enemies, superior competitive abilities, or both. In the Sonoran Desert,  Erodium cicutarium  has increased in abundance over the last 30 years. While native species in this flora exhibit a strong among-species trade-off between relative growth rate and water-use efficiency,  E. cicutarium  seems to have a higher relative growth rate for its water-use efficiency value relative to the pattern across native species. This novel trait combination could provide the non-native species with a competitive advantage in this water-limited environment. To test the hypothesis that  E. cicutarium  is able to achieve high growth rates due to release from native herbivores, we compared the effects of herbivory on  E. cicutarium  and its native congener,  Erodium texanum . We also compared these two species across a range of environmental conditions, both in a common garden and in two distinct seasons in the field, using growth analysis, isotopic compositions and leaf-level gas exchange. Additionally, we compared the competitive abilities of the two  Erodium  species in a greenhouse experiment. We found no evidence of herbivory to either species. Physiological measurements in a common environment revealed that  E. cicutarium  was able to achieve high growth rates while simultaneously controlling leaf-level water loss. Non-native  E. cicutarium  responded to favourable conditions in the field with greater specific leaf area and leaf area ratio than native  E. texanum . The non-native  Erodium  was a stronger competitor than its native congener in a greenhouse competition experiment. The ability to maintain relatively higher values of water-use efficiency:relative growth rate in comparison to the native flora may be what enables  E. cictarium  to outcompete native species in both wet and dry years, resulting in an increase in abundance in the highly variable Sonoran Desert.  One primary goal in invasion biology is to understand how non-native species are able to outcompete native species and increase in abundance in their introduced range ( Levine  et al. , 2003 ;  Bossdorf  et al. , 2005 ;  Richardson and Pysek, 2006 ;  Moles  et al. , 2012 ). The enemy release hypothesis (ERH) states that non-native species perform better in their introduced range because they experience a decrease in natural enemies that restrict performance ( Keane and Crawley, 2002 ). It is also possible that invasive species are successful because they possess specific life history or physiological traits that allow them to outcompete natives ( Rejmanek, 1996 ;  Rejmanek and Richardson, 1996 ;  Kolar and Lodge, 2001 ;  Sakai  et al. , 2001 ). Many physiological studies have demonstrated that invasive species have traits that enable them to grow quickly, including higher specific leaf area (SLA), leaf nitrogen content and rates of CO 2  assimilation relative to native species ( Baruch and Goldstein, 1999 ;  Leishman  et al. , 2007 ;  Feng and Fu, 2008 ;  Feng  et al. , 2008 ). Thus, non-native species may be successful because they are physiologically superior to native species in terms of their ability to capture and use resources ( Funk and Vitousek, 2007 ). These traits that frequently characterize non-natives often trade off with the ability to tolerate predation, so a release from natural enemies may allow populations with such traits to succeed in new environments.  According to the ERH, the release from natural herbivores allows non-native species to grow faster than native species that may be experiencing herbivory (ERH;  Keane and Crawley, 2002 ). This hypothesis requires that defense mechanisms come at a cost to growth and fitness ( Inbar  et al. , 2001 ;  Stamp, 2003 ). Release from herbivory could allow individuals to invest in traits for growth and resource acquisition without the associated cost, allowing them to grow larger in high-resource conditions due to a breakdown of the growth–defense trade-off ( Blumenthal, 2006 ). If defense mechanisms result in a fitness cost, a release from herbivory could favour individuals that invest less in defense and more in growth and reproduction ( Handley  et al. , 2008 ). Given that competitive ability is often linked with size and fecundity ( Goldberg and Fleetwood, 1987 ;  Gurevitch  et al. , 1990 ;  Wang  et al. , 2010 ), this release from predation could allow non-native populations to evolve to be stronger competitors ( Blossey and Notzold, 1995 ). However, traits related to high growth rates and competitive abilities also trade off with traits related to abiotic stress tolerance, dispersal abilities and other tolerances and preferences, such that breakdowns in any of these trade-offs may explain the success of invasive species without a release from natural enemies ( Turnbull  et al. , 1999 ;  Agrawal  et al. , 2010 ;  Molina-Montenegro  et al. , 2012 ).  At the University of Arizona's Desert Laboratory in the Sonoran Desert, we have identified a trade-off between leaf-level water-use efficiency (WUE) and relative growth rate (RGR) in the winter annual plant community, such that species with high RGR have low WUE and vice versa ( Angert  et al. , 2007 ,  2009 ;  Huxman  et al. , 2008 ;  Kimball  et al. , 2013 ). These patterns were documented using stable isotopes of carbon (as a proxy for WUE) and growth analysis and, subsequently, have been supported by a large number of studies ( Huxman  et al. , 2013 ). When compared with the native flora, the non-native species present in our community ( Erodium cicutarium  and  Schismus barbatus ) have higher WUE for their given RGR ( Fig. S1 ). The high values of RGR relative to WUE for these two non-native species may indicate an unstable community, in which the non-natives will outcompete natives ( Kimball  et al. , 2013 ). Our long-term demographic data indicate that one of these species,  E. cicutarium , has experienced a slight increase in abundance over the last 30 years despite a general decline in the numbers of all winter annual species ( Kimball  et al. , 2010 ;  Venable and Kimball, 2013 ). It is unclear how or why the non-natives in our system are able to achieve higher RGR for their given WUE, but an understanding of this may be critical to understanding both the spread of invasive species and the future dynamics of invaded plant communities.   Erodium cicutarium  is native to the Mediterranean region and was introduced to the Sonoran Desert during the 1870s ( Mensing and Byrne, 1998 ). It now occurs throughout North America and is abundant in many different habitats, including California Grassland, Mojave Desert and Chihuahuan Desert ( Brooks, 2002 ;  Kimball and Schiffman, 2003 ;  Schutzenhofer and Valone, 2006 ). The competitive ability of  E. cicutarium  is known to increase with addition of nitrogen, burning, and increased precipitation in the Mojave Desert ( Brooks, 2000 ,  2002 ,  2003 ) and with burning and cattle grazing in California grasslands ( Meyer and Schiffman, 1999 ;  Kimball and Schiffman, 2003 ).  Erodium cicutarium  germinated and reproduced earlier than other Sonoran Desert winter annuals over the last 30 years ( Kimball  et al. , 2011 ), which may help to explain its success in dry years ( Kimball  et al. , 2012 ).  In this study, we focused on mechanisms that may have determined the success of  E. cicutarium  in our Sonoran Desert winter annual system. We compared the performance of  E. cicutarium  with a commonly found native congener with a similar growth form,  Erodium texanum.  We chose to focus on  E. cicutarium  rather than  S. barbatus , the other non-native species that exhibits high RGR and WUE, because  S. barbatus  is a grass, and native grasses do not occur in high abundance at our study site. In addition to being members of the same genus,  E. texanum  and  E. cicutarium  are similar to each other in many other ways, including buffered population dynamics, early life history transitions, high integrated WUE, high germination fractions and increased ability to photosynthesize at low temperatures ( Venable, 2007 ;  Huxman  et al. , 2008 ;  Kimball  et al. , 2011 ;  Gremer  et al. , 2012 ). These similarities make  E. texanum  a good choice for a native comparison to clarify mechanisms driving the success of  E. cicutarium . We also focused our attention on trait relationships of  E. cicutarium  compared with the general patterns found in the native flora. We addressed the following questions. (i) Does non-native  E. cicutarium  experience less herbivory than native  E. texanum , as would be predicted by the ERH? (ii) Are there unique combinations of physiological traits related to use of the primary limiting resource, water, and related to growth components that enable  E. cicutarium  to achieve both high RGR and WUE? (iii) Is  E. cicutarium  able to outcompete  E. texanum ? We used a combination of manipulative field experiments, common garden contrasts and observations in natural field settings to understand the mechanisms by which  E. cicutarium , a problematic invasive species, has succeeded in its introduced range.  Herbivore exclusion plots were established at the University of Arizona's Desert Laboratory at Tumamoc Hill in Tucson, AZ, USA to test the enemy release hypothesis. Specifically, we compared the performance of the non-native, invasive species  E. cicutarium  with its native congener,  E. texanum , in control and herbivore-exclusion plots.  On 10 December 2007, shortly after winter germination, 16 control and 16 exclusion plots were placed in areas where both species were present. We did not manipulate the density of plants in this experiment, so individuals are likely to have experienced some competition for resources in all plots. The plots were 50 cm ×50 cm, with data collected from a 25 cm × 25 cm area in the centre, and plots were placed in blocks to control for any non-visible environmental gradient. Hardware cloth was placed around each plot, with bird netting placed over the top. Carbaryl insecticide (active ingredient 1-naphthyl  N -methylcarbamate, brand SEVIN) was applied weekly with a backpack sprayer at a concentration of 59.1 ml/3.785 L water/92.9 m 2  (2 fl oz/gal water/1000 ft 2 ) throughout the growing season. Control plots had hardware cloth placed on the south and west sides to control for the influence of shading while still allowing herbivores to enter the plot, and were sprayed weekly with water to control for any influence of additional water received during pesticide application. The amount of shading and water added to both the pesticide and control plots was minimal, and the plots did not appear any greener than the surrounding landscape, so it is unlikely that shading or watering influenced plants in the study plots.  On 1 April 2008, at the end of the growing season, all  E. cicutarium  and  E. texanum  individuals were harvested from each plot. We noted the number of individuals per species per plot, and we counted the number of fruits on each individual plant. Overall biomass was determined by weighing dried plants. To determine whether the number of individuals, the average number of fruits produced by individuals per plot, or the average biomass of individuals per plot varied depending on the block, species, or treatment, we performed separate mixed-model ANOVAs for each dependent variable, with block as a random factor.  Our previous physiological measurements in the Sonoran Desert winter annual community indicated that  E. cicutarium  had higher RGR for its given integrated WUE (measured as carbon isotope ratios) than native species, including the congener  E. texanum  ( Fig. S1 ). Given that integrated water-use efficiency is an estimate of instantaneous WUE over the lifetime of the leaf ( Farquhar  et al. , 1989 ), more detailed measures of water loss were necessary to understand whether  E. cicutarium  achieved high WUE through low conductance and/or through high values of carbon assimilation. To determine whether the native and non-native  Erodium  species have differences in their physiology that may explain differences in WUE and RGR, we grew both species in a controlled environment and conducted measurements of growth and water loss.  In late January 2009, seeds of non-native  E. cicutarium  and native  E. texanum  were germinated on agar in Petri dishes. When seedlings were 2 weeks old, 24 individuals of each species were transplanted into 164 ml ConeTainer pots (Stuewe &amp; Sons, Inc., Corvallis, OR, USA) filled with a 2:3 mixture of 30-grit silica sand to Sunshine Soil Mix #3. Plants were placed in a single growth chamber set to a daytime high temperature of 21°C, and a night-time low of 5°C, which is close to average for the typical germination months of the winter growing season. After 2 weeks, on 4 February 2009, plants were transferred to the Desert Biome at the University of Arizona's Biosphere 2 facility (daytime high temperature of 19°C and low of 5°C). On 25 February, after all physiological measurements were completed but prior to reproduction, plants were divided into above- and below-ground material and dried at 60°C for 2 weeks to determine total biomass and the ratio of root mass to total biomass (RMR). General linear models were used to determine whether biomass varied depending on the species.  Just prior to reproduction, we measured stomatal conductance ( g  s ) with a Decagon leaf porometer on five individuals of each species at four different times throughout the day (08.30, 10.30, 13:30 and 16:30 h). As only four measurements were taken during the day, stomatal conductance was assumed to be zero at dawn and dusk to integrate under curves with six total time points. To estimate total daily patterns of leaf water exchange with the atmosphere, the trapz function in R was used to evaluate the area under the curve during a 12 h period ( Borchers, 2013 ). To test whether differences between species in daily water loss characteristics were due to chance, we conducted a permutation test. For each of 1000 permutations, species identities were randomized and daily water loss was estimated as described above. These randomized values were compared with observed values to test whether observed species differences were larger than expected by chance.  Using plants grown in natural settings in the field, we performed sequential harvests in 2 years with different rainfall patterns (2004–05 and 2007–08) for both  E. cicutarium  and  E. texanum  to understand how  E. cicutarium  achieved higher growth rates than natives for its given WUE. Summary growth components (e.g. SLA, RMR) during 2004–05 for  E. texanum , but not  E. cicutarium  (despite its inclusion in the 2004–05 study), were previously reported along with other native members of the winter annual community ( Angert  et al. , 2007 ). We repeated this growth analysis during the 2007–08 growing season following the methods presented by  Angert  et al.  (2007)  to determine whether growth of the two species varied depending on environmental conditions that differed between years. We used mixed-model ANCOVAs to analyse RGR (ln-transformed biomass over time). The analysis included ln-transformed biomass as the dependent variable, year (2004–05 vs. 2007–08 growing seasons) and species ( E. cicutarium  vs.  E. texanum ) as categorical variables, and time since germination (plant age) as a covariate. Of key interest is the year-by-species interaction included in the analyses to understand the potential differential performance of the invasive vs. native species across different environmental conditions. The plot from which individuals were collected was included as a random factor. We also tested whether the rate of dry mass increase per unit area (net assimilation rate; NAR) varied depending on age, year, species, or the interaction between year and species, with a similar motivation for interpretation as RGR. Values for RGR and NAR were calculated by linear regression as the slope of ln-transformed biomass through time and ln-transformed mass per leaf area through time.  To determine whether components of RGR varied with species, year, or their interaction, we analysed SLA (the ratio of leaf area to dry leaf mass), leaf area ratio (LAR; the ratio of leaf dry mass to total plant dry mass), root:shoot ratio, or leaf mass ratio (LMR; the ratio of leaf dry mass to total plant dry mass) using mixed-model ANOVAs of ln-transformed mid-season values (just prior to reproduction, 95 days after germination in each year). Plot was included as a random factor. We also compared the mid-season relative change in LAR (LAR 95 days after germination  – LAR 53 days after germination /LAR 53 days after germination ) to determine how species responded to mid-season precipitation in each year. This analysis provided a means to evaluate these two species in terms of the established growth strategies identified by  Angert  et al.  (2007) , where species in the community were generally divided into those that responded to resource availability by increasing carbon assimilation during cool post-rain conditions (high-WUE species) vs. those that produced large amounts of leaves later in the growing season (high-LAR species). Samples of dried leaf tissue from five individuals of each species in each year were sent to the stable isotope laboratory at University of Arizona for analysis of leaf nitrogen content and carbon isotope ratios. Carbon isotope ratio values were converted to  13 C discrimination values, or Δ ( Farquhar  et al. , 1989 ). Leaf nitrogen and Δ were analysed by ANOVAs with year, species and the species-by-year interaction as factors.  Individuals of non-native  E. cicutarium  and native  E. texanum  were transplanted from the field (the Desert Laboratory at Tumamoc Hill) into pots shortly after germination on 5 and 6 February 2009 and placed in the greenhouse at the University of Arizona. Six different combinations were planted in 4-inch pots containing a 2:3 mixture of 30-grit silica sand to Sunshine Soil Mix #3. The six planting combinations were as follows: (i)  E. cicutarium  planted alone; (ii)  E. texanum  planted alone; (iii)  E. cicutarium  with four individuals of  E. cicutarium ; (iv)  E. cicutarium  with four individuals of  E. texanum ; (v)  E. texanum  with four individuals of  E. texanum ; and (vi)  E. texanum  with four individuals of  E. cicutarium . The greenhouse was set to mimic the average daily outdoor temperatures during February and March, which ranged from 20 to 24°C. Each pot received equal amounts of water (∼6 ml in each pot) every day during the initial establishment period and every other day after the first 2 weeks. When plants had finished reproducing at the end of the growing season on 31 March 2009, we recorded the number of seeds produced by each focal plant. Plants were harvested, divided into above-ground and below-ground biomass, dried to a constant mass and weighed.  Number of individuals, mean number of fruits and mean mass of  Erodium texanum  (ERTE) and  Erodium cicutarium  (ERCI) individuals in control and herbivore exclusion plots. Values are means ± SEM.  Biomass and root mass ratio (root mass/total biomass) of  E. cicutarium  (ERCI) and  E. texanum  (ERTE) grown in a common environment at the University of Arizona's Biosphere 2 facility in Tucson, AZ, USA. Values are means ± 1 SEM.  Instantaneous conductance (top panel) measured with a leaf porometer at four different times during the day on non-native  E. cicutarium  (ERCI) and native  E. texanum  (ERTE) individuals growing in pots at University of Arizona's Biosphere 2 facility. The graph below shows integrated water loss over the course of a day for the two species as estimated from instantaneous measures, with the addition of two zero values at dawn and dusk.  Results from mixed-model ANOVAs on growth components of  Erodium cicutarium  and  Erodium texanum  collected from sequential harvests of plants growing in the field during two separate growing seasons  Plot was included as a random factor in all analyses. Relative growth rate (RGR) was analysed as the change in ln-transformed dry biomass over time, while net assimilation rate (NAR) was the change in ln-transformed mass per leaf area through time. Mid-season (95 days after germination) values of specific leaf area (SLA), leaf area ratio (LAR), root-to-shoot ratio and leaf mass ration (LMR) were ln-transformed prior to analysis.  Results from ANOVAs testing whether leaf nitrogen and leaf  13 C isotope discrimination (Δ, per mil) varied depending on species, year or the species-by-year interaction  Relative growth rate (RGR; measured as the slope of ln-transformed biomass by age), specific leaf area (SLA), change in leaf area ratio (LAR 95 days after germination  – LAR 53 days after germination /LAR 53 days after germination ) and the ratio of root biomass to shoot biomass for both species in 2 years. Values are means ± 1 SEM. Standard errors are not given for the change in LAR, because that value was calculated from mean values at two different time points.  Results of two-way ANOVAs on the relative interaction intensity (RII) calculated for number of seeds, total biomass, above-ground mass or root mass to determine whether the strength of the interaction depended on the species ( E. cicutarium  or  E. texanum ), the competitor (none,  E. cicutarium  or  E. texanum ) or the interaction between species and competitor  Relative interaction intensity (RII) for four response variables (root biomass, above-ground biomass, seed set and total biomass) indicating the strength of the interaction between  E. texanum  and  E. cicutarium  individuals in the competition experiment. More negative numbers indicate stronger effects of competition. See Materials and methods for the details on calculation of RII ( Armas  et al. , 2004 ). Error bars indicate ±1 SEM.  Identification of the mechanisms underlying differential performance of these native and invasive species across years and conditions in our system provides some insight into the challenge of understanding species invasions, particularly because we know the traits that are responsible for multi-decade population and community dynamics in this variable environment ( Huxman  et al. , 2013 ). It is clear that a novel combination of leaf-level physiological and whole-plant allocation strategies in comparison to the native flora contributes to the invasive success of  E. cicutarium  in the Sonoran Desert. The ability of  E. cicutarium  to achieve both high leaf-level water-use efficiency and high growth rates is consistent with previous studies suggesting that non-native species exhibited unique trait combinations that enhanced their capacity to outcompete natives in their introduced range ( Blumenthal, 2006 ;  Leishman  et al. , 2007 ;  Molina-Montenegro  et al. , 2012 ;  Kimball  et al. , 2013 ). Unique trait combinations of non-native species may be expressed in the native range or may have evolved in the novel range, perhaps due to enemy release ( Thebaud and Simberloff, 2001 ;  Blair and Wolfe, 2004 ;  Bossdorf  et al. , 2005 ). Here, although we did not find support for enemy release, we did find evidence of superior competitive abilities of non-native  E. cicutarium . The faster growth of  E. cicutarium , along with its success in competition trials, supports numerous other studies in which invasive species exhibited higher growth rates than natives, giving them a competitive advantage ( Pattison  et al. , 1998 ;  Daehler, 2003 ;  Leger and Rice, 2003 ).  The finding that  E. cicutarium  had greater SLA and LAR in 2004–05 suggests greater ability to take advantage of warm and wet periods with high plant density when the growth rate of  E. texanum  is restricted. This ability of  E. cicutarium  is consistent with performance patterns we identify in members of the native flora with high RGR and low WUE, in which some species use canopy display as a means to increase growth rate when resources are available, termed ‘morphological responders’ by  Angert  et al.  (2007) . At the same time, the strategy in  E. texanum  that allows for relatively greater performance during the cool periods immediately following winter rains, ‘physiological responders’, is still operational in  E. cicutarium , as has been seen in the photosynthetic patterns of a number of species in the flora ( Huxman  et al. , 2008 ). Thus, it appears that the invasive species in this system employs characteristics from both ends of the spectrum of native species' strategies for dealing with environmental variation, relying on a morphological response when resources are abundant and the physiological capacity to use soil water when it is restricted to cool periods or low amounts.  Levels of herbivory did not differ between native  E. texanum  and non-native  E. cicutarium  as would be predicted by the ERH, suggesting that  E. cicutarium  may not be experiencing a release from natural enemies ( Keane and Crawley, 2002 ). We tested the ERH in only 1 year, and other studies of ERH have reported different results in different years, particularly in variable environments ( Davis  et al. , 2000 ;  Agrawal  et al. , 2005 ), but we do not think that this is a problem because we have not previously noticed significant levels of herbivory on  E. cicutarium , despite 30 years of long-term demographic studies ( Venable, 2007 ). One other, perhaps more serious, problem with our test of the ERH is that we excluded only animal herbivores and did not test for other kinds of enemies, such as fungal and viral pathogens ( Mitchell and Power, 2003 ). However, we did not notice mortality due to pathogens for any of the annuals in our long-term study plots during the year of this study. There is a fungus that attacks  E. cicutarium  ( Inouye, 1981 ), and seed herbivory by rodents influences both  Erodium  species ( Inouye  et al. , 1980 ), but these enemies influence both native and non-native species and do not support enemy release. The ERH may better explain success of non-native species in high-resource environments, where enemies are more likely to limit growth of natives ( Blumenthal, 2005 ,  2006 ).  Our result that non-native  E. cicutarium  was able to achieve greater overall biomass than native  E. texanum , despite its lower stomatal conductance, is consistent with the hypothesis that non-natives have higher resource-use efficiency ( Funk and Vitousek, 2007 ). Other studies comparing physiological traits of natives and co-occurring invasive species have identified several common trait differences of invasive species, including higher SLA, foliar nutrients, carbon assimilation rates and growth rates ( Baruch and Goldstein, 1999 ;  Funk and Vitousek, 2007 ;  Leishman  et al. , 2007 ). We found no differences between leaf nitrogen values from field-grown plants in two different years. Non-native  E. cicutarium  had higher RGR than native  E. texanum  in a warm year in the field, which occurred in part through greater SLA and LAR. The native species also had slightly lower integrated WUE in that year, although this difference was not significant. Both of the species contrasted here have relatively high long-term WUE relative to other winter annual species in the community ( Angert  et al. , 2007 ). Our data suggest that they achieve this high WUE in slightly different ways. In a separate experiment, both species had higher carbon assimilation rates and a greater ability to photosynthesize at cooler temperatures relative to other winter annuals ( Gremer  et al. , 2012 ). In the present study, the native  E. texanum  was able to respond to a mid-season rain event in the cool year by increasing LAR more than  E. cicutarium , perhaps due to its ability to achieve maximal photosynthetic rate at a slightly lower temperature ( Gremer  et al. , 2012 ). Non-native  E. cicutarium  exhibited significantly lower stomatal conductance than  E. texanum , indicating that it is achieving high leaf-level WUE by reducing water loss in addition to investing in carbon assimilation. It appears that, in this system, the ability of non-native species to use resources efficiently does not come at the cost of a reduced ability to grow rapidly when resources are abundant, which is present in the patterns of the remaining species in the community.  There is some disagreement as to whether invasive species differ in their resource-use efficiency ( Funk and Vitousek, 2007 ) or simply tend to have traits that allow for fast growth in high-resource environments ( Daehler, 2003 ;  Leishman  et al. , 2007 ,  2010 ). In our study system, the two non-natives ( E. cicutarium  and  S. barbatus ) seemed to be more efficient in the way that they used resources (water) and able to achieve higher RGR when resources were abundant ( Fig. S1 ). This may be a pattern that is general to all invasive species or it may be a result of these two strategies being so important in the dynamics of Sonoran Desert winter annual plants, given that this system is one of the few in existence where the physiological and growth strategies for the dominant species is well documented in the context of decades of generations of population dynamics ( Huxman  et al. , 2013 ). Our data suggest that invasive success derives from the combination of these water-use efficiency and growth response strategies in the context of the relative values existing in the local flora rather than the ranking values of either trait syndrome in isolation.  Results from our competition experiment indicated that non-native  E. cicutarium  was less impacted by competition than  E. texanum . Faster RGR of  E. cicutarium  may be a factor, because size has been demonstrated to go along with competitive ability in other studies ( Goldberg and Fleetwood, 1987 ;  Gurevitch  et al. , 1990 ;  Wang  et al. , 2010 ;  Gremer  et al. , 2013 ). Invasive species frequently outcompete natives in high-resource conditions similar to those in our greenhouse experiment ( Daehler, 2003 ;  Corbin and D'Antonio, 2004 ). It is unclear whether  E. cicutarium  would outcompete  E. texanum  in low-resource conditions as well, but our long-term demographic data indicate that  E. cicutarium  has maintained higher fitness than other winter annual species during dry years ( Kimball  et al. , 2012 ). From our measurements of growth in two different years, we would predict that non-native  E. cicutarium  would outcompete native  E. texanum  in the field, especially in warm years. Native  E. texanum  may exhibit greater growth in cool years than in warm years, yet this would probably not allow the native species to outcompete  E. cicutarium .  Among-species trade-offs are thought to be important in maintaining diversity in communities ( Kneitel and Chase, 2004 ;  Agrawal  et al. , 2010 ). It is likely that the ability of  E. cicutarium  to grow quickly while simultaneously controlling leaf-level water loss will contribute to instability of the Sonoran Desert winter annual community ( Molina-Montenegro  et al. , 2012 ;  Kimball  et al. , 2013 ). There has been a warming and drying of the Sonoran Desert, which has been accompanied by a delayed arrival of germination-triggering rain events, favouring species that germinate at cooler temperatures ( Kimball  et al. , 2010 ). The increase in abundance of  E. cicutarium , along with other species at the high-WUE end of the trade-off axis, seems to be due partly to the ability of high-WUE species to germinate in these cooler conditions and partly to their ability to withstand years with high late-season temperatures ( Kimball  et al. , 2010 ,  2012 ;  Gremer  et al. , 2012 ). This pattern of changing weather conditions suggests that  E. cicutarium  may continue to increase in abundance, probably due to its superior physiological traits.   Supplementary material is available at  Conservation Physiology  online.   We thank J. Horst for assistance with plant propagation and measurement. We thank Lisa Patrick Bentley for assisting with measurements at Biosphere 2 and for discussions related to this manuscript. We thank Anna Tyler for assistance at Biosphere 2. This work was supported by the National Science Foundation [DEB-0924658], by the Philecology Foundation of Fort Worth, TX, USA, and by University of California, Irvine's Center for Environmental Biology, which was founded in 2010 by a grant from Donald Bren and The Irvine Company. 