Redtail and red colobus monkeys show intersite urinary cortisol concentration variation in Kibale National Park, UgandaBehavioral, endocrine, and immunological correlates of immigration by an aggressive male into a natural primate groupHormones and social behavior in primatesVariation in behavioral and hormonal responses of adult male gray-cheeked mangabeys (<italic>Lophocebus albigena</italic>) to crowned eagles (<italic>Stephanoaetus coronatus</italic>) in Kibale National Park, UgandaReproductive tactics influence cortisol levels in individual male gray-cheeked mangabeys (<italic>Lophocebus albigena</italic>)New photographic evidence of the African golden cat (<italic>Profelis aurata</italic> Temminck) at Mainaro, Kibale National Park, UgandaComparative aspects of the metabolism and excretion of cortisol in three individual nonhuman primatesReview of factors influencing stress hormones in fish and wildlifeHabitat degradation and seasonality affect physiological stress levels of <italic>Eulemur collaris</italic> in littoral forest fragmentsRed-tail monkey groups in forest patches outside the protected area system in the Kampala areaSeasonal and altitudinal effects on glucocorticoid metabolites in a wild primate (<italic>Theropithecus gelada</italic>)How do howler monkeys cope with habitat fragmentationChimpanzees&ndash;red colobus monkeys: a predator&ndash;prey systemThe ecology of stress: a marriage of disciplinesReality as the leading cause of stress: rethinking the impact of chronic stress in natureBlood, urine, saliva and dip-sticks: experiences in Africa, New Guinea, and BostonBehavioural patterns associated with faecal cortisol levels in free-ranging female ring-tailed lemurs, <italic>Lemur catta</italic>Implications of small scale variation in ecological conditions for the diet and density of red colobus monkeysConstraints on group size in red colobus and red-tailed guenons: examining the generality of the ecological constraints modelThirty years of research in Kibale National Park, Uganda reveals a complex picture for conservationDo food availability, parasitism, and stress have synergistic effects on red colobus populations living in forest fragments?Population declines of colobus in Western Uganda and conservation value of forest fragmentsInteractions between the hypothalamic&ndash;pituitary&ndash;adrenal axis and the female reproductive system: clinical implicationsPhylogenetic influences on hormone levels across the primate orderDevelopmental effects of endocrine-disrupting chemicals in wildlife and humansWolf presence in the ranch of origin: impacts on temperament and physiological responses of beef cattle following a simulated wolf encounterWhat is conservation physiology? Perspectives on an increasingly integrated and essential scienceSocial dominance and stress hormonesLife history and the ecology of stress: how do glucocorticoid hormones influence life-history variation in animals?Measures of physiological stress: a transparent or opaque window into the status, management and conservation of species?Urinary androgens and cortisol metabolites in field-sampled bonobos (<italic>Pan paniscus</italic>)Behavioural and hormonal responses to predation in female chacma baboons (<italic>Papio hamadryas ursinus</italic>)Influence of reproductive season and rank on fecal glucocorticoid levels in free-ranging male Verreaux&apos;s sifakas (<italic>Propithecus verreauxi</italic>)Predator exposure alters stress physiology in guppies across timescalesSeasonal energetic stress in a tropical forest primate: proximate causes and evolutionary implicationsCortisol as a sensitive index of heat-intoleranceImpact of logging-induced ecological change on disease dynamics in African forest primatesEffects of logging on gastrointestinal parasite infections and infection risk in African primatesOn the use of non-invasive hormone research in uncontrolled, natural environments: the problem with sex, diet, metabolic rate and the individualOral administration of a corticotropin-releasing hormone receptor antagonist significantly attenuates behavioral, neuroendocrine, and autonomic responses to stress in primatesBehavioural and physiological aspects of stress and aggression in nonhuman primatesFifteen years after &lsquo;Wingspread&rsquo;&mdash;environmental endocrine disrupters and human and wildlife health: where we are today and where we need to goDaily ranging behavior of red colobus (<italic>Colobus badius tephrosceles</italic>) in Kibale Forest, UgandaUrinary cortisol levels of gray-cheeked mangabeys are higher in disturbed compared to undisturbed forest areas in Kibale National Park, UgandaResponses of rain-forest primates to habitat disturbance: a reviewField collection and preservation of urine in orangutans and chimpanzeesRadioimmunoassay of estrone conjugates from urine dried on filter paperFeeding behavior of common chimpanzees and redtail monkeys: seed dispersal in the Kibale Forest, UgandaSeed handling in chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) and redtail monkeys (<italic>Cercopithecus ascanius</italic>): implications for understanding hominoid and cercopithecine fruit-processing strategies and seed dispersalPsychological stress on female mice diminishes the developmental potential of oocytes: a study using the predatory stress modelPhytochemicals and reproductive function in wild female Phayre&apos;s leaf monkeys (<italic>Trachypithecus phayrei crepusculus</italic>)Spatial distribution of primates in a mosaic of colonizing and old growth forest at Ngogo, Kibale National Park, UgandaTree population dynamics in Kibale National Park, Uganda 1975&ndash;1998Primate population dynamics over 32.9 years at Ngogo, Kibale National Park, UgandaUrinary testosterone levels of wild male bonobos (<italic>Pan paniscus</italic>) in the Lomako Forest, Democratic Republic of CongoEffects of forest fragmentation on the physiological stress response of black howler monkeysDoes hierarchy stability influence testosterone and cortisol levels of bearded capuchin monkeys (<italic>Sapajus libidinosus</italic>) adult males? A comparison between two wild groupsGroup size elicits specific physiological response in herbivoresDemographic influences on the hunting behavior of chimpanzeesPredatory behavior of crowned hawk-eagles (<italic>Stephanoaetus coronatus</italic>) in Kibale National Park, UgandaLethal intergroup aggression leads to territorial expansion in wild chimpanzeesDistinguishing forest tree communities in Kibale National Park, western Uganda using ordination and classification methodsDominance, cortisol and stress in wild chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic>)Mass differences among male mangabey monkeys inhabiting logged and unlogged forest compartmentsMangabey (<italic>Cercocebus albigena</italic>) population density, group size, and ranging: a twenty-year comparisonTaphonomic analysis of skeletal remains from chimpanzee hunts at Ngogo, Kibale National Park, UgandaForaging success, agonism, and predator alarms: behavioral predictors of cortisol in <italic>Lemur catta</italic>Stress and reproduction: physiologic and pathophysiologic interactions between the stress and reproductive axesPrimates living outside protected habitats are more stressed: the case of black howler monkeys in the Yucat&aacute;n PeninsulaStress in free-ranging mammals: integrating physiology, ecology, and natural historyEffects of phytoestrogens on mammalian reproductive physiologyPlasma corticosteroids in Hereford bulls exposed to high ambient temperatureEffects of logging, hunting, and forest fragment size on physiological stress levels of two sympatric ateline primates in ColombiaNutritional correlates of population density across habitats and logging intensities in redtail monkeys (<italic>Cercopithecus ascanius</italic>)Stress in wildlife species: noninvasive monitoring of glucocorticoidsMethods in primate nutritional ecology: a user&apos;s guideTaphonomic aspects of crowned-hawk eagle predation on monkeysStress-induced suppression of testicular function in the wild baboon: role of glucocorticoidsThe influence of social hierarchy on primate healthHippocampal damage associated with prolonged glucocorticoid exposure in primatesThe association of intergroup encounters, dominance status, and fecal androgen and glucocorticoid profiles in wild male white-faced capuchins (<italic>Cebus capucinus</italic>)Raptor abundance and habitat use in a highly-disturbed-forest landscape in western UgandaEffects of forestry practices on vegetation structure and bird community of Kibale National Park, UgandaComparative ecology of redtail monkeys (<italic>Cercopithecus ascanius schmidti</italic>) in logged and unlogged forest compartments of the Budongo Forest Reserve, UgandaFrom process to pattern: how fluctuating predation risk impacts the stress axis of snowshoe hares during the 10-year cycleUrine and fecal sample collection on filter paper for ovarian hormone evaluationsNon-invasive monitoring of physiological stress in the Western lowland gorilla (<italic>Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic>): validation of a fecal glucocorticoid assay and methods for practical application in the fieldCrowned eagles (<italic>Stephanoaetus coronatus</italic>) in rainforest: observations on breeding chronology and diet at a nest in UgandaFace your fears: cleaning gobies inspect predators despite being stressed by themThe influence of chimpanzee predation on group size and anti-predator behaviour in red colobus monkeysAdvances in field-based studies of primate behavioral endocrinologySeasonal and social correlates of fecal testosterone and cortisol levels in wild male muriquis (<italic>Brachyteles arachnoides</italic>)Comparison of the behavior and ecology of red colobus and redtail monkeys in the Kibale Forest, UgandaPrey selectivity by crowned hawk-eagles on monkeys in the Kibale Forest, UgandaGroup fission in redtail monkeys (<italic>Cercopithecus ascanius</italic>) in the Kibale Forest, UgandaA microcalorimetric determination of creatinine in urine by the Jaffe reactionInfluence of chimpanzee predation on associations between red colobus and red-tailed monkeys at Ngogo, Kibale National Park, UgandaPrimate abundance along five transect lines at Ngogo, Kibale National Park, UgandaInfluence of chimpanzee predation on the red colobus population at Ngogo, Kibale National Park, UgandaEffects of stress on reproduction in non-rodent mammals: the role of glucocorticoids and sex differencesEndocrine disruption in wildlife: a critical review of the evidenceAgricultural encroachment in Uganda&apos;s Kibale ForestImplementing carbon sequestration projects in two contrasting areas: the Czech Republic and UgandaMean fecal glucocorticoid metabolites are associated with vigilance, whereas immediate cortisol levels better reflect acute anti-predator responses in meerkatsBehavioral and physiological responses of striped field mice (<italic>Apodemus agrarius</italic>) to predator odorSpatial structure in mangabey groupsEstrogenic plant consumption predicts red colobus monkey (<italic>Procolobus rufomitratus</italic>) hormonal state and behaviorEstrogenic plant foods of red colobus monkeys and mountain gorillas in UgandaPhysiological and behavioral effects of capture darting on red colobus monkeys (<italic>Procolobus rufomitratus</italic>) with a comparison to chimpanzee (<italic>Pan troglodytes</italic>) predationThe roles of phytoestrogens in primate ecology and evolutionChimpanzee-red colobus encounter rates show a red colobus population decline associated with predation by chimpanzees at NgogoHunting behavior of chimpanzees at Ngogo, Kibale National Park, UgandaRecent advances in noninvasive techniques to monitor hormone-behavior interactionsConservation physiologyGroup fission in red-tailed monkeys (<italic>Cercopithecus ascanius</italic>) in Kibale National Park, UgandaSteroid plant hormones: effects outside plant kingdom<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We compare cortisol levels in monkeys at two sites with varying habitat disturbance within Kibale National Park, Uganda. Both species have higher cortisol levels at the less disturbed of the two sites. Factors such as social dynamics or predation may be responsible, illustrating the subtleties of wild primate ecophysiology.Non-invasive measurement of urinary cortisol is a proven method of evaluating the impact of environmental stressors on wild primates. Variation in cortisol concentrations can reflect physiological stress, and prolonged elevation of circulating cortisol can significantly affect individual and population-level health. In a previous study, we found that urinary cortisol concentrations in grey-cheeked mangabeys (<italic>Lophocebus albigena</italic>) were higher at a highly disturbed site (Mainaro) in Kibale National Park, Uganda compared with a minimally disturbed site (Ngogo) in the same habitat. Here, we expand on this research, reporting on cortisol concentrations in two other cercopithecid monkeys (<italic>Cercopithecus ascanius</italic> and <italic>Piliocolobus rufomitratus</italic>) at the same two sites. We hypothesized that <italic>C. ascanius</italic> would show no difference between sites, given its preference for secondary forests, while <italic>P. rufomitratus</italic> would have higher cortisol concentrations at the disturbed site. Contrary to expectations, both species exhibited significantly higher cortisol concentrations at Ngogo (minimally disturbed) compared with Mainaro (disturbed). We suggest that these results may be caused by inter- or intragroup social dynamics, intersite differences in predation rate, fruit/food availability and chemistry, or a combination of these factors. These initial evaluations of urinary cortisol concentrations provide testable hypotheses on habitat disturbance and Kibale primate ecophysiology.Deterioration of environmental quality due to factors such as drought, increased predation and habitat disturbance can affect wild animal population health. Social factors, including competition for food and mating opportunities and instability in social relationships, can also influence well-being. Ecological or social perturbations may disrupt homeostasis and force immediate physiological adjustments, changing the hormonal milieu that regulates growth, immune function and reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C74">Reeder and Kramer, 2005</xref>). The development of methods to analyse stress biomarkers via non-invasive collection of urine and faeces from wild populations provides insights into ecophysiology in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C120">Wikelski and Cooke, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C79">Romano <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C27">Cooke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013b</xref>). Primate habitat disturbance varies greatly along a spectrum from large, relatively undisturbed swathes of suitable habitat (e.g. closed canopy forests) minimally affected by human activity to small, threatened fragments in landscapes extensively altered by humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C47">Johns and Skorupa, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C12">Bicca-Marques, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C57">Marsh, 2003</xref>). Comparing primate communities in undisturbed vs. disturbed habitats can illustrate the influence of environmental conditions on physiological stress.Cortisol is a glucocorticoid produced by the adrenal cortex under stimulation by adrenocorticotrophic hormone. It is responsible for classic stress responses to environmental challenges. It acts as an anti-inflammatory agent, facilitates the cellular uptake of glucose and acts as a catabolic agent. Its molecular structure and function are conserved across most vertebrates and all mammals, making it a viable and robust agent of investigation for conservation biology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C40">Griffin and Ojeda, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C67">Norris and Carr, 2013</xref>). Multiple stressors can stimulate increases in cortisol, such as food shortages, social instability, infection and injury, predation threat and habitat disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C83">Sapolsky, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C43">Honess and Marin, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C120">Wikelski and Cooke, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C2">Anestis, 2010</xref>). While the functional utility of short-term increases in cortisol are well known, chronically elevated cortisol can disrupt reproductive function, immunocompetence, growth and neurological function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C84">Sapolsky <italic>et al</italic>., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C23">Chrousos <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C41">Habib <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C14">Boonstra, 2013a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C15">b</xref>). Cortisol concentrations in primate urine reflect the amount of the hormone circulating in both conjugated and unconjugated forms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C7">Bahr <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>) and can be assessed using samples collected non-invasively in the field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C119">Whitten <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). As analytical methods improve, primatologists are providing more nuanced analyses of wild primate physiology and habitat-associated stressors such as habitat disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C17">Cavigelli, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C66">Muller and Wrangham, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C95">Strier and Ziegler, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C21">Chapman <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C59">Mart&iacute;nez-Mota <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C31">Dittami <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C4">Arlet <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C3">Arlet and Isbell, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C91">Shutt <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C77">Rimbach <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C9">Balestri <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).We previously found that urinary cortisol concentrations were higher in grey-cheeked mangabeys (<italic>Lophocebus albigena johnstoni</italic>) at a highly disturbed site than in conspecifics at a relatively undisturbed site in Kibale National Park, Uganda, presumably due to the physiological stress of living in the disturbed habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C46">Jaimez <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Here, we expand on this research to determine whether two other cercopithecid primates (redtail monkeys, <italic>Cercopithecus ascanius schmidti</italic>, and red colobus monkeys, <italic>Piliocolobus rufomitratus tephrosceles</italic>), sympatric with mangabeys at both sites, show similar disturbance-related differences in cortisol concentrations. We predicted that red colobus monkeys would show such differences because, like mangabeys, they preferentially use old-growth forest. In contrast, we predict that between-site differences would not occur in redtail monkeys, because they prefer young successional forest, like that covering much of the disturbed site.Map of Kibale National Park, Uganda.Red colobus monkeys are colobines whose diet comprises mostly young leaves and petioles but also includes fruits and mature leaves from a variety of species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C97">Struhsaker, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C18">Chapman and Chapman, 1999</xref>). They use a variety of habitat types and occupy some forest fragments outside the park (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C54">Lwanga, 2006</xref>), but they form relatively smaller groups and have higher parasite loads in forest fragments than within the park (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C37">Gillespie <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C21">Chapman <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Red colobus at Ngogo are under severe predation pressure from the large chimpanzee community there; hunting offtakes have been as much as 188 monkeys within 7&emsp14;months (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C105">Teelen, 2008</xref>). As a result, the local red colobus population has declined steeply in the last decade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C105">Teelen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C56">Lwanga <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C117">Watts and Amsler, 2013</xref>). Red colobus abundance is higher at Mainaro than at Ngogo; although limited data indicate a slightly higher mean group size at Ngogo (34&ndash;45 individuals per group for four groups; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C103">Teelen, 2007a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C104">b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C105">2008</xref>) than at Mainaro (mean&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;30 individuals per group; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C19">Chapman and Chapman, 2000</xref>), census data give much higher group abundance counts at Mainaro (mean&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.29 groups/km; G. P. Aronsen and S. Teelen, unpublished data) than at Ngogo (mean&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;of 0.06 groups/km; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C56">Lwanga <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>).Redtail monkeys, which are common at both sites, are smaller than mangabeys and red colobus. They use a broad mix of vegetation types, including old-growth forest, but apparently prefer young, regenerating forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C50">Lambert, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C88">Sheppard, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C10">Baranga, 2004</xref>). Redtails in unprotected forest fragments also have higher parasite loads than those within the park (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C38">Gillespie <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>), but they use areas where even colobines are uncommon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C20">Chapman <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>), indicating better ability to persist in suboptimal habitats. Redtail abundance may be slightly higher at Ngogo than at Mainaro; the mean number of groups encountered per kilometre during censuses there was 0.70 in 2007 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C56">Lwanga <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>), whereas the mean for Mainaro was 0.57 during 2007&ndash;2010 (G. P. Aronsen and S. Teelen, unpublished data). Published group size estimates are slightly higher for Ngogo (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;32 individuals; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C63">Mitani <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>) than for Mainaro (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;25; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C19">Chapman and Chapman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C63">Mitani <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>), although the variation in group size is considerable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C101">Struhsaker and Leland, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C121">Windfelder and Lwanga, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C56">Lwanga <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>).Animal encounter and urine collection followed the methods of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C46">Jaimez <italic>et al</italic>. (2012)</xref>. Between June and August 2010, G.P.A. and field assistants walked along existing forest transects to find primate groups; on encountering one group, they estimated its size and followed it until they lost it or until the end of the day. In Kibale, redtail day ranges average about 1&emsp14;km (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C51">Lambert, 1999</xref>); red colobus day ranges average &sim;570&emsp14;m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C45">Isbell, 1983</xref>). Redtails sampled at Ngogo were habituated, but those at Mainaro were not, and red colobus were poorly habituated at both sites. To avoid generating additional stress via human presence, we attempted to avoid resampling the same group on consecutive days by spacing out collection locations by distances &gt;1&emsp14;km. This method was deployed successfully by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C46">Jaimez <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>. In related species, urinary cortisol values reflect circulating concentrations 4&ndash;8&emsp14;h in the past (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C119">Whitten <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>), thereby reducing the potential impact of observational contact with researchers.The study period occurred during what is typically a dry season, but note that neither energy availability nor reproduction shows strong seasonal variation in red colobus or redtails (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C99">Struhsaker, 1997</xref>). At each site, two different groups were sampled from each species (four groups from each site; eight groups in total). While following groups, we used plastic pipettes to collect urine from vegetation at the ground layer immediately after we saw an animal void. We immediately placed the urine into 1.5&emsp14;ml snap tubes that were labelled with sample identification numbers and information on individual sex and age (if known), date and time of day. To minimize the risk of sample cross-contamination, urine was collected only when fresh and when it was clear that multiple individuals had not urinated in the same area. The GPS location was noted for each sample. No samples were collected on days when it rained. Collections were made over 15&emsp14;day periods at each site. Monkeys at Mainaro were assigned to the disturbed forest (DF) group category, while those at Ngogo were assigned to the undisturbed forest (UF) group category. No monkeys are individually tagged or identifiable at these sites. We made every effort to avoid repeated sampling of single individuals by systematically moving through the group&apos;s spatial distribution and collecting samples during feeding, travel and resting. We did not resample individuals in an area where a team member had already walked through. We sampled across age and sex classes and pooled data for analysis. There is a risk of repeated sampling when studying any primate group, but our use of multiple groups and attempts to move exhaustively across the group over the course of a day provided our best effort to limit pseudoreplication.Field handling and storage followed previously deployed and validated field protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C48">Knott, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C46">Jaimez <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). At camp, 100&ndash;200&emsp14;&mu;l of urine (depending on amount collected) from each sample was pipetted onto an Atago PAL-10S Portable Digital Clinical Refractometer to record specific gravity to supplement creatinine measurements to correct for urine concentration. The refractometer was cleaned between samples. Each urine sample was then transferred onto Whatman filter paper. Each piece of filter paper was placed on aluminum foil and labelled with a sample identification number and with information on the sex and age of the individual (when known), date and time of day. Between 100 and 200&emsp14;&mu;l of urine was evenly pipetted onto the filter paper, in duplicate when the volume was sufficient. To protect samples against mould contamination, each piece of filter paper was immediately placed into a small ziplock bag that was in turn placed on aluminum foil resting over a layer of silica. These ziplock bags were placed in the shade and left undisturbed for 2&emsp14;days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C16">Campbell, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C90">Shideler <italic>et al</italic>., 1995</xref>). Once dried, samples were wrapped in foil, labelled with the sample number and placed in plastic slide sheets for storage and transport back to the Yale University Reproductive Ecology Laboratory.Urinary cortisol was assayed as follows. Elution of the filter paper was conducted by insertion into labelled 16&emsp14;mm&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;100&emsp14;mm borosilicate tubes. Five millilitres of 100&percnt; methanol was added to each test tube, and tubes were sealed with parafilm and refrigerated overnight. The following morning, the filter paper was squeezed against the side of the tube using sterilized forceps. Sample tubes were dried under compressed air or nitrogen, reconstituted with 1&emsp14;ml of distilled water, vortexed for 2&emsp14;min and sealed with parafilm until they were assayed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C49">Knott, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C58">Marshall and Hohmann, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C31">Dittami <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Creatinine values were also assessed via Jaffe&apos;s reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C102">Taussky, 1954</xref>).Creatinine correction was calculated by dividing the cortisol value by the creatinine value. Immediately after creatinine assays were completed, samples were assayed in duplicate using an unmodified high-sensitivity salivary cortisol enzyme immunoassay suitable for detecting the range of reconstituted urine hormone values (catalogue 1-3102; Salimetrics, State College, PA, USA). This assay has previously been deployed successfully in non-human primates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C46">Jaimez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Coefficients of variation for internal high- and low-quality control were 0.45 and 5.16&percnt;. Blanks read below detection levels. Samples that were excluded either had concentrations below detection limits of the assay or had insufficient volume.Results showed heteroscedastic distribution, so we logarithmically transformed raw data. Runs tests and residual plotting confirmed normality, with all results having a <italic>P</italic>-value&emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;0.05. Associations between cortisol and collection times were determined using standard linear regression. We used Student&apos;s unpaired <italic>t</italic>-tests to assess differences in mean urinary cortisol values. Statistical analyses were conducted using Prism 6.02 for Windows (GraphPad, Inc., San Diego, CA, USA). The value of &alpha; was set at 0.05.This research adhered to the legal requirements of Uganda and to the American Society of Primatologists Principles for the Ethical treatment of Nonhuman Primates. The Yale University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee issued a waiver for the research because of its strictly non-invasive methods.Daily variation in cortisol in redtail (left) and red colobus monkeys (right). Mainaro data are grey circles and dashed lines; Ngogo data are black squares and solid lines. The 95&percnt; confidence intervals are plotted.Logarithmically transformed cortisol concentrations for redtail (left) and red colobus monkeys (right). Means and standard deviations are shown. Mainaro (disturbed forest) is grey, and Ngogo (undisturbed forest) is black. Intersite variation is significant for both species (for redtails, <italic>t</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;2.063, d.f.&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;48, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.045; and for red colobus, <italic>t</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;2.536, d.f.&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;28, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.017).Cortisol can serve as an indicator of physiological stress, and habitat disturbance can lead to increases in cortisol secretion. The hypothalamic&ndash;pituitary&ndash;adrenal feedback response is conservative across primates and largely consistent across the family Cercopithecidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C24">Coe <italic>et al</italic>., 1992</xref>). Our previous research showed that mangabeys had elevated cortisol at Mainaro relative to Ngogo, suggesting physiological stress due to habitat disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C46">Jaimez <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). In northern Kibale, mangabeys and red colobus in disturbed habitats show longer travel duration, lower body mass and (for red colobus) higher faecal cortisol concentrations relative to conspecifics in less disturbed areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C69">Olupot <italic>et al</italic>., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C68">Olupot, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C38">Gillespie <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C21">Chapman <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C22">2007</xref>).Given these results for mangabeys, we predicted similar cortisol elevations for Mainaro red colobus, but no difference between Mainaro and Ngogo for redtails. Instead, both species showed higher cortisol concentrations at Ngogo, the less disturbed of our two study sites. Groups at both sites also showed the expected diurnal decrease in cortisol concentrations, but the decrease was non-significant, suggesting physiological stress as the reason for the between-site differences. We therefore need an explanation for why these results differ from those reported earlier for mangabeys. Factors that may contribute independently or in combination to cortisol variation are described below.Plasma cortisol concentrations are influenced by environmental perturbations and subsequent changes to food and/or activity levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C76">Rhynes and Ewing, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C36">Follenius <italic>et al.</italic>, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C59">Mart&iacute;nez-Mota <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C11">Beehner and McCann, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C35">Foerster <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C73">Rangel-Negr&iacute;n <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Fragmented habitat structure may allow for increased insolation (and therefore ambient temperature) and increased travel time, but these variables are expected to affect Mainaro (disturbed) populations more than Ngogo (undisturbed). The study was conducted during the dry season at Kibale, but temperature and rainfall data for the study period were not markedly different from previous years (J. S. Lwanga, unpublished data).Interindividual agonism influences primate cortisol concentrations. Factors such as male&ndash;male competition, female dominance, resource access, reproductive status and increased group size can all lead to increased social conflict (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C1">Alberts <italic>et al</italic>., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C96">Strier <italic>et al</italic>., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C28">Creel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C66">Muller and Wrangham, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C33">Fichtel <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C4">Arlet <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C60">Mendon&ccedil;a-Furtado <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). During our study period, group sizes were consistent with previously reported data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C19">Chapman and Chapman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C97">Struhsaker, 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C98">1980</xref>). Ngogo redtail group fission (and associated agonism) has been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C121">Windfelder and Lwanga, 2004</xref>), and thus, could be a source of intersite cortisol variation. The red colobus group distribution was relatively small at Ngogo during the study period (see Predation section below), making this explanation less viable. It is possible that we sampled Ngogo groups during a period of social instability, which could be tested via more long-term sampling of specific groups.Spatiotemporal variation in food availability can also lead to increased encounter rates and conflict between groups or species, thus altering primate cortisol concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C71">Pride, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C85">Schoof and Jack, 2013</xref>). While Ngogo has an old-growth forest, access to preferred fruiting trees/resources could lead to higher competition and associated increases in cortisol concentrations. During the study period, no interspecific/intergroup aggression or encounters were observed, and the fruits eaten by each species are neither high demand nor uncommon. At Mainaro, both redtails and red colobus fed on <italic>Chrysophyllum albidum</italic> and <italic>Uvariopsis congensis</italic> fruits most frequently. These resources are neither rare nor uncommon within Kibale. At Ngogo, redtails fed from these tree species, while red colobus were feeding most heavily on <italic>Ptyerygota mildbraedii</italic> fruits. This tree species is rare at Mainaro, but very common at Ngogo.The influence of exogenous sources on endocrine function has been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C25">Colborn <italic>et al</italic>., 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C107">Tyler <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C44">Hotchkiss <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>), but many aspects remain unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C75">Retana-M&aacute;rquez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C122">Zhabinskii <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Research on Ugandan red colobus has shown that consumption of <italic>Milettia dura</italic> can have an effect on cortisol concentrations due to phytoestrogen concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C113">Wasserman <italic>et al</italic>., 2012a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C114">b</xref>). This specific plant species was not eaten during the study period, and we are unaware of phytohormone studies of the plant species consumed during our study. This is an additional confounding factor, requiring both sampling of plants consumed by primates and analysis of these species&apos; pharmacokinetic influence on endocrine function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C78">Rode <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C53">Lu <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C80">Rothman <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C116">Wasserman <italic>et al</italic>., 2013b</xref>).Effects of predation pressure on cortisol concentrations are well documented in other animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C106">Tilbrook <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C32">Engh <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C3">Arlet and Isbell, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C89">Sheriff <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C111">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C93">Soares <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C61">Michelena <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C26">Cooke <italic>et al</italic>., 2013a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C34">Fischer <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C8">Baker <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Variation in predation rates may explain the cortisol concentration variation between Mainaro and Ngogo, especially for red colobus. Red colobus are the preferred prey of chimpanzees wherever the two species are sympatric (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C13">Boesch, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C94">Stanford, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C118">Watts and Mitani, 2002</xref>). The Ngogo chimpanzee community is the largest yet recorded and exerts unusually high predation pressure on the local red colobus population. While Ngogo chimpanzees hunt all diurnal primate species, effort and offtake is comparatively low for those other than red colobus. This is especially so for redtails and mangabeys, the most abundant primate species there (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C56">Lwanga <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). Predation by Ngogo chimpanzees has strongly affected red colobus demography and distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C62">Mitani and Watts, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C118">Watts and Mitani, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C70">Pobiner <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C105">Teelen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C117">Watts and Amsler, 2013</xref>). Census data show a steady decline of red colobus density within the chimpanzees&apos; home range, with encounter rates for red colobus declining steeply since 1998, almost certainly because of predation by chimpanzees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C64">Mitani <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C56">Lwanga <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C117">Watts and Amsler, 2013</xref>). Chimpanzees sometimes wait under or stalk red colobus groups for more than an hour before hunting them or leaving and sometimes attack the same group repeatedly over several hours (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C118">Watts and Mitani, 2002</xref>; D. Watts, personal observation). Besides their much lower frequency, hunts of redtails have much shorter durations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C118">Watts and Mitani, 2002</xref>). By implication, exposure to chimpanzees should have much greater physiological effects on red colobus than on redtails or mangabeys, and these effects could easily outweigh any direct effects of variation in energy availability. Following a chimpanzee predation event, Kanyawara red colobus faecal samples (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;6) showed elevated cortisol concentrations 2&ndash;5&emsp14;days afterwards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C115">Wasserman <italic>et al</italic>., 2013a</xref>). Given this, the pattern of elevated urinary cortisol in Ngogo red colobus may be associated with an unobserved chimpanzee predation event, constant vigilance for chimpanzee presence and/or variation in urinary/faecal cortisol concentrations following predation events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C7">Bahr <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C110">Voellmy <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).Crowned hawk-eagles (<italic>Stephanoaetus coronatus</italic>) are also major primate predators in Kibale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C92">Skorupa, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C100">Struhsaker and Leakey, 1990</xref>), and redtails are their most common prey at Ngogo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C63">Mitani <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C81">Sanders <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). Polyspecific associations between redtails and red colobus are more frequent at Ngogo than at Kanyawara, and redtails appear to initiate and maintain associations to limit eagle predation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C103">Teelen, 2007a</xref>). Habitat disturbance strongly restricts crowned hawk-eagle distribution in the Kibale region, where the species occurs only inside the park (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C86">Seavy and Apodaca, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C87">Sekercioglu, 2002</xref>). How much its distribution within Kibale varies is unknown. Crowned hawk-eagle home range size is estimated at 10&emsp14;km<sup>2</sup>, which implies that few pairs could use the Mainaro study area given its narrow east&ndash;west width (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV006F1">1</xref>). Crowned hawk-eagles and other raptors may have higher densities or higher predation success at Ngogo than at Mainaro; if so, this could explain why redtail cortisol concentrations were lower at Mainaro.Our previous study described higher concentrations of cortisol in mangabeys at Mainaro than at Ngogo, the inverse of the patterns seen in redtails and red colobus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C46">Jaimez <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Why does this contrast exist? Available data indicate that successful predation of mangabeys by chimpanzees and crowned hawk-eagles is relatively low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C42">Ham, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C112">Waser, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C118">Watts and Mitani, 2002</xref>; D. P. Watts, unpublished data). Adult male mangabeys often chase crowned hawk-eagles; they show elevated faecal cortisol concentrations for days afterwards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C3">Arlet and Isbell, 2009</xref>). At Ngogo, mangabeys usually flee from hunting attempts by chimpanzees, and, as for redtails, average hunt duration is short (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C118">Watts and Mitani, 2002</xref>). Consequently, chimpanzee predation attempts probably have limited physiological effects, and any such effects are likely to be outweighed by those of variation in food availability and variation in foraging effort.Our preliminary results illustrate the complexity of associating endocrine variation with single variables such as habitat fragmentation. The increased cortisol concentrations recorded in Ngogo redtails and red colobus relative to their Mainaro conspecifics may be associated with one or several variables, such as social group instability, fruit and leaf phytochemistry and/or predation pressure. The downstream effects of increased cortisol concentrations on individual fitness are under debate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C82">Sapolsky, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C72">Rabin <italic>et al</italic>., 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C39">Goymann, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C52">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C14">Boonstra, 2013a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C15">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C29">Crespi <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV006C30">Dantzer <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). If increased cortisol has a detrimental impact on aspects of senescence, immune function and fertility, the Ngogo red colobus population, already under severe predation pressure, may dwindle further due to the lethal combination of high predation loss and severe psychological/physiological stress. For Ngogo redtails, increased cortisol concentrations may be an indicator of impending social group fission, hierarchy instability or other stressful events. At Mainaro, which is currently undergoing restoration, the relatively lower cortisol concentrations suggest that this habitat currently provides a suitable environment for redtail and red colobus monkeys. The Mainaro mangabeys, with their relatively higher requirements for mature, undisturbed forests, may still be struggling with environmental stressors.Our study provides insights on the evaluation of primate condition and concerns within a national park, and the results are useful for conservation biology and park/site management protocols. The present results indicate that the Mainaro restoration efforts are providing suitable habitat for some, but not all, primate species, and continued efforts to bring Mainaro back into a more old-growth state will enhance and improve primate diversity. The results also indicate that primate population declines (red colobus) may result from biogenic (intra- or interspecific factors) rather than anthropogenic causes. Future studies at Kibale and for other primate species must combine physiology, socioecology, habitat structure, ecological community and nutritional data collection. Monitoring these variables will provide a more nuanced and cohesive evaluation of glucocorticoid responses in wild primates and provide measures of individual/community health and potential stressors.We received funding support from the Yale Institute for Biospheric Studies Program in Reproductive Ecology, the L.S.B. Leakey Foundation, the Great Ape Trust of Iowa and the Yale University Department of Anthropology.We thank the Ugandan President&apos;s Office, the Uganda Wildlife Authority and the Uganda National Council for Science and Technology for their permission to work in Kibale National Park. We thank the UWA/FACE Project Director (W. Chemutai), the Ngogo Chimpanzee Project Manager (J. Lwanga) and the camp staff of Ngogo and Mainaro for logistics in the field. G.P.A. especially thanks P. Birungi, D. Kamekune, P. Mwesigwa, F. Kamekune and J. Turyasingura for their field assistance during this project, and Stephanie Anestis for laboratory support. We appreciate the comments of two anonymous reviewers in improving this manuscript.