Expression patterns of ethylene biosynthesis genes from bananas during fruit ripening and in relationship with finger dropThe comparative consumer acceptability of triploid banana fruitInactivation of 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate oxidase involves oxidative modificationsEthylene: a gaseous signal molecule in plantsMolecular biology of ethylene during tomato fruit development and maturation<italic>Eto Brute</italic>? Role of ACS turnover in regulating ethylene biosynthesisMechanical characterisation of banana fruitsCharacterization of differential ripening pattern in association with ethylene biosynthesis in the fruits of five naturally occurring banana cultivars and detection of a GCC-box-specific DNA-binding proteinAn insight into the sequential, structural and phylogenetic properties of banana 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase 1 and study of its interaction with pyridoxal-5′-phosphate and aminoethoxyvinylglycineA Ser/Thr protein kinase phosphorylates MA-ACS1 (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic> 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid synthase 1) during banana fruit ripeningThe banana (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic>) genome and the evolution of monocotyledonous plantsThe regulation of MADS-box gene expression during ripening of banana and their regulatory interaction with ethyleneThe use of ethylene-suppressed lines to assess differential sensitivity to ethylene of the various ripening pathways in cantaloupe melonsEffects of exogenous propylene and fruit calcium on ripening of non-chilled and chilled Anjou pearsGénomique fonctionnelle et marqueurs de qualité chez l'abricotGenetic regulation of fruit development and ripeningMitogen-activated protein kinase 3 and 6 regulate <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>-induced ethylene production in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Ethylene-regulation of fruit softening and softening-related genes in peachFinger dropping from bunches of Australian Cavendish bananasGenomic organization of a diverse ACC synthase gene family in banana and expression characteristics of the gene member involved in ripening of banana fruitsPhysiological and biochemical changes during banana ripening and finger dropDifferential feedback regulation of ethylene biosynthesis in pulp and peel tissues of banana fruitMultiple sequence alignment with Clustal XResponses of banana fruit to treatment with 1-methylcyclopropeneCo-ordination of early and late ripening events in apples is regulated through differential sensitivities to ethyleneTurnover of LeACS2, a wound-inducible 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid synthase in tomato, is regulated by phosphorylation/dephosphorylationThe role of ethylene in kiwifruit softeningRecent advances in ethylene researchCorrelation between banana storage life and minimum treatment time required for ethylene responseCharacterization of ethylene biosynthesis associated with ripening in banana fruitAnalysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>−ΔΔCT</sup> methodEIN3-like gene expression during fruit ripening of Cavendish banana (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic> cv. Grande naine)Extraction and purification of total RNA from banana tissues (small scale)Expression patterns of cell wall modifying genes from banana during ripening in relationship with finger dropFactors affecting the development of finger drop in bananas after ripeningTREEVIEW: an application to display phylogenetic trees on personal computersEthylene, storage and ripening temperatures affect Dwarf Brazilian banana finger dropDifferent banana genotypes in relation to their susceptibility to finger drop and fruit characterizationCatalytic inactivation of ACC oxidase is associated with a decrease in the apparent pI of the proteinPrimer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmersEffects of relative humidity on banana finger dropInfluence of the ripening environment on the development of finger drop in bananasProtein phosphatase 2A controls ethylene biosynthesis by differentially regulating the turnover of ACC synthase isoformsApplication of thermal sums concept to estimate the time to harvest new banana hybrids for exportA MADS-box gene necessary for fruit ripening at the tomato ripening-inhibitor (rin) locusA modified hot borate method significantly enhances the yield of high-quality RNA from cotton1-Aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid synthase 2 is phosphorylated by calcium-dependent protein kinase 1 during cotton fiber elongationEthylene biosynthesis and signaling networks<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ETO1 specifically interacts with and negatively regulates type 2 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthasesThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Ethylene biosynthesis genes were transcriptionnally enhanced by finger drop during banana fruit ripening. Among them, there are ethylene- and ripening- (<italic>MaACO1, MaACS1</italic>) and wounded-related (<italic>MaACS2</italic>). Thus, this process might be associated with ethylene production and share in common some components with wounding, another breaking event.Banana finger drop is defined as dislodgement of individual fruits from the hand at the pedicel rupture area. For some banana varieties, this is a major feature of the ripening process, in addition to ethylene production and sugar metabolism. The few studies devoted to assessing the physiological and molecular basis of this process revealed (i) the similarity between this process and softening, (ii) the early onset of related molecular events, between the first and fourth day after ripening induction, and (iii) the putative involvement of ethylene as a regulatory factor. This study was conducted with the aim of identifying, through a candidate gene approach, a quality-related marker that could be used as a tool in breeding programmes. Here we examined the relationship between ripening ethylene biosynthesis (EB) and finger drop in order to gain further insight into the upstream regulatory steps of the banana finger drop process and to identify putative related candidate genes.Postharvest ripening of green banana fruit was induced by acetylene treatment and fruit taken at 1–4 days after ripening induction, and total RNA extracted from the median area [control zone (CZ)] and the pedicel rupture area [drop zone (DZ)] of peel tissue. Then the expression patterns of EB genes (<italic>MaACO1</italic>, <italic>MaACO2</italic>, <italic>MaACS1</italic>, <italic>MaACS2</italic>, <italic>MaACS3</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic>) were comparatively examined in CZ and DZ via real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction.Differential expression of EB gene was observed in CZ and DZ during the postharvest period examined in this study. <italic>MaACO1</italic>, <italic>MaACS2</italic> and <italic>MaACS1</italic> were more highly induced in DZ than in the control, while a slight induction of the <italic>MaACS4</italic> gene was observed. No marked differences between the two zones were observed for the <italic>MaACO2</italic> gene.The finger drop process enhanced EB gene expression including developmental- and ripening-induced genes (<italic>MaACO1</italic>), specific ripening-induced genes (<italic>MaACS1</italic>) and wound-induced genes (<italic>MaACS2</italic>). Thus, this process might be associated with a specific ethylene production in DZ of the pedicel area and the result of crosstalk between developmental, ripening and wound regulatory pathways. <italic>MaACO1</italic>, <italic>MaACS1</italic>, <italic>MaACS2</italic>, and to a lesser extent <italic>MaACS4</italic> genes, which are more highly induced in DZ than in CZ, could be considered as putative candidates of the finger drop process.Ethylene is a gaseous plant hormone that regulates many developmental events and biotic and abiotic stress responses of plants. Banana fruits undergo a climacteric ripening process. This is characterized by a ripening-related increase in respiration and a burst of ethylene production concomitantly with physicochemical and biochemical changes, including chlorophyll breakdown, increased starch degradation and sugar synthesis, and fruit softening.Finger drop is a key feature that is closely associated with ripening of some banana varieties. This phenomenon has a substantial economic impact for the banana marketing sector. Indeed, bananas are marketed in hands of generally 4–9 fruits. Dislodgement of individual fruits from the hand at the pedicel area considerably reduces the commercial value of the product because hands with missing fingers or fingers without pedicels cannot be sold to consumers. Despite this economic importance, very few studies have been devoted to this phenomenon.The finger drop process was first observed in bananas of the Cavendish subgroup in 1934 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C20">Hicks 1934</xref>). It was defined as physiological softening and weakening, thus causing individual fruit in a hand to separate from the crown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C2">Baldry <italic>et al.</italic> 1981</xref>). The sensitivity to finger drop within <italic>Musa</italic> germplasm varies according to the variety and ploidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C37">New and Marriott 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C40">Pereira <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>), growing and postharvest ripening, and storage conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C44">Semple and Thompson 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C39">Paull 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C43">Saengpook <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). At the biochemical level, changes in water-soluble pectin, i.e. a cell wall polysaccharide component, have also been reported to be associated with finger drop. In addition to the activities of some cell wall hydrolases including pectate lyase and polygalacturonase, an increase in water-soluble pectin has been observed in the drop zone (DZ) as compared with control fruit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C21">Imsabai <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Recent molecular studies performed in Cavendish bananas also showed that a change in the expression of major cell-wall-modifying genes occurs specifically in the finger drop area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C36">Mbéguié-A-Mbéguié <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Overall, major molecular changes in the expression of genes coding for cell-wall-modifying proteins (CWMPs) occurred 1–4 days after ripening induction, but in a sequential manner. Firstly, there were changes in the expression of pectolytic and cell-wall-loosening genes, mainly during Days 1–2, followed by changes in the expression of xyloglucan genes, mainly during Days 3–4. The fact that some CWMP genes are involved in both finger drop and the fruit-softening process, with transcriptional regulation by ethylene, suggests that these two processes that occur during banana fruit ripening might involve common regulatory mechanisms and factors, with ethylene being one of them.Numerous physicochemical, biochemical and molecular findings have shown that fruit softening is one of the ripening physiological processes that is most sensitive to ethylene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C16">Gerasopoulos and Richardson 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C24">Jiang <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C27">Kim <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C13">Flores <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C17">Grimplet 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C19">Hayama <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C25">Johnston <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>).In higher plants, including banana, 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) synthase (ACS) and ACC oxidase (ACO) catalysed the two key steps of the ethylene biosynthesis (EB) pathway: the formation of methionine via <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-<sc>l</sc>-methionine (AdoMet) and the cyclic non-protein amino acid ACC, respectively. In banana, ethylene production displays a sharp peak at the onset of ripening, followed by a rapid decrease thereafter due to a slight decline in the ACC content and a sharp decrease of <italic>in vivo</italic> ACO activity attributed to the availability of its cofactors, especially iron and ascorbate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C9">Choudhury <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>).The ACS and ACO proteins have been widely studied at both biochemical and molecular levels in different species. ACC oxidase and ACS are encoded by a multigenic family whose members are differentially regulated at transcriptional and translational levels by various developmental environmental and hormonal signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C4">Bleecker and Kende 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C49">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C30">Lin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). At least nine ACS and three ACO genes have been isolated from banana and published in the literature or directly registered in the GenBank database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C55">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C56">Inaba <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). However, only a few of them were fully characterized in regard to ripening and none in regard to the finger drop process. The ACS and ACO genes are transcriptionally and differentially regulated according to the tissue and stimuli. One ACS (<italic>MaACS1</italic>) and two ACO (<italic>MaACO1</italic> and <italic>MaACO2</italic>) genes were found to be ripening related (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C55">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C56">Inaba <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Post-translational regulation has also been reported in several plants, and mainly for ACS enzymes. This regulation is based on the C-terminal region of the ACS protein that can be directly phosphorylated by protein kinase, leading to an increase in protein stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C30">Lin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C18">Han <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C26">Kamiyoshihara <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C45">Skottke <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C48">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C11">Choudhury <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>), or bound to a substrate-specific adaptor, i.e. the ETO1 protein, and directed to the ubiquitin (Ub)/26S proteasome system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C6">Chae and Kieber 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C51">Yoshida <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). The ACS activity enzyme encoded by a ripening-related gene <italic>MaACS1</italic> from banana was also subjected to post-translational regulation during fruit ripening. A few studies also reported a proteolytic cleavage of the protein leading to a decrease in the apparent pI of the protein and its inactivation, suggesting that this protein might also be under post-translational regulation as was ACS protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C3">Barlow <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C41">Ramassamy <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>).In this study, we investigated, at the transcriptional level, the putative relationship between the finger drop process and EB, i.e. two processes that occur during banana fruit ripening. To this end, the transcript abundance of ACS and ACO genes from banana was estimated comparatively in the median zone and DZ during the ripening of bananas harvested at the commercial maturity stage. Our findings suggest a possible role of ethylene and ripening-regulated elements in the regulation of the finger drop mechanism.The banana fruits (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic>, AAA, Cavendish, cv Grande Naine) used in this study were collected from at least four banana plants taken randomly from a banana farm near the CIRAD research station (elevation 250 m; andosol; rainfall 3500 mm/year), Guadeloupe (French West Indies). Banana plants were grown under conventional field practices and, on the basis of heat concept unit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C46">Umber <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), fruits were harvested at commercial maturity stage [i.e. 900 degree-day (dd)], which corresponds to ∼90 days after flowering.After harvest, internal fruit of the median hand of all banana bunches, considered to be comparable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C31">Liu 1976</xref>), were pooled and kept for 24 h at 20 °C in chambers. Fruits were then placed into sealed Plexiglas boxes, and their ripening was induced by injection of 1000 p.p.m. acetylene and the boxes were kept for 24 h at 20 °C and ambient humidity. At the end of treatment, fruits were removed from the boxes and kept ripening at 20 °C in air and ambient temperature. During postharvest ripening, a sample of three fruits was taken daily to assess the postharvest ripening process and finger drop development.The physiological stage of fruit was assessed through measurement of soluble solid content (SSC). To this end, 5 g of fresh powder of pulp tissue were homogenized in an equivalent volume of distilled water and the mixture was centrifuged for 10 min at 10 000 × <italic>g</italic> and 4 °C. The fruit juice was collected and the SSC was determined using a digital Refracto 30PX/GS refractometer from Mettler Toledo (Grosseron, Saint-Herblain, France) and expressed in Brix. The development of finger drop was measured as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C8">Chillet <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>).All experiments were performed on three fruits at each time point. Immediately after these analyses, peel tissue corresponding to the median part of the fruit [control zone (CZ)] and to the rupture area of the fruit pedicel (DZ), and pulp tissue were sampled separately, frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80 °C until use for total RNA extraction and gene expression analysis.Total RNAs were extracted twice from a pooled sample tissue using a modified hot borate method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C47">Wan and Wilkins 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C35">Mbéguié-A-Mbéguié <italic>et al</italic>. 2008<italic>b</italic></xref>). At each developmental stage, peel tissue from three fruits was pooled due to the small quantity of peel material obtained per fruit, mainly from the DZ, thus making it difficult to blend in a coffee grinder.<bold>Sequences of gene-specific primers used in this study</bold>. The actin, <italic>MaACO1</italic>, <italic>MaACO2</italic> and <italic>MaACS2</italic> gene-specific primers used in this study were those previously described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C34">Mbéguié-A-Mbéguié <italic>et al</italic>. (2008<italic>a</italic>)</xref>. <italic>MaACS1</italic>, <italic>MaACS3</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic> primers were designed using primer-BLAST software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C42">Rozen and Skaletsky 2000</xref>) and mainly within the 3′-untranslated region for <italic>MaACS1</italic>, and within the coding region for <italic>MaACS3</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic> sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C56">Inaba <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Each assay using the gene-specific primers amplified a single product of the correct size, and the PCR efficiency (slope) of primers within the 86–99 % range (3.7–3.37) was calculated as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C34">Mbéguié-A-Mbéguié <italic>et al</italic>. (2008<italic>a</italic>)</xref>The relative fold differences in expression of each gene between samples were determined using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> formula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C33">Livak and Schmittgen 2001</xref>) with the actin gene as reference and the fruit CZ of peel tissue sampled at harvest before ripening induction used as calibrator.<bold>Finger drop pattern during postharvest fruit ripening</bold>. Peel tissue of control (CZ) and drop (DZ) zones used in this study are illustrated in (A). Finger drop pattern observed during fruit ripening and measured via the pedicel rupture force are illustrated in (B).<bold>Ethylene biosynthesis gene expression during postharvest ripening of Cavendish bananas assessed using reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction</bold>. RNA was extracted twice from CZ and DZ of banana peel tissues sampled at harvest and then at 1–4 days after ripening induction. The <italic>y</italic>-axis represents the relative fold difference in mRNA level and was calculated using the 2<sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> formula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C33">Livak and Schmittgen 2001</xref>) with actin as the reference. The mRNA fold difference was relative to that of peel tissue from the CZ of fruit sampled at harvest. Each data point is the mean of values obtained through a qPCR reaction performed in triplicate on one sample. Each sample was prepared from four fruits originating from three replicate bunches. Vertical bars indicate the standard deviation (SD). The SD was lower than the symbol when no bar is shown. The experiment was performed on two independent RNA extractions with similar results.No change was observed in the <italic>MaACO2</italic> mRNA level in both CZ and DZ tissues. At harvest, the <italic>MaACS3</italic> level was 2-fold higher in the DZ compared with the control. This level decreased markedly at Day 1 after ripening induction to reach a level comparable to that observed in the CZ, and then the <italic>MaACS3</italic> mRNA level remained constant in both tissues. The other EB genes, i.e. <italic>MaACO1</italic>, <italic>MaACS1</italic>, <italic>MaACS2</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic>, were highly and transiently induced in DZ compared with the control, <italic>MaACO1</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic> being the most and least expressed ones, respectively. For the <italic>MaACS1</italic>, <italic>MaACS2</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic> genes, mRNA accumulation peaked 2 days after ripening induction. <italic>MaACS4</italic> was the unique gene presenting, at harvest time, a low transcript level in the DZ compared with the control.Finger drop is a major fruit ripening feature for some banana varieties. Our findings confirmed this by showing a progressive decrease in rupture pedicel force, concomitantly with finger drop sensitivity, throughout fruit ripening, along with a decrease in the SSC, as expressed by the Brix value (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS041F1">1</xref>). Our previous findings also showed that molecular mechanisms related to the banana finger drop phenomenon occurred earlier after ripening induction as was ripening ethylene production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C36">Mbéguié-A-Mbéguié <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). This led us to suggest ripening ethylene as a potential upstream regulator of the finger drop process. Assuming that this putative regulation—if it takes place—might involve EB components, in this study we examined the changes in expression of EB genes during postharvest ripening of banana fruit taken at 1–4 days after ripening induction, and in both median zone (CZ) and DZ.Ethylene biosynthesis genes are transcriptionally induced in peel tissue by ripening (i.e. an increase in their mRNA accumulation in the median zone), <italic>MaACS1</italic> and <italic>MaACO1</italic> being the highly expressed ones, consistent with the important role played by these genes in ripening EB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C56">Inaba <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), while no marked changes were observed in the expression of <italic>MaACS3</italic>, <italic>MaACS4</italic> and <italic>MaACO2</italic> genes in CZ, suggesting that these genes might be less important during ripening of banana peel tissue. In contrast with previous studies showing that <italic>MaACS2</italic> gene was expressed only in banana pulp tissue and upon wounding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>), our data showed a low but transient induction of <italic>MaACS2</italic> in control zone of peel suggesting that this gene was ripening regulated in peel tissue. The discrepancy between the two data may be due to the analytical method, i.e. northern blot used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref> and qPCR used in this study.The finger drop process enhanced EB gene expression, including the MaACO1, MaACS1, MaACS2 and MaACS4 genes, of which the corresponding mRNA was accumulated to a great extent in DZ compared to the control. Therefore, we hypothesized that the finger drop process is associated with ethylene production occurring specifically in the DZ with a putative involvement of one ACC oxidase (<italic>MaACO1</italic>) and three ACC synthase (<italic>MaACS1</italic>, <italic>MaACS2</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic>) genes. However, this hypothesis needs to be validated through the measurement of ethylene produced by peel tissue taken from DZ in comparison to that taken from the median zone.The <italic>MaACO1</italic> and <italic>MaACS2</italic> genes previously identified as wound-inducible genes in pulp and leaf banana tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C34">Mbéguié-A-Mbéguié <italic>et al</italic>. 2008<italic>a</italic></xref>) were also transcriptionally enhanced by finger drop. Although the tissues and physiological stages examined in these previous studies are different, our data suggested that finger drop might also imply a wound-related mechanism. Considering that ripening and wounding processes are both associated with ethylene production, it should be interesting to assess whether finger drop, wounding and ripening share some ethylene transduction pathway components.<bold>Phylogenetic analysis of ACS (A) and ACO (B) sequences from banana and other plant species.</bold> The phylogenetic tree was constructed with the Gonnet residue weights and after a complete sequence alignment performed using the ClustalX algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C23">Jeanmougin <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>). For multiple alignments, the gap opening penalty was 10, with a gap extension penalty of 0.2 and the delay divergent sequences was set at 30 %. The consensus tree was displayed using the TREEVIEW program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C38">Page 1996</xref>). All banana sequences are indicated by underlining while those whose expression was examined in this study are in bold. ACC synthase sequences used for phylogenetic tree construction are: <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> [<italic>MaACS1</italic> (AB021906), <italic>MaACS2</italic> (AB021907), <italic>MACS2</italic> (AF056162), <italic>MaACS3</italic> (AB021908), <italic>MaACS4</italic> (AB266314), <italic>MaACS6</italic> (AJ223186)], <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> [<italic>AtACS2</italic> (Q06402), <italic>AtACS4</italic> (NP_179866), <italic>AtACS5</italic> (AAG50098), <italic>AtACS6</italic> (Q9SAR0), <italic>AtACS7</italic> (AAG48754), <italic>AtACS8</italic> (AAG50090), <italic>AtACS9</italic> (AAG48755)], <italic>Cucumus sativum</italic> [<italic>CsACS1</italic> (BAA33374), <italic>CsACS2</italic> (BAA33375), <italic>CsACS3</italic> (BAA33376)], <italic>Doritaenopsi</italic> sp<italic>.</italic> [<italic>DsACS1a</italic> (L07882), <italic>DsACS1b</italic> (L07883)], <italic>Lupinus albus</italic> [L<italic>uACS1</italic> (AF119411), <italic>LuACS2</italic> (AF119412), <italic>LuACS3</italic> (AF119413), <italic>LuACS4</italic> (AF119410), <italic>LuACS5</italic> (AF119414)], <italic>Solanum lycopersicon</italic> [<italic>SlACS1a</italic> (AAF97614), <italic>SlACS1b</italic> (AAF97615), <italic>SlACS2</italic>(CAA41855), <italic>SlACS3</italic>(AAB48945), <italic>SlACS4</italic>(AAA03164), <italic>SlACS6</italic>(BAA34923), <italic>SlACS7</italic>(AAC32317)], <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> [<italic>StACS1a</italic> (Z27233), <italic>StACS1b</italic> (Z27234), <italic>StACS2</italic> (Z27235)] and <italic>Vigna radiata</italic> [<italic>VrASC1</italic> (CAA77688), <italic>VrACS6</italic> (U34986), <italic>VrACS7</italic> (U34987)]. ACC oxidase sequences used for phylogenetic tree construction are: <italic>Musa acuminata</italic> [<italic>MaACO1</italic>(AY804252), <italic>MaACO2</italic> (X95599), <italic>MAO1B</italic>(AF030410)], <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> [<italic>AtACO1</italic> (AEC06898), <italic>AtACO2</italic> (AEE33960), <italic>AtACS3</italic> (Q8H1S4), <italic>AtACS5</italic> (Q43383), <italic>AtACS6</italic> (AAG48754), <italic>AtACS7</italic> (AAG50090), <italic>AtACS9</italic> (AAG48755), <italic>AtACO10</italic> (Q9LSW6)], <italic>Cucumus sativum</italic> [<italic>CsACO1</italic> (AB006806), <italic>CsACO2</italic> (AB006807)], <italic>Diospyros kaki</italic> [<italic>DkACO1</italic> (AB073008), <italic>DkACO2</italic> (AB073009)], <italic>Doritaenopsis</italic> sp<italic>.</italic> [<italic>DsACO1</italic> (L37103), <italic>DsACO2</italic>(L07912)], <italic>Solanum lycopersicon</italic> [<italic>SlACO1</italic> (X58273), <italic>SlACO4</italic> (AB013101), <italic>SlACO5</italic> (AJ715790)], <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> [<italic>StACO1</italic> (AF384820), <italic>StACO2</italic> (AF384821)] and <italic>Vigna radiata</italic> [<italic>VrASO1</italic> (U06046), <italic>VrACO2</italic>(AM180697)].A previous study suggested that MaACS2, MaACS3 and MaACS4 are members of the same subgroup of the ACS family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C32">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C56">Inaba <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Consistent with this, the phylogenetic tree includes <italic>MaACS2</italic>, <italic>MaACS3</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic> into a divergent subgroup family of Type 2 ACS. However, this needs to be confirmed with a phylogenetic tree constructed with the complete <italic>MaACS2</italic>, <italic>MaACS3</italic> and <italic>MaACS4</italic> polypeptide sequences, as those used here are partial and lack the last 80 amino acid residues. Two main subfamilies are observed for the ACO phylogenetic tree (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS041F3">3</xref>B). Banana ACO genes examined in this study are grouped with the other major ACO genes, consistent with the high conservation of these proteins. Based on the present data (i.e. the limited number of ACO and ACS genes examined), a putative relationship between ACO and ACS lineages and their corresponding function in regard to finger drop cannot yet be established. A more detailed analysis of the expression of the members of both ACO and ACS family genes is necessary before assigning a functional homology to this lineage. This is now possible with the availability of the banana genome sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C52">D'Hont <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>).In conclusion, our data showed that the finger drop process might be associated with ethylene production, implying a large number of EB genes. However, this hypothesis needs to be validated through the measurement of ethylene produced at DZ.The finger drop process is probably a result of the crosstalk between ethylene (i.e. ripening and wounding) and developmental regulatory pathways. The ethylene transduction pathway model has been proposed and the related components identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C5">Cara and Giovannoni 2008</xref>). On the other hand, MADS-box genes have recently been identified as a major component in the molecular circuit of the developmental regulation of fruit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C57">Vrebalov <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C54">Giovannoni 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS041C53">Elitzur <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). It should be interesting to identify the ethylene and developmental transduction components involved in the finger drop process. This represents an interesting challenge to gain further insight into the banana ripening process and especially the physiological events occurring in banana peel tissue, whose ripening process clearly differs compared with that of pulp.Finally, with the prospect of identifying ripening-related markers through a candidate gene approach, <italic>MaACO1</italic>, <italic>MaACS1</italic>, <italic>MaACS2</italic>, and to a lesser extent <italic>MaACS4</italic> genes that are induced in DZ to a greater extent than in CZ could be considered as putative candidates related to the upstream regulatory steps of the finger drop process. However, and before their use in molecular breeding schemes for banana improvement, these candidates need to be validated through functional studies using cultivars contrasting their tendency to develop finger drop.The work is a part of the ongoing research project ‘<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Qualité des Produits Végétaux’</grant-sponsor> funded by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Fonds Européen de Dévéloppement Régional (FEDER)</grant-sponsor> Convergence: Guadeloupe 2007–2013.D.M.-A-M. designed the project, performed all the molecular biology experiments, constructed the phylogenetic tree, analysed the qPCR data (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS041F2">2</xref>) and wrote the manuscript. O.H. performed all the physicochemical experiments, including fruit sampling, treatment, monitoring of postharvest ripening and physicochemical data analysis described in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS041F1">1</xref>.None declared.We thank Mr Poumaroux and the banana growers of Guadeloupe for providing the bananas assessed in this study.