 Giving drought the cold shoulder: a relationship between drought tolerance and fall dormancy in an agriculturally important crop  Qualitative and quantitative polymerase chain reaction assays for an alfalfa ( Medicago sativa )-specific reference gene to use in monitoring transgenic cultivars  Highlights in the USA and Canada  Nucleotide sequence of an alfalfa calmodulin cDNA  Studies on extraction and on availability to plants of adsorbed plus soluble sulfate  Specific and unspecific responses of plants to cold and drought stress  Using morphological traits to identify persistent alfalfas for dryland agriculture in NSW, Australia  Mapping genetic factors associated with winter hardiness, fall growth, and freezing injury in autotetraploid alfalfa  Reexamining the relationship between fall dormancy and winter hardiness in alfalfa  A cold-induced gene from  Medicago sativa  encodes a bimodular protein similar to developmentally regulated proteins  Differential accumulation of carbohydrates in alfalfa cultivars of contrasting winter hardiness  Temperature and drought stress  Alfalfa winter hardiness: a research retrospective and integrated perspective  Molecular genetic perspectives on cross-talk and specificity in abiotic stress signalling in plants  The estimation of the phosphorus fertiliser requirements of wheat in southern New South Wales by soil analysis  Dehydrins: a commonality in the response of plants to dehydration and low temperature  Membrane integrity in anhydrobiotic organisms: toward a mechanism for stabilizing dry cells  Anhydrobiosis  Raffinose and stachyose accumulation, galactinol synthase expression, and winter injury of contrasting alfalfa germplasms  Sugar/osmoticum levels modulate differential abscisic acid-independent expression of two stress-responsive sucrose synthase genes in Arabidopsis  Water use efficiency, transpiration and net CO 2  exchange of four alfalfa genotypes submitted to progressive drought and subsequent recovery  Food reserves and their translocation to the crown buds as related to cold and drought resistance in alfalfa  Alfalfa yield and plant water relations with variable irrigation  Autumn defoliation effects on alfalfa winter survival, root physiology, and gene expression  Plant dehydrins and stress tolerance: versatile proteins for complex mechanisms  Canopy temperature and stomatal conductance of water-stressed dormant and nondormant alfalfa types  Development and characterization of SSR markers and their use to assess genetic relationships among alfalfa germplasms  Contrasting hydraulic regulation in closely related forage grasses: implications for plant water use  Arabidopsis CBF1 overexpression induces COR genes and enhances freezing tolerance  A cDNA from  Medicago sativa  encodes a protein homologous to small GTP-binding proteins  Stress signaling in plants: a mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway is activated by cold and drought  Exploring the temperature-stress metabolome of Arabidopsis  Improving plant drought, salt, and freezing tolerance by gene transfer of a single stress-inducible transcription factor  OligoCalc: an online oligonucleotide properties calculator  Drought, salt, and temperature stress-induced metabolic rearrangements and regulatory networks  New cold-regulated and drought-regulated gene from  Medicago sativa   Coping with desiccation  Development of a DTPA soil test for zinc, iron, manganese, and copper  Superoxide dismutase enhances tolerance of freezing stress in transgenic alfalfa ( Medicago sativa  L.)  Water-deficit tolerance and field performance of transgenic alfalfa overexpressing superoxide dismutase  Winter survival of transgenic alfalfa overexpressing superoxide dismustase  Conserving water through deficit irrigation of alfalfa in the intermountain area of California  Isolation and sequence determination of the plant homologue of the eukaryotic initiation factor 4D cDNA from alfalfa,  Medicago sativa   An alfalfa cDNA encodes a protein with homology to translationally controlled human tumor protein  Water deficit alters canopy structure but not photosynthesis in regrowing alfalfa ( Medicago sativa  L.)  Yield, yield components and shoot morphology of four contrasting alfalfa ( Medicago sativa ) cultivars grown in three cool temperate environments  Genotype by environment interactions of alfalfa ( Medicago sativa  L.) in a cool temperate climate  Effect of summer irrigation on seasonal changes in taproot reserves and the expression of winter dormancy/activity in four contrasting alfalfa cultivars  Yield and water-use efficiency of contrasting lucerne genotypes grown in a cool temperate environment  Biochemistry and physiology of raffinose family oligosaccharides and galactosyl cyclitols in seeds  Protection mechanisms in the resurrection plant  Xerophyta viscosa  (Baker): both sucrose and raffinose family oligosaccharides (RFOs) accumulate in leaves in response to water deficit  Isolation and characterization of a phosphoprotein phosphatase type 2A gene from alfalfa  Alfalfa—most important perennial forage legume in animal husbandry  When defense pathways collide. The response of Arabidopsis to a combination of drought and heat stress  Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers  Alfalfa  The relationship between field winter injury and fall growth score for 251 alfalfa cultivars  Molecular responses to drought, salinity and frost: common and different paths for plant protection  Seeding-year cutting affects winter survival and its association with fall growth score in alfalfa  Enhanced tolerance to multiple abiotic stresses in transgenic alfalfa accumulating trehalose  The role of sugar, vitrification and membrane phase transition in seed desiccation tolerance  Important roles of drought- and cold-inducible genes for galactinol synthase in stress tolerance in  Arabidopsis thaliana   Fall dormancy  Plant cold acclimation: freezing tolerance genes and regulatory mechanisms  Characterization of the ABA-regulated global responses to dehydration in Arabidopsis by metabolomics  Multilevel genomic analysis of the response of transcripts, enzyme activities and metabolites in Arabidopsis rosettes to a progressive decrease of temperature in the non-freezing range  Nodulation and symbiotic dinitrogen fixation  Accurate normalization of real-time quantitative RT-PCR data by geometric averaging of multiple internal control genes  Physiological genetics of alfalfa improvement: past failures, future prospects  Yields of alfalfa varieties with different fall-dormancy levels in a temperate environment  Cloning and sequencing of the cDNA for  cas17 , a cold acclimation-specific gene of alfalfa  cDNA sequence, expression, and transcript stability of a cold acclimation-specific gene,  cas18 , of alfalfa ( Medicago falcata ) cells  Polyadenylated H3 histone transcripts and H3 histone variants in alfalfa  Salt and drought stress signal transduction in plants  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Fall dormant/freezing tolerant plants often also exhibit superior tolerance to drought conditions compared to their non-fall dormant/freezing intolerant counterparts. This experiment aimed to investigate this phenomenon in an agriculturally important crop. Seven alfalfa cultivars with varying levels of fall dormancy/freezing tolerance were exposed to a water deficit. The more fall dormant cultivars had superior tolerance to a mild water deficit. Two genes, CAS18 (encodes for a dehydrin like protein) and CorF (encodes for a galactinol synthase), were up regulated in association with this drought tolerance. Both these genes are early response genes, providing clues to the stress signalling pathways involved.  The growth of fall dormant/freezing tolerant plants often surpasses the growth of non-fall dormant/non-freezing tolerant types of the same species under water-limited conditions, while under irrigated conditions non-fall dormant types exhibit superior yield performance. To investigate the mechanism behind this phenomenon, we exposed seven diverse alfalfa ( Medicago sativa ) cultivars to water-limited and fully watered conditions and measured their shoot growth, shoot water potential and gas exchange parameters and the relative abundance of taproot RNA transcripts associated with chilling stress/freezing tolerance. Fall dormant cultivars had greater shoot growth relative to the fully watered controls under a mild water deficit (a cumulative water deficit of 625 mL pot −1 ) and did not close their stomata until lower shoot water potentials compared with the more non-fall dormant cultivars. Several gene transcripts previously associated with freezing tolerance increased in abundance when plants were exposed to a mild water deficit. Two transcripts,  corF  (encodes galactinol synthase) and  cas18  (encodes a dehydrin-like protein), increased in abundance in fall dormant cultivars only. Once water deficit stress became severe (a cumulative water deficit of 2530 mL pot −1 ), the difference between fall dormancy groups disappeared with the exception of the expression of a type 1 sucrose synthase gene, which decreased in fall dormant cultivars. The specific adaptation of fall dormant cultivars to mild water deficit conditions and the increase in abundance of specific genes typically associated with freezing tolerance in these cultivars is further evidence of a link between freezing tolerance/fall dormancy and adaption to drought conditions in this species.  Drought is a major limitation to agricultural production. Drought causes a cessation of plant growth and in extreme cases leads to the senescence of part or the whole of plants. There is a diverse range of adaptations to water-limited conditions within the plant kingdom, and environments that may be extreme for one species may be relatively benign for another. Adaptation to and tolerance of water deficit stress is often associated with adaptation to and tolerance of freezing temperatures as both environmental conditions lead to osmotic and oxidative stresses at a cellular level ( Thomashow 1999 ;  Zhu 2002 ) and disrupt plant water status ( Chinnusamy  et al.  2004 ). Cross-talk between the stress signalling pathways involved in both environmental stresses is a common phenomenon ( Chinnusamy  et al.  2004 ) and often the same or similar metabolites accumulate in response to both stresses ( Kaplan  et al.  2004 ;  Rizhsky  et al.  2004 ;  Usadel  et al.  2008 ;  Urano  et al.  2009 ).  Alfalfa (syn. lucerne;  Medicago sativa ) is a globally important forage legume crop with a total area of production of ∼32.5–35 million hectares worldwide ( Russelle 2001 ;  Radovic  et al.  2009 ). Its importance is further increased by its ability to fix atmospheric nitrogen (through a symbiotic relationship with the rhizobia  Sinorhizobium  ( Ensifer )  meliloti ), making it an important source of nitrogen within agricultural production systems ( Vance  et al.  1988 ). Based on their level of fall/winter growth, alfalfa cultivars can be separated into four fall dormancy groups: fall dormant, semi-fall dormant, non-fall dormant and highly non-fall dormant ( Barnes  et al.  1988 ). This in turn can be related back to the genetic pedigree of a cultivar ( Barnes  et al.  1988 ;  He  et al.  2009 ), with non-fall dormant types entirely comprised of ssp.  sativa  and fall dormant types containing some spp.  falcata  in their background. As part of the characterization process of new alfalfa cultivars, they are scored on a scale of 1–11, with 1 assigned to the most fall dormant cultivars and 11 assigned to the most non-fall dormant cultivars, based on their shoot length 1 month after defoliation in late autumn ( Teuber  et al.  1998 ). This score strongly correlates to the level of plant injury when the cultivar is exposed to freezing temperatures ( Sheaffer  et al.  1992 ;  Schwab  et al.  1996 ) and consequently is an important consideration when selecting cultivars to be grown in environments that expose plants to sub-zero temperatures over the winter.  A consistent trend in alfalfa field experiments undertaken in the cool temperate regions of Australia under water-limited conditions is the superior yield performance of fall dormant cultivars of alfalfa compared with non-fall dormant cultivars ( Pembleton  et al.  2010 a  ,   b  ). This is despite there being no difference in the soil water use pattern between cultivars under such conditions ( Pembleton  et al.  2011 ). Interestingly, in these environments there is no need for adaptation to freezing temperatures over the winter and when water deficit is alleviated non-fall dormant cultivars outperform or at least equal the yield of fall dormant cultivars ( Pembleton  et al.  2010 a  ,   b  ). Adaptation of fall dormant cultivars of alfalfa to water-limited conditions has been noted in the literature for some time (e.g.  Grandfield 1943 ). When exposed to a water deficit, fall dormant and semi-fall dormant cultivars have been identified as being able to maintain a higher shoot water potential ( Grimes  et al.  1992 ;  Pembleton  et al.  2009 ), greater rates of stomatal conductance ( Hattendorf  et al.  1990 ) and taproot carbohydrate reserves ( Boschma and Williams 2008 ) compared with non-fall dormant and highly non-fall dormant cultivars.  Many reports have highlighted the similarities between gene families (including dehydrins, protein kinases and transcription factors) that are upregulated in plants exposed to cold temperatures and water deficits (see  Chinnusamy  et al.  2004 ;  Beck  et al.  2007 ;  Krasensky and Jonak 2012  for reviews). Transgenic modification of alfalfa with a superoxide dismutase from  Nicotiana plumbaginifolia  Viv. ( McKersie  et al.  1993 ,  1996 ,  1999 ) or a trehalose from yeast ( Suarez  et al.  2009 ) has improved tolerance to both freezing and water deficit stress. Furthermore, the alfalfa gene transcripts  cas17  ( Wolfraim and Dhindsa 1993 ),  cas18  ( Wolfraim  et al.  1993 ) and CAR1/ cor 15 ( Laberge  et al.  1993 ) have been noted to increase in abundance when plants are exposed to either water deficit or freezing stress. In the field, it has been identified that the expression of freezing tolerance/fall dormancy, nitrogen storage and carbon partitioning genes during late autumn is enhanced by exposure to water deficit conditions over summer ( Pembleton  et al.  2010 c  ). Clearly, several candidate genes may contribute to the superior performance of fall dormant cultivars when exposed to water deficits. To date, no attempt has been made to screen these genes to determine which are responsible for this specific adaptation. Given that alfalfa cultivars can be easily classified into a quantitative ranking of freezing tolerance based on their fall dormancy rating and that fall dormant cultivars exhibit superior adaptation to water-limited conditions compared with non-fall dormant and highly non-fall dormant cultivars, it is an ideal species to assess and explore the linkage between freezing tolerance and drought tolerance in perennial forages. This paper reports on a study undertaken to investigate the adaptation of seven alfalfa cultivars/lines representing a fall dormancy score from 3 (dormant) to 10 (highly non-fall dormant) to a water deficit and the expression profile of select genes. The aim of these experiments was to determine what level of fall dormancy is required to achieve superior tolerance to water deficit stress and to establish the relationship between the expression of genes known to be cold inducible or associated with freezing tolerance and the response of cultivars with differing levels of fall dormancy to a water deficit.  Bare (uncoated/untreated) seeds of alfalfa cultivars were sourced from commercial seed companies. These cultivars represented a broad range of fall dormancy (FD) ratings and were Q31 (FD rating of 3; Seed Distributors, Wingfield, SA, Australia), Grasslands Kaituna (FD rating of 4.5; Wrightson Seeds Australia, Truganina, VIC, Australia), A5225 (FD rating of 5; Cal/West Seeds, Woodland, CA, USA), SARDI 7 (FD rating of 7; Heritage Seeds, Mulgrave, VIC, Australia), Sequel HR (FD rating of 9; Wrightson Seeds Australia) and SARDI 10 (FD rating of 10; Heritage Seeds). In addition, an experimental line FFI DT1 (putative FD rating of 2; SARDI, Urrbrae, SA, Australia) was also included.  Daily maximum (black line) and minimum (grey line) air temperatures and photoperiod (broken line) at the Cradle Coast Campus of the University of Tasmania in Burnie, TAS, Australia from August 2011 to May 2012. Arrows indicate when the pots of alfalfa used in the fall dormancy screening test were defoliated. The arrow marked with the asterisk indicates when shoot length was assessed.  The water deficit experiment was undertaken within the glasshouse research facility of the Tasmanian Institute of Agriculture at the Cradle Coast Campus of the University of Tasmania in Burnie, TAS, Australia. Within the glasshouse, air temperature was maintained at an average of 22 °C during the day (ranging between 25 and 18 °C) and at an average of 10 °C during the night (ranging between 14 and 8 °C). Photoperiod was extended beyond the natural day-length to 14 h with the aid of three 400-W halogen lamps suspended 2 m above the plant canopy, covering an area of 7 m × 7 m. These growing conditions were maintained with the aid of a computer-based glasshouse control system (Priva Maximizer; Priva Computers Inc., Vineland Station, ON, Canada). Temperatures and day-length were monitored using sensors and a data logger (HOBO microstation data logger and sensors; Onset Computer Corp.) separate to the glasshouse environmental control system.  Approximately 16 viable seeds were sown into 10-L (340 mm high, 96 mm radius) polyethylene bag pots containing 13.2 kg of dry sandy soil sourced from a local landscaping supplier. This soil had a baseline chemical fertility of 14 mg kg −1  of P (Olsen extraction;  Olsen  et al.  1954 ), 140 mg kg −1  of K (Colwell extraction;  Colwell 1963 ), 0.15 mg kg −1  of Cu, 100 mg kg −1  of Fe, 5.6 mg kg −1  of Mn, 3.1 mg kg −1  of Zn (DTPA extraction;  Lindsey and Norvell 1978 ) and 6.8 mg kg −1  of S (KCl40 extraction;  Barrow 1967 ). The soil had a volumetric soil water content of 0.11 mm mm −1  at a soil water potential of −10 kPa. To address soil fertility limitations, each kilogram of soil received 0.19 g of Osmocote ®  (Scotts Australia Pty Ltd), 0.13 g of triple super phosphate (21 % P, 1 % S) and 0.08 g of muriate of potash (50 % K). Immediately following sowing, pots were watered by hand until water was observed to drain through the pot. Emergence was observed at 4 DAS. At 8, 14 and 21 DAS, plants were spray inoculated with rhizobia ( S.  ( E. )  meliloti , Group AL; Becker Underwood Pty Ltd) followed by a hand watering to wash the inoculant into the soil. At 28 DAS, plants were thinned by hand to eight plants per pot. From then on water was applied through a purpose-built drip emitter irrigation system designed and calibrated to deliver water to each pot at a rate of 2 ± 0.02 L h −1 . Plants were grown until 65 DAS and then defoliated to 50 mm. Plants were allowed to grow for a further 28 days (93 DAS) before they were once again defoliated to 50 mm. At this point the watering treatments commenced. Plants were grown for a further 35 days to the conclusion of the experiment (128 DAS). Following both defoliations, each pot was fertilized with 2.5 g of Osmocote ® , 1.7 g of triple super phosphate and 1.0 g of muriate of potash.  Cumulative water applied to the pots that received 100 % of their water requirement (solid line), and the pots that received 25 % of their water requirement (broken line) over the 35 days of water-deficient treatment.  Shoot water potential and gas exchange measurements of plants commenced 3 days prior to the application of water deficit treatments and then occurred at 7-day intervals until the conclusion of the experiment. Measurements occurred between 1000 and 1400 h and were undertaken on plants that were scheduled to be destructively harvested at 35 days after the commencement of watering treatments. Shoot water potential was determined with a pressure chamber (Model 615; PMS Instrument Company, Albany, OR, USA) on the upper 50 mm of two shoots randomly selected per pot. Gas exchange parameters were determined on the middle leaflet on the third most recently emerged leaf on two randomly selected shoots using a portable infrared gas analysis system (LI6400XT; LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE, USA). Following measurement, the middle leaflet was severed at the petiole and scanned on a flatbed scanner (HP Scanjet 3670; Hewlett-Packard Australia Pty Ltd, Blackburn, VIC, Australia). The resulting image was then analysed using image analysis software (IMAGE J version 1.45h; National Institute of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA) to determine the area of the leaflet. Gas exchange measurements were adjusted based on leaf area, and the net carbon exchange rate and stomatal conductance were then calculated as per the equations outlined in the LI6400XT manual (LI-COR Biosciences).  At each destructive harvest, the pots selected for harvest were defoliated to 50 mm above the soil surface and the number of shoots per pot was counted. The leaves were hand separated from the stems. Total leaf area was determined using a flatbed scanner (HP Scanjet 3670; Hewlett-Packard Australia Pty Ltd) coupled with image analysis software (IMAGE J version 1.45h). Soil was washed free from the roots and crowns. Crowns were cut from the taproot at the lowest crown branch or crown bud. Roots were dried with a paper towel to remove excess water and were then weighed. The uppermost 50 mm of the roots were then diced and snap frozen by immersion in liquid nitrogen before being transferred to a −80 °C freezer. The upper 50 mm of roots were chosen as this was a consistent section of the taproot free of nodules and fibrous roots. The remainder of the root system was then weighed and immediately placed in a −20 °C freezer. Leaves, stems and crowns were dried at 60 °C in a fan-forced oven until a consistent weight was achieved while the roots frozen in the −20 °C freezer were freeze dried for 7 days. Once dry, all material was weighed. The original root dry mass was calculated using the root dry matter content and the original root weight.  The taproot material that was snap frozen and stored at −80 °C was ground to a fine powder in liquid nitrogen with a mortar and pestle. Total RNA was extracted from 100 mg of ground material using the Invitrogen TriZol ®  Plus RNA extraction kit (Life Technologies Australia, Mulgrave, VIC, Australia). The manufacturer's instructions were modified by vortexing of the extraction tube containing the TriZol ®  reagent, chloroform and sample mixture when the procedure called for shaking by hand and by the addition of a second chloroform phase separation. Following extraction, RNA quantity was determined fluorometrically using a Qubit ®  2.0 fluorometer with the broad-range total RNA assay kit (Life Technologies) and RNA integrity was visually checked with ultraviolet light after gel electrophoresis of 1 µg of RNA in 1.5 % agarose gels stained with SYBR ®  Green (SYBR ®  safe gel stain; Life Technologies). Following extraction, 20.5 µL of extracted RNA solution was DNase digested using the stringent protocol of the Ambion DNA-free™ kit (Life Technologies Australia). Following the digestion, RNA was re-quantified using the Qubit ®  2.0 fluorometer. The absence of genomic DNA contamination was assessed by performing PCRs on 0.35 ng of RNA with forward (5′-GATCAGTGAACTTCGCAAAGTAC-3′) and reverse (5′-AGGGATGCTGCTACTTTGATG-3′) primers designed to amplify a 154 base pair (bp) fragment of the alfalfa acetyl carboxylase gene ( Alexander  et al.  2007 ; GenBank accession L25042). Products from these PCR reactions were then visually compared with products from PCRs undertaken with alfalfa RNA samples known to contain genomic DNA contamination by electrophoresis in 2.0 % agarose gels stained with SYBR ®  Green. Any RNA samples that amplified a fragment were re-digested with DNase and re-quantified, and the second PCR products were visualized via gel electrophoresis. Synthesis of cDNA was undertaken using the iScript™ cDNA synthesis kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories Pty Ltd, Gladesville, NSW, Australia) using 0.35 µg of DNase-digested RNA. Following cDNA synthesis, 6 µL from each of the 192 samples was combined to create a ‘calibrator’ sample. This sample was then serially diluted to create 1 : 5, 1 : 50, 1 : 500 and 1 : 5000 dilutions to aid in generating a standard curve required for determining the amplification efficiency of the primer pairs. In addition to this, 2 µL of cDNA synthesized from each sample collected prior to the implementation of water treatments was combined and then diluted 1 : 50.  Primer pairs (F: forward; R: reverse of the eight reference and eight genes of interest) used in the qPCR analysis of the relative abundance of reference genes (Ref) and genes of interest (GOI) in the taproot tissue of alfalfa cultivars exposed to a water deficit.  Real-time qRT-PCR reactions were undertaken in 384-well plates using a Roche 480 LightCycler ®  PCR system, using SYBR ®  Green I Master mix (Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, Germany). Each reaction contained 5 µL of SYBR ®  Green I Master mix, 2 µL of a 1 : 50 dilution of template cDNA, 0.5 µL of each primer pair (10 µmol L −1  concentrations) and 2 µL of water. Each plate also contained reactions for generating a standard curve for each primer pair, a plate calibrator sample, negative controls and the 1 : 50 dilution of the cDNA collected from each sample that was harvested before the commencement of water deficit treatments. Each reaction was undertaken in triplicate and all liquid handling was undertaken using an automated liquid handling system (epMotion 5075LH; Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany). The conditions of real-time qRT-PCR reactions were as follows: 95 °C for 5 min, followed by 55 cycles of 95 °C for 10 s, 58 °C for 10 s and 72 °C for 8 s. At the end of the PCR reaction, a melting curve analysis (58–95 °C) was undertaken. LightCycler ®  480 software (version 1.5; Roche Diagnostics) was used to determine the crossing point (Cp) values. Cp values and the standard curves were used to determine the concentration of each gene in each sample following adjustment using the plate calibrator sample. Relative concentration values for each of the genes of interest were normalized using the geometric mean of the concentration of the three most stably expressed reference genes identified using the GeNorm version 3.5 software package ( Vandesompele  et al.  2002 ). Normalized concentration values were divided by the normalized concentration values from the sample generated by taking an equal volume of cDNA from the samples collected prior to the implementation of the water deficit treatments to give a relative concentration.  Shoot length (mm) of seven alfalfa cultivars (cultivar fall dormancy score given in parentheses) in late autumn (5 May 2012; 42 days after defoliation). Plants were grown outdoors in pots at Burnie, TAS, Australia. Error bars represent the standard errors of the means ( n  = 4). Cultivars grouped into fall dormant (FD), non-fall dormant (NFD) and highly non-fall dormant (HNFD) groups exhibited no significant difference in shoot length.  Soil water content in the pots that received 100 % of their water requirement (solid line), and the pots that received 25 % of their water requirement (broken line) over the 35 days of water-deficient treatment. The horizontal dotted line indicates a soil water content of 11 % (equivalent to a soil water potential of −10 kPa for the growing medium).  Shoot mass per plant and total plant mass (g DM plant −1 ) of seven alfalfa cultivars (presented individually and grouped based on fall dormancy grouping) after 14 or 35 days of receiving either 100 or 25 % of their water requirement. One-tail  t -tests were used to identify decreases between plants receiving 100 or 25 % of their water requirement within a cultivar. Differences are indicated by NS:  P  &gt; 0.05, * P  &lt; 0.05, ** P  &lt; 0.01, *** P  &lt; 0.001.  Shoots per plant, mass per shoot and leaf area per plant of alfalfa plants (the average of seven cultivars) receiving either 100 or 25 % of their water requirements after 14 and 35 days of treatment.  Shoot mass per plant, total plant mass, mass per shoot, number of shoots per plant and leaf area per plant expressed as a proportion of the value achieved by the fully watered controls (relative value) at 14 and 35 days after the initiation of treatments. Cultivars were grouped into fall dormant (FD), non-fall dormant (NFD) and highly non-fall dormant (HNFD) fall dormancy groups based on their level of fall dormancy identified in the fall dormancy screening test. Bars with different letters were identified as being different from each other using ANOVA with non-orthogonal contrasts ( P  &lt; 0.05). Error bars represent the standard errors of the mean ( n  = 4 to 16).  Shoot water potentials of seven alfalfa cultivars (upper panels) and the seven cultivars grouped by their fall dormancy groups (lower panels) through 35 days of receiving either 100 % of their water requirement or 25 % of their water requirement. Error bars represent the standard errors of the mean ( n  = 4).  While differences in the shoot water potential occurred between cultivars when exposed to a water deficit, these differences were inconsistent throughout the experiment (Fig.  6 ). For example, SARDI 10 had the lowest shoot water potential after 12 days of treatment but had the highest shoot water potential after 19 days of treatment. When grouped by fall dormancy, there were no differences ( P  = 0.396) in the shoot water potential within either watering treatments. There was a sharp decline in shoot water potential 19 days after the beginning of the water deficit treatments in all cultivars.  Relationship between shoot water potential and stomatal conductance/carbon exchange rate of alfalfa cultivars grouped into fall dormant, non-fall dormant or highly non-fall dormant dormancy groups. Plants received either 100 % (open circles) or 25 % (closed circles) of their water requirement over 35 days. A logistical function was fitted to the data (solid line). The vertical broken line indicates shoot water potentials at which a 50 % decline in carbon exchange rate and a 90 % decline in stomatal conductance (stomatal closure) occurred. The grey areas represent the standard errors around these estimates.  Results of pairwise variation analysis (upper panel) and average expression stability calculations (lower panel) undertaken using GeNorm from the quantitative PCR of alfalfa gene transcripts using primers designed for eight potential reference genes (Phos, phosphoprotein phosphatase type 2A; His, histone H3; Cal, calmodulin; ADP, ADP-ribosylation factor; EIF, elongation initiation factor; GhyP, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; GTP, GTP-binding protein; and Tum, translationally controlled tumour protein). The broken horizontal line on the upper panel represents the 0.15 suggested cutoff for determining the optimum number of reference genes required for normalization.  Relative increase in gene transcript abundance (relative to fully watered controls) of eight genes in the taproots of alfalfa cultivars (grouped into fall dormant (FD), non-fall dormant (NFD) or highly non-fall dormant (HNFD) groups based on their level of fall dormancy observed in the fall dormancy screening experiment) receiving 25 % of their water requirement. Values above the bars are the transformed means (log transformation) with the associated standard errors in parentheses. Bars with different letters within the same gene and number of days from treatment were identified as being different ( P  &lt; 0.05) using ANOVA with non-orthogonal contrasts on transformed data.  The abundance of  sucrose synthase  gene transcripts (relative to the fully watered controls) was lower in the fall dormant cultivars compared with the non-fall dormant and highly non-fall dormant cultivars after 35 days of treatment. The expression of the sucrose synthase gene at 14 days of treatment was not statistically different among the fall dormancy groupings.  The shoot growth of the water deficit stressed plants relative to fully watered controls at 14 days of treatment differed by fall dormancy grouping, with the fall dormant cultivars able to maintain shoot growth for longer periods under a water deficit (Fig.  5 ). Past research has noted that in the cool temperate environments of Australia that do not expose alfalfa crops to extreme winter temperatures, fall dormant cultivars outperform non-fall dormant cultivars in terms of forage yield in the face of mild to moderate drought ( Pembleton  et al.  2010 a  ,   b  ) despite having no need for the freezing tolerance that fall dormancy is associated with. Similarly, in certain temperate environments in China that receive nearly 1000 mm of annual precipitation,  Wang  et al.  (2009)  noted differences in annual forage yield among fall dormancy groupings during drought (600 mm annual rainfall) years but not during years receiving rainfall close to the long-term average. Fall dormancy group by environmental interactions was observed in North America as well, with superior performance of fall dormant cultivars in water-limited environments ( Orloff and Hanson 2008 ). However, the confounding effects of both summer droughts and freezing winter temperatures make it difficult to attribute this expression of fall dormancy group by environmental interactions to the superior freezing or to the drought tolerance of fall dormant cultivars.  The fall dormant group also did not fully close their stomata until lower shoot water potentials were reached when compared with the highly non-fall dormant types. By the 35th day of treatment, there was no difference in relative shoot growth among the fall dormancy groupings and the consequences of a low shoot water potential on stomatal conductance were similar among the fall dormancy groups. The cumulative water deficit (water applied to the 100 % replacement water requirement treatment minus water applied to the 25 % replacement water requirement treatment) by this time was four times as great as the water deficit at 14 days (a 2530-mL deficit compared with a 625-mL deficit). This was reflected in plant shoot water potential for which there was no difference between the fully watered and the water deficit treated plants up to the 12th day of treatment while a 2.5-fold decrease from the fully watered plants occurred between 19 and 33 days of treatment. The timing of when the acclimation to water deficit was observed to occur in relation to the severity of the water deficit stress suggests that the specific acclimation to water deficit by more fall dormant cultivars of alfalfa is expressed early after the onset of water deficits and that more extended stress restricts growth equally for all cultivars. This observation is further supported by the difference between the fall dormancy groupings in the relationship between shoot water potential and stomatal conductance. The superior vigour of the fall dormant cultivars over non-fall dormant cultivars under a mild water deficit as indicated in Fig.  5  helped this fall dormancy grouping maintain stomatal conductance and leaf area expansion under lower shoot water potentials (Fig.  7 ). This would enable increased net plant photosynthesis and a further continuation of shoot growth in these cultivars in the face of mild to moderate water deficits, as has been previously observed under field conditions ( Orloff and Hanson 2008 ;  Wang  et al.  2009 ;  Pembleton  et al.  2010 a  ,   b  ). A similar stomatal regulation strategy has been observed in the water deficit tolerant forage grass tall fescue ( Festuca arundinacea ) compared with the water deficit sensitive perennial ryegrass ( Lolium perenne ) ( Holloway-Phillips and Brodribb 2011 ).  The maintenance of stomatal conductance, leaf area expansion and shoot growth at lower shoot water potentials would require osmotic adjustment within the plant. Osmotic adjustment is a key strategy that alfalfa plants use to minimize damage when exposed to freezing temperatures ( Castonguay  et al.  2006 ). The analysis of gene transcript abundance after 14 days of treatment identified that the transcripts for several genes that have been associated with the adaptation to freezing temperatures in alfalfa increased in abundance relative to the fully watered controls when exposed to a water deficit. The genetic basis of acclimation to freezing temperatures is common among all alfalfa fall dormancy groups ( Castonguay  et al.  1997 ). Consequently, the presence of freezing tolerance gene transcripts across all the fall dormancy groups as shown in Fig.  9  could be expected. After 14 days of water deficit, the  cas18  and  corF  gene transcripts had an increase in abundance that was related to fall dormancy grouping and their relative adaptation to water deficit indicated by the plant growth measurements. However, after 35 days of exposure to water deficit there was no pattern in gene transcript abundance that was related to fall dormancy and consequently water deficit tolerance. In Arabidopsis ( Arabidopsis thaliana ), wheat ( Triticum aestivum ),  Nicotiana benthamiana  and rice ( Oryza sativa ), homologues of the  cas18  and  corF  genes have been identified as early response genes following the exposure to a water deficit ( Zhu 2002 ). The signalling pathways leading to the expression of these genes are constitutively maintained within the cell, leading to a rapid increase in their transcript abundance after exposure to stress (typical of dehydrins;  Hanin  et al.  2011 ). The other genes that exhibited an increase in transcript abundance are homologues of delayed response genes identified by  Jaglo-Ottosen  et al.  (1998)  and  Kasuga  et al.  (1999) . The signalling pathways for these genes need to be constructed before they are expressed ( Zhu 2002 ). The differential expression of the early response genes observed at Day 14 but not at Day 35 of treatment suggests that although the non-fall dormant cultivars possess a functional form of the freezing tolerance genes, they may not have an as efficient signalling pathway for these genes in place compared with the fall dormant cultivars. This may partly explain the difference in adaptation at a plant growth/physiology level between fall dormancy groups treated to mild water deficit stress (14 days of treatment) but not to severe water deficit stress (35 days of treatment) as observed in this experiment. The creation of plants that under/overexpress genes may be required to fully understand the impact these genes and their signalling pathways have on the adaptation of plants to a water deficit.  The  cas18  gene transcript encodes for a protein that has considerable homology to dehydrins isolated from other species ( Wolfraim  et al.  1993 ;  Close 1997 ). Dehydrins are thought to maintain cellular membrane integrity during dehydration ( Close 1997 ;  Hanin  et al.  2011 ) and this has been the hypothesized role for the cas18 protein during freezing adaptation. Given the upregulation of this gene transcript in the drought-tolerant fall dormant cultivars when exposed to a water deficit, it is conceivable that the role of the cas18 protein during adaption to a water deficit is similar to that of dehydrins in other species.  The  corF  transcript encodes for galactinol synthase, a key enzyme in the formation of raffinose family oligosaccharides (RFOs) ( Peterbauer and Richter 2001 ). The concentration of RFOs in alfalfa taproots has previously been correlated with freezing tolerance and winter survival ( Castonguay  et al.  1995 ;  Cunningham  et al.  2003 ), and an increase in the tissue concentration of RFOs has been associated with dehydration tolerance in  Xerophyta viscosa  ( Peters  et al.  2007 ) and Arabidopsis ( Taji  et al.  2002 ). Differences in the levels of  corF  gene transcripts in the taproots of alfalfa cultivars grouped into fall dormancy groups during the onset of fall dormancy have been noted by  Cunningham  et al.  (2003) . The role of RFOs in both freezing and water deficit stress tolerance may be through the protection of cellular structures or the stabilization of cellular membranes ( Leopold 1990 ;  Crowe  et al.  1992 ).  The reduced abundance of the type 1 sucrose synthase gene transcripts in the water deficit tolerant fall dormant alfalfa cultivars after 35 days of treatment is novel given the requirement for increased concentrations of osmolytes in the cytosol when the plant is exposed to a water deficit. Furthermore, simple sugars, including sucrose, are thought to help stabilize membranes during freezing desiccation ( Crowe and Crowe 1992 ;  Sun  et al.  1994 ). Interestingly, Sus1 in Arabidopsis was also reported to be induced by changes in leaf osmotic potential via an ABA-independent mechanism during low-temperature stress and osmotic stress ( Déjardin  et al.  1999 ). Whereas transcript levels of  Sus1  could increase several fold after osmotic stress exposures, researchers failed to observe any changes to the sucrose synthase protein levels on a western blot even after long-term cold and drought treatments.  Déjardin  et al.  (1999)  proposed that  Sus1  is under tight post-transcriptional control during osmotic stress and that  Sus1  mRNA might perhaps be produced and stored for use during specific stages of cold hardening or during plant recovery from the stress. In alfalfa the maintenance of taproot starch reserves has been linked with the long-term persistence in drought-prone environments ( Boschma and Williams 2008 ). Given the role that sucrose synthase plays in utilizing the glucose released from starch degradation, the downregulation of this gene in the fall dormant cultivars could be a consequence of a long-term energy maintenance strategy under drought conditions in these cultivars. If true, this response indicates that fall dormant cultivars are not only more tolerant of mild water deficit conditions compared with more non-fall dormant cultivars but they may also be more persistent when exposed to severe long-term droughts. Further research is required to understand the role of sucrose synthase in alfalfa under different environmental conditions.  From the transcript abundance profiles and the punitive proteins these transcripts encode for, it can be concluded that the adaptation of the fall dormant cultivars is due to improved protection of cellular structures and membranes in the short term. The transcripts involved in stress signalling, protein storage and cellular regulation while also increased in abundance did not show any differential expression related to the adaptation of fall dormant cultivars to water deficit. The absence of differential expression of these transcripts is interesting as cross-talk between stress signalling pathways as well as the difference in cellular regulation has been linked to associations between abiotic stress tolerance including both freezing and drought ( Zhu 2002 ;  Seki  et al.  2003 ;  Chinnusamy  et al.  2004 ). Consequently, if the drought tolerance of non-fall dormant alfalfa cultivars is to be improved without the use of gene modifications, focus should be placed on the improvement of the protective cellular structures and membranes by breeding together cultivars with desired gene expression patterns.  While this study is not the first to examine the responses of alfalfa cultivars to exposure to a water deficit (see  Pembleton  et al.  2009 ;  Erice  et al.  2011  for others), it is the first that has examined a broad enough range of fall dormancy to be able to conclude that decreasing levels of fall dormancy reduce adaptation to mild water deficit conditions. In support of this finding, transcripts of two genes that are associated with freezing tolerance increased in abundance in the more fall dormant types when exposed to a mild water deficit, while the transcript of a type 1 sucrose synthase gene associated with phloem loading and carbon channelling in roots decreased when the fall dormant types were exposed to a severe water deficit. The identification of a partial separation between fall dormancy and freezing tolerance by  Brouwer  et al.  (2000)  and  Brummer  et al.  (2000)  along with the linkage between freezing tolerance and water deficit tolerance at a molecular level identified in this study suggests that it will be possible to achieve greater drought tolerance in non-fall dormant cultivars. This study has identified that alfalfa cultivars must be of the fall dormant type to exhibit superior adaptation to a water deficit. The stress adaptation pathways associated with the upregulation of the freezing tolerance genes  cas18  and  corF  during mild water deficit stress and the downregulation of a type 1 sucrose synthase gene during severe water deficit stress appear to be the molecular mechanism by which fall dormant cultivars of alfalfa ‘give drought the cold shoulder’.  This work was supported by  Dairy Australia Ltd  and the  Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry Awards of the 2011 Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry (DAFF) Science and Innovation Awards for Young People in Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry .  K.G.P. conceived the study, designed the experiments and carried out the experiments. P.S. helped design and supervised the qRT-PCR analysis. Both authors drafted the paper and approved the final draft.  None declared.  The authors appreciate the seed kindly provided by David Squib and James Sewell of PGG Wrightson Seeds Australia, David Barnett and Tom Damin of Seed Distributors Australia, Dr Jonathan Reich of Cal/West Seeds USA and Dr Allan Humphries of SARDI. The authors thank Prof. Derick Moot and the anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments on earlier drafts of this paper. 