Ethylene and the responses of plants to phosphate deficiencyPhosphate sensing in root developmentTemporal responses of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root architecture to phosphate starvation: evidence for the involvement of auxin signallingA quantitative analysis of the factors affecting plant nutrient uptake from some soils<italic>Superroot</italic>, a recessive mutation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, confers auxin overproductionEffect of phosphorus deficiency on growth angle of basal roots in <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>Ethylene: a regulator of root architectural responses to soil phosphorus availabilityA central regulatory system largely controls transcriptional activation and repression responses to phosphate starvation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Global expression pattern comparison between <italic>low phosphorus insensitive 4</italic> and WT <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> reveals an important role of reactive oxygen species and jasmonic acid in the root tip response to phosphate starvationSignalling network in sensing phosphate availability in plantsRegulation of root growth by auxin and ethylene is influenced by phosphate supply in white clover (<italic>Trifolium repens</italic> L.)Comparison of the effects of a localised supply of phosphate, nitrite, ammonium and potassium on the growth of the seminal root system, and the shoot in barleyNutrient supply and the growth of the seminal root system in barley. III. Compensatory increase in growth of lateral roots, and in rates if phosphate uptake, in response to a localized supply of phosphateDecreased ethylene biosynthesis, and induction of aerenchyma, by nitrogen- or phosphate-starvation in adventitious roots of <italic>Zea mays</italic> LHormone interactions during lateral root formationTissue-specific expression of the ethylene biosynthetic machinery regulates root growth in maizeIdentification of candidate phosphorus stress induced genes in <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> through clustering analysis across several plant speciesEnhanced sensitivity to ethylene in nitrogen- or phosphate-starved roots of <italic>Zea mays</italic> L. during aerenchyma formationPhosphorus stress in common bean: Root transcript and metabolic responsesEthylene–auxin interactions regulate lateral root initiation and emergence in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Ethylene in root growth and developmentEffects of applying ethylene to the root system of <italic>Zea mays</italic> L. on growth and nutrient concentration in relation to floodingDifferential effects of sucrose and auxin on localized phosphate deficiency-induced modulation of different traits of root system architecture in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Ethylene insensitivity impedes a subset of responses to phosphorus deficiency in tomato and petuniaThe <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> AP2/ERF transcription factor RAP2.11 modulates plant response to low-potassium conditionsEthylene signalling is involved in regulation of phosphate starvation-induced gene expression and production of acid phosphatases and anthocyanin in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Ethylene inhibits lateral root development, increases IAA transport and expression of PIN3 and PIN7 efflux carriersStimulation of root acid phosphatases by phosphorus deficiency is regulated by ethylene in <italic>Medicago falcate</italic>Nitrate and phosphate availability and distribution have different effects on root system architecture of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Phosphate availability alters architecture and causes changes in hormone sensitivity in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root systemTopsoil foraging—an architectural adaptation of plants to low phosphorus availabilityRegulation of root elongation under phosphorus stress involves changes in ethylene responsivenessThe <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> SUMO E3 ligase SIZ1 controls phosphate deficiency responses<italic>SIZ1</italic> regulation of phosphate starvation-induced root architecture remodelling involves the control of auxin accumulationAuxin and ethylene: collaborators or competitors?A role for auxin redistribution in the responses of the root system architecture to phosphate starvation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Ethylene's role in phosphate starvation signaling: more than just a root growth regulatorEthylene regulates lateral root formation and auxin transport in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Dissecting the plant transcriptome and the regulatory responses to phosphate deprivationPhosphate import in plants: focus on the PHT1 transportersRoot developmental adaptation to phosphate starvation: better safe than sorryPhosphate availability alters lateral root development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by modulating auxin sensitivity via a mechanism involving the TIR1 auxin receptorThe Janus face of ethylene: growth inhibition and stimulation<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RING E3 ligase XBAT32 regulates lateral root production through its role in ethylene biosynthesisPhosphate acquisitionInhibition of auxin movement from the shoot into the root inhibits lateral root development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Ethylene regulates root growth through effects on auxin biosynthesis and transport-dependent auxin distributionPhosphate starvation induces a determinate developmental program in the roots of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Occurrence of ethylene, and its significance, in anaerobic soilApolastic alkalinisation is instrumental for the inhibition of cell elongation in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root by the ethylene precursor 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate acidEthylene directs auxin to control root cell expansionRoot tip contact with low-phosphate media reprograms plant root architectureEthylene upregulates auxin biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings to enhance inhibition of root cell elongationDissection of local and systematic transcriptional responses to phosphate starvation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>Arabidopsis CULLIN3</italic> genes regulate primary root growth and patterning by ethylene-dependent and -independent mechanismsAttentuation of phosphate starvation responses by phosphite in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>Arabidopsis pdr2</italic> reveals a phosphate-sensitive checkpoint in root developmentER-resident proteins PDR2 and LPR1 mediate the developmental response of root meristems to phosphate availabilityUnique and overlapping expression patterns among the Arabidopsis 1-amino-cyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase gene family membersThe <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene HYPERSENSITIVE TO PHOSPHATE STARVATION3 encodes ETHYLENE OVERPRODUCER 1The effect of iron on the primary root elongation of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> during phosphate deficiencyHormonal factors controlling the initiation and development of lateral roots. II. Effects of exogenous growth factors on lateral root formation in pea rootsPhosphate availability regulates root system architecture in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Regulation of phosphate starvation responses in higher plantsHPS4/SABRE regulates plant responses to phosphate starvation through antagonistic interaction with ethylene signallingThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.This review considers the evidence that ethylene biosynthesis is up-regulated by locally-generated signals in response to a change in external P supply, where the hormone then mediates, with auxin, changes in root system architecture. Subsequent changes in endogenous P evoke systemic responses whereby ethylene again is important in inducing some of the key signature changes observed in P-deprived tissues (eg. phosphate transporter and acid phosphatase up-regulation).The consideration as to how plants uptake and transport phosphorus (P) is of significant agronomic and economic importance, in part driven by finite reserves of rock phosphate. Our understanding of these mechanisms has been greatly advanced, particularly with respect to the responses of plants to P deficiency and the genetic dissection of the signalling involved. Further, the realization that there are two tiers of transcriptional responses, the local, in which inorganic P (Pi) acts as an external signal independent of the endogenous P level, and the systemic involving root–shoot signalling, has now added a dimension of both clarity and complexity. Notwithstanding, it is now clear that the hormone ethylene plays a key role in mediating both levels of responses. This review, therefore, covers the role of ethylene in terms of mediating responses to P deficiency. The evidence that Pi supply regulates ethylene biosynthesis and sensitivity, and that this, in turn, regulates changes in root system architecture and in Pi-deprivation responses is examined here. While ethylene is the focus, the key interactions with auxin are also assessed, but interactions with the other hormone groups, which have recently been reviewed, are not covered. The emerging view that ethylene is a multi-faceted hormone in terms of mediating responses to P deficiency invites the dissection of the transcriptional cues that mediate changes in ethylene biosynthesis and/or sensitivity. Knowledge of the nature of such cues will subsequently reveal more of the underpinning interactions that govern P responses and provide avenues for the production of germplasm with an improved phosphate use efficiency.The mechanisms by which plants access sufficient phosphate (P) from the soil are of intense agronomic and academic interest. The chemical form of phosphorus P taken up by plants, orthophosphate (H<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub><sup>−</sup>; designated as Pi), represents only a small fraction of available (free) P in soils and is generally immobile. However, as a macro-element, relatively significant quantities are required for plant function, and measurement of the Pi content of the aerial and root tissue of plants, when compared with the level in the surrounding soil, suggests that efficient uptake and transport systems do operate in plants. The array of Pi transporters, and their expression, has been reviewed relatively recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C45">Raghothama and Karthikeyan 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C40">Nussaume <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), and the determination of the key role of the PHO1 protein has provided significant insight into how plants partition the essential element, in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> at least (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C9">Chiou and Lin 2011</xref>).Further insight into the mechanisms by which plants uptake and partition phosphate, particularly in terms of changes in root growth dynamics and function, occurs via approaches where phosphate is limiting. In particular, understanding the mechanisms and controls regulating the observed changes in root system architecture (RSA) is an active research field inviting speculation as to how alterations in the levels of both endogenous and exogenous Pi can influence such fundamental (and rapid) changes in growth. In this review, we focus on one aspect of this control: the interaction of Pi level and ethylene biosynthesis and signalling. We examine the emerging view that ethylene may play a role in both modulating RSA and regulating some of the signature cellular changes that accompany the responses of plants to low Pi supply. In terms of RSA, our focus is on changes to primary and lateral root growth. However, it is clear too that root hairs play an important role in Pi acquisition, and while the importance of these structures has been reviewed recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C41">Peret <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), they will not be considered here. In our examination of the role of ethylene, we will look (briefly) at the role of auxin, but beyond that, and while not wishing to undermine the importance of such interactions, we will not consider the interactions with other hormones in any detail. However, the reader is referred to more recent reviews of this topic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C14">Fukaki and Tasaka 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C9">Chiou and Lin 2011</xref>). Likewise, there is the intriguing Fe/Pi interaction that is emerging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C61">Ward <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), and which has been reviewed more recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C1">Abel 2011</xref>), and it is also apparent that ethylene signalling is fundamental in terms of plant responses to low-potassium conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C24">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). However, in the space available, we focus on the Pi and ethylene interaction.The observation that Pi supply can regulate root architecture arose from early considerations that the subtleties of root structure contribute largely to the efficiency of nutrient uptake, particularly for the immobile elements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C3">Baldwin 1975</xref>). Subsequently, changes in RSA (compensatory growth) were observed in barley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C11">Drew 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C12">Drew and Saker 1978</xref>), and in bean and other legumes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C5">Bonser <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C6">Borch <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). A summary of changes to the root architecture in bean suggests a root system that undergoes growth responses to maximize top soil foraging, but in tandem with a reduction in the metabolic cost of such soil mining (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C30">Lynch and Brown 2001</xref>).More recently, studies have inevitably changed to the model plant species <italic>Arabidopsis.</italic> In addition to the well-known array of genetic resources available, this species has a further advantage for use when dissecting the influence of Pi supply on root growth in that it does not form mycorrhizal associations, so making separation of <italic>in planta</italic> observations more apparent. In comparison with bean, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> also has a less complex root system when grown from seed over, typically, 14-day time courses. Initial studies using the accession Columbia revealed a signature response to low Pi supply comprising a decreased growth rate of the primary root (PR), in part mediated by a reduction in elongation of cells at the root cap, and an increase in mean lateral root (LR), length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C63">Williamson <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). With the decrease in PR length, LR density thus increased and the distance between the root tip and the first emerged LR also decreased in response to the low Pi treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C63">Williamson <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). The decrease in PR length and an increase in LR density in response to low Pi supply were confirmed in Columbia seedlings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C29">López-Bucio <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref>, with an increase in LR number also contributing. Interestingly, these authors also applied a range of P concentrations and noted a biphasic rather than linear response to P added, particularly in terms of PR length and LR density, perhaps indicating the operation of a ‘threshold’ concentration in terms of the controlling signalling. That these changes represent a re-allocation of resources in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> was demonstrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C2">Al-Ghazi <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref>, who showed that the total root length is unchanged (at least over the period measured), and so with the elongation of the PR decreasing, an increase in LR length is apparent. These authors thus summarized a sequence of changes in RSA for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> in response to low Pi that involves a decrease in PR elongation, an increase in LR elongation rate, a decrease in the initiation of laterals and an increase in the growth duration of LRs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C2">Al-Ghazi <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>).With these morphological changes in response to low P established in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, focus then shifted to understanding the mechanisms by which Pi supply induces these modifications. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C35">Nacry <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> showed, using a <italic>CycB1::uidA</italic> reporter construct, that the LR stimulation was mediated <italic>via</italic> the activation of existing primordia, while the initiation of new primordia was repressed in roots exposed to low Pi supply. The decrease in PR elongation involved a shift from indeterminate to determinate growth, with the progressive loss of meristematic cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C48">Sanchez-Calderon <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). So, how does a root sense a change in Pi supply?In earlier work, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C28">Linkohr <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> were able to show in elegant experiments with nutrient patches that the low P phenotype could be induced or repressed depending on the media through which the root was growing. Indeed, Pi sensing (to trigger reduction of PR elongation) was shown to be resident in the root cap and, significantly, independent of the Pi content of the root (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C52">Svistoonoff <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). The emergence of the concept of Pi as a signal had been proposed earlier by Ticconi and colleagues when they showed that application of the phosphate analogue, phosphite, could repress a range of P-starvation responses including transcriptional changes in P-starved seedlings of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C56">Ticconi <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>).In terms of transduction of the Pi signal in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C57">Ticconi <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> identified the <italic>pdr2</italic> locus that is disrupted in Pi sensing, but importantly application of phosphite was able to rescue the mutant phenotype demonstrating that PDR2 was involved in sensing the external Pi availability. Subsequent characterization has determined that PDR2 interacts with LOW PHOSPHATE ROOT 1 (LPR1) in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, a regulator previously identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C52">Svistoonoff <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> as being important in the root tip Pi response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C58">Ticconi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The mechanism so revealed suggests that PDR2, in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> at least, is required for the correct expression of SCARECROW (SCR), a regulator of stem cell maintenance in roots, and thus provides a signalling pathway in which local Pi sensing can lead to the switch from indeterminate to determinate growth in the PR tip as previously reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C48">Sanchez-Calderon <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref>.This role for Pi as a signal was extended in terms of documenting transcriptional changes accompanying local Pi sensing. Using split-root approaches, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C54">Thibaud <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> were able to show in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> that a (low) external Pi, irrespective of internal Pi levels in the root, could influence the transcription of a cluster of genes, designated the locally regulated genes, while a low internal Pi level influenced the transcription of another cluster, designated the systemically regulated genes. Of the genes analysed, the majority were either locally induced (73%) or repressed (68%) and these genes tended to encode proteins involved in hormone biosynthesis and signalling and in stress responses. The systemically induced genes were involved in Pi uptake, mobilization and recycling, suggesting that the changes in external Pi perceived by the plant roots initially elicit a general stress response to perhaps sensitize the plant to any subsequent longer-term nutrient stress. Interestingly, while internal Pi was essential to evoke the systemic response, reducing the flow of Pi into the root did not, suggesting that a Pi-independent signalling system is operating, such as the <italic>PHO2</italic> mRNA regulator, mir399, which is important in coordinating the response. Further, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C54">Thibaud <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> were also able to show that the systemically induced genes were marked by the possession of the PiBS motif, a target for the PHR1 transcription factor, while repressed genes do not contain the motif. While <italic>PHR1</italic> itself is only marginally induced by Pi starvation, mutation of the P1BS site impairs P responsiveness, but does not influence responses to other stresses (e.g. wounding) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C7">Bustos <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The dissection of such internal signalling events in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, particularly with respect to shoot-to-root communication, including the key roles of sucrose and MiR399, has been well reviewed recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C39">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C64">Yang and Finnegan 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C9">Chiou and Lin 2011</xref>).The other major player in the control of RSA is auxin. The hormone has long been proposed to be a major regulator from the early pea root decapitation experiments of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C62">Wightman <italic>et al.</italic> (1980)</xref>. More recent evidence of a role for auxin arose from <italic>in vivo</italic> studies using developmental mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C4">Boerjan <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>) or using factors that influence endogenous auxin transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C46">Reed <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Thus the interaction of Pi status, changes in RSA and the role of auxin is worthy of record, and a number of studies, primarily in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, have implicated the hormone (L<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C29">ópez-Bucio <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C2">Al-Ghazi <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C35">Nacry <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C22">Jain <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C42">Perez-Torres <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C33">Miura <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Of these, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C29">López-Bucio <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> used an array of auxin transport and signalling mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and concluded that low P served to increase the sensitivity of the roots to respond to auxin in terms of inducing the signature changes in RSA. Using a similar panel of mutants, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C35">Nacry <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> concluded that changes in auxin distribution/transport and/or synthesis may underpin these changes such that in low P, an over-accumulation of auxin in the PR represses elongation but activates existing LR primordia and the emergence of the laterals, while a decrease in auxin in the elongation zone decreased the formation of new lateral primordia. In support of this, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C33">Miura <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> transformed mutants of the SUMO E3 ligase (SIZ1) of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> that had an enhanced Pi response with <italic>DR5p::uidA</italic> and determined that the auxin accumulated earlier both in the PR tip (to decrease growth) and in the lateral primordia (to activate growth) in the <italic>siz1</italic> background when compared with wild type. Interestingly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C32">Miura <italic>et al.</italic> (2005</xref>) had shown previously that SIZ1 interacts with PHR1, a global regulator of the systemic Pi responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C7">Bustos <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C54">Thibaud <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), and the <italic>siz1</italic> mutant was shown to have elevated Pi levels. In terms of mechanism, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C42">Perez-Torres <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> looked at how this change of sensitivity may be mediated and concluded that Pi deprivation increases the expression of <italic>TIR1</italic> and the action of auxin then stimulates the degradation of the Aux/IAA repressors, thus sensitizing the tissue to auxin.Prior to a discussion as to how low Pi supply and ethylene interact to influence RSA, it is pertinent to review how the hormone influences root growth in P-supplied roots. The involvement of ethylene as a regulator of root growth has been well established since the early experiments of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C49">Smith and Russell (1969)</xref> with roots of barley. More recent evidence with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> includes perturbations that can regulate ethylene evolution, such as a mutation in the Cullin-RING ubiquitin ligase, CULLIN3, which leads to the stabilization and thus accumulation of 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate (ACC) synthase 5 (ACS5), and an up-regulation of ethylene biosynthesis. In these plants, repression of PR elongation is observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C55">Thomann <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). A general consensus thus exists whereby lower concentrations of the hormone can promote root extension, while higher concentrations are inhibitory for growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C21">Jackson <italic>et al.</italic> 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C20">Jackson 1991</xref>), so underlining the biphasic action of ethylene in regulating many aspects of vegetative growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C43">Pierik <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>).The role of ethylene in regulating RSA, and how this is mediated <italic>via</italic> auxin, is also well established. In the PR of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, it is clear that ethylene is stimulating auxin biosynthesis in the root tip, where the higher concentration that ensues inhibits growth, and also a redistribution to the elongation zone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C47">Ruzicka <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C53">Swarup <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C51">Strader <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). For the PR of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, some details as to the downstream mechanism of inhibition are emerging, which suggests that ethylene may work <italic>via</italic> auxin by increasing the cellular concentration of the hormone to a level that inhibits the auxin target H<sup>+</sup>-pumping ATPases so maintaining apolastic alkalinization. Ethylene may also increase ROS production that stimulates hydroxyproline-rich glycoprotein cross-linking which, acting in concert with alkaliniation, will serve to reduce the extensibility of the wall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C50">Staal <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).Ethylene also regulates the initiation of LR primordia and LR outgrowth, again controlled <italic>via</italic> auxin biosynthesis and distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C19">Ivanchenko <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C38">Negi <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, higher ethylene concentrations were observed to inhibit the ability of the pericycle to initiate new root primordia although the hormone did promote the emergence of existing primordia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C19">Ivanchenko <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Supporting evidence for the requirement for ethylene also arises from studies in which a mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> with a lesion in a member of the RING domain-containing ankyrin repeat subfamily of E3 ligases, XBAT32, resulted in ACS accumulation, an increase in ethylene biosynthesis and the production of fewer LRs in the <italic>xbat32</italic> background (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C44">Prasad <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). In terms of the mechanism of action of ethylene in LR formation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, one proposed role for the hormone is to up-regulate the expression of <italic>PIN3</italic> and <italic>PIN7</italic> resulting in increased auxin transport and the lack of establishment of a sufficient local auxin concentration to initiate new LR primordia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C26">Lewis <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). For a detailed account of the interaction between auxin and ethylene and the initiation and control of root growth and RSA, the reader is referred to the comprehensive review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C34">Muday <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>. However, of more pertinence to this review is the emerging view that P status regulates RSA architecture through documented changes in auxin biosynthesis and transport which is controlled ultimately <italic>via</italic> ethylene biosynthesis and/or signalling.Given the pertinence of the links between auxin signalling, phosphate supply and a role for ethylene, there have been few documented studies where investigators have measured ethylene levels in P-starved roots, and few in general on the regulation of ethylene biosynthesis in P-starved or P-supplied roots. Notably, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C59">Tsuchisaka and Theologis (2004)</xref> examined the differential expression of <italic>ACS</italic> genes in P-supplied roots of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C15">Gallie <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> examined the tissue-specific expression of both <italic>ACS</italic> and <italic>ACC oxidase (ACO)</italic> genes in the elongating P-supplied root of maize and concluded that ethylene production was limiting for root elongation, particularly the ACS isoform, <italic>ZmACS6</italic>. In terms of ethylene and altered P supply, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C13">Drew <italic>et al.</italic> (1989)</xref>, using maize in hydroponic culture, excised apical segments of emerged adventitious roots and noted that ethyene evolution, ACC levels, and ACO and ACS activity decreased, leading to the conclusion that P-starvation-induced aerenchyma formation was not directed by ethylene. In careful experiments with bean, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C6">Borch <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref> determined that P deficiency did not result in increased ethylene evolution at the root zone, although if the total root dry weight was compared, then an increase was noted in the low P treatment (to reflect the decreased total root mass). In tomato, low P treatment significantly increased ethylene production from the shoots, but decreased it in the roots, and while adventitious roots produced more ethylene, a significant decrease was noted in response to low P supply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C23">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). In this study, the ethylene evolution values are expressed on a per fresh weight (FW) basis, which may accentuate the differences given that lower FW values were again recorded for both shoots and roots in the P-deprived treatments.The multi-gene ACO family displays differential expression in roots in response to the low Pi treatment. The effects of P treatment [1 mM, P+ (-•-); 10 µM, P− (-▪-)] on the expression, as determined by qPCR, of <italic>TR-ACO1</italic> (A) and <italic>TR-ACO2</italic> (B) in the roots of wild-type white clover harvested at the time intervals indicated. The <bold>*</bold> indicates significant differences between treatments (<italic>P</italic>≤ 0.05); † indicates significant differences within a treatment from day 0.The key impetus for the investigation of changes in ethylene biosynthesis in response to P supply has been to characterize how the hormone does influence RSA in a P-starved tissue. Historically, approaches have progressed from the application of the hormone to the roots (often as added ACC), to the use of both ethylene biosynthesis and action inhibitors through to mutant backgrounds that are compromised in either ethylene signalling or P response. In earlier work, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C17">He <italic>et al.</italic> (1992)</xref> showed in maize that low P did not induce a perceptible increase in ethylene production, but it did result in sensitizing the tissues to exogenously applied ethylene in terms of the induction of aerenchyma formation. In bean, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C6">Borch <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref> showed that inhibiting ethylene biosynthesis with aminoethoxyglycine (AVG) abolished the documented low-P-induced changes to RSA. However, these workers also determined that the response to ethylene was, more correctly, determined by tissue and P supply such that in the PR, ethylene promotes growth in low P and inhibits it in sufficient P. Likewise, in the determination of LR density, ethylene decreases density in low P (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C6">Borch <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). These results in bean have been summarized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C30">Lynch and Brown (2001)</xref> in which they proposed that P availability affects ethylene responsiveness that operates conversely in PR growth and LR density. Thus, in bean, an increase in measured ethylene concentration growth in low P stimulated the growth of the PR and decreased LR frequency.In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> too, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C31">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref> measured the rate of PR elongation and concluded that while the rate is decreased in low P, ethylene is important for the maintenance of root elongation and further that the roots are more sensitive to ethylene in the low P media [as determined by the use of 1-methylcyclopropene (1-MCP) and AVG]. These studies highlight that ethylene production <italic>per se</italic> is one aspect of the role of the hormone, but sensitivity is equally important (and may be the ultimate regulator). In tomato and Petunia, the use of ethylene-insensitive mutants and the measurement of ethylene production allowed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C23">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> to conclude that, in these species at least, low P did not cause an increase in ethylene production, and so the changes in RSA measured were orchestrated <italic>via</italic> changes in sensitivity. Likewise, in the pasture legume white clover, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C10">Dinh <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> showed that ACC added to roots maintained in low P induced a ‘super-stimulation’ of LR number and mean LR length when compared with the stimulation induced by the low P treatment alone.To examine the mechanism by which ethylene may alter root growth, albeit <italic>via</italic> an increased sensitivity to the hormone, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C8">Chacon-Lopez <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> examined the P-induced cessation of PR growth in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> utilizing a QC marker. They noted that the previously observed consumption of the root meristem in the P-deficient treatment was abolished if either AVG or silver ions (Ag<sup>2+</sup>) were added. Further, if ACC was added to the P-sufficient media, consumption of the meristem was again observed although this did not proceed to completion, suggesting that ethylene does not act alone. However, the addition of jasmonic acid (JA) and ethylene did promote complete meristem consumption, implying that the rapid changes in RSA may have similarities to broad stress-associated responses. Finally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C65">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> characterized the <italic>hypersensitive to Pi starvation 4 (hps4)</italic> mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, a background that displays an exaggerated response in terms of RSA, and found it to be allelic to <italic>SABRE</italic>, a previously characterized gene that regulates cell expansion. A link with ethylene signalling in the P response was established when it was shown that added Ag repressed the observed increase in severity of phenotype in low P. Interestingly, these workers also observed that the mutant accumulated a higher auxin content in the apical 5 mm root tips as well as displaying an increased expression of auxin-biosynthesis-associated genes in harvested seedlings, leading the mechanism back to the phenomenon described in this review of ethylene-induced changes in auxin biosynthesis and signalling.It is now accepted that the influence of P-induced ethylene biosynthesis or signalling and changes in RSA is mediated, at one level, <italic>via</italic> the ethylene interactions with auxin. However, auxin does not induce the expression of the phosphate-starvation inducible (PSI) genes, and so the focus of research has shifted more recently to examining the possible other roles of ethylene in terms of inducing the PSI genes and influencing activity.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C25">Lei <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> characterized the <italic>hypersensitive to phosphate deprivation 2 (hsp2)</italic> mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> that displays an exaggerated response to Pi deficiency including increased inhibition of PR growth and a more marked induction of <italic>AtPT2</italic> expression. The mutation is allelic to the <italic>CTR1</italic> gene, suggesting that the phenotype was due to increased ethylene biosynthesis. Therefore to look at the role of ethylene more directly in terms of the regulation of PSI gene expression, <italic>AtPT2</italic> expression was characterized in the <italic>etr1-1</italic> and <italic>ein2-5</italic> mutant backgrounds and found not to be increased in response to low P, while induction of <italic>AtPT2</italic> expression was observed in the <italic>eto1-1</italic> background (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C25">Lei <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). To more directly examine the role of ethylene in the induction of <italic>AtPT2</italic>, these workers also showed that added ACC could induce <italic>AtPT2</italic> expression in low-P-treated plants, but not in the P-sufficient treatment, so underlining that low P sensitizes the plant to respond to ethylene. For the acid phosphatase (Apase) enzyme, root surface activity was highest in the <italic>hps2</italic> mutant, followed by wild type with very little induction in the <italic>ein2-5</italic> background in response to low P. Using another mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C60">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> characterized <italic>hypersensitive to phosphate starvation 3</italic> (<italic>hps3</italic>) and showed that it was a mutation in the <italic>ETO1</italic> gene, thus giving an ethylene ‘on’ phenotype. In common with other studies, these workers showed that treatment of the mutant with either AVG or Ag<sup>2+</sup> abolished the exaggerated root growth phenotype observed in response to low P treatment. Further, they also showed that there was an induction of root surface Apase (but not total Apase) and an induction of several PSI genes examined in the mutant that could also be abolished if treated with AVG and Ag<sup>2+</sup>.In other species, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C27">Li <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> showed that for <italic>Medicago falcata</italic>, transfer of plants from high to low P medium caused a decrease in Pi content in the roots that could be abolished if the plants were treated with AVG or Co<sup>2+</sup> (to inhibit ACO activity). Also, if plants that are maintained in high P are treated directly with ACC, then the Pi content of the roots decreases, an observation that was supported by examination of the expression of a higher-affinity transporter <italic>MfPT1</italic> that was up-regulated by Pi deficiency and reversed by AVG and Co<sup>2+</sup>. In common with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, surface Apase was stimulated in roots of P-sufficient plants treated with ACC, while the induction of activity in the P-deficient medium was abolished by AVG treatment. Taken together, these results do support the contention that ethylene may have pleiotropic effects in terms of mediating the responses of plant roots to P deficiency, and it is likely that further roles will be identified in the future.Overview of the proposed dual role of ethylene in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> in response to low Pi supply. The summary is predicated on the key observation that the occurrence of the hormone is a local response to changes in external Pi and involves increased biosynthesis (e.g. up-regulation of <italic>AtACO4</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C54">Thibaud <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and/or increased sensitivity (e.g. up-regulation of <italic>AtERF</italic> genes; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C54">Thibaud <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). These local changes in ethylene concentration/sensitivity then interact with auxin to mediate changes to RSA. Any ensuing changes in P status of the leaves evoke a second tier of changes, the systemic responses, whereby the hormone induces, but independent of auxin, a series of key signature changes to P depletion including the up-regulation of acid phosphatases and phosphate transporters.A second series of events, the systemic responses, are denoted by changes in the Pi-deprivation metabolic responses caused by complex root–shoot–root signalling and are reflective of changes in the endogenous Pi levels. More recently, ethylene, in a mechanism apparently independent of auxin, has been shown to also induce many of these changes (summarized in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT013F2">2</xref>), but it is not yet clear whether a distinct series of systemic cues induce ethylene production and/or changes in ethylene sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT013C36">Nagarajan and Smith 2012</xref>). Thus it is important to look further at the nature of the transcriptional cues that regulate ethylene biosynthesis and perception. As the hormone does play such a multi-faceted role in the response to P deficiency, any revelations of such control must reveal further avenues to improve phosphate use efficiency.The research reported in this article was funded by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">New Zealand Foundation for Science, Research and Technology and the Massey University Research Fund</grant-sponsor>.M.T.M. drafted the article and M.R., P.D. and S.L. commented on the draft.None declared.