Differential expression of several xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolase genes regulates flower opening and petal abscission in rosesEthylene-induced differential gene expression during abscission of citrus leavesComparative transcriptional survey between laser-microdissected cells from laminar abscission zone and petiolar cortical tissue during ethylene-promoted abscission in citrus leavesA simple procedure for the isolation of high quality RNA from ripening banana fruitOverexpression of polygalacturonase in transgenic apple trees leads to a range of novel phenotypes involving changes in cell adhesionStructural evidence for the evolution of xyloglucanase activity from xyloglucan endotransglycosylases: biological implications for cell wall metabolismChanges in expansin activity and gene expression during ethylene-promoted leaflet abscission in <italic>Sambucus nigra</italic>Antisense suppression of tomato endo-beta-1,4-glucanase Cel2 mRNA accumulation increases the force required to break fruit abscission zones but does not affect fruit softeningEndo1 4-β-glucanase gene expression and cell wall hydrolase activities during abscission in Valencia orangeStamen abscission zone transcriptome profiling reveals new candidates for abscission control: enhanced retention of floral organs in transgenic plants over-expressing <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ZINC FINGER PROTEIN2Xyloglucan endotransglucosylases: diversity of genes, enzymes and potential wall-modifying functionsAuxin regulation and spatial localization of an endo-1,4-beta-d-glucanase and a xyloglucan endotransglucosylase in expanding tomato hypocotylsCharacterization of a tomato xyloglucan endotransglucosylase gene that is down-regulated by auxin in etiolated hypocotylsMolecular characterization of a xyloglucan specific endo-(1,4)-beta-D-glucanase (xyloglucan endotransglucosylase) from nasturtium seedsPedicel breakstrength and cellulase gene expression during tomato flower abscissionChanges in carbohydrates and osmotic potential during rhythmic expansion of rose petalsThe structure and functions of xyloglucanXyloglucan endotransglycosylase, a new wall loosening enzyme activity from plantsPoplar carbohydrate-active enzymes. Gene identification and expression analysesTemporal and spatial expression of a polygalacturonase during leaf and flower abscission in oilseed rape and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Expression of polygalacturonases and evidence to support their role during cell separation processes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Cloning, characterization, and expression of xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolase and expansin genes associated with petal growth and development during carnation flower openingXyloglucans in the primary cell wallCAP3: a DNA sequence assembly programExpression of a xyloglucan endotransglycosylase gene is closely related to grape berry softeningTranscriptome sequencing with the Genome Sequencer FLX systemDevelopment and characterization of genomic and expressed SSRs for levant cotton (<italic>Gossypium herbaceum</italic> L.)Silencing polygalacturonase expression inhibits tomato petiole abscissionGroup III-A XTH genes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> encode predominant xyloglucan endohydrolases that are dispensable for normal growthCloning of tomato polygalacturonase expressed in abscissionThree different polygalacturonases are expressed in tomato leaf and flower abscission each with a different temporal expression patternCell wall remodeling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> stamen abscission zonesPlant separation: 50 ways to leave your motherAnalysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>−ΔΔ<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic></sup> methodTranscriptional regulation of ethylene receptor and CTR genes involved in ethylene-induced flower opening in cut rose (<italic>Rosa hybrida</italic>) cv. SamanthaMicroarray analysis of the abscission-related transcriptome in the tomato flower abscission zone in response to auxin depletionEthylene induced cotton leaf abscission is associated with higher expression of cellulase (<italic>GhCel1</italic>) and increased activities of ethylene biosynthesis enzymes in abscission zoneXyloglucan endotransglycosylase (XET) functions in gelatinous layers of tension wood fibers in poplar: a glimpse into the mechanism of the balancing act of treesXyloglucan endo-transglycosylase-mediated xyloglucan rearrangements in developing wood of hybrid aspenEndo-xyloglucan transferase, a novel class of glycosyltransferase that catalyzes transfer of a segment of xyloglucan molecule to another xyloglucan moleculeChanges in xyloglucan endotransglucosylase (XET) activity during hormone-induced growth in lettuce and cucumber hypocotyls and spinach cell suspension culturesEthylene and silver thiosulphate influence opening of cut rose flowersThe XTH family of enzymes involved in xyloglucan endotransglucosylation and endohydrolysis: current perspectives and a new unifying nomenclatureA flooding-induced xyloglucan endotransglucosylase homologue in maize is responsive to ethylene and associated with aerenchymaCharacterization of a new xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolase (XTH) from ripening tomato fruit and implications for the diverse modes of enzymic actionPetal abscission in rose (<italic>Rosa bourboniana</italic> var Gruss an Teplitz) is associated with the enhanced expression of an alpha expansin gene, RbEXPA1Biochemical and molecular characterization of xyloglucan endotransglucosylase from ripe kiwifruitExpression of XET-related genes and its relation to elongation in leaves of barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L.)Transcriptional activation of a pectate lyase gene, <italic>RbPel1</italic>, during petal abscission in rosePetal abscission in rose is associated with the differential expression of two ethylene-responsive xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolase genes, RbXTH1, and RbXTH2Endotransglycosylation of xyloglucans in plant cell suspension culturesAnalysis of promoter activity of members of the PECTATE LYASE-LIKE (PLL) gene family in cell separation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>MEGA5: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methodsSignals in abscissionBean leaf abscission: tissue specific accumulation of a cellulase mRNAGene expression profiles for cell wall-modifying proteins associated with soybean cyst nematode infection, petiole abscission, root tips, flowers, apical buds, and leavesCategories of petal senescence and abscission: a re-evaluation<italic>In vivo</italic> colocalization of xyloglucan endotransglycosylase activity and its donor substrate in the elongation zone of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> rootsRoot hair initiation is coupled to highly localized increase of xyloglucan endotransglycosylase action in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> rootsExpression of ethylene biosynthetic and receptor genes in rose floral tissues during ethylene-enhanced flower openingCell wall extensibility and effect of cell wall loosening proteins during rose flower openingDelaying flower opening of cut roses by <italic>cis</italic>-propenylphosphonic acidA comprehensive expression analysis of all members of a gene family encoding cell-wall enzymes allowed us to predict <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory regions involved in cell-wall construction in specific organs of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>A surprising diversity and abundance of xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolases in rice. Classification and expression analysisThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The movement of petals during flower opening (anthesis) and their separation from the parent plant during abscission requires cell wall modification at the junction (abscission zone) of the petal and thalamus. The present study shows differential ethylene mediated temporal regulation of various members of the rose XTH gene family during flower opening and abscission in the ethylene sensitive, early abscising fragrant rose and the less sensitive late abscising hybrid rose. These studies indicate that large scale changes in xyloglucan crosslinking in cell wall mediated by XTHs may facilitate movement and separation during flower opening and abscission respectively.Flower opening is a process that requires movement of petals from a closed position to a horizontal open position, while petal abscission requires cell-wall disassembly. Both processes are controlled by ethylene and require cell-wall modification at the junction (abscission zone) of the petal and thalamus to facilitate the movement or separation of petals. In the present study, a family of xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolase (XTH) genes was studied to understand their role in petal abscission in flowers of <italic>Rosa bourboniana</italic> (ethylene sensitive, early abscising) and <italic>Rosa hybrida</italic> (less ethylene sensitive, late abscising). Transcriptome sequencing of petal abscission zone cDNA was performed at different time points (ethylene treated and untreated) and screened for XTH genes. The study identified nine new XTH genes that showed differential changes in gene expression during flower opening and abscission. Of these, <italic>RbXTH3</italic>, <italic>RbXTH5</italic>, <italic>RbXTH6</italic> and <italic>RbXTH12</italic> were rapidly induced by ethylene within 1–4 h of ethylene treatment, corresponding to the period of flower opening. These genes also showed an early up-regulation during flower opening under ethylene-untreated (field abscission) conditions, indicating a possible role in anthesis and petal movement during flower opening. Other genes such as <italic>RbXTH4</italic> and <italic>RbXTH9</italic> were up-regulated later at 8–12 h after ethylene treatment and at 24–36 h under natural abscission conditions, indicating a possible role in abscission. Treatment with a higher ethylene dose (15 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene) accelerated abscission, leading to higher steady-state levels of XTH gene transcripts at an earlier time point compared with 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene. In contrast, transcript accumulation of most of the XTHs was considerably delayed in the late-abscising rose, <italic>R. hybrida</italic>, in keeping with the slower flower opening and delayed petal abscission. The results suggest coordinated action of different XTHs in cell-wall modification of xyloglucan moieties during flower opening as well as cell separation during abscission.Abscission is a process of detachment of plant organs such as leaves, flowers, flower parts, fruits and seeds from the parent body. The process of separation is primarily under developmental and hormonal control, but is also strongly affected by the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C53">Taylor and Whitelaw 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C32">Lewis <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Ethylene plays a significant role during abscission and enhances the abscission of leaves, fruits, flowers, etc., particularly in dicotyledonous plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C57">van Doorn 2001</xref>). Since abscission involves cell separation and dissolution of the middle lamella, the primary focus has been on some of the common cell-wall-modifying proteins and wall hydrolases such as polygalacturonases, endoglucanases, expansins, pectate lyases and pectin methyl esterases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C55">Tucker <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C29">Kalaitzis <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C30">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C14">del Campillo and Bennett 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C8">Burns <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C7">Brummell <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C4">Atkinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C19">Gonzalez-Carranza <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C20">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C6">Belfield <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C45">Sane <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C27">Jiang <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C36">Mishra <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C51">Sun and van Nocker 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C48">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>). However, since the cell wall is a complex structure consisting of several types of wall polymers, additional players are also expected to be involved although there is not much information on these.In recent years, the availability of complete genome sequences has allowed gene expression to be studied on a global scale using methods such as microarray and next-generation sequencing techniques. Their utilization in understanding the abscission zone (AZ) transcriptome in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> stamens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C9">Cai and Lashbrook 2008</xref>), citrus leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C1">Agusti <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C2">2009</xref>), tomato leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C35">Meir <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and soybean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C56">Tucker <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) has helped in advancing our knowledge regarding the expression of not only cell-wall hydrolases, but also several other classes of proteins that regulate the development of the AZ and govern the progression of the process. These studies have helped in highlighting the complexity of the abscission process.Xyloglucans are a major component of primary cell walls, accounting for up to 10–20 % of the wall component of most dicotyledonous plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C16">Fry 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C22">Hayashi 1989</xref>). They cross-link adjacent cellulose microfibrils through non-covalent linkages, thus providing strength to the growing walls. Xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolases (XTHs) are enzymes that modify the length of xyloglucans during cell expansion through cleavage of cross-linking xyloglucan moieties (xyloglucan endohydrolase or XEH activity) and their rejoining to other xyloglucan moieties (xyloglucan endotransglucosylase or XET activity), thereby enabling the cell wall to expand without weakening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C50">Smith and Fry 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C17">Fry <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C39">Nishitani and Tominaga 1992</xref>). Xyloglucan endotransglucosylase/hydrolases belong to a large multigene family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C10">Campbell and Braam 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C42">Rose <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C64">Yokoyama <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>), with diverse tissue-specific functions such as hydrolysis of seed storage carbohydrate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C13">de Silva <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>), hypocotyl elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C40">Potter and Fry 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C11">Catala <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C12">2001</xref>), leaf growth and expansion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C47">Schunmann <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>), aerenchyma formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C43">Saab and Sachs 1996</xref>), fruit softening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C46">Schroder <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C24">Ishimaru and Kobayashi 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C44">Saladié <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), root hair initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C59">Vissenberg <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C58">2001</xref>) and tension wood formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C37">Nishikubo <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C38">2011</xref>).We previously identified two XTH genes that showed ethylene-inducible expression in petal AZs and demonstrated that abscission was associated with an increase in XET action in AZ cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C49">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). In this work, we have performed a transcriptomic analysis of rose petal AZ cDNA through 454 pyrosequencing and show that a large number of XTH genes are transcriptionally active in the AZ during the course of flower opening and petal abscission.Flowers of the ethylene-sensitive, abscising rose <italic>Rosa bourboniana</italic> (cv Gruss an Teplitz) and the less ethylene-sensitive <italic>Rosa hybrida</italic>, which does not undergo abscission in the field, were chosen for study. Flowers of the same developmental stage (unpollinated, ready-to-open buds) were picked just prior to sunrise, cut with a sharp blade and the stalks immediately placed in water.Ethylene treatment was performed in a closed airtight chamber as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C45">Sane <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> by injecting ethylene at a concentration of 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> for 18 h for <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> (time of abscission 16–18 h) or for ∼52 h for <italic>R. hybrida</italic> (time of abscission 48–52 h). Petal AZs (2 mm<sup>2</sup> at the base of the petal in contact with the thalamus) were collected at 0 h (ethylene untreated), 1, 4, 8 and 12 h during ethylene treatment for <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> and additionally at 24, 36 and 48 h for <italic>R. hybrida</italic>. For higher ethylene doses, 15 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene was injected and petal AZs were collected at 0 h (untreated) and 60 min after ethylene treatment (time of abscission 3–4 h). Abscission zone tissue was immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and transferred to −70 °C until further use. In field-abscising (natural abscission) <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> flowers that underwent natural pollination-induced abscission (time of abscission 38–45 h), flowers were marked at the time of opening of the outermost whorl, and petal AZs were collected at time intervals of 0, 4, 8, 12, 24 and 36 h. Abscission zones were collected and processed as above.RNA was isolated from frozen petal AZs of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> and <italic>R. hybrida</italic> as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C3">Asif <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref>. RNA was also isolated from different tissues, namely petals, sepals, thalamus, pedicels and leaves, before ethylene treatment and after 12 h, 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene treatment. cDNA was prepared using the MuMLV Revertaid reverse transcriptase (Fermentas) and used for the expression analysis of different XTHs by real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR).Sequences of primers (forward and reverse) used for real-time PCR quantification of the gene expression of various RbXTH genes.For semi-quantitative reverse transcription–polymerase chain reaction (RT–PCR), total RNA from 8-h ethylene-untreated and ethylene-treated tissues such as sepals, petals, thalamus, pedicels and leaves was isolated and treated with DNase I (Fermentas) and purified. For cDNA preparation, 5 µg of purified total RNA from each sample were reverse transcribed using 3′AP and Revertaid reverse transcriptase (Fermentas). An equal quantity (25–30 ng) of cDNA was used for PCR amplification of the target transcript. Rose <italic>β-ACTIN</italic> was used as an internal control and PCR was carried out in an Eppendorf PCR machine (Mastercycler Epgradient S, Germany).For real-time PCR, rose <italic>β-ACTIN</italic> was used as an internal control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C49">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). The real-time reaction was carried out using the SYBR Green Dye master mix (Fermentas) in triplicate (technical replicates) for each sample consisting of pooled AZs from a given time point (collected over a month) on an ABI 7500 real-time PCR machine (Applied Biosystems Inc., USA). The data analysed were the mean of triplicates. For <italic>RbXTH3</italic> and <italic>RbXTH6</italic>, where a high but transient ethylene-induced expression was observed for 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene-treated AZ cDNA, the data were repeated on a biological replicate. The general steps performed during real-time PCR experiments were as follows: step 1, 50 °C for 2 min; step 2, 95 °C for 10 min; step 3, 95 °C for 15 s and 60 °C for 1 min, ×40 cycles. The <italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic> values obtained from the internal control (actin) and experimental samples were plotted on an Excel sheet and Δ<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic> values were calculated. The Δ<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic> value was used to calculate ΔΔ<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic> and the fold change in expression was calculated by the 2<sup>−ΔΔ<italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic></sup> method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C33">Livak and Schmittgen 2001</xref>). Relative change in the mRNA expression was calculated for each gene by normalizing the <italic>C<sub>T</sub></italic> values against the internal control rose β-actin and expressed as a ratio against the averaged value of 0 h which was considered as one.Amino acid sequence alignment of the different RbXTHs identified from transcriptome sequencing of rose AZ cDNA was carried out using CLUSTAL W. The sequences of RbXTH1 and RbXTH2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C49">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>) were also included along with those of <italic>Populus</italic> XET16A (as an example of a protein showing XTH activity) and nasturtium (<italic>Tropaeolum majus</italic>) TmNXG1 (as an example of a protein showing XEH activity) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C5">Baumann <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). For the dendrogram, only complete polypeptide sequences of rose XTHs (RbXTH1 to RbXTH6 and RbXTH12) were chosen along with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> XTHs, <italic>Populus</italic> XET16A and <italic>T. majus</italic> TmNXG1. Analysis was carried out using the MEGA 5 software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C52">Tamura <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The amino acid sequences were first aligned by CLUSTAL W and then a UPGMA (Unweighted Pair Group Method with Arithmetic mean) tree was constructed by the bootstrap method.(A) CLUSTAL W alignment of the predicted amino acid sequences of different RbXTHs identified from transcriptome sequencing of rose AZ cDNA. The sequences of RbXTH1 and RbXTH2 were also included along with those of <italic>Populus</italic> XET16A and nasturtium (<italic>T. majus</italic>) TmNXG1. The conserved catalytic site DEI/LDF/IEFLG is highlighted in dark red. The <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation site (NxS/T) is shown in violet. The DYNII extension in TmNXG1, responsible for XEH activity as well as the GR residues (conserved between XTH4, XTH5, XTH9 and TmNXG1) are shown in red.(B) Phylogenetic analysis of the full-length rose XTH amino acid sequences with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> XTHs, <italic>Populus</italic> XET16A and nasturtium (<italic>T. majus</italic>) TmNXG1 sequences. Analysis was carried out using the MEGA 5 software. The amino acid sequences were aligned by CLUSTAL W and the UPGMA dendrogram was constructed by the bootstrap method.A phylogenetic analysis of the seven full-length RbXTHs (including RbXTH1 and RbXTH2) was carried out using MEGA5 with PtXTH16 and TmNXG1 and all the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> XTH sequences. As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT030F1">1</xref>B and reported previously by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C64">Yokoyama <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref>, the majority of the XTHs in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (classified as Group I and Group II) clustered together. RbXTH1 and RbXTH2 appeared in one subclade (with RbXTH1 appearing closest to PtXET16), while RbXTH3 and RbXTH6 (along with RbXTH12) appeared in separate subclades of the combined Group I/II. RbXTH4 and RbXTH5 appeared in a separate group (designated as Group III) that included TmNXG1. Some of the Group III members, such as AtXTH31 and AtXTH32 (besides TmNXG1), have been shown to function as XEHs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C28">Kaewthai <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).(A) Real-time PCR analysis of <italic>RbXTH4</italic>, <italic>RbXTH7</italic> and <italic>RbXTH9</italic> transcript accumulation in petal AZs of 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene-treated flowers of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> and <italic>R. hybrida</italic> and in flowers of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> undergoing natural abscission (NAZ). Total RNA from petal AZs was isolated from the 0-h, ethylene-untreated sample (control) as well as from samples treated with ethylene. Reactions were run in triplicate from a pool of AZ RNA samples harvested from at least 50 flowers. The averaged value of the 0-h (ethylene untreated, control) AZ sample was considered as 1 and the averaged values of the other samples were calculated against the 0-h sample. Rose <italic>β-ACTIN</italic> was used as an internal control for normalization. (B) Real-time PCR analysis of <italic>RbXTH3</italic> and <italic>RbXTH6</italic> transcript accumulation in petal AZs of 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene-treated flowers of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> and <italic>R. hybrida</italic> and in the flowers of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> undergoing natural abscission. Analysis was carried out as described in (A). (C) Real-time PCR analysis of <italic>RbXTH5</italic> and <italic>RbXTH12</italic> transcript accumulation in petal AZs of 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene-treated flowers of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> and <italic>R. hybrida</italic> and in the flowers of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> undergoing natural abscission. Analysis was carried out as described in (A).In contrast to the relatively late accumulation of the above-mentioned genes, <italic>RbXTH3</italic> and <italic>RbXTH6</italic> showed a rapid and very high but transient transcript accumulation in ethylene-treated <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> petal AZs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT030F2">2</xref>B). The relative transcript levels of <italic>RbXTH3</italic> and <italic>RbXTH6</italic> increased by ∼100- and 75-fold, respectively, within 4 h of ethylene treatment as against the 0-h sample. After this, the transcript levels declined rapidly at 8 h/12 h, although they still showed a 20-fold increase in <italic>RbXTH6</italic> compared with the 0-h sample. Unlike in <italic>R. bourboniana</italic>, petal abscission in <italic>R. hybrida</italic> was not associated with any change in the transcript levels of <italic>RbXTH3</italic> but with only a small change in <italic>RbXTH6</italic> (which occurred at the 24-h stage). Interestingly, under field conditions, <italic>RbXTH3</italic> showed a gradual increase during abscission up to 36 h, while <italic>RbXTH6</italic> showed a substantial increase as early as 4 h onwards right up to 24 h with only a slight decrease at 36 h.The third set of genes shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT030F2">2</xref>C included <italic>RbXTH5</italic> and <italic>RbXTH12</italic>, which were also rapidly up-regulated within 1–4 h of ethylene treatment (although not to the extent of <italic>RbXTH3</italic> and <italic>RbXTH6</italic>) before showing a decline. In <italic>R. hybrida</italic>, only a marginal increase in the transcript level of <italic>RbXTH12</italic> was observed at 36–48 h. No significant change was observed in <italic>RbXTH5</italic>. Interestingly, both genes showed a rapid and substantial increase in transcript accumulation during the entire course of natural petal abscission right from the 4-h time point onwards, with peak values at 36 h.Two genes, <italic>RbXTH8</italic> and <italic>RbXTH10</italic>, could not be studied due to difficulties in amplification.Real-time PCR analysis of <italic>RbXTH</italic> gene transcript accumulation in petal AZs of 1-h high-dose (15 µL L<sup>−1</sup>) ethylene-treated flowers of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> compared against the ethylene-untreated control AZ sample (0 h). The expression of each gene was measured at 0 h and at the 1-h high-dose ethylene time point. The relative expression at 0 h for each gene was considered as 1 (and is depicted as ‘0-h’ expression) and the relative expression of the gene of interest at the 1-h time point was calculated accordingly as described in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT030F2">2</xref>A.Comparative transcript accumulation of different <italic>RbXTH</italic> genes in ethylene-untreated and ethylene-treated tissues of <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> as determined by semi-quantitative RT–PCR. Cut rose flowers were treated with or without 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene for 8 h. <italic>β-ACTIN</italic> was used as an internal control.Xyloglucans are an important component of dicotyledonous cell walls, accounting for up to 20 % of the cell wall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C16">Fry 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C22">Hayashi 1989</xref>). Thus, it is not surprising that plant genomes contain a large number of XTH genes with up to 33 genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C63">Yokoyama and Nishitani 2001</xref>), 29 in rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C64">Yokoyama <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) and 41 in <italic>Populus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C18">Geisler-Lee <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Although these genes have been shown to have diverse expression patterns during plant development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C64">Yokoyama <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>), their involvement in organ abscission has only recently been observed through large-scale gene expression studies in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C31">Lashbrook and Cai 2008</xref>), citrus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C2">Agusti <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and tomato (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C35">Meir <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Our studies have led to the identification and characterization of nine hitherto unknown XTH genes in abscission through 454 pyrosequencing in addition to the two (<italic>RbXTH1</italic> and <italic>RbXTH2</italic>) previously identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C49">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). This is a considerably larger number than reported previously in AZs in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, citrus or tomato, indicating that abscission in rose petals may proceed through large-scale modifications in xyloglucan cross-linking. Some of these genes, such as <italic>RbXTH3</italic>, <italic>RbXTH5</italic>, <italic>RbXTH6</italic> and <italic>RbXTH12</italic>, are rapidly up-regulated within 1–4 h of ethylene treatment in <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> and, except for <italic>RbXTH3</italic>, remain quite high until 8 h. Under our conditions, this early period from 0 to 4 h corresponds to anthesis when flowers open and petals unfurl. Ethylene has been shown to facilitate flower opening in roses and other flowers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C41">Reid <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C62">Yamamoto <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C34">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C60">Xue <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), and this opening can be partly blocked by 1-methyl cyclopropene. Flower opening is associated with petal expansion and expression of several expansins and XTHs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C15">Evans and Reid 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C61">Yamada <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C21">Harada <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). In addition to cell-wall expansion of petals, movement of the petals from a vertically upright position (at the 0 stage buds) to a horizontal position (4 h open stage) would have to involve changes in the cell wall at the point of attachment of the petals to the thalamus, i.e. at the AZ, so as to allow the petals to change position and unfurl. In this respect, it is interesting to note that the ethylene-induced AZ-related expression of <italic>RbXTH3</italic>, <italic>RbXTH5</italic>, <italic>RbXTH6</italic> and <italic>RbXTH12</italic> appears much higher than their expression in the adjacent ethylene-sensitive tissues such as the thalamus and petals. It is likely that the ethylene-mediated up-regulation of these four genes might facilitate rapid changes in the cross-linking xyloglucan moieties in the AZ, leading to a greater flexibility of the cell wall, which in turn might allow the petals to move from an upright position to an open horizontal position. Thus, these are more likely to represent genes that are required for flower opening rather than abscission. Indeed, the high expression level of most of these genes earlier during the course of natural abscission (where abscission is delayed) also suggests a role in flower opening rather than abscission. Of these, <italic>RbXTH6</italic> is expressed predominantly in petal AZs with very little expression in other tissues, suggesting a specific role in flower opening. Most of these genes show very little expression in non-reproductive tissues such as leaves and pedicels. Other genes such as <italic>RbXTH4</italic> and <italic>RbXTH9</italic> appear later, from 8 to 12 h in ethylene-treated flowers and much later during natural abscission, similar to what has been observed previously for <italic>RbXTH1</italic> and <italic>RbXTH2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C49">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). Since they are up-regulated just prior to abscission, these are more likely to represent genes that are activated in response to abscission cues. Such temporal differences in transcription have also been observed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> stamen abscission for XTHs as well as other wall hydrolase genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C31">Lashbrook and Cai 2008</xref>). Treatment with 15 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene accelerates abscission to just 3 h with abscission occurring without complete petal opening. This is associated with a much earlier (and higher) transcript accumulation of most XTH genes than when treated with 0.5 µL L<sup>−1</sup> ethylene, suggesting a strong correlation between ethylene, XTH gene activation and cell separation in the AZ.Interestingly, the same dose of ethylene that activates the XTH genes within 1–8 h in <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> leads to activation of only some of these genes in <italic>R. hybrida</italic> and that too after a delay of ∼16–24 h (or more). The inability of these genes to get activated rapidly even when the flowers are exposed to exogenous ethylene indicates that some components of ethylene perception or signalling may be affected in <italic>R. hybrida</italic>, leading to a slower and delayed response in these plants. Although one cannot rule out a change in promoter sequences of these genes between <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> and <italic>R. hybrida</italic>, it seems rather unlikely that promoters of all XTH genes in <italic>R. hybrida</italic> would have undergone a change that makes them relatively insensitive to ethylene.Of all the genes studied, <italic>RbXTH7</italic> shows a different expression pattern in that it is actually down-regulated by ethylene in <italic>R. bourboniana</italic> and <italic>R. hybrida</italic> but up-regulated from the 4-h time point under conditions of natural abscission. The expression pattern appears to indicate an ethylene-induced repression of <italic>RbXTH7</italic>. This does not explain the high expression levels under natural conditions but it does suggest that regulatory controls under natural field conditions (where the flowers are still attached to the parent body) and under excised ethylene-induced conditions may be different, leading to a change in expression patterns.We have previously shown that transcription of the XTH genes is associated with an increase in XET activity as determined by <italic>in situ</italic> co-localization of fluorescent sulforhodamine-conjugated xyloglucan oligosaccharides in the AZ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C49">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). Our studies had revealed a strong fluorescence in the 8-h ethylene-treated petal AZs and the 24-h natural AZ samples. The present study shows that this increase in XET activity is likely to be a consequence of not just RbXTH1 and RbXTH2 functions but also from the cumulative action of most of the XTHs identified from these two studies. However, while transglucosylase action had clearly been demonstrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT030C49">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> (2011<italic>b</italic>)</xref>, the presence of xyloglucan endohydrolase action is still unclear. Three of the proteins, viz. RbXTH4, RbXTH5 and RbXTH9, do show some domain similarity to TmNXG1 and are clustered in the same group, and might well function to aid abscission via hydrolysis of the xyloglucan moieties. However, these would require further enzymatic studies using expressed proteins of RbXTH4, RbXTH5 and RbXTH9.This study shows that petal abscission in rose is associated with transcriptional up-regulation of a large repertoire of XTH genes that most likely aids both movement during flower opening as well as petal abscission through complex tissue-specific ethylene-responsive expression of the genes.RbXTH3-JX259257RbXTH4-JX259258RbXTH5-JX259259RbXTH6-JX259260RbXTH7-JX259261RbXTH8-JX259262RbXTH9-JX259263RbXTH10-JX259264RbXTH12-JX259265This work was supported by funds from the Department of Biotechnology, Government of India, New Delhi, from a network project (BSC0107) from the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), India and by CSIR Senior Research Fellowships to A.P.S. and S.P.P.A.P.S. carried out the transcriptome work and A.P.S., S.D. and S.P.P. performed the RT–PCR analysis. K.K. performed the phylogenetic analysis, while D.L. carried out the assembly and bioinformatic analysis of the transcriptome for identification for XTHs. U.N.D., P.N. and A.P.S. discussed the results. A.P.S. planned the work and wrote the paper.None declared.We thank Mr Ram Awadh for taking care of the plants.