Genetic diversity of an Azorean endemic and endangered plant species inferred from inter-simple sequence repeat markersOffspring spatial patterns in <italic>Picconia excelsa</italic> (Oleaceae) in the Canarian laurel forestGenetic diversity and structure of the narrow endemic <italic>Wyethia reticulate</italic> and its congener <italic>W. bolanderi</italic> (Asteraceae) using RAPD and allozyme techniquesGenetic diversity among spatially isolated populations of <italic>Euryanitida</italic> Korth (Theaceae) based on inter-simple sequence repeatsNonanchored inter simple sequence repeat (ISSR) markers: reproducible and specific tools for genome fingerprintingHigh informative nature of inter simple sequence repeat (ISSR) sequences amplified with tri- and tetra-nucleotide primers from cauliflower (<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var<italic>. botrytis</italic> L.) DNAISSR as new markers for genetic characterization and evaluation of relationships among phytoplanktonMeasuring genetic variability in plant populationsArbitrarily amplified DNA markers as characters for phylogenetic inferenceWood anatomy and technological properties of an endangered species: <italic>Picconia azorica</italic> (Oleaceae)A perspectiva arquipelágica; AçoresDeveloping a sampling strategy for <italic>Baptisia arachnifera</italic> based on allozyme diversityRAPD profiling in detecting genetic variation in endemic <italic>Coelonema</italic> (Brassicaceae) of Quinghai–Tibet plateau of ChinaHigh population differentiation and genetic variation in the endangered Mexican pine, <italic>Pinus rzedowskii</italic> (Pinaceae)Espécies florestais das ilhas - AçoresPopulation genetic consequences of small population size: implications for plant conservationConservation of noble hardwoods in EuropeDetecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation studyAnalysis of molecular variance inferred from metric distances among DNA haplotypes: application to human mitochondrial DNA restriction sitesRandom amplified polymorphic DNA analysis of olive (<italic>Olea europaea</italic> L.) cultivarsA programme for the management of forest tree genetic resources in the Azores islandsPhyleogeography and perspectives of an endangered Macaronesian endemic: <italic>Picconia azorica</italic> (Tutin) Knobl. (Oleaceae)Plant genetic diversity in the Canaries: a conservation perspectiveGenetics and conservation biologyGenetic diversity and differentiation processes in the ploidy series of <italic>Olea europaea</italic> L.: a multiscale approach from subspecies to insular populationsMolecular markers reveal no genetic differentiation <italic>Myrica rivas-martinezz</italic>i and <italic>M. faya</italic> (Myricaceae)The use of ISSR and RAPD markers for genetic diversity among South Tunisian BarleyAllozyme diversity in plant speciesFactor influencing levels of genetic diversity in woody plant speciesRAPD variation within and among natural populations of outcrossing buffalograss <italic>Buchloe dactyloides</italic> (Nutt) EngelmCLUMPP: a cluster matching and permutation program for dealing with label switching and multimodality in analysis of population structureHas the debate over genetics and extinction of island endemics truly been resolved?Colonization and diversification: towards a phylogeographic synthesis for the Canary IslandsLack of allozyme and ISSR variation in the rare endemic tree species, <italic>Berchemiaberchemiaefolia</italic> (Rhammnaceae) in KoreaGenetic variation and clonal diversity of <italic>Psammochloa villosa</italic> (Poaceae) detected by ISSR markersGenetic diversity within and among <italic>Pinus pinaster</italic> populations: comparison between AFLP and microsatellite markersA perspectiva macaronésicaVegetative propagation of the endangered Azorean tree, <italic>Picconia azorica</italic>Population genetics and conservation of the Azorean tree <italic>Picconia azorica</italic>‘How local is local?’—A review of practical and conceptual issues in the genetics of restorationConservation of genetic diversity in the endangered plant <italic>Eriogonum ovalifolium</italic> var<italic>. vineum</italic> (Polygonaceae)Genetic distance between populationsAnalysis of gene diversity in subdivided populationsEstimation of average heterozygosity and genetic distance from a small number of individualsMolecular phylogeography, intraspecific variation and the conservation of tree speciesComparison of different nuclear DNA markers for estimating intraspecific genetic diversity in plantsEffects of life history traits and sampling strategies on genetic diversity estimates obtained with RAPD markers in plantsQuantitative methods to improve the understanding and utilisation of animal genetic resourcesAnalysis of population genetic structure and variability using RAPD markers in the endemic and endangered <italic>Limonium dufourii</italic> (Plumbaginaceae)GenAlEX 6.5: genetic analysis in Excel. Population genetic software for teaching and research—an updateThe comparison of RFLP, RAPD, AFLP and SSR (microsatellite) markers for germplasm analysisInference of population structure using multilocus genotype dataDISTRUCT: a program for the graphical display of population structureConservation genetics and clonality in two critically endangered eucalypts from the highly endemic south-western Australian floraChorology and diversity of the Azorean floraEndemic vascular plants of the Azores: an updated listOn the verge of extinction: genetics of the critically endangered Iberian plant species, <italic>Bordereachouardii</italic> (Discoreaceae) and implications for conservation managementList of vascular plants (Tracheobionta)Genetic variability and differentiation among populations of the Azorean endemic gymnosperm <italic>Juniperus brevifolia</italic>: baseline information for a conservation and restoration perspectiveA comparison of three indirect methods for estimating average levels of gene flowGenetic structure of an endangered plant, <italic>Antirrinum microphyllum</italic> (Scrophulariaceae): alloenzyme and RAPD analysisAre Macaronesian islands refugia of relict plant lineages? A molecular surveyThe genetical structure of populationsGenome fingerprinting by simple sequence repeat (SSR) anchored polymerase chain reaction amplification<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Kermit RitlandThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<italic>Picconia azorica</italic> is an endangered endemic species of the Azores whose hard and high density wood is very appreciated for the production of toys, agricultural tools, furniture and religious statuary. Its renewed economic interest represents a good opportunity for establishing conservation programmes. To contribute with information useful for the decision making we performed the genetic analysis of 230 samples from 11 populations collected in three Azorean islands. The majority of the genetic variability was found within populations and no genetic structure was detected between populations and between islands, indicating that the oceanic barriers do not greatly affect gene flow.Knowledge of the levels and distribution of genetic diversity is important for designing conservation strategies for threatened and endangered species so as to guarantee sustainable survival of populations and to preserve their evolutionary potential. <italic>Picconia azorica</italic> is a valuable Azorean endemic species recently classified as endangered. To contribute with information useful for the establishment of conservation programmes, the genetic variability and differentiation among 230 samples from 11 populations collected in three Azorean islands was accessed with eight inter-simple sequence repeat markers. A total of 64 polymorphic loci were detected. The majority of genetic variability was found within populations and no genetic structure was detected between populations and between islands. Also the coefficient of genetic differentiation and the level of gene flow indicate that geographical distances do not act as barriers for gene flow. In order to ensure the survival of populations <italic>in situ</italic> and <italic>ex situ</italic> management practices should be considered, including artificial propagation through the use of plant tissue culture techniques, not only for the restoration of habitat but also for the sustainable use of its valuable wood.Knowledge of genetic variability, together with information about demography, reproductive biology and dynamics, is very important when establishing any conservation and management programme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C52">Newton <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C26">Francisco-Ortega <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C39">Juan <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C27">Frankham 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C38">Jamieson 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C68">Silva <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) that aims to preserve genetic variability within and among populations and consequently safeguard their potential for adaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C18">Eriksson 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C68">Silva <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Information about genetic diversity patterns may also give insight into the evolutionary history of a taxon, providing the means to assess the future risk of diversity erosion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C48">Neel and Ellstrand 2003</xref>).The development of molecular genetic methods has been a significant advance providing tools for answering questions on the diversity among flora and fauna and to help define strategies for conservation purposes. Inter-simple sequence repeat (ISSR) markers offer the possibility of randomly scanning the whole genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C42">Mariette <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>) as no sequence information or prior genetic studies are required (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C75">Zietkiewicz <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>), and have proved to be valuable, efficient and cost-effective tools in the characterization and evaluation of genetic diversity within and between species and populations of several endemic and endangered plant species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C56">Palacios and González-Candelas 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C15">Delgado <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C62">Rossetto <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C41">Li and Ge 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C40">Lee <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C71">Torres <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C3">Bahulikar <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C13">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C65">Segarra-Moragues <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C32">Guasmi <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Inter-simple sequence repeats are DNA sequences delimited by two inverted SSR and are especially useful in detecting diversity in closely related, or even clonal, individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C75">Zietkiewicz <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>). The use of just a single PCR primer to amplify ISSR sequences between simple sequence repeat (SSR) provides multilocus patterns that are very reproducible, abundant and polymorphic in plant genomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C75">Zietkiewicz <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C5">Bornet and Branchard 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C6">Bornet <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C7">2004</xref>), making this technology a good reliable molecular tool to determine the genetic diversity of Azorean endemic and endangered species.The archipelago of the Azores is located in the North Atlantic Ocean between latitudes 36°55′N and 39°43′N, and longitudes 24°46′W and 31°16′W. It is composed of nine volcanic islands divided into three groups: the eastern (São Miguel and Santa Maria), the central (Terceira, Graciosa, São Jorge, Pico and Faial) and the western group (Flores and Corvo). From the about 200 species native to the Azorean flora only 70 have been described as endemic for the Azores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C63">Schaefer 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C64">2005</xref>), representing 7.2 % of the Azorean flora (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C4">Borges <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). The abusive use of Azorean forests for over five centuries, the expansion of pasture and agricultural fields and the introduction of exotic/imported species led to a substantial reduction of the natural native forest populations. Only recently there has been an increased interest in the endemic forest species for reforestation, particularly of rare species and species with a high wood quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C24">Ferreira and Eriksson 2006</xref>).<italic>Picconia azorica</italic> (Oleaceae Family), locally named <italic>pau-branco</italic>, is a xerophytic, evergreen shrub or a small tree, endemic to the Azores archipelago. This species grows up to 8 m tall and has simple, lanceolate to ovate, opposite leaves with entire margins; it flowers from March to July, producing small white flowers in axillary clusters and its fleshy fruits are dark blue drupes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C44">Martins <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Although <italic>P. azorica</italic> has been present in all nine Azorean islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C29">Frutuoso 1583</xref>), currently is scattered in small patches of coastal forests and marginal sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C63">Schaefer 2003</xref>). Clearly, the over-exploitation of its appreciated wood for manufacturing toys, agricultural tools, furniture and religious statuary, as well as human disturbance that promoted habitat degradation, expansion of agricultural land, deforestation and introduction of aggressive exotic species led this species to becoming almost extinct in some islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C43">Martín <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). In fact, it is extinct in Graciosa island and near to extinction in São Miguel and Terceira islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C11">Cardoso <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C67">Silva <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C25">Ferreira <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), thus being a priority Azorean endemic species for conservation, listed as endangered (EN B1 + 2c) on the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C36">IUCN Red List (2013)</xref> and protected according to the Directive Habitats (Annexes II and IV) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C19">European Commission 1992</xref>) and the Bern Convention (Annex I) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C14">Council of Europe 1993</xref>). <italic>Picconia azorica</italic> is one of the two residual species of the <italic>Picconia</italic> genera which became extinct in continental land. However the Azores, together with Madeira and the Canary islands, are considered refuge areas for this genus. Therefore, <italic>P. azorica</italic> due to its fragile status demands urgent specific management and conservation measures for restoration of depleted natural populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C43">Martín <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Ecological restoration plans to prevent the erosion of <italic>P. azorica</italic> genetic resources are necessary, primarily because of its endangered status, for its biological and economical relevance and for its major ecological importance. Unfortunately, there are limited numbers of studies on the Azorean endemic forests and no detailed characterization about the biology and management of <italic>P. azorica</italic> has been made so far (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C25">Ferreira <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). For the genetic characterization of <italic>P. azorica,</italic> chloroplast markers were used under phylogenetic and phylogeographical perspectives, due to their uniparental inheritance, revealing absence of geographical structure and limited intra-specific genetic diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C25">Ferreira <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), suggesting the need for a sound assessment of the species genetic structure at the nuclear level. Only recently a limited number of SSRs were isolated from <italic>P. azorica</italic> and used for the characterization of different populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C45">Martins <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), showing high levels of intra-population diversity and low genetic differentiation between populations. Simple sequence repeats are codominant markers that reveal a high number of alleles, still the variation detected is pre-determined at the sequence sites and the number of analysed loci in diversity studies is usually low (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C42">Mariette <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). In our study we access the genetic variability and differentiation, as well as phylogeographical patterns within different populations of São Miguel, Terceira and Pico islands of such an endangered endemic Azorean species, by using ISSR markers, as conservation should be based on genetic diversity at the whole-genome level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C42">Mariette <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). These islands were selected as they are the most populated ones and therefore more susceptible to human habitat disturbance and also because Pico is the island with more area forested with <italic>P. azorica</italic> and since the earliest colonization of the archipelago an exporter of this valuable wood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C29">Frutuoso 1583</xref>).Populations of <italic>P. azorica</italic> from S. Miguel, Pico and Terceira islands used in this study. <italic>N</italic>, number of individuals sampled. For population locations, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu034/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">see <bold>Supporting Information</bold></ext-link>.DNA was extracted by downscaling the protocol described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C22">Fabbri <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref> using 100 mg of leaves, so that extraction could be performed with 800 μL of CTAB extraction buffer in 2 mL microtubes.Primers used for ISSR amplification of <italic>P. azorica</italic>.<sup>a</sup> Melting temperature.Polymerase chain reactions were carried out in a total volume of 25 μL containing 20 ng DNA, 0.2 μM of primer, 0.2 mM of each dNTPs and 1 U of DreamTaq DNA polymerase (Fermentas) in reaction buffer. Amplification was performed in a UNO II Biometra thermocycler with 5 min denaturation at 94 °C, followed by 35 cycles of 30 s denaturation at 96 °C, 45 s annealing at the appropriate melting temperature (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU034TB2">2</xref>), 1 min 30 s elongation at 72 °C and a final 20 min elongation step at 72 °C. Amplification products were separated for 3 h at 120 V on a 2 % TAE agarose gel stained with SybrGreen Premium (NZYTech) along with GeneRuler 1 kb Plus DNA ladder (Fermentas) for estimation of the molecular size of the amplified fragments. Gels were recorded under ultraviolet light with a GelDoc XR+ system and analysed with the Image Lab 3.0 software (BioRad). To confirm that fragments were being consistently amplified, one sample was replicated across all runs. Furthermore, to minimize the effects of electrophoresis and staining on band variability two replicate experiments were carried out for each ISSR primer–sample combination. In every case the banding patterns on the first and second amplification/gels were identical. To ensure that neither self-amplification nor contamination was occurring, negative controls were also prepared.Amplified bands of size ranging from 0.4 to 2 kb were scored manually as present (1) or absent (0) and compiled into a data matrix. As we were studying an Azorean endemic species monomorphic loci were considered for the analysis of genetic parameters as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C2">Ayres and Ryan (1999)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C17">Ellstrand and Elam (1993)</xref>.Genetic diversity was measured at individual, population and island levels. At the individual level, a cladogram of all the 233 samples based on the similarity analysis of fingerprint patterns was drawn using the unweighted pair group method arithmetic average (UPGMA) algorithm using Dice's coefficient as implemented in NTSYSpc (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C60">Rohlf 1992</xref>) and was plotted into a dendrogram.To learn about the genetic diversity among populations and among islands, we calculated Nei's coefficient (<italic>h</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C49">Nei 1972</xref>), Shannon's information index (<italic>I</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C66">Shannon and Weaver 1949</xref>), unbiased Nei's genetic distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C51">Nei 1978</xref>), coefficient of genetic differentiation between populations (<italic>G</italic><sub>ST</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C50">Nei 1973</xref>) and gene flow (<italic>N<sub>m</sub></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C69">Slatkin and Barton 1989</xref>) in the software POPGENE 1.31 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C74">Yeh <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>) with 1000 permutations. Different analysis indexes were used to enhance the significance of the results. The estimates of genetic diversity obtained by Shannon's index (<italic>I</italic>) and Nei's gene diversity (<italic>h</italic>) were compared by Pearson's rank coefficient correlation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C70">Sokal and Rohlf 1995</xref>) using IBM SPSS statistics 20 software and to compare analysis between marker systems, as these should not be based on the comparison of levels of diversity within populations, but on the comparison of the ranking of different populations by correlation analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C42">Mariette <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>).The number of different alleles (<italic>N</italic><sub>a</sub>) and the number of effective alleles (<italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C8">Brown and Weir 1983</xref>) were also computed with POPGENE 1.31 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C74">Yeh <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>) to allow comparison of populations with different sample sizes and where the number and distribution of alleles differ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C55">Ojango <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).To learn about the partitioning of genetic variabilty among islands, among populations and among individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C21">Excoffier <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C35">Huff <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>), an analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) was performed with GenAlEx 6.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C57">Peakall and Smouse 2012</xref>) by resampling 999 times.Genetic differentiation among populations (<italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub>) based on the Euclidean distances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C35">Huff <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>) and among individuals was calculated with GenAlEx 6.5. The former were plotted in a tree using the UPGMA method from the NEIGHBOR module from Phylip 3.695 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C23">Felsenstein 2005</xref>) and the latter were used to carry out a principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) in GenAlEx 6.5. The Mantel test computed with GenAlEx 6.5 with 999 replications was used to evaluate correlations between the pairwise Euclidean genetic distance of individuals and their geographical distance, and between pairwise genetic differentiation (<italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub>) and geographical distances of each population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C35">Huff <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>). This software was also used to estimate the number of migrants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C28">Frankham <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>).To investigate the genetic structure and the degree of admixture between each sample and between the 11 Azorean populations, the Bayesian clustering procedure of STRUCTURE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C59">Pritchard <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>) was used by running an admixture model with correlated frequencies between populations. A 10 000 initial burn-in was used, followed by 10 000 MCMC iterations as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C20">Evanno <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> with 10 independent replicates each. The tested number of clusters varied from 1 to 14 (the number of populations plus three). The most likely number of clusters (<italic>K</italic>) was estimated by using the maximum value of <italic>L</italic>(<italic>K</italic>) and by calculating Δ<italic>K</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C20">Evanno <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). A mean of the 10 permuted matrices was estimated using CLUMPP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C37">Jakobsson and Rosenberg 2007</xref>) and the <italic>LargeKGreedy</italic> algorithm. The output of the cluster analysis was visualized with DISTRUCT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C61">Rosenberg 2004</xref>).The number of populations of <italic>P. azorica</italic> (<italic>n</italic>) which are necessary to represent 99.99 % of the total genetic diversity among populations (<italic>P</italic>) was calculated according to the modified equation of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C12">Ceska <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref>: <italic>P</italic> = 1−(<italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub>)<italic><sup>n</sup></italic>.Genetic diversity within 11 populations of <italic>P. azorica. N</italic>, sample size; <italic>n</italic>, number of polymorphic loci; <italic>P%</italic>, percentage of polymorphic loci; <italic>N</italic><sub>a</sub>, number of different alleles; <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>, number of effective alleles; <italic>I</italic>, Shannon's information index; <italic>h</italic>, Nei's gene diversity; SD, standard deviation.Relationship of 230 <italic>P. azorica</italic> genotypes from three islands in the Azores: São Miguel (green), Pico (black) and Terceira (pink); and three <italic>P. excelsa</italic> samples from Madeira island (orange). UPGMA tree based on Dice's coefficient.Analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) for 11 populations of <italic>P. azorica</italic> distributed across three Azorean islands.Genetic differentiation and unbiased Nei's genetic distance among populations of <italic>P. azorica</italic>. Genetic differentiation (<italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub>) is listed below the diagonal and unbiased Nei's genetic distance is listed above the diagonal.Among all populations, genetic distance values &lt;0.04 were detected for all population pairs, except for population pairs LG–SA, LG–ASR, RQ–SA and RQ–ASR (0.047, 0.045, 0.050, 0.043, respectively) and for populations CL from São Miguel and PB from Terceira. While population CL showed genetic distances &gt;0.058 for all pairwise comparisons with populations from Pico and Terceira, population PB showed values &gt;0.044 for all pairwise comparisons with populations from São Miguel and Pico.UPGMA radial tree showing the genetic relationships based on pairwise <italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> values among 11 populations of <italic>P. azorica</italic>, occurring in three islands from the Azores.Two-dimensional representation of the first two axes of the principal component analysis from the matrix of genetic distances of 230 samples from 11 populations. Percentage of variance accumulates on the first two axes = 44.46 % (Axis 1 = 23.82 %; Axis 2 = 20.34 %). For population names see <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU034TB1">Table 1</xref>.The coefficient of genetic differentiation between populations (<italic>G</italic><sub>ST</sub>) was 0.0940 and the level of gene flow (<italic>N<sub>m</sub></italic>) calculated based on <italic>G</italic><sub>ST</sub> was estimated to be 4.818, suggesting a high gene flow between <italic>P. azorica</italic> populations and islands. The number of migrants calculated as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C28">Frankham <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> showed higher values among populations from Pico than among populations from the other two islands. The lowest value obtained among populations from Pico (3.438) was higher than the highest value obtained in the remaining islands (2.859). The estimated number of migrants between São Miguel and Terceira was 1.656, between São Miguel and Pico was 1.705 and between Pico and Terceira was 1.874.Insignificant correlation between the genetic distance of individuals and geographical distances (<italic>r<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.047, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001) was shown by the Mantel test. For pairwise <italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> and geographical distances a slightly positive correlation was obtained (<italic>r<sup>2</sup></italic> = 0.242, <italic>P</italic> = 0.005).The Bayesian analysis carried out in STRUCTURE for all populations demonstrated that there were no predominant genetic clusters. Average mean values of ln <italic>P</italic>(<italic>K</italic>) did not show any substantial increases when <italic>K</italic> varied from 1 to 14 <bold>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu034/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">see Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold>. Similar results were obtained when the analysis was performed separately for each island.According to the genetic differentiation <italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> value (0.17), the conservation of six populations is the minimum necessary in order to preserve 99.99 % of the total diversity of the 11 analysed populations.Inter-simple sequence repeat markers have been used in population genetic studies of plant species as they effectively detect very low levels of genetic variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C75">Zietkiewicz <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>). They are also potentially useful for analysing biogeographical patterns among populations within species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C9">Bussell <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). With these purposes eight ISSR markers were successfully used to study the Azorean endemic plant species <italic>P. azorica,</italic> using 230 samples collected on populations across the Azorean islands of São Miguel, Terceira and Pico so as to provide knowledge of the levels and distribution of genetic diversity within these islands to help in designing conservation strategies for this endemic species.The number of scored bands and the percentage of polymorphic loci obtained in this study can be considered enough for estimating genetic diversity within populations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C53">Nybom (2004)</xref> who conducted an analysis on a compilation of different DNA markers for estimating intraspecific genetic diversity in plants calculated an average of 54.9 polymorphic markers per study. The values of genetic diversity for all populations obtained by Shannon's index (<italic>I</italic>) and Nei's gene diversity (<italic>h</italic>) were higher for the former but highly correlated (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.010; <italic>P</italic> = 0.988). The estimated total diversity of <italic>I</italic> = 0.2465, <italic>h</italic> = 0.1503 was not expected as endemic and narrowly distributed plants usually show lower levels of genetic diversity and higher levels of genetic structure compared with their relatives with wider distribution areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C33">Hamrick and Godt 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C53">Nybom 2004</xref>). The fact that the species is wind pollinated and zoochory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C1">Arteaga <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C16">Dias <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) together with its long life cycle may explain the detected level of diversity. Long-lived species generally have a higher potential for long-range gene movement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C54">Nybom and Bartish 2000</xref>). Similar results were obtained for this species when other populations were characterized with SSR molecular markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C45">Martins <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), which showed a total genetic diversity (<italic>H</italic><sub>T</sub>) of 0.7. It is not surprising that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C45">Martins <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> obtained such a high level of total genetic diversity, as one of the SSR markers used detected a total of 31 alleles in 443 samples, indicating the presence of alleles at very low frequencies. Also other species from the <italic>Oleae</italic> complex, <italic>Olea europaea</italic> ssp. <italic>cerasiformis</italic> and <italic>O. europaea</italic> ssp. <italic>Guanchica</italic> living in insular habitats, in Madeira and the Canary Islands, respectively, also showed relatively high levels of total genetic diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C30">García-Verdugo <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Nevertheless, care should be taken when comparing data between studies as genetic diversity depends on numerous factors, namely life history, breeding system, growth life forms, geographical range and type of molecular method used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C58">Powell <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C53">Nybom 2004</xref>). For example, the molecular markers used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C25">Ferreira <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> are usually applied to identify genetic variances among different taxon and therefore limited intra-specific genetic diversity, and the absence of genetic structure was detected. Also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C45">Martins <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> analysed a wider geographical range by studying populations from eight islands and the number of samples per populations varied considerably. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C53">Nybom (2004)</xref>, the number of plants per population has a positive effect on gene diversity values, probably because larger sample sizes may increase data quality.The total genetic diversity was similar across islands, being slightly higher for Terceira, which also showed the higher genetic differentiation among populations due to the uneven distribution of alleles. Among all populations, the detected genetic diversity is evenly distributed with values higher for CM (<italic>I</italic> = 0.207, <italic>h</italic> = 0.134) from Pico, and lower for CL (<italic>I</italic> = 0.113, <italic>h</italic> = 0.080) and TR (<italic>I</italic> = 0.146, <italic>h</italic> = 0.096) from São Miguel. Population CM is one of the largest in terms of individuals and area of distribution; population CL is a very small isolated population highly disturbed by human activities; and TR is composed of a few dispersed individuals in a preserved natural forest of high altitude the conditions of which are considered to be out of the optimum range for the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C63">Schaefer 2003</xref>). When using the Pearson correlation analysis, we did find correlation (<italic>P</italic> = 0.05) between population size (log transformed) and genetic diversity when all populations were analysed, but when the smallest population (CL) was removed from the analysis correlations were not detected. Therefore, the diversity index from this population can be influenced by its reduced size (<italic>N</italic> = 4). The same analysis performed between islands and considering all populations did not find any correlation between population size and genetic diversity. Therefore, we have no indication that habitat fragmentation resulted in a pronounced loss of genetic diversity within <italic>P. azorica</italic> populations. If populations are small and isolated from one another with increased habitat fragmentation, the genetic flow could be capable of influencing the genetic structure and decreasing differentiation among populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C17">Ellstrand and Elam 1993</xref>). Our gene diversity data are strongly correlated (<italic>P</italic> = 0.023; <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.859) with the data obtained with SSR markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C45">Martins <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) for five of the common populations analysed. Population Santo Amaro (<italic>n</italic> = 24) from our study which corresponds to population Praínha (<italic>n</italic> = 2) from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C45">Martins <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> was not included in this analysis due to the discrepant number of samples analysed. The reasons for the highest diversity observed in PB population from Terceira, although occurring at high altitude, could be due to the difficulty in access and therefore less or no human disturbances. These factors have been described as the most suitable for successful long-distance dispersal in Macaronesia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C72">Vargas 2007</xref>), and could have minimized human disturbances. Also the phenogram based on Dice's coefficient showed a high genetic similarity among all <italic>P. azorica</italic> genotypes with no obvious clustering according to population and/or island. The only clear differentiation is between <italic>P. azorica</italic> from the Azores archipelagos and <italic>P. excelsa</italic> from Madeira island.For the endemic <italic>P. azorica</italic>, the results of AMOVA revealed that for each island most of the genetic diversity was found within populations (83 % for Terceira, 88 % for São Miguel and 96 % for Pico), a trend commonly reported in outcrossing and/or perennial species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C34">Hamrick <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>). Within and among islands, a low level of genetic differentiation was detected. Similar patterns of low differentiation among populations have also been reported in other insular trees of Macaronesia as <italic>Morella faya</italic> and <italic>Morella rivas-martinezzi</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C31">González-Pérez <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), where most of the genetic variability was found within populations (92 and 86 %, respectively). The genetic differentiation detected is a result of the high gene flow between populations and islands, corroborated by the number of migrants calculated, indicating that geographical distance was not found to be responsible for the reduction in gene flow between the different locations. Also levels of gene flow above one migrant between populations per generation were determined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C45">Martins <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>. Moreover, the lower value of total genetic diversity detected for Pico island reflects the continuous distribution of plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C73">Wright 1949</xref>) and a possible combination of founder and bottleneck effects, as Pico is the youngest island from Azores, and is caused by human interference that this species experienced.The Mantel test failed to reveal isolation by distance, as no genetic structure was observed for the species. Also the Bayesian approach implemented in STRUCTURE corroborates these results, indicating that geographical distances that separate the central and eastern islands do not seem to have acted as barriers preventing gene flow (maximum interisland distance roughly 246 km). A possible explanation could be that several bird species, including the two Azorean endemic bird taxa <italic>Columba palumbus azorica</italic> and <italic>Pyrrhula murina</italic>, feed on its fruits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C16">Dias <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) and as a result may have given an important contribution to <italic>P. azorica</italic> dissemination within and among islands, although the contribution of <italic>P. murina</italic> can be considered limited since it only exists in São Miguel. Regarding the results obtained here, it may also be considered that wind flow could provide further opportunities for long-distance dispersal of pollen.Due to the over-exploitation of <italic>P. azorica</italic> and the habitat degradation that led to its extinction in Graciosa island, this species has been considered as a priority Azorean endemic species for conservation and measures for restoration of depleted natural populations should be taken. Moreover, <italic>P. azorica</italic> is part of the habitat of the second most threatened bird in Europe—the Azores bullfinch (<italic>P. murina</italic>) protected under the Birds directive (Directive 2009/147/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 30 November 2009 on the conservation of wild birds) and therefore knowledge about <italic>P. azorica</italic> can indirectly contribute to the preservation of other species. However in order to guarantee sustainable survival of populations and to preserve their evolutionary potential, knowledge of the levels of genetic diversity and their distribution is important for designing conservation strategies for threatened and endangered species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C33">Hamrick and Godt 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C26">Francisco-Ortega <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). Population establishment and long-term persistence as well as long-term evolutionary potential of restored populations is ensured by within-population genetic diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C46">McKay <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>), as loss of genetic diversity can lead to a decrease in the species' ability to survive environmental changes and demographical fluctuations both in short and in long term (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C17">Ellstrand and Elam 1993</xref>). Although the conservation of six populations is considered the minimum necessary in order to preserve 99.99 % of the total diversity of the analysed populations, management should aim to conserve as many of the small populations as possible. Concentrating conservation efforts only on the few large populations would result in the likelihood of loss of genetic variability for the species.For long term, the most suitable strategy for the conservation of <italic>P. azorica</italic> is the protection and restoration of its habitat. Also artificial propagation of the species for timber use should be considered as the best preservation guaranteeing its <italic>ex situ</italic> conservation and sustainable survival, thus enhancing the <italic>in situ</italic> conservation. This could be sustainably achieved by propagation of seedlings and vegetative micropropagation of cuttings (D. Mendonâça <italic>et al.</italic>, submitted) and the reintroduction of the micropropagated plants into their populations of origin. Its valuable wood has been used in former times for the construction of toys, agricultural tools, furniture and religious statuary, and recent studies on its technological features support its use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU034C10">Caetano-Ferreira <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). The establishment of a breeding programme for wood quality together with plant tissue culture techniques and micropropagation would for sure avoid the destruction of the small populations and the extinction of the species, fostering its use.Population genetic analysis with ISSR markers in the endangered endemic species <italic>P. azorica</italic> detected a high within-population genetic diversity but low genetic differentiation between populations and between islands which can be explained by its life history traits, dispersal and gene flow. Neither isolation of some habitats nor population size affected genetic variability within the studied populations. The obtained data are important for establishing guidelines and priorities for germplasm and genetic diversity conservation, with <italic>in situ</italic> and <italic>ex situ</italic> conservation, together with renewed economic interest for its utilization, following reforestation programmes, representing good opportunities for conservation of this tree species.This project was supported by the Azorean Government (Secretary for Natural Resources). LA IBB-CBA is supported by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Portuguese Foundation for Science and Technology</grant-sponsor> (FCT, <grant-num xlink:type="simple">PEst-OE/EQB/LA0023/2013</grant-num>) and the Azorean Regional Science Fund (FRC). The authors thank A. Arraiol for providing samples of <italic>Picconia excelsa</italic> from Madeira Island. The following authors were supported by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">FRC: M.S.L.</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num xlink:type="simple">M3.1.7/F/023/2011</grant-num>), <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">D.M.</grant-sponsor> (<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">M3.1.7/F/010A/2009</grant-sponsor>), <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">S.X.B.</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num xlink:type="simple">M3.1.7/F/026/2011</grant-num>) and <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">A.R.B.</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num xlink:type="simple">M3.1.2/F/039/2011</grant-num>), and by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">FCT: C.M.</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num xlink:type="simple">SFRH/BPD/78059/2011</grant-num>).A.C.M. conceived the experiment. D.M., S.X.B. and C.M. collected the samples. M.S.L., A.R.B., C.M. and C.B. extracted the DNA. M.S.L. and A.R.B. performed the PCR and data analysis together with D.M. and S.X.B. M.S.L., D.M., S.X.B., A.R.B. and A.C.M. wrote the manuscript. All authors read the manuscript and agreed to submit it.None declared.The following Supporting Information is available in the online version of this article –<bold>Figure S1.</bold> Location of the samples collected from São Miguel Island.<bold>Figure S2.</bold> Location of the samples collected from Pico Island.<bold>Figure S3.</bold> Location of the samples collected from Terceira Island.<bold>Figure S4.</bold> Bayesian clustering performed by STRUCTURE for a set of 230 <italic>P. azorica</italic> genotypes from 11 different populations. (A) Δ<italic>K</italic> calculated as Δ<italic>K</italic> = <italic>m</italic>|<italic>L</italic>″(<italic>K</italic>)|/<italic>s</italic>[<italic>L</italic>(<italic>K</italic>)]; (B) ln Pr(<italic>G|K</italic>) values presented as a function of the number of clusters; (C) graphical presentations of different samples. Each sample is represented by a single vertical line broken into <italic>K</italic> colour segments, with lengths proportional to the estimated membership of the inferred cluster. Individuals are grouped into populations. For populations names see <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU034TB1">Table 1</xref>.The authors thank A. Arraiol for providing samples of <italic>Picconia excelsa</italic> from Madeira Island.