Habitat specificity of a threatened and endemic, cliff-dwelling halophyteDry coastal ecosystems of PortugalPlant community changes as ecological indicator of seabird colonies' impacts on Mediterranean IslandsOrigin of reciprocal translocations and their effects in <italic>Clarkia speciosa</italic>Experimental taxonomic studies in the <italic>Arabis holboellii</italic> and allied speciesRanunculus sect. Auricomus in Bayern und den angrenzenden Gebieten. I. Allgemeiner TeilRésultats de deux excursions géobotaniques à travers le Portugal septentrional et moyen IV. Esquisse sur la végétation dunaleThe role of ecology in biological conservationThe role of alien plants in the natural coastal vegetation in central-northern SpainArribas da faixa costeira de Cascais. Projecto de Recuperação de HabitatsKaryology of <italic>Limonium</italic> (Plumbaginaceae) species from the Balearic Islands and the western Iberian PeninsulaAssessing the residual effects of <italic>Carpobrotus edulis</italic> invasion, implications for restorationTipos de Vegetação e adaptações das plantas do litoral de Portugal continentalBiogeografia de Portugal ContinentalSintaxonomia da vegetação halocasmofítica das falésias marítimas portuguesas (Crithmo-Staticetea Br.-Bl. 1947)An overview of the Pegano harmalae-Salsoletea vermiculatae Br.-Bl. and. O. Bolòs 1958, vegetation class in continental PortugalThe application of the Habitats Directive in PortugalVascular plant communities in Portugal (Continental, the Azores and Madeira)On the conservation of natural habitats and of wild fauna and floraSeed production and dispersal in the non-native, invasive succulent <italic>Carprobrotus edulis</italic> (Aizoaceae) in coastal strand communities of central CaliforniaRoot profile and competition between the invasive, exotic perennial, <italic>Carprobrotus edulis</italic> and two native species in California coastal shrubsRarity and threat relationships in the conservation planning of Iberian floraEuropean Commission: seventh updated list of sites of community importance for the Mediterranean biogeographical regionConserving taxonomic complexityDie gattung Limonium im südwestmediterranen Raum<italic>Limonium</italic> MillerPlantas endémicas do litoral de Portugal ContinentalPlant life history traits of rare versus frequent plant taxa of sandplains: implications for research and management trialsA multivariate approach to plant community distribution in the coastal dune zonation of NW DenmarkHow successful are plant species reintroductions?Plant conservation: old problems, new perspectivesReticulate evolution and taxonomic concepts in the <italic>Ranunculus auricomus</italic> complex (Ranunculaceae): insights from morphological, karyological and molecular dataComplex hybridity in <italic>Isotoma petraea</italic>. 1. The occurrence of interchange heterozygosity, autogamy and a balanced lethal systemBreeding system and ecological traits of the critically endangered endemic plant <italic>Limonium barceloi</italic> (Gil and Llorens) (Plumbaginaceae)PlumbaginaceaeRelevant plant recovery programmes. Conservation management of plant micro-reserves and ecological restorationMolecular phylogenetics of <italic>Limonium</italic> and related genera (Plumbaginaceae): biogeographical and systematic implicationsNational inventories of crop wild relatives and wild harvested plants: case-study for PortugalThe meaning of mainland Portugal beaches and dunes' psammophilic plant communities: a contribution to tourism management and nature conservationBurial of plants as a selective force in sand dunesBioclimatic mapping using geostatistical approaches: application to mainland PortugalEvaluation of the stress-inducible production of proline in transgenic sugarcane (<italic>Saccharum</italic> spp): osmotic adjustment, chlorophyll fluorescence and oxidative stress<italic>Fitossociologia e Paisagem da Bacia Hidrográfica do Rio Paiva/Landscape and phytosociology of the Paiva River</italic>'<italic>s hydrographical basin</italic>Europe, ecosystems ofStudy of the evolutionary relationships among <italic>Limonium</italic> species (Plumbaginaceae) using nuclear and cytoplasmic molecular markersHistorical and biological determinants of genetic diversity in the highly endemic triploid sea lavender <italic>Limonium dufourii</italic> (Plumbaginaceae)Grouping and prioritization of vascular plant species for conservation: combining natural rarity and management needImpact of the invasive <italic>Carpobrotus edulis</italic> on <italic>Armeria pseudarmeria</italic> at Cabo da RocaPlant invasions of protected areas in Europe: an old continent facing new problemsSeven forms of rarityMapa de series, geoseries y geopermaseries de vegetación de España. Memoria del mapa de vegetación potencial de EspañaMolecular and morphological differentiation in <italic>Limonium dufourii</italic> (Plumbaginaceae), an endangered Mediterranean plantMale fertility versus sterility, cytotype, and DNA quantitative variation in seed production in diploid and tetraploid sea lavenders (<italic>Limonium</italic> sp., Plumbaginaceae) reveal diversity in reproduction modesEpigenetic rather than genetic factors may explain phenotypic divergence between coastal populations of diploid and tetraploid (<italic>Limonium</italic> sp.; Plumbaginaceae) in PortugalAbsence of geographic structure in European populations of <italic>Rubus fruticosus</italic> L. complex using chloroplast DNA microsatellitesTsunami relics on the coastal landscape west of Lisbon, PortugalEvaluating approaches to the conservation of rare and endangered plantsIntraspecific chromosome number variation: a neglected threat to the conservation of rare speciesStructural and numerical chromosomal polymorphism in natural populations of <italic>Alopecurus</italic> L. (Poaceae)The contribution of population and community to conservation scienceEvolutionary and plant geographical aspects of chasmophytic communitiesGenetic diversity and floral dimorphism in <italic>Limonium dendroides</italic> (Plumbaginaceae), a woody <italic>Canarian</italic> species on the way of extinctionInvasion by South African <italic>Carpobrotus</italic> (Aizoaceae) taxa in the Mediterranean Basin: the effects of insularity on plant reproductive systemsConsistent performance of invasive species within and among islands of the Mediterranean basinDistribution and conservation status of littoral vascular plant species along the European coastsEcological and evolutionary opportunities of apomixis: insights from Taraxacum and ChondrillaLocal and regional assessment of the impacts of plant invaders on vegetation structure and soil properties of Mediterranean islandsHierarchical grouping to optimize an objective functionGenetic bottlenecks and dysgenic gene flow into re-established populations of the grassland daisy, <italic>Rutidosis leptorrhynchoides</italic><bold>Guest Editor:</bold> Adele MuscoloThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Coastal cliff-tops are specific saline environments, where only highly specialized halophytes can thrive. Limonium spp. are commonly found in these ecological conditions, many of them being considered as threatened or with an unknown conservation status. The habitat requirements of Limonium multiflorum, an apomictic halophyte endemic to western Portugal, were investigated. Results showed the species narrow habitat specificity as well as its intolerance to competition with invasive alien plants. We conclude that in situ conservation of this rare and vulnerable species emerges as a priority in order to ensure that its biodiversity is not lost.Coastal areas and other saline environments are major contributors to regional and global biodiversity patterns. In these environments, rapidly changing gradients require highly specialized plants like halophytes. In European coastal cliff-tops, rocky and sandy seashores, and saltmarshes, typical halophytes from the genus <italic>Limonium</italic> are commonly found. Among them, the aneuploid tetraploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 35, 36, 37) <italic>Limonium multiflorum</italic>, endemic to the west coast of Portugal, is an interesting case study for investigating the ecology and conservation of a halophyte agamospermic species. Although it is listed in the IUCN red list of threatened species, information on its population size or rarity, as well as its ecology, in some respects is still unknown. Field surveys in the largest known population were performed (Raso cape, Portugal) in order to determine habitat requirements and conservation status. A total of 88 quadrats were monitored, 43 of which contained at least one <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> individual. For each sampled quadrat, four abiotic and four biotic variables as well as two spatially derived variables were recorded. Principal component analysis and cluster analysis showed narrow habitat specificity for this species which appeared to be intolerant to competition with invasive alien plants. We conclude that <italic>in situ</italic> conservation in a local ‘hotspot’ of this rare and vulnerable species emerges as a priority in order to ensure that biodiversity is not lost.Habitat assessment is a fundamental requirement for species conservation. Attempts to set plant conservation priorities revealed the need to consider attributes such as species ecological specificity, geographical rarity and rate of threat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C24">Domínguez Lozano <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C53">Pärtel <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). Furthermore, a study on plant life history traits in rare versus common <italic>taxa</italic> also showed that infrequent species exhibited a narrower geographical range and more habitat specialization than their common relatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C30">Farnsworth 2007</xref>). Thus, knowledge on habitat requirements of a rare species is crucial, in particular in the case of agamospermic species (defined by an asexual breeding system) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C24">Domínguez Lozano <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>), to help establish the best conservation methods.In Europe, coastal vegetation presents lower diversity values when compared with other world regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C50">Mucina 2013</xref>) but European dry coastal terrestrial habitats, which include maritime rocks, sea-cliffs and coastal slopes, show higher values in terms of plant diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C74">van der Maarel 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C75">van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996</xref>). Among the best represented flowering plant families of these habitats are the <italic>Plumbaginaceae</italic> with nearly 90 % of coastal species, including most members from the genus <italic>Limonium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C40">Kubitzki 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C75">van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996</xref>). This cosmopolitan halophytic genus comprises annual and perennial species found on cliff-tops, rocky and sandy seashores, and saltmarshes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C28">Erben 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C40">Kubitzki 1993</xref>). These habitats are an important source of endemics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C75">van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996</xref>), and nearly 37 % of all typical littoral species are considered threatened either because they have an extremely local distribution or because they are in decline as a result of negative human impacts in coastal areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C75">van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996</xref>).Knowledge of habitat requirements of threatened populations from rare species selected for conservation is crucial for assuring their viability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C68">Simberloff 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C10">Brussard 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C65">Schemske <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C34">Heywood and Iriondo 2003</xref>), since the establishment and expansion of a species is dependent on growth under favourable ecological conditions (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C4">Baumberger <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Increasing a species' survival prospects through reintroduction or reinforcement (increase population size and diversity) of native species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C1">Akeroyd and Wyse Jackson 1995</xref>), and knowing ecological processes in combination with demographic and genetic processes and breeding systems is therefore essential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C32">Godefroid <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). However, objective data for documenting habitat preferences of rare plant species are relatively scarce, in particular those on ocean-exposed high cliff-tops subjected to salt spray transported inland by wind (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C62">Salisbury 1952</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C45">Maun 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C31">Frederiksen <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>).The Portuguese coast is known for the richness of its flora due to a singular biogeographic position (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C9">Braun-Blanquet <italic>et al</italic>. 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C3">Asensi <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C75">van der Maarel and van der Maarel-Versluys 1996</xref>). About 35 % of all Portuguese Natura 2000 habitats consist of coastal habitats, including Atlantic ocean-exposed cliff-tops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C19">Costa <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C44">Martins <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). These locations present the original flora and vegetation on limestone, sandstone and marly clay areas, and include the rare and endemic cliff-dwelling <italic>Limonium multiflorum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C27">Erben 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C28">1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C18">Costa <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C29">Espírito-Santo <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). This species is listed in Annex II of Habitats Directive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C21">Council Directive 92/43/EEC 1992</xref>) and in the IUCN red list of threatened species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C37">IUCN 2013</xref>), and most of its known populations are located in Portuguese NATURA 2000 Sites of Community Importance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C25">EC 2013</xref>). Although <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> is considered a Portuguese crop wild relative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C43">Magos-Brehm <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>) and has an assessed conservation status of ‘Least Concern’ in the IUCN red list (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C37">IUCN 2013</xref>), information on its ecological preferences, essential for recovery plans, especially population restoration, population augmentation or population reintroduction is lacking.In the present study we assessed habitat requirements for <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>. Two main questions were addressed: (i) What are the main abiotic and biotic variables favourable for its persistence? (ii) What is the vegetation cover and respective species composition associated with its presence?Map of <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> distribution in the western coast of Portugal.Schematic drawing of the quadrat sampling of <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> in the coast of Raso cape.Thermopluviometric diagram based on the weather station in the coast of Raso cape. The red line corresponds to mean monthly temperature (°C) and the blue line corresponds to mean monthly precipitation (mm).Wind regime diagrams based on the weather station in the coast of Raso cape during <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> flowering peak (May–July).Field surveys used a grid of 10 × 10 m quadrats which was overlaid over the aerial photographs of the site and later transferred to the site using global positioning system (GPS) receivers. A total of 88 quadrats were surveyed, 43 of which contained at least one <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> individual (presence quadrat) and the remaining 45 were randomly selected quadrats containing no individuals from this species (absence quadrat) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU032F2">2</xref>). The random selection procedure was performed using R software's ‘sample’ routine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C57">R Core Team 2013</xref>). In quadrats where <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> was present censuses were carried out from April to June 2013. For each sampled quadrat four abiotic variables, namely rock formation (RockForm), cobble (Cobble), coarse sand (CoarseSd) and fine sand (FineSand) (all expressed in %), were recorded. Four biotic variables related to vegetation cover (Coverage) as well as invasive non-native species (INNS) cover, dead organic matter (lignified or not) (DOM) cover and litter (Residues) cover were also estimated (expressed in %) in each quadrat. To facilitate data collection, each quadrat was then sub-divided into sub-quadrats of 1 m<sup>2</sup>, and the percent coverage value obtained for the sub-quadrats of the same 100 m<sup>2</sup> quadrat were averaged. Two spatial variables, distance from coastline (Dist_coa) and mean quadrat slope (Mean_slo), were also derived using the ArcGIS<sup>®</sup> 10.0 software, by ESRI.To define <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> habitat requirements we performed a principal component analysis (PCA) on the resulting data matrix using abiotic, biotic and spatially derived variables. In order to discriminate the vegetation structure and composition in the monitored quadrats, a cluster analysis using Euclidean distance and Ward clustering method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C78">Ward 1963</xref>) was performed using the set of quadrats containing <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>. To ensure that the group of quadrats (clusters) had the same influence from the environmental variables, Kruskal–Wallis tests of variance were performed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C70">Sokal and Rohlf 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C81">Zar 2010</xref>). To complete habitat characterization of <italic>L. multiflorum,</italic> the most frequent and abundant plant species within each cluster was defined as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C4">Baumberger <italic>et al</italic>. (2012)</xref>. The mean coverage of each species within each group was also calculated. All statistical analyses were conducted using the STATISTICA software (StatSoft V10). Bioclimatic and biogeographic nomenclature followed the proposals of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C58">Rivas-Martínez (2007)</xref>. Taxonomic nomenclature followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C46">Menezes de Sequeira <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>.On the western coast most <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> populations occur at inaccessible cliff sites and/or show very small size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C61">Róis <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Under these circumstances, this study was conducted at the best accessible site and on the largest known population for this species, in Raso cape. Study site rocks were bare of vegetation up to ∼7–8 m asl, due to strong exposure to Atlantic storms and waves over the years.Two first axes of PCA based on <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> presence and absence quadrats. Red symbols mean that <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> was recorded whereas blue symbols signify that it was absent. Axis 1 represents 44.8 % of variation, and Axis 2, 19.7 %. CoarseSd, coarse sand; Cobble, cobble; Coverage, vegetation cover; Dist_coa, distance from coast; DOM, dead organic matter cover; FineSand, fine sand; INNS, invasive non-native species cover; Mean_slo, mean slope; Residues, litter cover; RockForm, rock formation.Mean values ± standard error of abiotic, biotic and spatial-related variables in each of four environmental groups based on the presence data of PCA. Bold letters within a row indicate non-significant with post hoc multiple comparison Tukey's test (<italic>α</italic> = 0.05; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). <italic>P</italic> value &lt;0.001. ns, non-significant; CoarseSD, coarse sand; Cobble, cobble; Coverage, vegetation cover; Dist_coa, distance from coast; DOM, dead organic matter cover; FineSd, fine sand; INNS, invasive non-native species cover; Mean_slo, mean slope; Residues, litter cover; RockForm, rock formation.Mean coverage (%) of the most frequent species in each of the four environmental groups (clusters) based on the presence data of PCA.Cluster dendogram of the four clusters containing <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>. The dissimilarity between groups was calculated based on species variables using Euclidean distance and the Ward aggregation method. Cluster definition 1 accounts for a high percentage of <italic>C. edulis</italic> (&gt;65 %); Cluster 2 by a moderate percentage of <italic>C. edulis</italic> (&lt;35 %); Cluster 3 is defined by <italic>A. welwitschii</italic> (9.67 %) and <italic>P. incurva</italic> (21.33 %); and Cluster 4 represents quadrats with the highest <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> frequency (0.84 %).Vegetation composition also varied between clusters. Cluster 1 was dominated by <italic>Carpobrotus edulis</italic> with a coverage percentage &gt;65 % whereas Cluster 2 presented a moderate coverage of <italic>C. edulis</italic> (&lt;35 %). In this cluster significant mean coverage was observed for psammophilous species like the perennials <italic>Armeria welwitschii</italic> and <italic>Elymus farctus</italic> subsp. <italic>boreo-atlanticus</italic>. As for Cluster 3, significant frequencies of the perennial <italic>Limonium ovalifolium</italic> and the therophyte <italic>Parapholis incurva</italic> were revealed. Finally, Cluster 4 which had the greatest coverage percentage of <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> (0.835 %) of all clusters appeared to be associated with chasmophytic species such as <italic>C. maritimum</italic>, and other perennials like <italic>Frankenia laevis</italic> and <italic>Inula crithmoides</italic>.In this study we show that <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> grows on sea-cliffs preferentially up to 50 m asl in karstic crevices within exposed rocks more or less filled with substrate, or on shallow soil above the rock strata and on scree slopes. The presence of <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> was favoured by the presence of rock formation, cobble, low percentage of vegetation coverage, low frequency of invasive non-native species and closest distance to coast. In fact, as pointed out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C79">Warming (1909)</xref>, <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>'s preference for salt-rich rock crevices seems to be a strategy to use such locations as refuges, thus avoiding competition with many other coastal plants that are unable to colonize such habitats. Furthermore, as it happens in endemic <italic>Limonium</italic> spp., populations tend to be fragmented and usually show low population sizes as a consequence of many social and economic activities like urbanization, tourism and traffic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C59">Rodríguez <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C52">Palop-Esteban <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C71">Suárez-García <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C39">Khan <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C61">Róis <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) on their habitats. This is also the case of <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C36">ICNF 2013</xref>), in particular, in the Raso cape population (A.F. and V.S., unpubl. res.).Vegetation composition significantly differs among the four floristically defined groups. Cluster 1 is dominated by the alien plant <italic>C. edulis</italic> with <italic>E. farctus</italic> subsp. <italic>boreo-atlanticus</italic>'s due to nitrophilous coarse sand dunes corresponding to <italic>Elytrigietum junceo-boreoatlanticae</italic> association (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C20">Costa <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). The presence of <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> in this cluster can be explained by 5 % of rock outcrop, uncovered with sand. Cluster 2 includes the farthest quadrats from the sea where rock depressions filled up with fine sand and cobble appear. In this cluster <italic>A. welwitschii</italic>, <italic>F. laevis</italic> and <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> predominate. This cluster presents a poor floristic composition, as it happens in the previous cluster, due to invasion of <italic>C. edulis</italic>, possibly related with the proximity to roads (higher nitrification)<italic>.</italic> Cluster 3 is typically formed by species of rocky substrate, with a high slope and direct influence of wind loaded with salt. Here <italic>L. ovalifolium</italic>, <italic>C. maritimum</italic>, <italic>A. welwitschii</italic>, <italic>F. laevis</italic>, <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>, <italic>P. coronopus</italic> form the perennial community <italic>Limonietum multifloro-virgati</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C17">Costa <italic>et al</italic>. 1998<italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C20">2012</xref>). In their clearings <italic>P. incurva</italic>, <italic>Medicago minima</italic>, <italic>Andryala arenaria</italic> form the poor, annual association <italic>Parapholido incurvae–Catapodietum marini</italic>. Also, the presence of <italic>Lotus creticus</italic> is due to coarse sand. Cluster 4 also exhibits species that constitute the <italic>Limonietum multifloro-virgati</italic> association (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C17">Costa <italic>et al</italic>. 1998<italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C20">2012</xref>), namely <italic>C. maritimum</italic>, <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>, <italic>I. crithmoides</italic>, <italic>F. laevis</italic>, <italic>P. coronopus</italic>. The referred species are at their ecological optimum in this rocky sea-cliff cluster although a small percentage of coarse sand explains the presence of <italic>E. farctus</italic> subsp. <italic>boreo-atlanticus</italic> and <italic>L. creticus.</italic> Plant survival in this ecological context is difficult due to low availability of fresh water, low level of essential nutrients and the abrasive action of strong winds laden with salt and increasing conditions of extreme dryness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C17">Costa <italic>et al</italic>. 1998<italic>b</italic></xref>). To overcome this some plants respond with adaptations, such as adopting the hemicryptophyte or therophyte life forms, presenting succulent leaves and/or salt glands in the leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C79">Warming 1909</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C15">Costa 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C33">Grigore <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>).Our results show that both native and non-native vegetation cover are negatively correlated with <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> presence, emphasizing its preferences for sites where competition with other species is low. Among the species having a greater negative effect in their persistence is the exotic, invasive, crawling <italic>C. edulis</italic>. This species commonly invades coastal habitats in Mediterranean Europe forming mantles on maritime rocks, cliffs and sand dunes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C22">D'Antonio 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C73">Traveset <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C55">Pyšek <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) competing directly with native plant species, suppressing the growth and establishment of other plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C23">D'Antonio and Mahall 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C77">Vilà <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>), altering certain soil parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C77">Vilà <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C14">Conser and Connor 2009</xref>) or creating litter accumulation on the soil surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C48">Molinari <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). Although <italic>C. edulis</italic> seems to develop well on rocky substrates at sites where seagulls' (<italic>Larus</italic> sp.) nutrient-rich droppings are frequent (M.D.E.-S., unpubl. res.), in our study it seems to compete mainly with species showing preference for sand substrates. Remarkably, some littoral species show strong resilience to <italic>C. edulis</italic> invasion, like the narrow endemic cliff-species <italic>Armeria pseudoarmeria</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C54">Pinto-Ricardo <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) or other <italic>Limonium</italic> spp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C69">Snogerup 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C72">Suehs <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C11">Campos <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>).For the effective protection of the rare and endemic <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> not only ecological data but also life story, demography and genetic data should be taken into account to ensure that maximum genetic variation is preserved. In this context, one of the factors to be considered in conserving <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> is related with chromosome polymorphisms since euploid and aneuploid cytotypes occur within populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C60">Róis <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Although, it was first described as an unbalanced aneuploid tetraploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 35) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C27">Erben 1978</xref>), both unbalanced and balanced tetraploid cytotypes (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 35, 36, 37) and diverse karyological polymorphisms were found within and among populations, with greater variability in the Raso cape population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C60">Róis <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). This has also been observed in other <italic>Limonium</italic> taxa (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C13">Castro and Rosseló 2007</xref>), and even in a variety of genera from different plant families (e.g. <italic>Brassicaceae</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C6">Böcher 1954</xref>; <italic>Campanulaceae</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C38">James 1965</xref>; <italic>Onagraceae</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C5">Bloom 1974</xref>; <italic>Plumbaginaceae</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C27">Erben 1978</xref>; <italic>Poaceae</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C67">Sieber and Murray 1981</xref>; <italic>Ranunculaceae</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C8">Borchers-Kolb 1983</xref>). These cytological differences should be considered to ensure that maximum genetic variation is preserved. Furthermore, the resultant combination of incompatible cytotypes could result in the failure of reintroduced plants to reproduce and may bring reproductive instability to augmented populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C80">Young and Murray 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C26">Ennos <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C66">Severns and Liston 2008</xref>).Noticeably, male sterility and gynodioecism are found in plants from experimental collections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C60">Róis <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>) and field plants (Heike Sprenger and A.D.C., unpubl. res.). However, these plants are capable of producing large numbers of viable seeds with variable ploidy levels, as revealed by flow cytometry seed screening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C60">Róis <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>) and reproduce through apomixis (A.S.R. and A.D.C., unpubl. res.). This form of uniparental reproduction is found in ‘taxonomically complex groups’ like in other <italic>Limonium</italic> spp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C27">Erben 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C51">Palacios <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C42">Lledó <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>) and also in dandelions (<italic>Taraxacum</italic> spp.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C76">van Dijk 2003</xref>), blackberries (<italic>Rubus fruticosus</italic> agg.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C63">Salvini <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>) and in <italic>Ranunculus</italic> spp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C35">Hörandl <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>), which generates a diverse mixture of related individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C26">Ennos <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>).While some <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> populations are located in natural parks (Parque Natural Sintra-Cascais) and other areas under legal protection (e.g. Site of Community Importance—SCI Sintra/Cascais PTCON0008; SCI Peniche/Sta Cruz PTCON0056), in the past decades no information on population size along its distribution range has been available. However, we hypothesized that population decline might have occurred due to increasing urban development in the coastal areas and the impact of tourism. For instance, in Raso cape, sightseeing tourists, sports fishing and other socio-economic activities, together with competition associated with invasion by non-native species are cumulatively leading to population decline (V.S., A.F. and A.D.C., unpubl. res.). Notably, methylation-sensitive amplified polymorphism (MSAP) data from <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> natural populations reveal low levels of genetic/epigenetic diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C61">Róis <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Altogether these data mean that none of the populations analysed could restore the genotypic diversity observed in any other <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> population. Hence, habitat protection emerges as the top priority to prevent population extinction of the narrow-specialist <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>. For the conservation of this species, management actions such as those referred by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C41">Laguna <italic>et al</italic>. (2013)</xref>, namely limiting access to populations, for example, the experimental exclusion of herbivores by means of fences to protect populations of <italic>L. dufourii</italic> in ‘Marsh dels Moros’ (Spain) and to perform selective removal and control of invasive species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C41">Laguna <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>), are required. Other technical solutions could be population reinforcements, reintroduction or establishment of new populations, the goal of which is the introduction of new specimens. In the case of <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>, attempts to create new populations through experimental actions like sowing seeds directly <italic>in situ</italic> did not prove to be successful (A.D.C. and V.S., unpubl. res.) but population reinforcements by planting newly produced specimens using seed stock that originated from the same natural populations (e.g. Raso cape) appears to give better results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C12">Caperta <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Complementary <italic>ex situ</italic> conservation actions for this species such as collection and storage of seeds preserved in João do Amaral Franco Seed Bank (Ajuda Botanical Garden) have also been conducted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C12">Caperta <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) with the hope that the genetic diversity contained in these collections could be representative of natural populations. Thus, to conserve <italic>L. multiflorum</italic>, it is preferable to develop small, localized experimental actions as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C41">Laguna <italic>et al</italic>. (2013)</xref> pointed out. In fact, only moderate success is reported for reintroduction projects due, for example, to insufficient long-term monitoring following reintroduction and/or lack of understanding of the underlying reasons for decline in existing plant populations (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C32">Godefroid <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).According to Rabinowitz' scheme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C56">1981</xref>), in which species were classified into categories according to their geographic range, habitat specificity and local population size, <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> can be classified as a ‘classic rarity’ since it presents both narrow geographic range and narrow habitat specificity, thus being considered a restricted endemic. Furthermore, species' populations observed throughout its entire range consistently present small sizes and low levels of genetic diversity as revealed by population genetic and epigenetic studies using MSAP markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C61">Róis <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Taking the above into consideration, as well as diverse social-economic impacts exerted on its populations, we considered that <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> deserves a status of ‘Vulnerable’ in the IUCN red list.As already pointed out for other ‘taxonomically complex groups’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU032C26">Ennos <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>), conservation of rare and endemic <italic>L. multiflorum</italic> is best achieved by facilitating evolutionary interactions among its members that generate and maintain their taxonomic biodiversity.Our work was funded by <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia (FCT)</grant-sponsor> (Portugal) (<grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">PEST-OE/AGR/UI0240/2011</grant-num>). <grant-sponsor id="cs2" rid="cn2" xlink:type="simple">A.D.C.</grant-sponsor> (Researcher, <grant-num id="cn2" rid="cs2" xlink:type="simple">CBAA/ISA) and A.S.R. (SFRH/BD/62542/2009</grant-num> grant) were supported by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">FCT</grant-sponsor>.A.D.C. and P.A. designed and coordinated the study. M.D.E.-S. coordinated the fieldwork and A.D.C., M.D.E.-S., A.P.P. and A.S.R. performed the fieldwork. A.F. and V.S. processed the raw data and carried out statistical analysis. J.C.C. and M.D.E.-S. performed the phytosociological analysis. A.D.C. and P.A. drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.None declared.We thank Manuela Rodrigues (Volunteer), Ana Cortinhas (CBAA/ISA) and Vanessa Mendonça (CBAA/ISA) for help in field work, Jorge Cadima (ISA) for help in defining the experimental design, and the anonymous reviewers for all the helpful comments and suggestions. We thank the Instituto da Conservação da Natureza e das Florestas (ICNF) for providing permissions for field work.