High water-use efficiency and growth contribute to success of non-native <italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> in a Sonoran Desert winter annual communityEnemy release? An experiment with congeneric plant pairs and diverse above- and belowground enemiesTradeoffs and adaptive negative correlations in evolutionary ecologyLinking growth strategies to long-term population dynamics in a guild of desert annualsFunctional tradeoffs determine species coexistence via the storage effectMeasuring plant interactions: a new comparative indexLeaf construction cost, nutrient concentration, and net CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation of native and invasive species in HawaiiThe evolution of an invasive plant: an experimental study with <italic>Silene latifolia</italic>Evolution of increased competitive ability in invasive nonindigenous plants: a hypothesisEcology. Interrelated causes of plant invasionInteractions between resource availability and enemy release in plant invasionPracma: Practical numerical math functions R package version 1.5.0Phenotypic and genetic differentiation between native and introduced plant populationsCompetition between alien annual grasses and native annual plants in the Mojave DesertPeak fire temperatures and effects on annual plants in the Mojave DesertEffects of increased soil nitrogen on the dominance of alien annual plants in the Mojave DesertCompetition between native perennial and exotic annual grasses: implications for an historical invasionPerformance comparisons of co-occurring native and alien invasive plants: implications for conservation and restorationFluctuating resources in plant communities: a general theory of invasibilityCarbon isotope discrimination and photosynthesisNitrogen allocation, partitioning and use efficiency in three invasive plant species in comparison with their native congenersSpecific leaf area relates to the differences in leaf construction cost, photosynthesis, nitrogen allocation, and use efficiencies between invasive and noninvasive alien congenersResource-use efficiency and plant invasion in low-resource systemsCompetitive effect and response in four annual plantsVariation in photosynthetic response to temperature in a guild of winter annual plantsWater-use efficiency and relative growth rate mediate competitive interactions in Sonoran Desert winter annual plantsCompetition among old-field perennials at different levels of soil fertility and available spaceTesting the evolution of increased competitive ability (EICA) hypothesis in a novel frameworkPhotosynthetic resource-use efficiency and demographic variability in desert winter annual plantsUnderstanding past, contemporary, and future dynamics of plants, populations, and communities using Sonoran Desert winter annualsSuitability of stressed and vigorous plants to various insect herbivoresInteractions among unrelated species: granivorous rodents, a parasitic fungus, and a shared prey speciesEffects of predation and competition on survivorship, fecundity, and community structure of desert annualsExotic plant invasions and the enemy release hypothesisDiffering effects of cattle grazing on native and alien plantsContemporary climate change in the Sonoran Desert favors cold-adapted speciesDifferences in the timing of germination and reproduction relate to growth physiology and population dynamics of Sonoran Desert winter annualsFitness and physiology in a variable environmentPhenotypic selection favors missing trait combinations in coexisting annual plantsTrade-offs in community ecology: linking spatial scales and species coexistenceProgress in invasion biology: predicting invadersInvasive California poppies (<italic>Eschscholzia californica</italic> Cham.) grow larger than native individuals under reduced competitionLeaf trait relationships of native and invasive plants: community- and global-scale comparisonsNative and exotic invasive plants have fundamentally similar carbon capture strategiesMechanisms underlying the impacts of exotic plant invasionsPre-mission invasion of <italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> in CaliforniaFire season and mulch reduction in a California grassland: a comparison of restoration strategiesRelease of invasive plants from fungal and viral pathogensInvasions: the trail behind, the path ahead, and a test of a disturbing ideaCan a breakdown in competition–colonization tradeoffs help explain the success of exotic species in the California flora?Growth, biomass allocation and photosynthesis of invasive and native Hawaiian rainforest speciesA theory of seed plant invasiveness: the first sketchWhat attributes make some plant species more invasive?Plant invasions: merging the concepts of species invasiveness and community invasibilityThe population biology of invasive species. <italic>Annu Rev Ecol Syst</italic>Positive and negative effects of exotic <italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> on an arid ecosystemOut of the quagmire of plant defense hypothesesAre plants really larger in their introduced ranges?Seed mass and the competition/colonization trade-off: a sowing experimentBet hedging in a guild of desert annualsPopulation and Community Dynamics in Variable Environments: The Desert Annual System, Environmental Fluctuation, Temporal Dynamics and Ecological ProcessAre competitive effect and response two sides of the same coin, or fundamentally different?<bold>Editor:</bold> Lawren SackThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Erodium cicutarium, an invasive plant, has recently increased in abundance in the Sonoran Desert. We tested hypotheses for its success, and found no evidence for a release from natural enemies. Instead, E. cicutarium was able to achieve higher growth rates while controlling leaf-level water loss, allowing it to out-compete natives.The success of non-native, invasive species may be due to release from natural enemies, superior competitive abilities, or both. In the Sonoran Desert, <italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> has increased in abundance over the last 30 years. While native species in this flora exhibit a strong among-species trade-off between relative growth rate and water-use efficiency, <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> seems to have a higher relative growth rate for its water-use efficiency value relative to the pattern across native species. This novel trait combination could provide the non-native species with a competitive advantage in this water-limited environment. To test the hypothesis that <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> is able to achieve high growth rates due to release from native herbivores, we compared the effects of herbivory on <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> and its native congener, <italic>Erodium texanum</italic>. We also compared these two species across a range of environmental conditions, both in a common garden and in two distinct seasons in the field, using growth analysis, isotopic compositions and leaf-level gas exchange. Additionally, we compared the competitive abilities of the two <italic>Erodium</italic> species in a greenhouse experiment. We found no evidence of herbivory to either species. Physiological measurements in a common environment revealed that <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> was able to achieve high growth rates while simultaneously controlling leaf-level water loss. Non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> responded to favourable conditions in the field with greater specific leaf area and leaf area ratio than native <italic>E. texanum</italic>. The non-native <italic>Erodium</italic> was a stronger competitor than its native congener in a greenhouse competition experiment. The ability to maintain relatively higher values of water-use efficiency:relative growth rate in comparison to the native flora may be what enables <italic>E. cictarium</italic> to outcompete native species in both wet and dry years, resulting in an increase in abundance in the highly variable Sonoran Desert.One primary goal in invasion biology is to understand how non-native species are able to outcompete native species and increase in abundance in their introduced range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C44">Levine <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C12">Bossdorf <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C53">Richardson and Pysek, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C48">Moles <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The enemy release hypothesis (ERH) states that non-native species perform better in their introduced range because they experience a decrease in natural enemies that restrict performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C33">Keane and Crawley, 2002</xref>). It is also possible that invasive species are successful because they possess specific life history or physiological traits that allow them to outcompete natives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C51">Rejmanek, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C52">Rejmanek and Richardson, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C40">Kolar and Lodge, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C54">Sakai <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Many physiological studies have demonstrated that invasive species have traits that enable them to grow quickly, including higher specific leaf area (SLA), leaf nitrogen content and rates of CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation relative to native species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C6">Baruch and Goldstein, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C42">Leishman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C20">Feng and Fu, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C21">Feng <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Thus, non-native species may be successful because they are physiologically superior to native species in terms of their ability to capture and use resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C22">Funk and Vitousek, 2007</xref>). These traits that frequently characterize non-natives often trade off with the ability to tolerate predation, so a release from natural enemies may allow populations with such traits to succeed in new environments.According to the ERH, the release from natural herbivores allows non-native species to grow faster than native species that may be experiencing herbivory (ERH; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C33">Keane and Crawley, 2002</xref>). This hypothesis requires that defense mechanisms come at a cost to growth and fitness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C30">Inbar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C56">Stamp, 2003</xref>). Release from herbivory could allow individuals to invest in traits for growth and resource acquisition without the associated cost, allowing them to grow larger in high-resource conditions due to a breakdown of the growth–defense trade-off (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C10">Blumenthal, 2006</xref>). If defense mechanisms result in a fitness cost, a release from herbivory could favour individuals that invest less in defense and more in growth and reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C27">Handley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Given that competitive ability is often linked with size and fecundity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C23">Goldberg and Fleetwood, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C26">Gurevitch <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C61">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), this release from predation could allow non-native populations to evolve to be stronger competitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C8">Blossey and Notzold, 1995</xref>). However, traits related to high growth rates and competitive abilities also trade off with traits related to abiotic stress tolerance, dispersal abilities and other tolerances and preferences, such that breakdowns in any of these trade-offs may explain the success of invasive species without a release from natural enemies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C58">Turnbull <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C2">Agrawal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C49">Molina-Montenegro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).At the University of Arizona's Desert Laboratory in the Sonoran Desert, we have identified a trade-off between leaf-level water-use efficiency (WUE) and relative growth rate (RGR) in the winter annual plant community, such that species with high RGR have low WUE and vice versa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C3">Angert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C4">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C28">Huxman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C38">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). These patterns were documented using stable isotopes of carbon (as a proxy for WUE) and growth analysis and, subsequently, have been supported by a large number of studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C29">Huxman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). When compared with the native flora, the non-native species present in our community (<italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> and <italic>Schismus barbatus</italic>) have higher WUE for their given RGR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cou006/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Fig. S1</ext-link>). The high values of RGR relative to WUE for these two non-native species may indicate an unstable community, in which the non-natives will outcompete natives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C38">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Our long-term demographic data indicate that one of these species, <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>, has experienced a slight increase in abundance over the last 30 years despite a general decline in the numbers of all winter annual species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C35">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C60">Venable and Kimball, 2013</xref>). It is unclear how or why the non-natives in our system are able to achieve higher RGR for their given WUE, but an understanding of this may be critical to understanding both the spread of invasive species and the future dynamics of invaded plant communities.<italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> is native to the Mediterranean region and was introduced to the Sonoran Desert during the 1870s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C45">Mensing and Byrne, 1998</xref>). It now occurs throughout North America and is abundant in many different habitats, including California Grassland, Mojave Desert and Chihuahuan Desert (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C14">Brooks, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C34">Kimball and Schiffman, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C55">Schutzenhofer and Valone, 2006</xref>). The competitive ability of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> is known to increase with addition of nitrogen, burning, and increased precipitation in the Mojave Desert (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C13">Brooks, 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C14">2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C15">2003</xref>) and with burning and cattle grazing in California grasslands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C46">Meyer and Schiffman, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C34">Kimball and Schiffman, 2003</xref>). <italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> germinated and reproduced earlier than other Sonoran Desert winter annuals over the last 30 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C36">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), which may help to explain its success in dry years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C37">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).In this study, we focused on mechanisms that may have determined the success of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> in our Sonoran Desert winter annual system. We compared the performance of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> with a commonly found native congener with a similar growth form, <italic>Erodium texanum.</italic> We chose to focus on <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> rather than <italic>S. barbatus</italic>, the other non-native species that exhibits high RGR and WUE, because <italic>S. barbatus</italic> is a grass, and native grasses do not occur in high abundance at our study site. In addition to being members of the same genus, <italic>E. texanum</italic> and <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> are similar to each other in many other ways, including buffered population dynamics, early life history transitions, high integrated WUE, high germination fractions and increased ability to photosynthesize at low temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C59">Venable, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C28">Huxman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C36">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C24">Gremer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). These similarities make <italic>E. texanum</italic> a good choice for a native comparison to clarify mechanisms driving the success of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>. We also focused our attention on trait relationships of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> compared with the general patterns found in the native flora. We addressed the following questions. (i) Does non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> experience less herbivory than native <italic>E. texanum</italic>, as would be predicted by the ERH? (ii) Are there unique combinations of physiological traits related to use of the primary limiting resource, water, and related to growth components that enable <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> to achieve both high RGR and WUE? (iii) Is <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> able to outcompete <italic>E. texanum</italic>? We used a combination of manipulative field experiments, common garden contrasts and observations in natural field settings to understand the mechanisms by which <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>, a problematic invasive species, has succeeded in its introduced range.Herbivore exclusion plots were established at the University of Arizona's Desert Laboratory at Tumamoc Hill in Tucson, AZ, USA to test the enemy release hypothesis. Specifically, we compared the performance of the non-native, invasive species <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> with its native congener, <italic>E. texanum</italic>, in control and herbivore-exclusion plots.On 10 December 2007, shortly after winter germination, 16 control and 16 exclusion plots were placed in areas where both species were present. We did not manipulate the density of plants in this experiment, so individuals are likely to have experienced some competition for resources in all plots. The plots were 50 cm ×50 cm, with data collected from a 25 cm × 25 cm area in the centre, and plots were placed in blocks to control for any non-visible environmental gradient. Hardware cloth was placed around each plot, with bird netting placed over the top. Carbaryl insecticide (active ingredient 1-naphthyl <italic>N</italic>-methylcarbamate, brand SEVIN) was applied weekly with a backpack sprayer at a concentration of 59.1 ml/3.785 L water/92.9 m<sup>2</sup> (2 fl oz/gal water/1000 ft<sup>2</sup>) throughout the growing season. Control plots had hardware cloth placed on the south and west sides to control for the influence of shading while still allowing herbivores to enter the plot, and were sprayed weekly with water to control for any influence of additional water received during pesticide application. The amount of shading and water added to both the pesticide and control plots was minimal, and the plots did not appear any greener than the surrounding landscape, so it is unlikely that shading or watering influenced plants in the study plots.On 1 April 2008, at the end of the growing season, all <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> and <italic>E. texanum</italic> individuals were harvested from each plot. We noted the number of individuals per species per plot, and we counted the number of fruits on each individual plant. Overall biomass was determined by weighing dried plants. To determine whether the number of individuals, the average number of fruits produced by individuals per plot, or the average biomass of individuals per plot varied depending on the block, species, or treatment, we performed separate mixed-model ANOVAs for each dependent variable, with block as a random factor.Our previous physiological measurements in the Sonoran Desert winter annual community indicated that <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> had higher RGR for its given integrated WUE (measured as carbon isotope ratios) than native species, including the congener <italic>E. texanum</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cou006/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Fig. S1</ext-link>). Given that integrated water-use efficiency is an estimate of instantaneous WUE over the lifetime of the leaf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C19">Farquhar <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>), more detailed measures of water loss were necessary to understand whether <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> achieved high WUE through low conductance and/or through high values of carbon assimilation. To determine whether the native and non-native <italic>Erodium</italic> species have differences in their physiology that may explain differences in WUE and RGR, we grew both species in a controlled environment and conducted measurements of growth and water loss.In late January 2009, seeds of non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> and native <italic>E. texanum</italic> were germinated on agar in Petri dishes. When seedlings were 2 weeks old, 24 individuals of each species were transplanted into 164 ml ConeTainer pots (Stuewe &amp; Sons, Inc., Corvallis, OR, USA) filled with a 2:3 mixture of 30-grit silica sand to Sunshine Soil Mix #3. Plants were placed in a single growth chamber set to a daytime high temperature of 21°C, and a night-time low of 5°C, which is close to average for the typical germination months of the winter growing season. After 2 weeks, on 4 February 2009, plants were transferred to the Desert Biome at the University of Arizona's Biosphere 2 facility (daytime high temperature of 19°C and low of 5°C). On 25 February, after all physiological measurements were completed but prior to reproduction, plants were divided into above- and below-ground material and dried at 60°C for 2 weeks to determine total biomass and the ratio of root mass to total biomass (RMR). General linear models were used to determine whether biomass varied depending on the species.Just prior to reproduction, we measured stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) with a Decagon leaf porometer on five individuals of each species at four different times throughout the day (08.30, 10.30, 13:30 and 16:30 h). As only four measurements were taken during the day, stomatal conductance was assumed to be zero at dawn and dusk to integrate under curves with six total time points. To estimate total daily patterns of leaf water exchange with the atmosphere, the trapz function in R was used to evaluate the area under the curve during a 12 h period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C11">Borchers, 2013</xref>). To test whether differences between species in daily water loss characteristics were due to chance, we conducted a permutation test. For each of 1000 permutations, species identities were randomized and daily water loss was estimated as described above. These randomized values were compared with observed values to test whether observed species differences were larger than expected by chance.Using plants grown in natural settings in the field, we performed sequential harvests in 2 years with different rainfall patterns (2004–05 and 2007–08) for both <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> and <italic>E. texanum</italic> to understand how <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> achieved higher growth rates than natives for its given WUE. Summary growth components (e.g. SLA, RMR) during 2004–05 for <italic>E. texanum</italic>, but not <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> (despite its inclusion in the 2004–05 study), were previously reported along with other native members of the winter annual community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C3">Angert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). We repeated this growth analysis during the 2007–08 growing season following the methods presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C3">Angert <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> to determine whether growth of the two species varied depending on environmental conditions that differed between years. We used mixed-model ANCOVAs to analyse RGR (ln-transformed biomass over time). The analysis included ln-transformed biomass as the dependent variable, year (2004–05 vs. 2007–08 growing seasons) and species (<italic>E. cicutarium</italic> vs. <italic>E. texanum</italic>) as categorical variables, and time since germination (plant age) as a covariate. Of key interest is the year-by-species interaction included in the analyses to understand the potential differential performance of the invasive vs. native species across different environmental conditions. The plot from which individuals were collected was included as a random factor. We also tested whether the rate of dry mass increase per unit area (net assimilation rate; NAR) varied depending on age, year, species, or the interaction between year and species, with a similar motivation for interpretation as RGR. Values for RGR and NAR were calculated by linear regression as the slope of ln-transformed biomass through time and ln-transformed mass per leaf area through time.To determine whether components of RGR varied with species, year, or their interaction, we analysed SLA (the ratio of leaf area to dry leaf mass), leaf area ratio (LAR; the ratio of leaf dry mass to total plant dry mass), root:shoot ratio, or leaf mass ratio (LMR; the ratio of leaf dry mass to total plant dry mass) using mixed-model ANOVAs of ln-transformed mid-season values (just prior to reproduction, 95 days after germination in each year). Plot was included as a random factor. We also compared the mid-season relative change in LAR (LAR<sub>95 days after germination</sub> – LAR<sub>53 days after germination</sub>/LAR<sub>53 days after germination</sub>) to determine how species responded to mid-season precipitation in each year. This analysis provided a means to evaluate these two species in terms of the established growth strategies identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C3">Angert <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>, where species in the community were generally divided into those that responded to resource availability by increasing carbon assimilation during cool post-rain conditions (high-WUE species) vs. those that produced large amounts of leaves later in the growing season (high-LAR species). Samples of dried leaf tissue from five individuals of each species in each year were sent to the stable isotope laboratory at University of Arizona for analysis of leaf nitrogen content and carbon isotope ratios. Carbon isotope ratio values were converted to <sup>13</sup>C discrimination values, or Δ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C19">Farquhar <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>). Leaf nitrogen and Δ were analysed by ANOVAs with year, species and the species-by-year interaction as factors.Individuals of non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> and native <italic>E. texanum</italic> were transplanted from the field (the Desert Laboratory at Tumamoc Hill) into pots shortly after germination on 5 and 6 February 2009 and placed in the greenhouse at the University of Arizona. Six different combinations were planted in 4-inch pots containing a 2:3 mixture of 30-grit silica sand to Sunshine Soil Mix #3. The six planting combinations were as follows: (i) <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> planted alone; (ii) <italic>E. texanum</italic> planted alone; (iii) <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> with four individuals of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>; (iv) <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> with four individuals of <italic>E. texanum</italic>; (v) <italic>E. texanum</italic> with four individuals of <italic>E. texanum</italic>; and (vi) <italic>E. texanum</italic> with four individuals of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>. The greenhouse was set to mimic the average daily outdoor temperatures during February and March, which ranged from 20 to 24°C. Each pot received equal amounts of water (∼6 ml in each pot) every day during the initial establishment period and every other day after the first 2 weeks. When plants had finished reproducing at the end of the growing season on 31 March 2009, we recorded the number of seeds produced by each focal plant. Plants were harvested, divided into above-ground and below-ground biomass, dried to a constant mass and weighed.Number of individuals, mean number of fruits and mean mass of <italic>Erodium texanum</italic> (ERTE) and <italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> (ERCI) individuals in control and herbivore exclusion plots. Values are means ± SEM.Biomass and root mass ratio (root mass/total biomass) of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> (ERCI) and <italic>E. texanum</italic> (ERTE) grown in a common environment at the University of Arizona's Biosphere 2 facility in Tucson, AZ, USA. Values are means ± 1 SEM.Instantaneous conductance (top panel) measured with a leaf porometer at four different times during the day on non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> (ERCI) and native <italic>E. texanum</italic> (ERTE) individuals growing in pots at University of Arizona's Biosphere 2 facility. The graph below shows integrated water loss over the course of a day for the two species as estimated from instantaneous measures, with the addition of two zero values at dawn and dusk.Results from mixed-model ANOVAs on growth components of <italic>Erodium cicutarium</italic> and <italic>Erodium texanum</italic> collected from sequential harvests of plants growing in the field during two separate growing seasonsPlot was included as a random factor in all analyses. Relative growth rate (RGR) was analysed as the change in ln-transformed dry biomass over time, while net assimilation rate (NAR) was the change in ln-transformed mass per leaf area through time. Mid-season (95 days after germination) values of specific leaf area (SLA), leaf area ratio (LAR), root-to-shoot ratio and leaf mass ration (LMR) were ln-transformed prior to analysis.Results from ANOVAs testing whether leaf nitrogen and leaf <sup>13</sup>C isotope discrimination (Δ, per mil) varied depending on species, year or the species-by-year interactionRelative growth rate (RGR; measured as the slope of ln-transformed biomass by age), specific leaf area (SLA), change in leaf area ratio (LAR<sub>95 days after germination</sub> – LAR<sub>53 days after germination</sub>/LAR<sub>53 days after germination</sub>) and the ratio of root biomass to shoot biomass for both species in 2 years. Values are means ± 1 SEM. Standard errors are not given for the change in LAR, because that value was calculated from mean values at two different time points.Results of two-way ANOVAs on the relative interaction intensity (RII) calculated for number of seeds, total biomass, above-ground mass or root mass to determine whether the strength of the interaction depended on the species (<italic>E. cicutarium</italic> or <italic>E. texanum</italic>), the competitor (none, <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> or <italic>E. texanum</italic>) or the interaction between species and competitorRelative interaction intensity (RII) for four response variables (root biomass, above-ground biomass, seed set and total biomass) indicating the strength of the interaction between <italic>E. texanum</italic> and <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> individuals in the competition experiment. More negative numbers indicate stronger effects of competition. See Materials and methods for the details on calculation of RII (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C5">Armas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Error bars indicate ±1 SEM.Identification of the mechanisms underlying differential performance of these native and invasive species across years and conditions in our system provides some insight into the challenge of understanding species invasions, particularly because we know the traits that are responsible for multi-decade population and community dynamics in this variable environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C29">Huxman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). It is clear that a novel combination of leaf-level physiological and whole-plant allocation strategies in comparison to the native flora contributes to the invasive success of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> in the Sonoran Desert. The ability of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> to achieve both high leaf-level water-use efficiency and high growth rates is consistent with previous studies suggesting that non-native species exhibited unique trait combinations that enhanced their capacity to outcompete natives in their introduced range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C10">Blumenthal, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C42">Leishman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C49">Molina-Montenegro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C38">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Unique trait combinations of non-native species may be expressed in the native range or may have evolved in the novel range, perhaps due to enemy release (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C57">Thebaud and Simberloff, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C7">Blair and Wolfe, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C12">Bossdorf <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Here, although we did not find support for enemy release, we did find evidence of superior competitive abilities of non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>. The faster growth of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>, along with its success in competition trials, supports numerous other studies in which invasive species exhibited higher growth rates than natives, giving them a competitive advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C50">Pattison <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C17">Daehler, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C41">Leger and Rice, 2003</xref>).The finding that <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> had greater SLA and LAR in 2004–05 suggests greater ability to take advantage of warm and wet periods with high plant density when the growth rate of <italic>E. texanum</italic> is restricted. This ability of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> is consistent with performance patterns we identify in members of the native flora with high RGR and low WUE, in which some species use canopy display as a means to increase growth rate when resources are available, termed ‘morphological responders’ by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C3">Angert <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>. At the same time, the strategy in <italic>E. texanum</italic> that allows for relatively greater performance during the cool periods immediately following winter rains, ‘physiological responders’, is still operational in <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>, as has been seen in the photosynthetic patterns of a number of species in the flora (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C28">Huxman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Thus, it appears that the invasive species in this system employs characteristics from both ends of the spectrum of native species' strategies for dealing with environmental variation, relying on a morphological response when resources are abundant and the physiological capacity to use soil water when it is restricted to cool periods or low amounts.Levels of herbivory did not differ between native <italic>E. texanum</italic> and non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> as would be predicted by the ERH, suggesting that <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> may not be experiencing a release from natural enemies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C33">Keane and Crawley, 2002</xref>). We tested the ERH in only 1 year, and other studies of ERH have reported different results in different years, particularly in variable environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C18">Davis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C1">Agrawal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), but we do not think that this is a problem because we have not previously noticed significant levels of herbivory on <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>, despite 30 years of long-term demographic studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C59">Venable, 2007</xref>). One other, perhaps more serious, problem with our test of the ERH is that we excluded only animal herbivores and did not test for other kinds of enemies, such as fungal and viral pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C47">Mitchell and Power, 2003</xref>). However, we did not notice mortality due to pathogens for any of the annuals in our long-term study plots during the year of this study. There is a fungus that attacks <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C31">Inouye, 1981</xref>), and seed herbivory by rodents influences both <italic>Erodium</italic> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C32">Inouye <italic>et al.</italic>, 1980</xref>), but these enemies influence both native and non-native species and do not support enemy release. The ERH may better explain success of non-native species in high-resource environments, where enemies are more likely to limit growth of natives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C9">Blumenthal, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C10">2006</xref>).Our result that non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> was able to achieve greater overall biomass than native <italic>E. texanum</italic>, despite its lower stomatal conductance, is consistent with the hypothesis that non-natives have higher resource-use efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C22">Funk and Vitousek, 2007</xref>). Other studies comparing physiological traits of natives and co-occurring invasive species have identified several common trait differences of invasive species, including higher SLA, foliar nutrients, carbon assimilation rates and growth rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C6">Baruch and Goldstein, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C22">Funk and Vitousek, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C42">Leishman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). We found no differences between leaf nitrogen values from field-grown plants in two different years. Non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> had higher RGR than native <italic>E. texanum</italic> in a warm year in the field, which occurred in part through greater SLA and LAR. The native species also had slightly lower integrated WUE in that year, although this difference was not significant. Both of the species contrasted here have relatively high long-term WUE relative to other winter annual species in the community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C3">Angert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Our data suggest that they achieve this high WUE in slightly different ways. In a separate experiment, both species had higher carbon assimilation rates and a greater ability to photosynthesize at cooler temperatures relative to other winter annuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C24">Gremer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In the present study, the native <italic>E. texanum</italic> was able to respond to a mid-season rain event in the cool year by increasing LAR more than <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>, perhaps due to its ability to achieve maximal photosynthetic rate at a slightly lower temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C24">Gremer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> exhibited significantly lower stomatal conductance than <italic>E. texanum</italic>, indicating that it is achieving high leaf-level WUE by reducing water loss in addition to investing in carbon assimilation. It appears that, in this system, the ability of non-native species to use resources efficiently does not come at the cost of a reduced ability to grow rapidly when resources are abundant, which is present in the patterns of the remaining species in the community.There is some disagreement as to whether invasive species differ in their resource-use efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C22">Funk and Vitousek, 2007</xref>) or simply tend to have traits that allow for fast growth in high-resource environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C17">Daehler, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C42">Leishman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C43">2010</xref>). In our study system, the two non-natives (<italic>E. cicutarium</italic> and <italic>S. barbatus</italic>) seemed to be more efficient in the way that they used resources (water) and able to achieve higher RGR when resources were abundant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cou006/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Fig. S1</ext-link>). This may be a pattern that is general to all invasive species or it may be a result of these two strategies being so important in the dynamics of Sonoran Desert winter annual plants, given that this system is one of the few in existence where the physiological and growth strategies for the dominant species is well documented in the context of decades of generations of population dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C29">Huxman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Our data suggest that invasive success derives from the combination of these water-use efficiency and growth response strategies in the context of the relative values existing in the local flora rather than the ranking values of either trait syndrome in isolation.Results from our competition experiment indicated that non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> was less impacted by competition than <italic>E. texanum</italic>. Faster RGR of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> may be a factor, because size has been demonstrated to go along with competitive ability in other studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C23">Goldberg and Fleetwood, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C26">Gurevitch <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C61">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C25">Gremer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Invasive species frequently outcompete natives in high-resource conditions similar to those in our greenhouse experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C17">Daehler, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C16">Corbin and D'Antonio, 2004</xref>). It is unclear whether <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> would outcompete <italic>E. texanum</italic> in low-resource conditions as well, but our long-term demographic data indicate that <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> has maintained higher fitness than other winter annual species during dry years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C37">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). From our measurements of growth in two different years, we would predict that non-native <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> would outcompete native <italic>E. texanum</italic> in the field, especially in warm years. Native <italic>E. texanum</italic> may exhibit greater growth in cool years than in warm years, yet this would probably not allow the native species to outcompete <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>.Among-species trade-offs are thought to be important in maintaining diversity in communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C39">Kneitel and Chase, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C2">Agrawal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). It is likely that the ability of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> to grow quickly while simultaneously controlling leaf-level water loss will contribute to instability of the Sonoran Desert winter annual community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C49">Molina-Montenegro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C38">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). There has been a warming and drying of the Sonoran Desert, which has been accompanied by a delayed arrival of germination-triggering rain events, favouring species that germinate at cooler temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C35">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). The increase in abundance of <italic>E. cicutarium</italic>, along with other species at the high-WUE end of the trade-off axis, seems to be due partly to the ability of high-WUE species to germinate in these cooler conditions and partly to their ability to withstand years with high late-season temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C35">Kimball <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C37">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU006C24">Gremer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). This pattern of changing weather conditions suggests that <italic>E. cicutarium</italic> may continue to increase in abundance, probably due to its superior physiological traits.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cou006/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary material is available at <italic>Conservation Physiology</italic> online.</ext-link>We thank J. Horst for assistance with plant propagation and measurement. We thank Lisa Patrick Bentley for assisting with measurements at Biosphere 2 and for discussions related to this manuscript. We thank Anna Tyler for assistance at Biosphere 2. This work was supported by the National Science Foundation [DEB-0924658], by the Philecology Foundation of Fort Worth, TX, USA, and by University of California, Irvine's Center for Environmental Biology, which was founded in 2010 by a grant from Donald Bren and The Irvine Company.