Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> enhances aerobic scope of a coral reef fishComplete intracellular pH protection during extracellular pH depression is associated with hypercarbia tolerance in white sturgeon, <italic>Acipenser transmontanus</italic>Patterns of acid-base regulation during exposure to hypercarbia in fishesAcid–base regulation in fishes: cellular and molecular mechanismsCalibration of a hand-held haemoglobin analyser for use on fish bloodSpecies-specific effects of near-future CO<sub>2</sub> on the respiratory performance of two tropical prey fish and their predatorAcclimation of ion regulatory capacities in gills of marine fish under environmental hypercapniaHypercapnia induced shifts in gill energy budgets of Antarctic notothenioidsA comparison of the equilibrium constants for the dissociation of carbonic acid in seawater mediaEffects of elevated water temperature and food availability on the reproductive performance of a coral reef fishRapid transgenerational acclimation of a tropical reef fish to climate changeThe growing human footprint on coastal and open-ocean biogeochemistryDifferences in thermal tolerance among sockeye salmon populationsImpacts of ocean acidification on respiratory gas exchange and acid–base balance in a marine teleost, <italic>Opsanus beta</italic>The multifunctional fish gill: dominant site of gas exchange, osmoregulation, acid-base regulation, and excretion of nitrogenous wasteCounter-gradient variation in respiratory performance of coral reef fishes at elevated temperaturesThe relationship between oxygen consumption and ion loss in a freshwater fishHigh-frequency dynamics of ocean pH: a multi-ecosystem comparisonFishes in high-CO<sub>2</sub>, acidified oceansTolerance of chronic hypercapnia by the European eel <italic>Anguilla anguilla</italic>The RCP greenhouse gas concentrations and their extensions from 1765 to 2300Swimming performance in Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic>) following long-term (4–12 months) acclimation to elevated seawaterFuture ocean acidification will be amplified by hypoxia in coastal habitatsParental environment mediates impacts of increased carbon dioxide on a coral reef fishIncreased CO<sub>2</sub> stimulates reproduction in a coral reef fishInteracting effects of elevated temperature and ocean acidification on the aerobic performance of coral reef fishesImpact of global warming and rising CO<sub>2</sub> levels on coral reef fishes: what hope for the future?From record performance to hypoxia tolerance: respiratory transition in damselfish larvae settling on a coral reefElevated temperature reduces the respiratory scope of coral reef fishesMS Excel program developed for CO<sub>2</sub> system calculationsPhysiology and climate changeClimate change effects on fishes and fisheries: towards a cause-and-effect understandingThe relationship between gas and ion transfer across the gills of fishesFinding the best estimates of metabolic rates in a coral reef fishPlasma-accessible carbonic anhydrase at the tissue of a teleost fish may greatly enhance oxygen delivery: <italic>in vitro</italic> evidence in rainbow trout, <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>Root effect hemoglobin may have evolved to enhance general oxygen deliveryThermal legacies: transgenerational effects of temperature on growth in a vertebrateTemperature during embryonic development has persistent effects on thermal acclimation capacity in zebrafishAnthropogenic changes to seawater buffer capacity combined with natural reef metabolism induce extreme future coral reef CO<sub>2</sub> conditionsThe influence of swimming activity on water balance in the rainbow trout (<italic>Salmo gairdneri</italic>)<bold>Editor</bold>: Steven CookeBoth authors contributed equally to this project.This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The uptake of anthropogenic CO<sub>2</sub> by the ocean has been suggested to impact marine ecosystems by decreasing the respiratory capacity of fish and other water breathers. We investigated the aerobic metabolic scope of the spiny damselfish, <italic>Acanthochromis polyacanthus</italic>, from the Great Barrier Reef, Australia when exposed for 17 days to CO<sub>2</sub> conditions predicted for the end of the century (946 μatm CO<sub>2</sub>). Surprisingly, resting O<sub>2</sub> consumption rates were significantly lower and maximal O<sub>2</sub> consumption rates significantly higher in high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed fish compared with control fish (451 μatm CO<sub>2</sub>). Consequently, high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed fish exhibited an unexpected increase in absolute (38%) and factorial aerobic scopes (47%). Haematological and muscle water changes associated with exercise were not affected by CO<sub>2</sub> treatment. Thus, contrary to predictions, our results suggest that elevated CO<sub>2</sub> may enhance aerobic scope of some fish species. Long-term experiments are now required to assess the response to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> further, because developmental and transgenerational effects can be dramatic in fish. Ultimately, understanding the variability among species regarding the effects of CO<sub>2</sub> on aerobic scope will be critical in predicting the impacts of ocean acidification on marine communities and ecosystems.Atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> levels are rising, leading to a corresponding increase in CO<sub>2</sub> and a decrease in pH at the ocean surface, a process known as ocean acidification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C11">Doney, 2010</xref>). Future CO<sub>2</sub> levels are expected to impact marine ecosystems widely, because the scope for aerobic performance in fish and other water breathers is predicted to decrease at higher CO<sub>2</sub> levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C30">Pörtner and Farrell, 2008</xref>). Reductions in aerobic scope (the difference between resting and maximal oxygen consumption rates) result in less energy being available for life-history processes, such as growth and reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C9">Donelson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C31">Pörtner and Peck, 2010</xref>). Thus, understanding how elevated CO<sub>2</sub> influences aerobic scope is important for predicting the ecological impacts of ocean acidification on marine ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C18">Ishimatsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C30">Pörtner and Farrell, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C26">Munday <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).Consistent with theoretical predictions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C30">Pörtner and Farrell, 2008</xref>), reduced aerobic scope at near-future CO<sub>2</sub> levels (∼1000 μatm) has been demonstrated in two coral reef cardinalfishes (<italic>Ostorhinchus doederleini</italic> and <italic>Ostorhinchus cyanosoma</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C25">Munday <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). The negative effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> on cardinalfishes may be attributed to the fish living in tropical waters near the upper end of their thermal range, as they are particularly temperature-sensitive species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C15">Gardiner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). However, in other tropical fishes, near-future CO<sub>2</sub> levels appear to have a beneficial or hormetic effect on aerobic performance and life-history traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C24">Miller <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C5">Couturier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Recent studies have even demonstrated a mechanistic basis for enhanced oxygen delivery to tissues in the presence of low levels of hypercapnia that is unique to teleost fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C34">Rummer and Brauner, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C35">Rummer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), but it is unknown how widespread the phenomenon may be. Moreover, at even higher CO<sub>2</sub> levels the benefits may disappear, as indicated by research on Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic>), in which no changes in oxygen consumption rates were observed at CO<sub>2</sub> levels several times higher than end-of-century predictions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C21">Melzner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Likewise, Couturier <italic>et al.</italic> reported that juvenile damselfish (<italic>Pomacentrus amobinensis</italic>) no longer exhibited a higher maximal aerobic capacity at CO<sub>2</sub> levels only moderately higher than end-of-century predictions (at ∼1400–2400 μatm; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C5">Couturier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). In fact, most of the earlier studies on fish exposed to CO<sub>2</sub> levels 5–50 times greater than end-of-century predictions demonstrated no effect on performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C19">McKenzie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C6">Deigweiher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C18">Ishimatsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C1">Baker <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C2">Brauner and Baker, 2009</xref>). Given that the physiological responses observed in fish at near-future CO<sub>2</sub> levels (&lt;1000 μatm) may be different from responses at the extreme CO<sub>2</sub> levels often used in earlier studies (5000 to &gt;50 000 μatm), it is important to test the effects of climate change-relevant CO<sub>2</sub> levels on fish and other marine species to determine if they have generally negative effects, as predicted by theory, or potentially positive effects in some species, as suggested by recent experimental studies.Habitat may also play an important role in determining the sensitivity of a species to increased CO<sub>2</sub>. Fluctuating CO<sub>2</sub> levels are common in coastal marine ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C17">Hofmann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), and coral reef ecosystems may already experience diurnal fluctuations in CO<sub>2</sub> that reach or even exceed the average projected levels for the year 2100 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C22">Melzner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C38">Shaw <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Therefore, some species may already show homeostatic adaptations to frequent CO<sub>2</sub> fluctuations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C19">McKenzie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C18">Ishimatsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C1">Baker <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C2">Brauner and Baker, 2009</xref>) that explain their ability to maintain performance at projected future CO<sub>2</sub> levels. Given that increased uptake of CO<sub>2</sub> by the ocean will affect both the average CO<sub>2</sub> level and the magnitude of extreme CO<sub>2</sub> levels, it is important to consider both physiological sensitivity and the habitat occupied in determining which species will exhibit positive and which species will exhibit negative responses to rising CO<sub>2</sub> levels in the ocean.We tested the effect of surface ocean CO<sub>2</sub> levels projected for 2100 under Representative Concentrations Pathway 8.5 (RCP 8.5 = 936 μatm; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C20">Meinshausen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) on resting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM1" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and maximal O<sub>2</sub> consumption rates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM2" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> to calculate aerobic scope for the spiny damselfish, <italic>Acanthochromis polyacanthus</italic>, a model species for studying climate change impacts on reef fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C27">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C28">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C10">Donelson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In addition to our primary aim, we also measured key haematological and tissue variables to examine the physiological status of CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed fish immediately following exercise to provide insight into the physiological mechanisms that may underlie the effects of CO<sub>2</sub> on aerobic performance.Mean seawater data (±SEM) and range for each treatment (values to nearest integer, one or two decimal places)Aquaria were supplied with seawater at present-day control CO<sub>2</sub> levels (451 μatm) or high-CO<sub>2</sub>-equilibrated seawater (946 μatm). High-CO<sub>2</sub> seawater was achieved by CO<sub>2</sub> dosing a 60 l header tank to a set pH<sub>NBS</sub> (National Bureau of Standards) to match the surface ocean CO<sub>2</sub> level projected for 2100 under RCP 8.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C20">Meinshausen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). A pH controller (Aqua Medic GmbH, Bissendorf, Germany) delivered a steady stream of CO<sub>2</sub> into a powerhead in the bottom of the header tank if the pH rose above the set point. The pH was monitored regularly to ensure that it remained within ±0.05 of desired levels. Individual aquaria received CO<sub>2</sub>-equilibrated seawater from the 60 l header tank at ∼500 ml min<sup>−1</sup>. Control aquaria received seawater from a 60 l header tank diffused with ambient air. The temperature in each aquarium was measured twice daily. Seawater total alkalinity and pH<sub>NBS</sub> for CO<sub>2</sub> calculations were measured from replicate water samples of control and high-CO<sub>2</sub> water taken at the start and end of the experiment. Total alkalinity was estimated by Gran titration using certified reference materials (Dr A. G. Dickson, Scripps Institution of Oceanography). Average seawater partial pressure of CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub>) was calculated using these parameters in CO2SYS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C29">Pierrot <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) using constants from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C8">Dickson and Millero (1987)</xref> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COT023TB1">1</xref>).Intermittent-flow respirometry has been found to provide a reliable estimate of standard or resting metabolic rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C33">Roche <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) and was therefore used to determine resting O<sub>2</sub> consumption rates for eight control and eight high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed fish in CO<sub>2</sub> conditions. Fish were placed individually into 1615 ml, darkened respirometry chambers submerged in a temperature-controlled aquarium (29<bold>°</bold>C) and allowed 90 min to habituate to the chamber. Submersible pumps supplied a constant water flow (900 l h<sup>−1</sup>) from the aquaria through the chambers. In preliminary experiments, we determined that 90 min was ample time to ensure that O<sub>2</sub> consumption rates had reached the lowest possible values, after which O<sub>2</sub> consumption rates did not vary significantly. Thus, at 90 min, the water flow to each chamber was stopped for 15 min every 30 min over a period of 90 min (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cot023/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary material, Fig. S1</ext-link>). The time for which the water flow was interrupted was short enough to ensure that O<sub>2</sub> did not fall below 80% saturation. The temperature-compensated O<sub>2</sub> concentration (in milligrams per litre) of the water within each chamber was continuously recorded (1 s<sup>−1</sup>) using oxygen-sensitive REDFLASH dye on contactless spots (2 mm) adhered to the inside of each chamber and linked to a Firesting Optical Oxygen Meter (Pyro Science e. K., Aachen, Germany) via fibre-optic cables. Data were analysed using LabChart version 6.1.3 (ADInstruments, Colorado Springs, CO, USA). The value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM3" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (in milligrams per kilogram per hour) was calculated from the average of the three slopes of O<sub>2</sub> concentration (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cot023/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary material, Fig. S1</ext-link>), minus the background O<sub>2</sub> consumption, which was measured daily before and at the end of each trial (assumed linear) and did not exceed 5% of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM4" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> of the fish.Following the measurement of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM5" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, fish were held in individual mesh baskets for 1 h and fed <italic>ad libitum</italic> to boost O<sub>2</sub> consumption further. The maximal O<sub>2</sub> consumption rate was then determined in a circular swim respirometer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C27">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). To determine maximal oxygen consumption rates, fish were placed individually into a 1612 ml sealed vertical cylinder submerged in a temperature-controlled aquarium (29<bold>°</bold>C). A water current within the cylinder was created using a magnetic stirring bar and plate (below the cylinder), and the water speed was increased to the maximal speed at which the fish could sustain a steady position (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C27">Nilsson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref> for a diagram and a detailed description of the set-up). Criteria for obtaining the maximal sustained swimming speed at which <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM6" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> could be determined were that the fish had to be swimming against the current using pectoral fins only while maintaining the same position in the cylinder. Increasing the speed of the water current would result in the fish losing position. The decrease in O<sub>2</sub> concentration in the cylinder was monitored with an oxygen probe (WTW OXI 340i, Weilheim, Germany) for up to 7 min, during which time the rate of O<sub>2</sub> decline was stable. Data were analysed offline, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM7" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> was calculated as described above for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM8" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Absolute <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM9" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and factorial aerobic scopes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM10" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> were calculated for each fish.Immediately following the measurment of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM11" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, fish were euthanized by cranial concussion. The caudal fin was severed, blood was collected to analyse haemoglobin, glucose, and lactate concentrations, and epaxial muscle was dissected to calculate the percentage of water in the muscle. Additionally, eight control and eight high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed fish not subjected to respirometry were sampled to determine resting physiological status. Haemoglobin (Hb) concentration in blood was determined using 10 μl of whole blood and the HemoCue<sup>®</sup> Hb 201 System, Australia Pty Ltd, Tumbi Umbi, NSW, Australia and reported as grams per 100 ml and millimolar haemoglobin tetramer (Hb<sub>4</sub>) using calibration curves previously verified on this species and according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C4">Clark <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>. Whole blood glucose and lactate concentrations (millimolar) were determined from two 15 μl samples using the Accutrend<sup>®</sup> Plus (Roche Diagnostics Australia Pty Ltd Dee Why, NSW, Australia). Fulton's body condition factor (<italic>K</italic> = (<italic>W</italic> × 100) × <italic>L</italic><sup>−3</sup>, where <italic>W</italic> is wet mass in grams and <italic>L</italic> is standard length in millimetres) was calculated to assess the length-to-weight ratio. The volume of plasma was insufficient for other analyses <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM12" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (e.g. Cl<sup>−</sup>,, total CO<sub>2</sub>, and catecholamines).Student's paired <italic>t</italic>-tests were used to compare <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM13" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM14" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> between control and high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed fish. Two-way ANOVAs and Holm–Sidak <italic>post hoc</italic> tests were used to compare haematological and tissue parameters between control and high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed fish at rest and post-exercise. Statistical analyses were conducted using SigmaPlot (Systat Software, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).The effect of 17 days of exposure to high-CO<sub>2</sub> on resting and maximal O<sub>2</sub> consumption rates and absolute and factorial aerobic scope in spiny damselfish. (<bold>A</bold>) Resting (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM26" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; filled circles) and maximal oxygen consumption rates (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM27" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>; open circles). (<bold>B</bold>) Absolute aerobic scope <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM28" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. (<bold>C</bold>) Factorial aerobic scope <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM29" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. Values are means ± SEM. Asterisks demarcate significant differences from control values (Student's paired <italic>t</italic>-test).The effect of high CO<sub>2</sub> and maximal swimming on body metrics, blood, and tissue variables of spiny damselfishAbbreviations: [Hb], haemoglobin concentration; n.s., non-significant. Asterisks demarcate significant differences between rest and post-swimming values within a given parameter; there were no effects of CO<sub>2</sub> treatment or interaction between CO<sub>2</sub> treatment and exercise (two-way ANOVA).When exposed to CO<sub>2</sub> levels relevant to end-of-century projections RCP 8.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C20">Meinshausen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) for 17 days, spiny damselfish demonstrated an enhanced aerobic scope compared with control fish, contradicting predictions that elevated CO<sub>2</sub> will reduce aerobic performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C18">Ishimatsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C30">Pörtner and Farrell, 2008</xref>). The response differs from the 47% decrease in aerobic scope observed in coral reef cardinalfishes exposed to similar CO<sub>2</sub> levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C25">Munday <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), as well as the unchanged <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM19" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM20" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> for other teleosts exposed to much higher CO<sub>2</sub> levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C19">McKenzie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C6">Deigweiher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C18">Ishimatsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C21">Melzner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). However, the response found in the present study is similar to the response of another damselfish, juvenile <italic>Pomacentrus amboinensis</italic>, which exhibited a 28–39% increase in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM21" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> at similar CO<sub>2</sub> levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C5">Couturier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Parameters related to blood oxygen-carrying capacity, energy metabolism, and tissue hydration revealed the expected differences between fish at resting and post-swimming, but were not influenced by CO<sub>2</sub> treatment. We discuss potential mechanisms for this unexpected enhancement of performance in conditions of elevated CO<sub>2</sub>.Exposure to very high levels of CO<sub>2</sub> (5000 to &gt;50 000 μatm; 5–50 times higher than in present study) and the associated decrease in seawater pH induce hyperventilation and several physiological modifications at the fish gill, including increases in ion and acid–base regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C14">Evans <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C2">Brauner and Baker, 2009</xref>). Within the first 96 h of exposure to high CO<sub>2</sub>, fish elevate plasma [HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>] via equimolar decreases in [Cl<sup>−</sup>] to counter increased [H<sup>+</sup>] (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C2">Brauner and Baker, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C13">Esbaugh <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Ion exchange occurs largely at the gill, and when the main ion transporters operate at higher rates, rearrangements to energy budgets could result (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C7">Deigweiher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Increased gill energy requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C7">Deigweiher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>) suggest that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM22" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> could increase during high-CO<sub>2</sub> exposure, yet many studies have shown no change in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM23" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C18">Ishimatsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C5">Couturier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Furthermore, in the present study, we observed a decrease in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM24" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> during high-CO<sub>2</sub> exposure, suggesting decreased energy demands. A plasma acidosis is a characteristic response to elevated environmental CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C3">Claiborne <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), but it is important to note that at the climate change-relevant CO<sub>2</sub> levels (946 μatm) in this study, environmental <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> is still likely to be much lower than the plasma <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> of resting fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C13">Esbaugh <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The levels of hypercapnia used here still represent an outward, yet reduced, blood-to-environment CO<sub>2</sub> gradient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C13">Esbaugh <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), but may not be problematic in comparison to higher levels examined in previous studies that would have severely impacted CO<sub>2</sub> diffusion.Compared with control conditions, high-CO<sub>2</sub>-exposed spiny damselfish increased <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="COTIM25" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>. During maximal aerobic exercise, fish can increase functional respiratory surface areas by increasing gill blood perfusion, pressure, and lamellar recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C39">Wood and Randall, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C14">Evans <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). While increasing gill surface area may satisfy increased O<sub>2</sub> requirements, there may be a cost to osmoregulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C32">Randall <italic>et al.</italic>, 1972</xref>). Marine fish increase drinking rates to compensate for water loss over the gills, but may consequently expend more energy excreting excess ions across the gills. This did not appear to be the case in the present study. Here, exercised fish exhibited an increase in muscle water, which may indicate an increase in drinking; however, the response was uniform between control and CO<sub>2</sub> treatment groups. Thus, although the upper limit to aerobic activity may be set by the need to defend ion balance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C16">Gonzalez and McDonald, 1992</xref>), this critical threshold may not have been reached at the CO<sub>2</sub> levels used in this study. Exercising spiny damselfish may be able to afford increases in the functional respiratory surface area of the gill, thereby boosting O<sub>2</sub> uptake, but without significant ion and acid–base disturbances at these low levels of hypercapnia.Whole blood lactate concentrations were also elevated in both control and CO<sub>2</sub>-treated fish post-exercise, with no effect of CO<sub>2</sub>. The finding suggests that both groups of fish were reaching roughly the same aerobic/anaerobic threshold and were potentially exerted to a similar extent. Nevertheless, the fish exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> for 17 days were able to do this while increasing O<sub>2</sub> consumption rates. It may be that exposure to mild hypercapnia, as in this experiment, combined with the stress of exercise resulted in a release of catecholamines into the bloodstream, which has recently been demonstrated in rainbow trout to aid in increasing O<sub>2</sub> uptake and potentially delivery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C34">Rummer and Brauner, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C35">Rummer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Clearly, more research is necessary to understand the mechanisms underpinning the increase in aerobic scope during mild hypercapnia observed here in the spiny damselfish.Contrary to predicted physiological impacts of climate change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C30">Pörtner and Farrell, 2008</xref>), aerobic scope of <italic>A. polyacanthus</italic> was increased upon exposure to predicted end-of-century CO<sub>2</sub> levels. The finding adds to a growing number of studies showing that the effect of increased CO<sub>2</sub> levels on aerobic performance varies dramatically among fish species, ranging from decreasing aerobic performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C25">Munday <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) or no change in aerobic performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C19">McKenzie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C6">Deigweiher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C18">Ishimatsu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C21">Melzner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) to increasing aerobic performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C5">Couturier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). If aerobic scope underpins the performance of fish populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C31">Pörtner and Peck, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C12">Eliason <italic>et al.,</italic> 2011</xref>), ocean acidification could play an important role in altering the relative abundances of species, and thereby ecosystem dynamics and the structure of marine communities, especially in the face of fluctuating CO<sub>2</sub> levels in coastal marine ecosystems. In the light of recent findings of strong developmental and transgenerational acclimation effects in fish exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> and/or temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C23">Miller et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C36">Salinas and Munch, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT023C37">Scott and Johnston, 2012</xref>), it is even more important to understand this variable, perhaps species-specific response in aerobic scope that has important implications for the future structure of marine communities.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cot023/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supplementary material is available at <italic>Conservation Physiology</italic> online.</ext-link>We thank Lizard Island Research Station for excellent research facilities and technical support, as well as Dr A. J. Morash for helpful discussions. This work was supported by the Australian Research Council (P.L.M.); the Australian Research Council Centre of Excellence for Coral Reef Studies (J.L.R., P.L.M.); the University of Oslo and Research Council of Norway (G.E.N., J.A.W.S., C.S.C.); and the United States National Institute of General Medical Sciences of the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">National Institutes of Health</grant-sponsor> (grant number P20GM103395 to J.A.W.S.). The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">National Institutes of Health</grant-sponsor>.