 Developing a new research tool for use in free-ranging cetaceans: recovering cortisol from harbour porpoise skin  Key aspects of analytical method validation and linearity evaluation  Absence of circadian patterns of secretion of melatonin or cortisol in Weddell seals under continuous natural daylight  Measuring environmental stress in East Greenland polar bears, 1892&ndash;1927 and 1988&ndash;2009: what does hair cortisol tell us?  Tracking stress: localization and stability of corticosterone in feathers  Isotope turnover rates and diet&ndash;tissue discrimination in skin of ex situ bottlenose dolphins ( Tursiops truncatus )  Application of ICP-MS to examining the utility of skin as a monitoring tissue for trace elements in bottlenose dolphin,  Tursiops truncatus   Anatomic site and interanimal variability in morphologic characteristics of bottlenose dolphin ( Tursiops truncatus ) skin likely to affect dermal absorption studies  Urinary cortisol sampling: a non-invasive technique for examining cortisol concentrations in the Weddell seal,  Leptonychotes weddellii   Hands-on and hands-off measurement of stress  Review: Minimally invasive sampling media and the measurement of corticosteroids as biomarkers of stress in animals  Analysis of endogenous cortisol concentrations in the hair of rhesus macaques  Decrease stress; train your animals: the effect of handling methods on cortisol levels in harbor porpoises ( Phocoena phocoena ) under human care  Predicting 21st-century polar bear habitat distribution from global climate models  Phylogeography, kinship and molecular ecology of sperm whales ( Physeter macrocephalus )  Stress level in wild harbor porpoises ( Phocoena phocoena ) during satellite tagging measured by respiration, heart rate and cortisol  Review of stress in marine mammals  Stress response of wild bottlenose dolphins ( Tursiops truncatus ) during capture&ndash;release health assessment studies  Isolation and characterization of microsatellite DNA markers for spinner dolphin ( Stenella longirostris )  Seasonal difference of diurnal variations in serum melatonin, cortisol, testosterone, and rectal temperature in Indo-Pacific bottlenose dolphins ( Tursiops aduncus )  Polychlorinated biphenyls and reproductive hormones in female polar bears at Svalbard  Determination of ten steroid hormones in animal waste manure and agricultural soil using inverse and integrated clean-up pressurized liquid extraction and gas chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry  Determination of steroid hormones in blood by GCMS/MS  Skin swabbing for genetic analysis, application on dusky dolphins ( Lagenorhynchus obscurus )  Epidermal growth in the bottlenose dolphin,  Tursiops truncatus   Determination of steroid hormones in whale blow: it is possible  Overcoming the challenges of studying conservation physiology in large whales: a review of available methods  Baleen hormones: a novel tool for retrospective assessment of stress and reproduction in bowhead whales ( Balaena mysticetus )  Rapid separation of lipid classes in high yield and purity using bonded phase columns  Hair cortisol concentration as a noninvasive measure of long-term stress in free-ranging grizzly bears ( Ursus arctos ): considerations with implications for other wildlife  Lipokeratinocytes of the epidermis of a cetacean ( Phocoena phocoena )  Histologic findings in free-ranging Sarasota Bay bottlenose dolphin ( Tursiops truncatus ) skin: mercury, selenium, and seasonal factors  Review of cetacean biopsy techniques: factors contributing to successful sample collection and physiological and behavioral impacts  Diurnal patterns of cortisol and thyroid hormones in the Harbor seal ( Phoca vitulina ) during summer and winter seasons  Salivary cortisol in captive dolphins ( Tursiops truncatus ): a non-invasive technique  Epidermal ultrastructure of the southern right whale calf ( Eubalaena australis )  Structure of the integument of southern right whales  Eubalaena australis   Evidence that ship noise increases stress in right whales  Global mercury and selenium concentrations in skin from free-ranging sperm whales ( Physeter macrocephalus )  Baseline, diurnal variations, and stress-induced changes of stress hormones in three captive beluga whales,  Delphinapterus leucas   A non-invasive technique for analyzing fecal cortisol metabolites in snowshoe hares ( Lepus americanus )  Assessing stress in animal populations: do fecal and plasma glucocorticoids tell the same story?  Steroidogenesis in the skin: implications for local immune functions  Endocrinology  Stress and marine mammals  Adrenal responsiveness to stimulation by adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) in captive beluga whales,  Delphinapterus leucas   Seasonal epidermal moult in beluga whales,  Delphinapterus leucas   Health effects from long-range transported contaminants in Arctic top predators: an integrated review based on studies of polar bears and relevant model species  Tissue healing in two harbor porpoises ( Phocoena phocoena ) following long-term satellite transmitter attachment  Measurement of cortisol in human hair as a biomarker of systemic exposure  Diurnal and annual changes in serum cortisol concentrations in Indo-Pacific bottlenose dolphins  Tursiops aduncus  and killer whales  Orcinus orca   Time allocation and diving behavior of harbor porpoises ( Phocoena phocoena ) in Danish and adjacent waters  Fecal cortisol metabolite analysis for noninvasive monitoring of adrenocortical function in the cheetah ( Acinonyx jubatus )  Cortisol, aldosterone, and leucocytes in the stress response sf bottlenose dolphins,  Tursiops truncatus   Non-invasive multidisciplinary approach to the study of reproduction and calf development in bottlenose dolphin ( Tursiops truncatus ): the Rimini Delfinario experience  Influence of sample degradation and tissue depth on blubber cortisol in beluga whales  Validation of blubber progesterone concentrations for pregnancy determination in three dolphin species and a porpoise  Plasma biochemical values from apparently healthy free-ranging polar bears from Svalbard  Measuring cortisol and DHEA in fingernails: a pilot study  Assessing individual systemic stress through cortisol analysis of archaeological hair  Do marine mammals experience stress related to anthropogenic noise?  Present address: George Mason University, Department of Environmental Science and Policy, 400 University Drive, Fairfax, VA 22030, USA.  Present addresses: Department of Integrative Biology, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720, USA and Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720, USA.  Present address: School of Education and Environment, Division of Natural Sciences, Kristianstad University, SE-291, 88 Kristianstad, Sweden.   Editor:  Steven Cooke  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  In this paper we present a new analytical method that allows the extraction of the stress hormone cortisol from naturally sloughed cetacean skin cells. Skin cortisol is unaffected by short-term cortisol fluctuations and could thus be used to assess chronic stress levels in cetaceans.  We developed a chemical analytical procedure for sampling, extracting and determining epidermal skin cortisol concentrations (SCCs) in the harbour porpoise ( Phocoena phocoena ) using gas chromatography&ndash;tandem mass spectrometry. In brief, this involved a pressurized liquid extraction with a two-step solid-phase clean-up. A derivatization step was conducted prior to detection. To evaluate the new assay, cortisol was analysed in three different sample types obtained from four harbour porpoises: skin plates, dorsal fin skin plugs (with and without lidocaine) and epidermal scrapes. Skin cortisol concentrations could be measured using the new assay in the majority of the tested skin samples down to a minimal sample size of 49 mg dry weight (dw). Water content ranged from 10 to 46&percnt; in the plug samples, which had SCCs from 2.1 to 77.7 ng/g dw. Epidermal scrape samples had the highest water content (83&ndash;87&percnt;) and lower SCCs (0.6&ndash;15 ng/g dw), while the skin plates had intermediate water contents (60&ndash;66&percnt;) and SCCs of 2.6&ndash;13.0 ng/g dw. SCC was slightly higher in plugs with lidocaine than without (average values of 41 and 33 ng/g dw, respectively). Substantial within-individual variations in cortisol concentrations are also common in other matrices such as blood and hair. Some important factors behind this variation could be e.g. the animal&apos;s sex, age, body condition, reproductive stage, and the body region sampled, as well as season, moulting cycles and water temperature. Clearly, more research into SCCs is required. The findings described here represent the first critical steps towards using epidermal skin cell samples to assess chronic stress levels in cetaceans and the development of a widely applicable health-assessment tool in these species.  Marine mammals face numerous anthropogenic stressors, including chemical pollution, underwater noise and climate change, the combined consequences of which are often difficult to assess ( Durner  et al. , 2009 ;  MMC, 2009 ;  Wright, 2009 ;  Sonne, 2010 ). Chronically stressful situations have been shown to affect the general state of marine mammal health in various ways; these include, but are not limited to, impaired immune function, increased mortality and reduced production of offspring ( Fair and Becker, 2000 ;  St Aubin and Dierauf, 2001 ;  Sonne, 2010 ). In most mammals, cortisol is the dominant circulating glucocorticoid associated with a stress response and is typically measured in blood samples ( St Aubin, 2001 ). However, baseline blood concentrations can be difficult to ascertain owing to short-term natural diurnal and seasonal fluctuations ( Barrell and Montgomery, 1989 ;  Suzuki  et al. , 2003 ;  Oki and Atkinson, 2004 ). Furthermore, the acute stress response associated with capture, handling and sampling, especially in wild animals, is itself reflected in the blood within minutes ( Cook  et al. , 2000 ;  Eskesen  et al. , 2009 ;  Fair  et al ., 2014 ). The cortisol peak caused by such an acute stressor may potentially obscure baseline values or overshadow any effects on cortisol concentrations resulting from exposure to other (longer-term) stressors. These difficulties are enhanced in free-ranging marine mammals, where many species are simply too difficult or too large to capture or handle. Consequently, several forums have identified the pressing need for more suitable methods of assessing stress responses, and chronic stress in particular, in marine mammals (e.g.  Wright  et al. , 2007 ;  ONR, 2009 ).  This has led to a growing interest in several promising new cortisol matrices in marine mammals, including vibrissae, hair, urine, saliva, baleen and faeces ( Constable  et al. , 2006 ;  Pedernera-Romano  et al. , 2006 ;  Bechsh&oslash;ft  et al. , 2012 ;  Rolland  et al. , 2012 ;  Fair  et al.  2014 ;  Hunt  et al.  2014 ). Whale blow may also be a potential candidate ( Hogg  et al. , 2009 ;  Tizzi  et al. , 2010 ;  Dunstan  et al. , 2012 ). Keratinous materials, such as vibrissae and hair, have been shown to be feasible indicators of chronic stress responses ( Cook, 2012 ). Unfortunately, these two matrices are of little use when assessing chronic stress in cetaceans, because these species have little (if any) hair as adults. However, all other currently available minimally invasive matrices, such as faeces, may only be used to assess short-term cortisol fluctuations over extended time periods ( Terio  et al ., 1999 ;  Suzuki  et al ., 2003 ;  Pedernera-Romano  et al ., 2006 ;  Desportes  et al ., 2007 ;  Sheriff  et al ., 2009 ,  2010 ;  Schmitt  et al ., 2010 ;  Funasaka  et al ., 2011 ;  Cook, 2012 ). Unfortunately, the collection of such samples from animals in the wild is opportunistic at best (e.g.  Rolland  et al. , 2012 ). Thus, no reliable methods currently exist for assessing cortisol at baseline levels or over the longer term in free-ranging cetaceans. Such methods would preferably involve matrices that reflect chronic, not acute, cortisol concentrations and, ideally, also be minimally invasive to avoid handling/sampling artifacts.  Considering this, expert discussions have highlighted skin (epidermis) as a potential alternative hormone matrix (e.g.  Wright  et al. , 2007 ;  ONR, 2009 ). Cetacean epidermal cells have previously been used for genetic, diet and contaminant studies (e.g. heavy metals and trace elements;  Hunt  et al. , 2013 ;  Savery  et al. , 2013 ;  Browning  et al. , 2014 ), but never for assessment of hormones. Hormones have, however, been found in cetacean blubber ( Trego  et al. , 2013 ;  Trana  et al. , 2015 ), a matrix closely associated with skin.  Cortisol released into the bloodstream following an acute stressor (e.g. capture) would not be anticipated to enter the skin matrix for days or even weeks ( Hicks  et al. , 1985 ;  Browning  et al. , 2014 ). Thus, cortisol in cetacean skin is expected to reflect levels of chronic stress. Validation of this statement is still required, but if found to be true, skin samples could provide information on long-term physiological status in cetaceans in terms of chronic stress. Furthermore, cetacean skin samples can be obtained in non- or at least minimally invasive ways ( Noren and Mocklin, 2012 ). In fact, cetacean skin samples for DNA analyses have already been collected non-invasively and without direct handling of the animal using green kitchen scourers, although with mixed success ( Harlin  et al. , 1999 ; but see also  Farro  et al ., 2008 ).  Accordingly, the main aim of this study was to develop a chemical analytical procedure for sampling, extracting and determining epidermal skin cortisol concentrations (SCCs) in the harbour porpoise ( Phocoena phocoena ) by use of gas chromatography&ndash;tandem mass spectrometry (GC-MS/MS).  Skin cortisol concentration (in nanograms per gram dry weight) as measured in skin samples from harbour porpoises ( Phocoena phocoena )  Abbreviations: dw, dry weight; LOD, limit of detection; NA, not available.  a &plusmn;1.5 corresponds to 11.6&percnt; (relative standard deviation).  b Signal-to-noise ratio &lt;3.  c Missing internal standard.  ( a ) Outline of a harbour porpoise ( Phocoena phocoena ) with indications of sampling locations of skin plates and biopsy plugs taken from dead bycaught animals in Danish waters and used in the development of the skin cortisol analysis method presented in this study. The shaded square area indicates the location of the skin plate, 10 cm&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;10&emsp14;cm in size. Points 1&ndash;3 indicate the approximate locations of the 6&emsp14;mm biopsies. ( b ) Outline of a harbour porpoise ( P. phocoena ) indicating where alongside the animal&apos;s left and right side non-invasive skin sampling devices were used to collect samples of sloughed skin cells. (Porpoise outline adapted from the Wikimedia Commons file &lsquo;Harbor_porpoise_size.svg&rsquo;.)  Prior to commencing this project, several non-invasive skin sampling techniques had been tested on nine free-ranging harbour porpoises caught in pound nets in Danish waters and handled in the ongoing tagging project there ( Teilmann  et al. , 2007 ). Sampling involved simply running one of the various sterilized collection devices along each side of each animal once using single, not overly forceful strokes that were easy to replicate (Fig.  1 b). The devices tested were as follows: (i) a green kitchen sccourer; (ii) a plastic laboratory tube; (iii) P40 and P80 grit emery cloth; and (iv) a rubberized ice scraper ( Supplementary material Fig. 1 ). For reasons discussed in detail in the results section of the paper, the ice scraper was the only one of these tested devices to yield sufficient epidermal skin samples. The collected samples ultimately used here were transported on dry ice (&minus;70&deg;C) and stored in a &minus;20&deg;C freezer for 8 or 11 months (for IDs 2012/60022 and 47501, respectively) before analysis. No plugs taken for the purpose of tagging were used in this study.  To evaluate the new assay, cortisol was analysed in three different skin samples: those obtained by the minimally invasive use of a rubberized ice scraper; the dorsal fin plugs taken during simulated tagging procedures on lethally bycaught animals (with or without prior application of lidocaine); and the skin plates, also from the lethally bycaught animals. Sample size [dry weight (dw)] and water content of these samples are shown in Table  1 . Plug 1 was analysed on its own, while plugs 2 and 3 were pooled to test for potential effects of an increased sample size (lidocaine-covered samples and clean samples were analysed separately).  The method developed was initially based on the work of  Hansen  et al . (2011a) , in which three steroid hormone classes were extracted and analysed from environmental matrices (i.e. soil and animal manure). We believed this method to be adaptable because we expected that cortisol would have similar physicochemical properties to those steroid hormone classes and that cetacean skin would have a high lipid content, much like the environmental matrices analysed.  Cortisol with an analytical purity &gt;96&percnt; was used in calibration, optimization and method development studies. As a part of our quality assurance and quality control scheme, a derivatization quality control standard (DCS), 17&beta;-estradiol-17-acetate (purity &gt;99&percnt;), and an instrument control standard (ICS), estrone-3-methyl ether (purity &gt;99&percnt;), were added to each sample. All three compounds were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (Glostrup, Denmark). The deuterated analogue of cortisol, d 4 -cortisol (purity &gt;98&percnt;; Toronto Research Chemicals, Ontario, Canada), was applied to all samples as an internal standard (IS). All organic solvents were of high-performance liquid chromatography grade, with a purity &gt;99.5&percnt;. The derivatization reagents  N -methyl- N -trimethylsilyl-trifluoroacetamide (MSTFA),  N -trimethylsilylimidazole (TMSI) and 1,4-dithioerythritol (DTE) were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (Glostrup, Denmark). The derivatization mixture consisted of 1000&emsp14;&mu;l MSTFA, 50&emsp14;&mu;l of a 40&emsp14;&micro;g&emsp14;&micro;l &minus;1  DTE pyridine dilution and 2&emsp14;&mu;l TMSI. Cortisol, IS, DCS and ICS were all dissolved in methanol in separate volumetric glass flasks to produce stock solutions of &sim;100&emsp14;ng&emsp14;&micro;l &minus;1 . Moreover, working dilutions in methanol were prepared from these stock solutions. Helium was used as the carrier gas and argon as the collision gas in the GC-MS/MS process.  Method development was performed using 10&emsp14;cm&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;10&emsp14;cm skin plates, a size chosen to ensure sufficient material for the exploratory use. In skin plate and plug samples, only the 2&emsp14;mm top layer of epidermal cells was used to ensure that no blubber was included in the analysis. For the scrape samples, the epidermal cells were used as they were collected. Water content and dry weight were then determined by weighing samples before and after 24&emsp14;h of lyophilization using a freeze dryer (FD3; Heto Lab equipment, Aller&oslash;d, Denmark) operating at &minus;48&deg;C and 1&emsp14;Pa (10 &minus;5 &emsp14;bar).  As mentioned above, the pressurized liquid extraction (PLE) extraction procedure used was adapted from a method for measuring cortisol in animal manure and agricultural soil ( Hansen  et al ., 2011a ), using the ASE 200 PLE system (Dionex, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). Prior to extraction, 22&emsp14;ml PLE stainless-steel cells were packed with 1&emsp14;g activated silica gel (particle size 0.063&ndash;0.100&emsp14;mm mesh; Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) and 1&emsp14;g diatomaceous earth (DE; Dionex). Furthermore, sample tissue was mixed with 1&emsp14;g activated DE and ground in a mortar before being applied to the cell. Silica gel and DE were activated for 24&emsp14;h at 105&deg;C before use. A single cellulose filter (size 19.8&emsp14;mm; Dionex) was applied at the bottom and at the top of the cell. Cortisol was extracted using a methanol and acetone mixture (1:1, v/v) at 1500&emsp14;psi and 80&deg;C with a 5&emsp14;min preheat followed by two 5&emsp14;min static extraction cycles with 60&percnt; flush volume and 120&emsp14;s purge period.  The crude PLE extracts were subjected to a two-step clean-up process to reduce matrix components that may interfere with the sensitive GC-MS/MS system ( Hansen  et al ., 2011b ).The first step used an amino-propyl column (NH 2 , 500&emsp14;mg amino-propyl SPE cartridge; Waters Sep-pak, Dublin, Ireland), which had been preconditioned twice, each time using 2 ml  n -heptane, to remove fatty acids and phospholipids ( Kaluzny  et al. , 1985 ). The PLE extracts were evaporated close to dryness (&sim;1&ndash;2&emsp14;ml left in the vials) at 60&deg;C under a gentle stream of N 2  with circular motions. Two millilitres of isopropanol was added to the vial and evaporated close to dryness a second time. After this, a second aliquot of 2&emsp14;ml of isopropanol was added, and the mix once again evaporated close to dryness, before 100&emsp14;&mu;l CHCl 3  was added to the vials and the extracts transferred to the preconditioned NH 2  column. The vials were then washed with 200&emsp14;&mu;l CHCl 3 :isopropanol (2:1,v/v), to ensure a quantitative transfer of the analyte from the vials to the column. Finally, the steroid hormones were re-extracted from the column using 5&emsp14;ml CHCl 3 : isopropanol (2:1, v/v).  The second clean-up step for separating the steroid hormones from lipids (such as mono-, di- and triglycerides, sterols, stanols and cholesterols) required a silica gel SPE column consisting of a 3&emsp14;ml glass column (LiChrolut; Merck, Darmstadt, Germany), a cellulose filter and 1&emsp14;g activated silica gel soaked in  n -heptane ( Hansen  et al. , 2011a ,  b ). The extracts from the first step were evaporated to dryness and reconstituted in 50&emsp14;&mu;l CHCl 3  and 450&emsp14;&mu;l  n -heptane before being loaded into the silica gel column. The vials were washed with 500&emsp14;&mu;l  n -heptane to ensure quantitative transfer. The gel columns were then flushed with 5&emsp14;ml  n -heptane followed by 10&emsp14;ml  n -heptane:acetone (90:10, v/v). Hereafter, androgens, estrogens and progestagens were eluted with 5&emsp14;ml  n -heptane:acetone (65:35, v/v;  Hansen  et al. , 2011a ). One final flush in 5&emsp14;ml methanol was used to extract the more polar hormones, such as the corticosteroids, including cortisol.  The purified extract was evaporated to dryness and transferred to a GC-vial with a 300&emsp14;&mu;l insert using two times 100&emsp14;&mu;l methanol. Next, 100&emsp14;&mu;l 0.2&emsp14;ppm DCS solution was added, and the purified extract was evaporated to dryness using N 2  as described in the previous subsection. The steroid hormones were derivatized using 50&emsp14;&mu;l derivatization reagent mixture (1000&emsp14;&mu;l MSTFA, 50&emsp14;&mu;l DTE dilution and 2&emsp14;&mu;l TMSI) at 60&deg;C for 1&emsp14;h. The extract was then reconstituted in 200&emsp14;&mu;l 0.1&emsp14;ppm ICS  n -heptane solution ( Hansen  et al. , 2011a ).  A Bruker Scion&trade; TQ hyphenated system (EI interface; Bruker Daltonik, Bremen, Germany) with a GC PTV-injector and a Zebron-5HT Inferno column (30&emsp14;m&emsp14;&times;&emsp14;0.25&emsp14;mm, 0.25&emsp14;&mu;m; Phenomenex Inc., Torrance, CA, USA) was used to determine SCC. A sample size of 10&emsp14;&mu;l was injected with a solvent-split/splitless PTV-program starting at 120&deg;C and kept in the injector for 0.30&emsp14;min (glass split liner with a glass frit; Varian Inc., Palo Alto, CA, USA) before it was subjected to a temperature ramp of 200&deg;C/min to 325&deg;C, where the temperature was held for 11.50&emsp14;min. The column oven temperature programme was set at 150&deg;C for the first 2&emsp14;min, before increasing the temperature to 230&deg;C (25&deg;C/min); this temperature was maintained for 3.7&emsp14;min. The total run time was 30&emsp14;min, during which a constant carrier gas flow of 1.0&emsp14;ml/min helium was applied. The triple-quadrupole mass spectrometer was operated in positive electron ionization mode using selected reaction monitoring mode with argon as the collision gas. The optimized ion transitions and collision energies were 578.4&emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;331.1 (collision energy 10&emsp14;V), 578.4&emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;374.2 (collision energy 10&emsp14;V) and 578.4&emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;432.2 (collision energy 30&emsp14;V) for cortisol. The IS, d 4 -cortisol, yielded two transitions: 582.4&emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;311.1 (collision energy 18&emsp14;V) and 582.4&emsp14;&gt;&emsp14;378.4 (collision energy 5&emsp14;V). A reference chromatogram is displayed in  Supplementary material Fig. 3 .  The assay described above was then subjected to a PLE optimization and recovery experiment, to determine absolute recovery and relative recovery rates, as well as a standard addition experiment (see  Supplementary material ). The primary reason for using GC-MS/MS instead of a radioimmunoassay when measuring SCCs was the hope that the newly developed method can later be expanded to cover more glucocorticoid hormones (which would not all be measurable by using radioimmunoassay). In addition, this method should avoid the cross-reactivity that is frequently observed when using radioimmunoassays.  Initially, the absolute recovery of each step in the method was found, followed by a determination of full assay absolute and relative recovery using a pre- and postspike approach. Full assay and instrument variation were based on the d 4 -cortisol peak area. Experimental details of this as well as of the GC-MS and derivatization procedure, the PLE-optimization and recovery experiment and the standard addition tests can be found in the  Supplementary material .  We aimed to obtain an optimal 100&percnt; absolute recovery when analysing skin samples, but were able to achieve only 20.6&percnt; for cortisol and 20.1&percnt; for the internal standard (d 4 -cortisol) when spiked at 100&emsp14;ng per sample. While not ideal, this is a sufficient recovery rate for use in a new analysis method with no other contemporaries. In any case, and more importantly, we found an impressive relative recovery rate of 102.4&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;10.5&percnt; when using d 4 -cortisol as an internal correction standard for cortisol ( Supplementary material ).  In the standard addition experiment, the native cortisol concentration was determined in triplicate from a homogenized sample, subdivided into three aliquots (sample sizes of 306&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;3&emsp14;mg dw). The endogenous concentration of cortisol was 13.0&emsp14;ng/g, with an assay repeatability of 11.6&percnt; (relative standard deviation,  n &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;3). Furthermore, one sample was injected three times to determine instrument repeatability for cortisol and d 4 -cortisol. The peak area variations (relative standard deviation) were 2.7 and 1.7&percnt; for cortisol and d 4 -cortisol, respectively, in the skin samples containing 306&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;3&emsp14;mg dw. Given that no skin reference material was available, the limits of detection (LODs) were evaluated visually based on signal-to-noise ratios. The instrument LOD and limit of quantification (LOQ) in neat standards were calculated using a cortisol calibration curve with a linier dynamic range of a cortisol standard curve from 2.5&emsp14;ppb to 2.5&emsp14;ppm and a  r  2  of 0.9978. The calculated instrument LOD and LOQ were 37 and 113&emsp14;ppb, respectively ( Araujo, 2009 ).  Of the devices tested, only the ice scraper consistently collected enough material (sample size of &ge;49&emsp14;mg&emsp14;dw,  n &emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;4, two each from two tagged male porpoises, ID 47501 and ID 2012/60022; Table  1 ) that could be easily extracted for the ensuing analysis. The samples collected via the other techniques were more variable in size (and would thus require multiple strokes to be assured of reaching the critical sample size of &ge;49&emsp14;mg&emsp14;dw) and, with the exception of the plastic tube, harder to extract from the collection devices.  Cortisol could be measured using the new assay in 79&percnt; of the tested skin samples, reliably down to the limit seen in this study of 49&emsp14;mg&emsp14;dw in one clean plug sample (14 samples in total, out of which two were below the LOD and one was not available owing to missing internal standard; see Table  1 ). The instrument control standard deviated &lt;10&percnt; within batch, and the derivatization reaction was to completion (99&percnt; or higher) in all skin samples. The signal-to-noise ratio of d 4 -cortisol was &gt;30 in every sample except for one (47501 left), where d 4 -cortisol could not be detected. Water content in the plug samples ranged from 10 to 46&percnt; and the SCCs from 2.1 and 77.7&emsp14;ng/g&emsp14;dw. The skin scrape samples had the highest water content (83&ndash;87&percnt;) and lower concentrations of cortisol (0.6&ndash;15&emsp14;ng/g&emsp14;dw), while the two skin plates had water contents and SCCs of 60 and 66&percnt; and 2.6 and 13.0&emsp14;ng/g&emsp14;dw, respectively. Measured SCCs were slightly higher in plugs with lidocaine than without, with average values of 41 and 33&emsp14;ng/g&emsp14;dw, respectively.  Cortisol concentration could be determined in all plug samples of sufficient size (&ge;49&emsp14;mg&emsp14;dw), including those treated with lidocaine. Use of the rubberized ice scraper provided sufficient sample material for the assay as described here. Accordingly, it is clearly possible to obtain samples from any smaller cetacean already in hand, for example in connection with tagging, disentanglement efforts or health assessments (although it should be noted that collection of skin prior to direct handling at the sample site is advised because direct handling may result in loss of sloughed skin cells and thus a considerably smaller scraper sample). Although remote skin collection was not attempted here, it may also be possible to collect sufficient samples of skin naturally sloughed by larger cetaceans at sea ( Harlin  et al. , 1999 ;  Engelhaupt, 2004 ). Skin biopsy punches from tissue banks could also be used as source material, which would enable retrospective temporal studies. Cortisol has proved highly stable in other keratinous matrices ( Bortolotti  et al. , 2009 ;  Warnock  et al. , 2010 ;  Webb  et al. , 2010 ), so it is entirely possible that even relatively old frozen skin samples (even if lipokeratinocytic in nature;  Menon  et al. , 1986 ;  Pfeiffer and Rowntree, 1996 ;  Reeb  et al. , 2007 ) could provide useful analysis material.  Considerable differences in measured SCCs were observed both between and within sample types (Table  1 ). However, substantial differences in inter-individual cortisol concentrations are commonly observed in other matrices, such as blood and hair ( Tryland  et al. , 2002 ;  Haave  et al. , 2003 ;  Davenport  et al. , 2006 ;  Suav&eacute;  et al. , 2007 ;  Eskesen  et al. , 2009 ). Although we do not know whether this is the case in the present study, such differences can be dependent on factors such as the animal&apos;s sex, age, body condition, reproductive stage and which body region is sampled, as well as season, moulting cycles and water temperature ( St Aubin  et al. , 1990 ;  Suzuki  et al. , 2003 ;  Macbeth  et al. , 2010 ;  Funasaka  et al. , 2011 ).  Water content in the samples may also play a role. Differences between the scrape samples were already visible to the naked eye during the clean-up process of the analysis ( Supplementary material   Fig. 2 ), with the colour of these samples ranging from clear to yellow and green. This difference in colour was not observed between the plug samples. It is also possible that the presence of algae (or other interfering compounds) may potentially be increasing the weight of the sample and thus influencing the concentration calculation. Although the low sample size should again be kept in mind here, this could be another potential factor in the observed variation in scrape SCCs.  As evident in Table  1 , a single clean plug from a sampled animal yielded enough material to provide a cortisol reading. However, this was not the case for the single lidocaine-treated plugs. Whether this was due to the lidocaine or to the lower sample weight of the lidocaine-treated plugs remains to be resolved. It was not possible to fully determine whether lidocaine application compromised the assay. However, the finding that the SCC values obtained from the various plug samples for any given animal were much closer to each other than to the SCC value of that animal&apos;s skin plate suggests that the analgesic had little, if any, effect.  Another possible cause of some of the observed differences is that the plugs were from dead animals, while the scrapes were from live animals. However, given that the concentrations in the skin plate were closer to the flank scrapes (Table  1 ), we believe that it is more likely that the differences observed are due to natural variation between body regions (keeping in mind that there could also potentially be variations in cortisol over the length of the flank scrape itself). Such intra-individual differences between body regions have also been reported elsewhere and are likely to relate to diversity in physiological parameters, such as epidermal cell growth rates, degree of vascularization and variations in epidermal thickness ( Colbert  et al. , 1998 ;  Bryan  et al. , 2010 ;  Miller  et al. , 2011 ). Choice of cetacean body region(s) to be sampled in further SCC studies should thus be considered carefully.  The present study describes an analytical method for quantifying cortisol in harbour porpoise epidermal skin cells. In addition, it documents that cortisol concentrations can be assessed in a range of different harbour porpoise skin samples. Based on the methodology described here, ensuing studies should investigate questions such as whether other hormones can be measured in cetacean skin and whether SCC is related to other hormones, such as aldosterone, which also appears to be of importance in the cetacean stress response ( Thomson and Geraci, 1986 ;  St Aubin and Geraci, 1990 ;  Fair  et al. , 2014 ). Another question is whether SCC reflects only adrenal activity or whether some of the cortisol is locally derived (as has been shown in other mammals;  Slominski  et al. , 2013 ). This will require, at least in part, an exploration of the relationship between blood cortisol concentration and SCC. A study by  Trego  et al.  (2013)  lends credibility to the existence of biologically relevant concentrations of hormones in skin as their study linked progesterone in blubber, a matrix very closely associated with skin, with pregnancy in four different species of cetaceans.  Besides these questions, the essential next step in the use of SCCs is a physiological validation to determine the biological relevance of the SCC values obtained and how long the hormonal response to an acute stressor takes to get into, and persist within, the skin matrix. Importantly, there is also a need to understand how hormones carried in the bloodstream are incorporated into the skin matrix; by diffusion or by simple cell renewal.  Browning  et al.  (2014)  found that isotope signatures took 14&ndash;23 days before their signal was detectable in the epidermis of bottlenose dolphins, while  Hicks  et al.  (1985)  found the skin cell renewal rate in bottlenose dolphins to be somewhat slower than that, with 99&percnt; of the [6- 3 H]-thymidine-labelled skin cells reaching the epidermis by day 22 after injection.  In addition, the relationship between blood cortisol concentrations and cortisol concentrations measured in the skin samples must be assessed, and basal cortisol concentrations and any inter- or intra-individual fluctuations must be evaluated. Finally, as discussed above, studies of the potential influence on SCC of basic variables, such as body region, sex, age, reproductive status and season, are also required in order to assess the further uses of cetacean skin in stress-related research. The present study provides a basis for these further investigations. Despite the outstanding questions, the findings described here represent the first critical steps towards the use of epidermal skin to assess chronic stress levels in cetaceans. The potential use of cortisol obtained from cetacean skin samples as a measure for chronic stress in these species has widespread management implications. As managers gain greater appreciation of the role of stress responses in mediating cumulative impacts, the potential exists for SCC to become a powerful tool for monitoring the general health of various cetacean populations.   Supplementary material is available at  Conservation Physiology  online .  The analyses presented here were funded in part by the  Office of Naval Research  [grant no.  N000141210896 ], the  Aage V. Jensen Foundation ,  Humane Society International  and  OceanCare . The authors thank each organization for their interest and support.  The authors would like to thank everyone at Fjord &amp; B&aelig;lt for their advice and suggestions regarding the selection of sampling methods and techniques. We would also like to thank all those involved in the collection of samples, which made this project possible. Specifically, we thank the various fishermen and scientists involved in the Danish tagging programme. All samples included in this project were obtained during the ongoing harbour porpoise studies under authorization from Danish Forest and Nature Agency (SNS 342-00042) and the Animal Welfare Committee (Ministry of Justice, 2010/561-1801). 