Cytogenetic characterization and genome size of the medicinal plant <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (L.) G. DonLocalization and activity of rRNA genes on fenugreek (<italic>Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic> L.) chromosomes by fluorescent in situ hybridization and silver stainingA karyological survey of Asclepiadoideae, Periplocoideae, and Secamonoideae, and evolutionary considerations within Apocynaceae s.l.A drop-spreading technique to produce cytoplasm-free mitotic preparations from plants with small chromosomesBiosystematic studies on the genus <italic>Catharanthus</italic> Linn. (Apocynaceae)Molecular cloning and characterization of a vacuolar class III peroxidase involved in the metabolism of anticancer alkaloids in <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic>Changes induced by mycoplasma-like organisms (M.L.O.), etiologic agents of the Stolbur disease in the different tissues of the anther of <italic>Vinca rosea</italic> L<italic>.</italic> (Apocynaceae)Nuclear genome size: are we getting closer?Nuclear DNA content and genome size of trout and humanCytogenetics for the model system <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Rapid flow cytometric analysis of the cell cycle in intact plant tissuesAnalysis of nuclear DNA content and ploidy in higher plantsObservation on the chromosome numbers of medicinal plants of Shandong Province (II)Cloning and characterization of ribosomal-RNA genes from wheat and barleyA draft sequence of the rice genome (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>)G- and R-banded prometaphase karyotypes in cattle (<italic>Bos taurus</italic> L.)Towards resolving the <italic>Knautia arvensis</italic> agg. (Dispsacaceae) puzzle: primary and secondary contact zones and ploidy segregation at landscape and microgeographic scalesGenome size dynamics and evolution in monocotsChromosome numbers and genome size variation in Indian species of <italic>Curcuma</italic> (Zingiberaceae)Nomenclature for centromeric position on chromosomesMolecular cytogenetic analyses and phylogenetic studies in the <italic>Nicotiana</italic> section TomentosaeFlow cytometric and microscopic analysis of the effect of tannic acid on plant nuclei and estimation of DNA contentTwo new nuclear isolation buffers for plant DNA flow cytometry: a test with 37 speciesPlant flow cytometry—far beyond the stone ageChromosome observations of some medical plants in XinjiangA cytometric exercise in plant DNA histograms, with 2C-values for 70 speciesThe leaf epidermome of <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> reveals its biochemical specializationThe <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> genome and the diversification of grassesGene-to-metabolite networks for terpenoid indole alkaloid biosynthesis in <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> cellsThe B73 maize genome: complexity, diversity, and dynamicsThe Vinca alkaloids: from biosynthesis and accumulation in plant cells, to uptake, activity and metabolism in animal cellsAnalysis of the genome sequence of the flowering plant <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>The <italic>Catharanthus</italic> alkaloids: pharmacognosy and biotechnologyDraft genome sequence of pigeonpea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic>), an orphan legume crop of resource-poor farmersBiology and biochemistry of <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (L.) G. DonA draft sequence of the rice genome (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. ssp. <italic>indica</italic>)First nuclear DNA amounts in more than 300 angiospermsThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The genome size and organization of the important medicinal plant <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> is shown to correspond to 1C = 0.76 pg (~738 Mbps) and 2n = 16 chromosomes. The data  provide a sound basis for future studies including cytogenetic mapping, genomics and breeding.<italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> is a highly valuable medicinal plant producing several terpenoid indole alkaloids (TIAs) with pharmaceutical applications, including the anticancer agents vinblastine and vincristine. Due to the interest in its TIAs, <italic>C. roseus</italic> is one of the most extensively studied medicinal plants and has become a model species for the study of plant secondary metabolism. However, very little is known about the cytogenetics and genome size of this species, in spite of their importance for breeding programmes, TIA genetics and emerging genomic research. Therefore, the present paper provides a karyotype description and fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) data for <italic>C. roseus</italic>, as well as a rigorous characterization of its genome size.The organization of <italic>C. roseus</italic> chromosomes was characterized using several DNA/chromatin staining techniques and FISH of rDNA. Genome size was investigated by flow cytometry using an optimized methodology.The <italic>C. roseus</italic> full chromosome complement of 2<italic>n</italic> = 16 includes two metacentric, four subtelocentric and two telocentric chromosome pairs, with the presence of a single nucleolus organizer region in chromosome 6. An easy and reliable flow cytometry protocol for nuclear genome analysis of <italic>C. roseus</italic> was optimized, and the C-value of this species was estimated to be 1C = 0.76 pg, corresponding to 738 Mbp.The organization and size of the <italic>C. roseus</italic> genome were characterized, providing an important basis for future studies of this important medicinal species, including further cytogenetic mapping, genomics, TIA genetics and breeding programmes.<italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (L.) G. Don (formerly <italic>Vinca rosea</italic> L.) is an important medicinal plant that accumulates in its leaves the dimeric terpenoid indole alkaloids (TIAs) vinblastine and vincristine. These compounds were the first natural anticancer agents to be clinically used and, together with a number of semi-synthetic derivatives, are universally known as the Vinca alkaloids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C32">Sottomayor and Ros Barceló 2006</xref>). <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> is also the source of two other medicinal TIAs—the antihypertensive ajmalicine and the sedative serpentine.The great pharmacological importance of the TIAs and their low abundance in the plant (around 0.0005 % of dry weight) has stimulated intense research on the TIA pathway with the aim of manipulating plant metabolism to increase levels of the alkaloids. Consequently, <italic>C. roseus</italic> has become one of the most extensively studied medicinal plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C34">van der Heijden <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C36">Verpoorte <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). The biosynthesis of TIAs was shown to be highly complex, involving more than 30 enzymatic steps, and much is already known about the pathway, the enzymes/genes involved and its regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C36">Verpoorte <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C6">Costa <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Recent genomic/transcriptomic/proteomic/metabolomic approaches have contributed further with much molecular information on <italic>C. roseus</italic> metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C30">Rischer <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C36">Verpoorte <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C28">Murata <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). However, there are still many gaps in knowledge about the TIA pathway, its genetics and regulatory mechanisms.Recent easy access to high-throughput sequencing and the large size of the scientific community interested in <italic>C. roseus</italic> can be expected to generate a wealth of new genome sequence data in the near future. In fact, extensive transcriptomic data for <italic>C. roseus</italic> have just been released (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C37">Websites 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C38">2</xref>). This emerging genomic research would benefit much from accessibility to detailed cytogenetic data, but current information is very limited in scope and detail—previous publications report only the chromosome number of 2<italic>n</italic> = 16 for <italic>C. roseus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C26">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C4">Balamani and Rao 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C13">Ge and Li 1989</xref>). In fact, the use of detailed karyotypes is instrumental in assigning linkage groups and mapping genes in chromosomes, being essential for the integration of physical and genetic maps towards a full understanding of genome organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C10">Fransz <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Detailed karyological information will also help to obtain physical maps to assist breeding programmes, namely aiming at the production of varieties with higher levels of dimeric alkaloids and with resistance to afflicting diseases such as <italic>Pythium</italic> dieback. Other relevant applications may be to help in determining the ancestry of the TIA pathway and to facilitate the understanding of TIA genetics as a whole. On the other hand, flow cytometric techniques are now increasingly being applied to plant cells, enabling rapid and accurate quantification of genome size, and providing complementary useful information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C25">Loureiro <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).The present paper aims to rectify the above-mentioned shortcomings by providing a detailed karyotype description of <italic>C. roseus</italic> based on several DNA/chromatin staining techniques and fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (FISH) of rDNA. An accurate quantification of genome size is also provided using an optimized flow cytometry protocol developed before for recalcitrant species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C24">Loureiro <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).Seeds of <italic>C. roseus</italic> (L.) G. Don cv. Little Bright Eye were acquired from AustraHort (Australia). Seeds were germinated on moist filter paper for 2–4 weeks, and seedlings were transferred to pots with compost (COMPO SANA<sup>®</sup> Universal Potting Soil) all at 25 °C, with a 16 h photoperiod (photosynthetically active radiation 30 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>). Voucher specimens were deposited at the Herbarium of the Department of Biology of the University of Porto (PO 61912).Seeds were treated with 70 % ethanol for 1 min, followed by two washes of 5 min with distilled water. The seeds were germinated on moist filter paper, and 7–10 days later, 10- to 15-mm-long root tips were collected. Approximately 70–100 tips were placed in a micro-centrifuge tube containing distilled water and kept at 0–4 °C for 24 h to accumulate cells in metaphase. Water was then removed and root tips were fixed in ethanol : glacial acetic acid, 3 : 1 (v/v), for 2 h at room temperature (RT). Fixed root tips were stored at −20 °C in fresh fixing solution.Preparation of mitotic spreads was as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C3">Andras <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref>, with some modifications. After fixation, root tips were washed twice with distilled water for 5 min. Root apexes (2 mm) were isolated, incubated in 50 μL of 1 M HCl at 37 °C for 25 min, washed for 1 min at RT with 50 μL of TE buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl, 1 mM EDTA, pH 8.0), and incubated in 200 μL of an enzyme mixture [4 % (w/v) cellulase Onozuka R10 (Yakult Honsha Co., Hyogo, Japan) and 1 % (w/v) pectolyase (Seishim Pharmaceutical, Tokyo, Japan) in citrate buffer (0.01 M citric acid, 0.01 M sodium citrate, pH 4.6)] for 2 h 30 min at 37 °C. The resulting protoplast suspension was centrifuged at 700 <italic>g</italic> for 3 min at RT, and the protoplast pellet was washed twice with 200 μL of distilled water and twice with 200 μL of a fixing solution of methanol : glacial acetic acid, 4 : 1 (v/v). Finally, the protoplasts were resuspended in 70–100 μL of the fixing solution (1 μL per apex), and aliquots (∼8 μL) of this suspension were dropped from a height of ∼1 cm with a 20 μL micropipette onto the centre of uncoated microscope slides previously washed with 96 % ethanol. Slides were allowed to dry and then incubated at 37 °C for 24 h, prior to observation. For FISH assays, slides were previously coated with 3-aminopropyltriethoxysilane (APES; Sigma-Aldrich, Dorset, UK) and were always freshly prepared.For the silver staining of chromosomes, slides were prepared as above and silver staining was performed as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C1">Ahmad <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref>.For the fluorescence banding of chromosomes with actinomycin D and 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (AD/DAPI), slides were immersed in McIlvaine's buffer pH 7.0 (0.1 M citric acid plus 0.2 M Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>) for 30 min at RT, and then briefly rinsed with distilled water. A 20 μL volume of 25 μg mL<sup>−1</sup> AD in McIlvaine's buffer was applied and the slides were incubated in a humid chamber at RT for 15 min. The slides were washed with buffer for 10 min, briefly rinsed with distilled water, and incubated with 20 μL of 1 μg mL<sup>−1</sup> DAPI in McIlvaine's buffer for 10 min in a humid chamber at RT. Finally, the slides were briefly rinsed with distilled water, mounted in 8 μL of fluorescence mounting medium [McIlvaine's buffer: 87 % glycerol (1 : 1; v/v) and 2.33 % (w/v) DABCO], and kept at 4 °C in the dark for at least 24 h, prior to observation.For the C-banding of chromosomes, slides were immersed in denaturing solution (0.2 N NaOH in 70 % ethanol) for 5 min at RT, and washed twice with 2 × SSC for 1 and 5 min. Slides were dehydrated for 2 min baths in a graded series of 70, 85 and 100 % ethanol and air-dried. In all, 20 μL of 2 × SSC were applied, overlaid with a coverslip and incubated in a humid chamber at 60 °C for 1 h, followed by a brief rinse with distilled water. For staining, 20 μL of a solution with 2 μg mL<sup>−1</sup> propidium iodide (PI) and 1 μg mL<sup>−1</sup> DAPI in McIlvaine's buffer were applied, and the slides were incubated in a humid chamber for 15 min at RT. Finally, the slides were briefly rinsed with distilled water and mounted as described above for AD/DAPI staining.Four prometaphases at the same condensation state (as determined by the total length of the chromosome complement) were selected and homologues were paired manually and analysed using the program MicroMeasure 3.3 (available at <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C39">Website 3</xref>). Heterochomatin regions highlighted by AD/DAPI staining were also measured. The chromosome type was attributed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C21">Levan <italic>et al.</italic> (1964)</xref>.Heterologous rDNA sequences were used for FISH. Clone pTa71 contains an 8.9 kb rDNA genomic fragment of wheat, consisting of the transcribed and non-transcribed spacer regions of the gene unit 18S-5.8S-26S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C15">Gerlach and Bedbrook 1979</xref>), and was kindly supplied by Trude Schwarzacher and Pat Heslop-Harrison (University of Leicester, UK). Plasmid DNA was labelled by nick translation using biotin-14-dATP of the Bionick™ Labeling System (Invitrogen Life Technologies, Paisley, UK). Plasmid DNA (0.5–1 μg) was labelled using 50 μL of labelling reaction (using 5 μL of 10× enzyme mix) for 2 h at 16 °C, and the reaction was stopped with 5 μL of 500 mM EDTA (pH 8.0).Chromosomal DNA was denatured by immersing the slides in 0.2 N NaOH in 70 % ethanol for 5 min at RT, followed by two washes with 2 × SSC for 1 and 5 min. The slides were then dehydrated as above and air-dried. The hybridization mixture per slide consisted of 100 ng (∼2 ng μL<sup>−1</sup>) of labelled probe DNA, 1 × Denhardt's solution [0.02 % (w/v) Ficoll, 0.02 % (w/v) polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP), 0.02 % (w/v) bovine serum albumin], 50 % (v/v) formamide, 2 × SSC and 0.1 % (w/v) SDS. This mixture was denatured by boiling for 5 min, and then immediately quenched on ice for at least 10 min. Hybridization was performed at 37 °C for 48 h in a humid chamber, and the slides were then washed with 2 × SSC for 2 × 5 min at RT, 2 × SSC for 5 min at 52 °C, 2 × SSC for 5 min at RT, and 4 × SSC for 5 min at RT. Labelling was performed at 37 °C for 1 h in a humid chamber with 2 % (v/v) fluorescein–avidin D in 4 × SSC followed by washing for 2 × 5 min with 4 × SSC at RT. The slides were air-dried, counterstained with 2 μg mL<sup>−1</sup> DAPI for 15 min at RT, rinsed with distilled water, mounted as above, and kept at 4 °C in the dark for at least 24 h prior to observation. Monochromatic images (8 bit) were captured with a digital camera CCD SPOT (Diagnostic Instruments) coupled to a Zeiss Axioskop fluorescence microscope using an immersion objective Zeiss Neofluar ×100. Digital treatment of images was performed with PaintShopPro 6.02 and Fiji (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C40">Website 4</xref>).Flow cytometry analysis of <italic>C. roseus</italic> leaf samples was performed as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C24">Loureiro <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> with some modifications. Young leaf pieces (2nd–3rd pair) with ∼50 mg were cut and placed on glass Petri dishes. One millilitre of Woody Plant Buffer [WPB; 0.2 M Tris-HCl, 4 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>·6H<sub>2</sub>O, 2 mM EDTA, 86 mM NaCl, 10 mM sodium metabisulphite, 1 % PVP-10 (w/v), 1 % Triton X-100 (v/v), pH 7.5] was added to the samples, and the leaf pieces were intensively chopped using a razor blade. The resulting homogenate was filtered through a 50 μm nylon mesh, and 50 μL of RNase (1 mg mL<sup>−1</sup>; Sigma, St Louis, MO, USA) and 50 μL of PI (1 mg mL<sup>−1</sup>; Fluka, Buchs, Switzerland) were added to the filtrate. The mixture was incubated for 5 min at RT and loaded onto the flow cytometer (Epics XL with a 488 nm laser; Beckman Coulter, High Wycombe, UK) to determine the ploidy level and genome size. As the sample had a small genome size, we used <italic>Bellis perennis</italic> as a secondary internal reference standard, as also used recently by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C20">Leong-Škornicková <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C18">Kolár <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). <italic>Bellis perennis</italic> has a 2C-value of 3.65 pg DNA, which we routinely confirmed using as an internal standard <italic>Pisum sativum</italic> cultivar ‘Ctirad’ obtained from certified seeds and with a 2C-value of 9.09 pg DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C8">Doležel and Greilhuber 2010</xref>). Genome sizes were calculated according to the following formula: DNA content (pg/2C) = (G0-G1 average peak × DNA content of internal standard)/(G0-G1 average peak of internal standard). Mass values were converted into base-pair numbers using the factor 1 pg = 978 Mbp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C9">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>).Morphometric data of the eight chromosome pairs of the <italic>C. roseus</italic> karyotype measured at prometaphase<sup>a</sup><sup>a</sup>Values are means of measurements performed in four prometaphases in which the full chromosome complement was visible with high quality±standard deviations.<sup>b</sup>Chromosome types were classified according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C21">Levan <italic>et al.</italic> (1964)</xref>: m, metacentric; sm, submetacentric; st, subtelocentric; t, telocentric.<sup>c</sup>Length of short arm/total length of chromosome.<sup>d</sup>Values were estimated for prometaphase based on measurements performed at metaphase.<bold>Cytogenetic analyses of <italic>C. roseus</italic> on mitotic spreads prepared from root tip cells</bold>. (A–C) Mitotic spreads of <italic>C. roseus</italic> stained with silver nitrate. (A) Prophase revealing a single nucleolus. (B) Prometaphase revealing a single pair of homologous chromosomes associated to the nucleolus. (C) Prometaphase with an already disorganized nucleolus and with the NORs restricted to a single chromosome pair. (D) Fluorescent staining with AD and DAPI of a prometaphase. (E) C-banding and staining with PI and DAPI of a prometaphase, highlighting the NORs in red. (F) Fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization of rDNA of a metaphase. The probe (pTa71) was labelled with biotin-14-dATP and detected with fluorescein-avidin D, the chromosomes were counterstained with DAPI and the NORs are highlighted in green. Arrow indicates chromosome 8. (G) <italic>Catharanthus  roseus</italic> karyotype. Chromosomes are aligned by the centromeric region and are ordered from 1 to 8, from the larger to the smaller, according to the morphometric analysis. (H) Ideogram of <italic>C. roseus</italic> chromosomes. Centromeres, constrictions, bands and NORs are depicted in the picture; the small arm of chromosome 8 is represented by a dashed line since it is usually not visible. Scale bars = 5 μm.Most chromosomes are highly asymmetrical, either subtelocentric or telocentric, with centromere indexes below 25 %. No submetacentric chromosome was found. Chromosome 6 may be considered metacentric and chromosome 8, although it looks telocentric at the prometaphases used for the morphometric study (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS002F1">1</xref>G), is indeed metacentric. In fact, one of the arms of chromosome 8 is usually uncondensed and/or not preserved at prometaphase, and is only totally visible at metaphase (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS002F1">1</xref>F). In this later phase, it was possible to identify this chromosome and conclude that it is metacentric—measurements were performed and inferred for prometaphase (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS002TB1">1</xref>). Chromosomes 8 and 3 show constrictions in their long arms.The chromosome complement of <italic>C. roseus</italic> presents a single active nucleolar organizing region (NOR). In fact, examination of nuclei by silver staining (AgS) revealed the presence of a single nucleolus in interphase and prophase nuclei (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS002F1">1</xref>A), and prometaphases showed either a single pair of chromosomes attached to the nucleolus (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS002F1">1</xref>B) or a single pair of Ag-NOR dots located on the short arm of chromosome 6 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS002F1">1</xref>C). Likewise, C-banding/PI/DAPI staining strongly highlighted in red the same two regions of chromosome 6 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS002F1">1</xref>E), and FISH for rDNA (pTa71 probe—18S-5.8S-26S from wheat) resulted in conspicuous labelling of the same regions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS002F1">1</xref>F), indicating the presence of a single 18S-5.8S-26S locus.Staining of chromosomes with AD/DAPI enabled identification of heterochromatin regions in prometaphase chromosomes, which are essentially pericentromeric and associated to the NOR site. Measurement of those regions indicated that heterochromatin accounts for about 20 % of the total length of the chromosome complement.Nuclear DNA content<sup>a</sup> of <italic>C. roseus</italic><sup>a</sup>The nuclear DNA content was estimated relative to the internal reference standard <italic>B. perennis</italic>.<sup>b</sup>1 pg DNA = 978 Mbp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C9">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>).<sup>c</sup>CV is a mean of CVs of the G0–G1 peak obtained in different measurements.<sup>d</sup>Number of plants used.<bold>Representative histogram of particle counts per relative fluorescence intensity (PI) obtained after simultaneous analysis of nuclei isolated from <italic>C. roseus</italic> leaves and from the internal reference standard <italic>B. perennis</italic> (2C = 3.65 pg DNA)</bold>. Three peaks were observed: peak 1—nuclei at G0-G1 phase of <italic>C. roseus</italic>; peak 2—nuclei at G2 phase of <italic>C. roseus</italic>; peak 3—nuclei at G0-G1 phase of <italic>B. perennis</italic>. The G2 phase of <italic>B. perennis</italic> was out of the detection range. The inset represents the forward scatter log (FS log) vs. side scatter log (SS log), where a gating region was defined to exclude doublets and unidentified particles.Currently, the development of omic approaches and their growing convenience has driven attention away from the investigation of the organism itself. However, the knowledge accumulated by those approaches will only fully make sense when anchored and integrated to the whole organism picture, including its cytogenetic characterization, especially in what concerns genome sequence information. Although <italic>C. roseus</italic> is an extensively studied plant at the biochemical and molecular levels, very little was known hitherto about its chromosome organization. Previous publications report only the chromosome number of 2<italic>n</italic> = 16 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C26">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C4">Balamani and Rao 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C13">Ge and Li 1989</xref>), but no morphological description of the chromosomes had been performed. Here, a detailed characterization of <italic>C. roseus</italic> chromosomes was accomplished, including centromere indexes, chromosome lengths, distribution of heterochromatic regions and NOR localization.The chromosome complement of 2<italic>n</italic> = 16 observed confirmed previous reports and is within normal values for Apocynaceae [<italic>x</italic> = 8–12(+)], although in the low border, since the predominant number is <italic>x</italic> = 11 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C2">Albers and Meve 2001</xref>). The karyotype and respective ideogram are represented in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS002F1">1</xref>G and H, and include two metacentric, four subtelocentric and two telocentric chromosome pairs. Many of the chromosomes have a similar centromere localization, which initially made it difficult to differentiate them, but staining with AD/DAPI was found to be a very efficient method for chromosome characterization, producing a high number of morphological marks that enabled full distinction of the eight chromosome pairs. This was particularly true for prometaphase rather than metaphase chromosomes, and therefore prometaphase was used for karyotype characterization as performed by other authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C17">Iannuzzi 1996</xref>).All techniques used, namely AgS, C-banding/PI/DAPI, AD/DAPI and FISH of rDNA, converged for the presence of a single NOR localized in the small arm of chromosome 6. The localization and number of NOR per nucleus may vary from species to species or be conserved, and may, for example, reflect the occurrence of hybridization or differences in ploidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C22">Lim <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). The presence of only one nucleolus and one pair of NOR in <italic>C. roseus</italic> may thus be considered normal and is in line with a previous report from electron microscopy studies of this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C7">Cousin 1980</xref>).DNA amount and molecular size of each <italic>C. roseus</italic> chromosome estimated from the morphometric cytogenetic data and the C-value measured by flow cytometry<sup>a</sup>1 pg DNA = 978 Mbp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C9">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>).The 1C value of 0.76 pg (∼738 Mbp) determined here for <italic>C. roseus</italic> indicates a genome that is roughly six times bigger than the Arabidopsis genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C33">The Arabidopsis Genome Initiative 2000</xref>) and nearly two times bigger than the rice genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C16">Goff <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C41">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). However, it is well within the range of other plants whose genomes have recently been sequenced, such as sorghum (∼730 Mbp) or pigeon pea (∼833 Mbp), and indeed much smaller than the now sequenced 2.3 Gbp of the maize genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C29">Paterson <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C31">Schnable <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C35">Varshney <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). To put the <italic>C. roseus</italic> genome size into a broader perspective, the Plant DNA C-values Database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C5">Bennett and Leitch 2010</xref>) now indexes 6287 plant species with a 1C mean of 5.94 and comprising values ranging from 0.06 to 152.2. In fact, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C19">Leitch <italic>et al</italic>. (2010)</xref> report a mode and median genome size for angiosperms of 0.6 and 2.6, which make <italic>C. roseus</italic> genome size a quite common C-value among higher plants.In conclusion, we provide here the first detailed description of the organization of the <italic>C. roseus</italic> chromosome complement, and a careful estimation of the C-value of this species. This knowledge will be of importance for the systematization of emerging genome sequence information, and research aimed at investigating the ancestry of the TIA pathway and its genetic characterization. Moreover, this work may be the basis for physical mapping assisting in breeding programmes.We also provide an improved flow cytometry protocol (short incubation with PI and a buffer designed for recalcitrant woody species) for the easy and reliable evaluation of the C-value of <italic>C. roseus</italic> DNA, which may be used, namely, to monitor ploidy stability throughout regeneration procedures, particularly important when performing the production of genetically manipulated plants for TIA improvement.This work was funded by (i) Programa Operacional Ciência e Inovação (POCI 2010—financed by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">European Union and Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia from the Portuguese Government</grant-sponsor>), (ii) three scholar/fellowships from <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num xlink:type="simple">SFRH/BM/566/2000</grant-num> to G.G, <grant-num xlink:type="simple">SFRH/BPD/20669/2004</grant-num> to P.D, and <grant-num xlink:type="simple">SFRH/BPD/48853/2008</grant-num> to H.O), and (iii) a Scientific Mecenate award from <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Grupo Jerónimo Martins SA</grant-sponsor>.G.G performed all the cytogenetic assays. Authors L.C, H.O and P.D performed the cytometry studies and P.D was also involved in the planning of research and writing of the manuscript. C.S supervised the cytometry studies. M.S was involved in the planning and supervision of all the experimental work, and in writing the manuscript.None declared.The complete references with the full list of authors for <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C16">Goff <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C29">Paterson <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C31">Schnable <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS002C35">Varshney <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> are as follows:<bold>Goff SA, Ricke D, Lan TH, Presting G, Wang R, Dunn M, Glazebrook J, Sessions A, Oeller P, Varma H, Hadley D, Hutchison D, Martin C, Katagiri F, Lange BM, Moughamer T, Xia Y, Budworth P, Zhong J, Miguel T, Paszkowski U, Zhang S, Colbert M, Sun WL, Chen L, Cooper B, Park S, Wood TC, Mao L, Quail P, Wing R, Dean R, Yu Y, Zharkikh A, Shen R, Sahasrabudhe S, Thomas A, Cannings R, Gutin A, Pruss D, Reid J, Tavtigian S, Mitchell J, Eldredge G, Scholl T, Miller RM, Bhatnagar S, Adey N, Rubano T, Tusneem N, Robinson R, Feldhaus J, Macalma T, Oliphant A, Briggs S. 2002.</bold> A draft sequence of the rice genome (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>). <italic>Science</italic> <bold>296</bold>: 92–100.<bold>Paterson AH, Bowers JE, Bruggmann R, Dubchak I, Grimwood J, Gundlach H, Haberer G, Hellsten U, Mitros T, Poliakov A, Schmutz J, Spannagl M, Tang H, Wang X, Wicker T, Bharti AK, Chapman J, Feltus FA, Gowik U, Grigoriev IV, Lyons E, Maher CA, Martis M, Narechania A, Otillar RP, Penning BW, Salamov AA, Wang Y, Zhang L, Carpita NC, Freeling M, Gingle AR, Hash CT, Keller B, Klein P, Kresovich S, McCann MC, Ming R, Peterson DG, Mehboob-ur-Rahman, Ware D, Westhoff P, Mayer KF, Messing J, Rokhsar DS. 2009.</bold> The <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> genome and the diversification of grasses. <italic>Nature</italic> <bold>457</bold>: 551–556.<bold>Schnable PS, Ware D, Fulton RS, Stein JC, Wei F, Pasternak S, Liang C, Zhang J, Fulton L, Graves TA, Minx P, Reily AD, Courtney L, Kruchowski SS, Tomlinson C, Strong C, Delehaunty K, Fronick C, Courtney B, Rock SM, Belter E, Du F, Kim K, Abbott RM, Cotton M, Levy A, Marchetto P, Ochoa K, Jackson SM, Gillam B, Chen W, Yan L, Higginbotham J, Cardenas M, Waligorski J, Applebaum E, Phelps L, Falcone J, Kanchi K, Thane T, Scimone A, Thane N, Henke J, Wang T, Ruppert J, Shah N, Rotter K, Hodges J, Ingenthron E, Cordes M, Kohlberg S, Sgro J, Delgado B, Mead K, Chinwalla A, Leonard S, Crouse K, Collura K, Kudrna D, Currie J, He R, Angelova A, Rajasekar S, Mueller T, Lomeli R, Scara G, Ko A, Delaney K, Wissotski M, Lopez G, Campos D, Braidotti M, Ashley E, Golser W, Kim H, Lee S, Lin J, Dujmic Z, Kim W, Talag J, Zuccolo A, Fan C, Sebastian A, Kramer M, Spiegel L, Nascimento L, Zutavern T, Miller B, Ambroise C, Muller S, Spooner W, Narechania A, Ren L, Wei S, Kumari S, Faga B, Levy MJ, McMahan L, Van Buren P, Vaughn MW, Ying K, Yeh CT, Emrich SJ, Jia Y, Kalyanaraman A, Hsia AP, Barbazuk WB, Baucom RS, Brutnell TP, Carpita NC, Chaparro C, Chia JM, Deragon JM, Estill JC, Fu Y, Jeddeloh JA, Han Y, Lee H, Li P, Lisch DR, Liu S, Liu Z, Nagel DH, McCann MC, SanMiguel P, Myers AM, Nettleton D, Nguyen J, Penning BW, Ponnala L, Schneider KL, Schwartz DC, Sharma A, Soderlund C, Springer NM, Sun Q, Wang H, Waterman M, Westerman R, Wolfgruber TK, Yang L, Yu Y, Zhang L, Zhou S, Zhu Q, Bennetzen JL, Dawe RK, Jiang J, Jiang N, Presting GG, Wessler SR, Aluru S, Martienssen RA, Clifton SW, McCombie WR, Wing RA, Wilson RK. 2009.</bold> The B73 maize genome: complexity, diversity, and dynamics. <italic>Science</italic> <bold>326</bold>: 1112–1115.<bold>Varshney RK, Chen W, Li Y, Bharti AK, Saxena RK, Schlueter JA, Donoghue MT, Azam S, Fan G, Whaley AM, Farmer AD, Sheridan J, Iwata A, Tuteja R, Penmetsa RV, Wu W, Upadhyaya HD, Yang SP, Shah T, Saxena KB, Michael T, McCombie WR, Yang B, Zhang G, Yang H, Wang J, Spillane C, Cook DR, May GD, Xu X, Jackson SA. 2011.</bold> Draft genome sequence of pigeonpea (<italic>Cajanus cajan</italic>), an orphan legume crop of resource-poor farmers. <italic>Nature</italic> <italic>Biotechnology</italic> <bold>30</bold>: 83–89.