Hydrogen peroxide—a central hub for information flow in plant cellsSmall GTPase ‘Rop’: molecular switch for plant defense responsesRedox regulation of mammalian heat shock factor 1 is essential for Hsp gene activation and protection from stressReactive oxygen species: metabolism, oxidative stress, and signal transductionThe water-water cycle in chloroplasts: scavenging of active oxygens and dissipation of excess photonsThe role of radical burst via MAPK signalling in plant immunityAllelopathy and exotic plant invasion: from molecules and genes to species interactionsSalt-triggered expression of the ANAC092-dependent senescence regulon in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>A gene regulatory network controlled by the NAC transcription factor ANAC092/AtNAC2/ORE1 during salt-promoted senescenceORS1, an H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive NAC transcription factor, controls senescence in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Hydrogen peroxide effects on root hydraulic properties and plasma membrane aquaporin regulation in <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>Cell death of barley aleurone protoplasts is mediated by reactive oxygen speciesMembrane transport of hydrogen peroxideSpecific aquaporins facilitate the diffusion of hydrogen peroxide across membranesThe <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> peptide kiss of death is an inducer of programmed cell deathThe apoplastic oxidative burst in response to biotic stress in plants: a three-component system<italic>Myo</italic>-inositol abolishes salicylic acid-dependent cell death and pathogen defence responses triggered by peroxisomal hydrogen peroxidePeroxisomal hydrogen peroxide is coupled to biotic defense responses by ISOCHORISMATE SYNTHASE1 in a daylength-related mannerA calcium-dependent protein kinase is systemically induced upon wounding in tomato plantsCalmodulin: a prototypical calcium sensorThe EAR-motif of the Cys2/His2-type zinc finger protein Zat7 plays a key role in the defense response of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to salinity stressBoth the stimulation and inhibition of root hair growth induced by extracellular nucleotides in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> are mediated by nitric oxide and reactive oxygen speciesNO way back: nitric oxide and programmed cell death in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> suspension culturesH<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in plant peroxisomes: an <italic>in vivo</italic> analysis uncovers a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent scavenging systemDual action of the active oxygen species during plant stress responsesCytosolic ascorbate peroxidase 1 is a central component of the reactive oxygen gene network of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Hydrogen peroxide, nitric oxide and cytosolic ascorbate peroxidase at the crossroad between defence and cell deathSignal interaction between nitric oxide and reactive oxygen intermediates in the plant hypersensitive disease resistance responseSalicylic acid, active oxygen species and systemic acquired resistance in plantsPlant plasma membrane water channels conduct the signalling molecule H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>Networks of WRKY transcription factors in defense signallingReactive oxygen species produced by NADPH oxidase regulate plant cell growthTranscriptomic footprints disclose specificity of reactive oxygen species signalling in ArabidopsisMEKK1, MKK1/MKK2 and MPK4 function together in a mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade to regulate innate immunity in plantsControl of plant development by reactive oxygen speciesHydrogen peroxide as a signal controlling plant programmed cell deathHydrogen peroxide-induced cell death in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: transcriptional and mutant analysis reveals a role of an oxoglutarate-dependent dioxygenase gene in the cell death processReactive oxygen species as signals that modulate plant stress responses and programmed cell deathCross-talk between salicylic acid and NaCl-generated reactive oxygen species and nitric oxide in tomato during acclimation to high salinityRedox proteomics of protein-bound methionine oxidationThe <italic>RPM1</italic> plant disease resistance gene facilitates a rapid and sustained increase in cytosolic calcium that is necessary for the oxidative burst and hypersensitive cell deathReactive species and antioxidants. Redox biology is a fundamental theme of aerobic lifeCoupling oxidative signals to protein phosphorylation via methionine oxidation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>No single way to understand singlet oxygen signalling in plantsComplexity of the heat stress response in plantsFunctional analysis of oxidative stress-activated mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade in plantsDihydrosphingosine-induced programmed cell death in tobacco BY-2 cells is independent of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> productionThe oxidative burst in plant disease resistanceSalicylic acid promotes seed germination under high salinity by modulating antioxidant activity in ArabidopsisHydrogen peroxide stimulates salicylic acid biosynthesis in tobaccoBiotic and abiotic stress responses through calcium-dependent protein kinase (CDPK) signalling in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)A signalling pathway linking nitric oxide production to heterotrimeric G protein and hydrogen peroxide regulates extracellular calmodulin induction of stomatal closure in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Identification and analysis of seven H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive miRNAs and 32 new miRNAs in the seedlings of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. ssp. <italic>indica</italic>)Nitric oxide and protein <italic>S</italic>-nitrosylation are integral to hydrogen peroxide induced leaf cell death in riceCadmium activates <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> MPK3 and MPK6 via accumulation of reactive oxygen speciesMAPK phosphatase MKP2 mediates disease responses in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and functionally interacts with MPK3 and MPK6Nitric oxide and hydrogen peroxide in tomato resistance. Nitric oxide modulates hydrogen peroxide level in <italic>o</italic>-hydroxyethylorutin-induced resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> in tomatoArabidopsis GLUTATHIONE REDUCTASE1 plays a crucial role in leaf responses to intracellular hydrogen peroxide and in ensuring appropriate gene expression through both salicylic acid and jasmonic acid signalling pathwaysTargets of the WRKY53 transcription factor and its role during leaf senescence in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> MEKK1 can take a short cut: it can directly interact with senescence-related WRKY53 transcription factor on the protein level and can bind to its promoterCould heat shock transcription factors function as hydrogen peroxide sensors in plants?Reactive oxygen signalling and abiotic stressReactive oxygen species homeostasis and signalling during drought and salinity stressesOxidative stress, antioxidants and stress toleranceROS signaling: the new wave?Production and diffusion of chloroplastic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and its implication to signallingEmerging MAP kinase pathways in plant stress signallingNitric oxide, stomatal closure, and abiotic stressAscorbate and glutathione: keeping active oxygen under controlCalcium channels activated by hydrogen peroxide mediate abscisic acid signalling in guard cellsCytoplasmic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> prevents translocation of NPR1 to the nucleus and inhibits the induction of PR genes in ArabidopsisNetworking by small-molecule hormones in plant immunityA major role of the MEKK1-MKK1/2-MPK4 pathway in ROS signallingArabidopsis mitogen-activated protein kinase kinases MKK1 and MKK2 have overlapping functions in defense signalling mediated by MEKK1, MPK4, and MKS1Conditional oxidative stress responses in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> photorespiratory mutant <italic>cat2</italic> demonstrate that redox state is a key modulator of daylength-dependent gene expression, and define photoperiod as a crucial factor in the regulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced cell deathInfluence of salicylic acid on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production, oxidative stress, and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-metabolizing enzymes. Salicylic acid-mediated oxidative damage requires H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>Oxidative stress-induced calcium signalling in ArabidopsisOXI1 kinase is necessary for oxidative burst-mediated signalling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>The water-water cycle is essential for chloroplast protection in the absence of stressRegulation of solute flux through plasmodesmata in the root meristemCalmodulin-dependent activation of MAP kinase for ROS homeostasis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Proteomics reveals the overlapping roles of hydrogen peroxide and nitric oxide in the acclimation of citrus plants to salinityPerturbation of indole-3-butyric acid homeostasis by the UDP-glucosyltransferase <italic>UGT74E2</italic> modulates <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> architecture and water stress toleranceTranscriptional regulation of ROS controls transition from proliferation to differentiation in the rootReactive oxygen species in plant cell deathInvolvements of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and metallothionein in NO-mediated tomato tolerance to copper toxicityThe <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> prohibitin gene <italic>PHB3</italic> functions in nitric oxide-mediated responses and in hydrogen peroxide-induced nitric oxide accumulationCatalases in plantsSpermidine oxidase-derived H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> regulates pollen plasma membrane hyperpolarization-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeable channels and pollen tube growthReactive oxygen species are involved in brassinosteroid-induced stress tolerance in cucumberAtMKK1 mediates ABA-induced <italic>CAT1</italic> expression and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production via AtMPK6-coupled signalling in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> gp91<sup>phox</sup> homologs <italic>NbrbohA</italic> and <italic>NbrbohB</italic> participate in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation and resistance to <italic>Phytophthora infestans</italic>Transcriptional regulatory network triggered by oxidative signals configures the early response mechanisms of japonica rice to chilling stressMitogen-activated protein kinase is involved in abscisic acid-induced antioxidant defense and acts downstream of reactive oxygen species production in leaves of maize plantsNitric oxide induced by hydrogen peroxide mediates abscisic acid-induced activation of the mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade involved in antioxidant defense in maize leavesZmMPK5 is required for the NADPH oxidase-mediated self-propagation of apoplastic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in brassinosteroid-induced antioxidant defence in leaves of maizeExogenous application of salicylic acid alleviates cadmium toxicity and reduces hydrogen peroxide accumulation in root apoplasts of <italic>Phaseolus aureus</italic> and <italic>Vicia sativa</italic>Direct sensing of heat and oxidation by <italic>Drosophila</italic> heat shock transcription factorComparative proteomics analysis of the root apoplasts of rice seedlings in response to hydrogen peroxideThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/</uri>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The review discusses recent advances in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> plant biology, focusing on its signalling capabilities, the transduction pathways involved and its potential for interfering with other information transfer mechanisms in plant cells.Hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) was initially recognized as a toxic reactive oxygen species, able to cause damage to a variety of cellular structures. However, it became clear in the last decade that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can also act as a potent signalling molecule, involved in a plethora of physiological functions.In the present review, we offer a brief summary of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signalling events and focus on the mechanisms of its perception and signal transduction, the factors that act downstream, as well as H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> interference with other information transfer mechanisms.The significant scientific effort in the last 10 years to determine the position of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in signal transduction networks in plants demonstrated that it is essential for both the communication with external biotic and abiotic stimuli and the control of developmentally regulated processes. In addition, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> complements, synergizes or antagonizes many cellular regulatory circuits by active interaction with other signals and plant hormones during growth, development and stress responses. Therefore, further understanding of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signal transduction is not only of fundamental, but also of practical importance, since this knowledge may contribute to improve agricultural practices and reduce stress-induced damage to crops.Reactive oxygen species (ROS) are produced either after incomplete reduction of oxygen (hydrogen peroxide—H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>; superoxide radical—O<sub>2</sub><sup>−</sup>; hydroxyl radical—HO<sup>·</sup>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C38">Gechev <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>) or energy transfer to its chemically inert triplet ground state (singlet oxygen—<sup>1</sup>O<sub>2</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C44">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). These oxygen derivatives possess a strong oxidizing potential that leads to damage to a variety of biological molecules and are therefore unwelcome byproducts of normal metabolic processes in all aerobic organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C42">Halliwell 2006</xref>). During periods of biotic or abiotic stress, ROS levels can rise excessively, leading to an oxidative stress state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C4">Apel and Hirt 2004</xref>). Since plants are sessile organisms and cannot simply escape from adverse environmental conditions, they have developed an elaborate system to control cellular ROS concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C64">Mittler <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). In addition, plants have evolved a way to utilize lower concentrations of ROS as signalling molecules for a number of regulated processes during plant growth and development, like cell elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C32">Foreman <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>) and differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C83">Tsukagoshi <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), as well as in responses to a variety of environmental stimuli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C25">Dat <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C35">Gapper and Dolan 2006</xref>).Among the ROS compounds, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is the one that received most of the attention of the scientific community in the last decade. Hydrogen peroxide is the result of a two-step reduction of molecular oxygen (the first step leading to superoxide radical) and has a relatively long lifespan in comparison to other ROS. The long half-life (1 ms) of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and its small size allow it to traverse cellular membranes and migrate in different compartments, which facilitates its signalling functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C13">Bienert <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). As a result, it is now well proved that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is a regulator of a multitude of physiological processes like acquiring resistance, cell wall strengthening, senescence, phytoalexin production, photosynthesis, stomatal opening and the cell cycle. The multi-functionality on the one hand, and the danger it presents in elevated concentrations on the other hand, require the very strict control of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration in plant cells.<bold>The main mechanisms of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> synthesis and catabolism in different cellular structures.</bold> The apoplast is a space of active ROS production, due to the activity of NADPH-dependent oxidases (Rboh), cell wall peroxidases, amine oxidases and oxalate oxidases (the latter two are not included in the figure). Superoxide anions which result from the action of these enzymes are readily converted to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Apoplastic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> serves not only to induce oxidative burst during pathogen attack, but also to regulate cell wall rigidity. Inside the cell, the compartments that produce the highest amounts of ROS are the chloroplasts. Hydrogen peroxide is an undesirable byproduct of photosynthesis and a number of scavengers can be found in the chloroplasts that are able to disarm it by turning it into harmless water molecules. These include members of the glutathione-ascorbate cycle and peroxiredoxins/thioredoxins. Another site of active ROS synthesis is the mitochondria. In plants, excessive ROS accumulation in mitochondria can be alleviated by an alternative mechanism for electron transport which is carried out by alternative oxidase (AOX). Although processes like photorespiration and fatty-acid oxidation generate H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in peroxisomes and glyoxisomes, dangerous raising of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is normally prevented by the presence of the enzyme catalase. Finally, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and other ROS that leak out in the cytoplasm are easily handled by the activity of ROS-scavenging systems similar to those in the chloroplast.The biological effect of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is mostly dependent on its concentration, but also on the site of production, the developmental stage of the plant and previous exposures to different kinds of stress. Generally, at low concentrations it acts as a signalling molecule, while at higher concentrations it provokes the onset of cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C36">Gechev and Hille 2005</xref>). Hydrogen peroxide-induced cell death is essential for some developmental processes and environmental responses, including aleurone cell death, leaf senescence, hypersensitive response to pathogens, allelopathic plant–plant interactions, etc. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C12">Bethke and Jones 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C7">Bais <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C37">Gechev <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>).It is obvious that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is a molecule with enormous impact on normal plant cell functioning. Although much progress has been achieved in revealing its role in plants, there is still a lot to be unveiled. Yet, in this review we focus on the present state of the art in knowledge concerning H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and its signalling network.A wide range of environmental stimuli lead to a transient rise in cellular H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> levels. In these cases, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can be viewed as a signal that relays the initial stimuli to downstream effectors. The existence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> sensing proteins still remains enigmatic. However, it is presumed that increased H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> levels could be perceived directly by redox-sensitive transcription factors (TFs) that orchestrate downstream cascades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C61">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Good candidates for such TFs are class A heat shock factors (Hsfs), which are shown to be responsive to oxidative stress both in animals and plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C60">Miller and Mittler 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C45">Kotak <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Moreover, it was demonstrated that Hsfs of both <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mammalian origin are able to interact directly with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and as a result form DNA-binding-competent homotrimers in a reversible manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C97">Zhong <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C2">Ahn and Thiele 2003</xref>). Plants may utilize a similar mechanism to detect H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signals.In addition, a recent study suggested another intriguing alternative for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> perception <italic>in planta</italic>: the oxidation of methionine (Met) to methionine sulphoxide (MetSO) may couple oxidative signals to changes in the protein phosphorylation state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C43">Hardin <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The authors provide <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> evidence that Met oxidation by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> may compromise peptide phosphorylation when these residues are situated within phosphorylation motifs. As an example, the <italic>in vitro</italic> oxidation of Met<sup>538</sup> in leaf nitrate reductase (NR) strongly inhibits the phosphorylation of the adjacent Ser<sup>534</sup>. Moreover, exogenously applied H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> causes a reduction of Ser<sup>534</sup> phosphorylation <italic>in vivo</italic> as well, while the overexpression of a cytosolic MetSO repair enzyme has the opposite effect and leads to an increase in phosphorylation rates. Such a redox methionine-dependent switch would be a fast and efficient way to relay the oxidative signal further downstream. Future research on the topic should identify and catalogue proteins with suitable target Met residues in order to unravel how widespread this mechanism could be. A solution to achieve this is offered by a recently developed proteomic technology called COFRADIC (combined fractional diagonal chromatography) which, among its other useful applications, is able to identify oxidized methionine residues and quantify their degree of oxidation. In the first study using this new method, COFRADIC analyses on human Jurkat cells revealed that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-sensitive methionines are preferentially located in zones exposed to the protein surface, enriched for charged and poor in hydrophobic residues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C40">Ghesquière <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).One important feature that facilitates H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in its intermediary functions is its ability to diffuse across membranes. It was shown, for example, that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> produced by the chloroplast electron transport chain can leak out of chloroplasts in a light-intensity-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C65">Mubarakshina <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). However, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is a relatively neutral solute and native membranes present a significant barrier to its free diffusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C13">Bienert <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Hydrogen peroxide can be transported through specific membrane aquaporin homologues of the TIP (tonoplast intrinsic protein) and PIP (plasma membrane intrinsic protein) families. For instance, it was shown that expression of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana AtTIP1;1</italic> and <italic>AtTIP1;2</italic> genes in yeast cells decreased their survival rate in the presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, while blocking this aquaporin-mediated diffusion alleviated the effect of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C14">Bienert <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Moreover, a more recent analysis suggests that the Ar/R (aromatic/arginine) regions in PIP2 proteins are critical for their selectivity towards H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C30">Dynowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) and as all eight PIP2 proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> are conserved in these positions, presumably all of them are involved in the specific transport of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>.In turn, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is able to influence the transport of water and other solutes between cells. In <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> it was found that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> exerts concentration-dependent effects on root hydraulic conductivity, which is one of the determinants of root water uptake. Levels of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> &lt;1 mM increase conductivity, while those &gt;1 mM decrease it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C11">Benabdellah <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> root meristems, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatments induce modifications of plasmodesmal flux based on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> amounts in a similar manner—low concentrations boost plasmodesmal permeability while high concentrations inhibit it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C79">Rutschow <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). An attractive, but still speculative way to explain these phenomena is that low levels of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> create a signal for mild stress, which can be alleviated by increased flow of solutes and nutrients. Conversely, accumulation of higher amounts of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> produces a message for severe stress, like during pathogen invasion, which requires that the cell is isolated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C79">Rutschow <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).<bold>A simplified schematic representation of the major signalling components in the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-transduction network, their interactions and different outcomes in the plant cell.</bold> Stress conditions and a variety of environmental cues lead to accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, which serves as a second messenger and relays the signal to downstream effectors, including TFs, MAP-kinases, miRNAs, etc. Some of these effectors can in turn interact with each other. The information flow in this network is rarely straightforward, as it diverges in some points and converges in others. The final output of the cascade depends on the nature of the signal, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration, locus of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> synthesis, interaction with other active signalling pathways, previous exposure to stress, etc.The most typical targets of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> include effectors of calcium homeostasis, ion channels, protein kinases or phosphatases and TFs.Mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPKs) in plants form a large network implicated in a vast array of functions, including the relay of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C93">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C90">Xing <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Mitogen-activated protein kinases can either be activated by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation, or trigger an H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative burst themselves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C66">Nakagami <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C72">Pitzschke <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Thus, while H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> activates the ANP1 (an MAPK kinase kinase) protein, which in turn initiates a phosphorylation cascade with AtMPK3 and AtMPK6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C46">Kovtun <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>), the MEK2 pathway is part of an amplification mechanism upstream of <italic>Rboh</italic> genes, which are known to produce H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C91">Yoshioka <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). This positioning of MAPK cascades up- or downstream of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> indicates the complexity and multidirectionality of stress signalling networks.A prominent place among the module effectors modulated by ROS metabolism in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> holds the MEKK1–MKK1/2–MPK4 pathway. The MAPK kinase kinase MEKK1 is regulated by different stresses and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in a proteasome-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C72">Pitzschke <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). MEKK1 can activate the downstream kinases MPK3, MPK4 and MPK6. However, only <italic>mpk4</italic> mutants possess a similar phenotype to <italic>mekk1</italic> and have similar changes in gene expression. Therefore, it is MPK4 that is usually considered as an H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced MEKK1 target. The signal between MEKK1 and MPK4 is transmitted by the MAPK kinases MKK1 and MKK2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C73">Qiu <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). These are in part functionally redundant, as single <italic>mkk1</italic> or <italic>mkk2</italic> mutants have normal activities of MPK4, unlike the double <italic>mkk1/mkk2</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C34">Gao <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Analyses of gene expression reveal that of 32 TFs that are highly responsive to multiple ROS-generating conditions, 20 are regulated via the MEKK1–MKK1/2–MPK4 pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C72">Pitzschke <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). This confirms the central role of these factors in oxidative stress signalling. Surprisingly, a unique shortcut in MAPK pathways has been found for MEKK1—it can interact directly with the TF WRKY53 and phosphorylate it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C59">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). This modification increases WRKY53 DNA-binding activity and allows the immediate induction of stress and defence-related target genes by bypassing of downstream kinases. In addition, MEKK1 was demonstrated to possess the ability to bind WRKY53 promoter in a region which participates in the switch from a leaf-age-dependent to a systemic plant-age-dependent WRKY53 expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C59">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).In plants, transmission of pathogen and disease signals is also governed by MAPKs in a H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-dependent manner. This function is exerted in tobacco by SIPK and WIPK kinases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C6">Asai and Yoshioka 2008</xref>), whereas in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> it is exerted by their homologues MPK3 and MPK6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C66">Nakagami <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). MPK3/6 are not only activated by ANP1, as mentioned above, but also by the serine–threonine kinase OXI1, which similarly can be induced directly by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C77">Rentel <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Hydrogen peroxide may also be involved in <italic>MPK3/6</italic> responses to heavy metals, since these two MAPKs are activated after cadmium (Cd) treatment by a mechanism that presumably requires accumulation of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C54">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Recently, it has been proved that the MAPK phosphatase MPK2 can functionally interact with MPK3 and MPK6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C55">Lumbreras <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). By dephosphorylating regulatory residues in these targets, MPK2 provides a negative signal with profound effects on pathogen reactions, as shown by <italic>mpk2</italic> mutant phenotypes. Moreover, MPK2 seems to have differential functions in biotrophic versus necrotrophic responses, as <italic>mpk</italic>2 plants exhibit opposite symptoms when infected with the biotrophic <italic>Ralstonia solanacearum</italic> or the necrotrophic <italic>Botrytis cinerea. mpk</italic>2 mutants are more resistant to <italic>R. solanacearum</italic> and more susceptible to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, suggesting that MPK2 is a negative regulator of the HR-induced (hypersensitive response) cell death which protects against biotrophic pathogens but facilitates necrotrophic infections.Two recent studies show that brassinosteroids (BRs) are able to provoke apoplastic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation, which further switches on MPKs to increase stress tolerance in different species. In cucumber, <italic>Rboh</italic>, <italic>MPK1</italic> and <italic>MAPK3</italic> are among the target genes that are upregulated in this BR-induced process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C89">Xia <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>); in maize, BR-stimulated <italic>ZmMPK5</italic> induction drives an NADPH oxidase-mediated amplification loop required for the enhancement of the activities of antioxidant enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C95">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).The last link in the chain of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signal mediators is a variety of TFs. They induce a massive reprogramming of the transcriptome and lead to a second wave of effectors, which in turn switch on various responses like defensive mechanisms and the assembly of the cell death machinery. The TFs that are associated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> signalling are members of different families, including NAC, ZAT, WRKY, DREB, bZIP and MYB.In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, many NAC TFs control leaf senescence. Notably, 15 senescence-associated NAC TFs are upregulated by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C8">Balazadeh <italic>et al.</italic> 2010<italic>a</italic></xref>), of which <italic>ANAC032</italic> and <italic>ANAC042</italic> are the most significantly induced (around 25 times). ANAC042 has already been reported previously as a possible target of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C37">Gechev <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>) and it was proposed that its activation occurs through the OXI1/MPK3/6 cascade. Another key regulator of age- and salt-promoted senescence is ANAC092. As 40 % of its salt-dependent senescence regulon is actually affected by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, an oxidative burst obviously plays a role in ANAC092-mediated responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C8">Balazadeh <italic>et al.</italic> 2010<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C9"><italic>b</italic></xref>). More recently, a similar regulatory network, which includes cross-talk between salt and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, was also ascribed to ORS1, the paralogue of ANAC092 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C10">Balazadeh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Moreover, the authors even localized a H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive regulatory element in the proximal 230 bp of the <italic>ORS1</italic> promoter region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C10">Balazadeh <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).The zinc-finger TFs from the Zat family are also often related to oxidative stress. For example, <italic>Zat11</italic> and <italic>Zat12</italic> are highly induced by ROS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C33">Gadjev <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). In addition, overexpression of <italic>Zat12</italic> leads to increased levels of oxidative stress-responsive transcripts, while its inhibition results in higher sensitivity to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C78">Rizhsky <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C26">Davletova <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). In experiments with <italic>apx1</italic> mutants, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C61">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> (2008</xref>) nominated three Zat TFs as being involved in ROS signalling and abiotic stress–Zat7, Zat10 and the already mentioned Zat12. Remarkably, the induction of <italic>Zat7</italic> by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is impaired in knockout <italic>Zat12</italic> plants, which suggests a direct dependence of <italic>Zat7</italic> expression on Zat12. However, this relationship is probably more complex, as <italic>Zat12</italic>-overexpressing plants fail to modulate <italic>Zat7</italic> expression.WRKY TFs are often described as key players in plant responses to biotic, abiotic and oxidative stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C31">Eulgem and Somssich 2007</xref>). Of these TFs, WRKY52 and WRKY70 are the most widely discussed H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-inducible representatives of the family. WRKY52 is a senescence-related factor which can affect the expression of a variety of stress, defence and senescence-associated genes. Its overexpression leads to accelerated senescence, while its knockout provokes a delay in this process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C58">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). On the other hand, WRKY70 is specific for salt stress and shows a similar expression pattern to <italic>Zat7</italic> in <italic>apx1</italic> mutant plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C62">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). It was previously demonstrated that WRKY70, together with the HASTY TF, and Zat7 actually interact in a yeast two-hybrid assay through the EAR-domain of Zat7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C21">Ciftci-Yilmaz <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).Other H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced TFs from different families include DREB2A that are upregulated not only by oxidative stress, but also by drought, cold and heat stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C78">Rizhsky <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>), many bZIP, ERF and MYB factors that configure the response of japonica rice to chilling stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C92">Yun <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), and the redox-sensitive Hsfs which were described above as possible direct sensors of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>.Plant miRNAs are known to be ubiquitous regulators of gene expression at the post-transcriptional level and modulate a great diversity of biological responses by directing mRNA targets for cleavage or inducing translational silencing. Recently, in the first genome-wide study of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-regulated miRNAs in plants, seven miRNA families were found to be differentially expressed after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment in rice seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C53">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). These include miR169, miR397, miR528, miR827, miR1425, miR319a.2 and miR408-5p. Five of these miRNA families are upregulated by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (miR169, miR397, miR827, miR1425 and miR408-5p) and two are downregulated (miR528 and miR319a.2). Among the direct targets of these miRNAs fall: a HAP2-like TF for miR169; laccases for miR397 (presumably involved in lignin biosynthesis); pentatricopeptide repeat proteins for miR1425 (important for organellar biogenesis); major facilitator superfamily proteins for miR408-5p and miR827 (a group of secondary transporters); putative IAR1 proteins (IAA-alanine resistance protein 1), known to be important for auxin homeostasis, for miR528; and a putative metacaspase for miR319a.2.The oxidative stress resulting from different environmental cues also leads to the modulation of many effectors that help to carry out adaptive changes of cellular physiology. A convenient system to study the effects of endogenous peroxisome-produced H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is presented by <italic>cat2</italic> knockout plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C74">Queval <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). This model was used to identify defence-related components that are controlled by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. One such modulator in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is the early H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive UDP-glucosyltransferase UGT74E2, which influences the water stress response and plant architecture by its preference for auxin indole-3-butyric acid (IBA) as a substrate for glycosylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C82">Tognetti <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). <italic>UGT74E2</italic> is a gene that responds with a drastic boost of expression (&gt;100-fold) in <italic>cat2</italic> mutants subjected to high-light treatment. Genetic analyses with plants ectopically expressing <italic>UGT74E2</italic> indicated that IBA and indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) homeostasis were altered, which resulted in structural changes like increased shoot branching and compressed rosette structure, as well as in significantly improved survival during drought and salt stress. Hence, the action of this UDP-glucosyltransferase presents a link in the interplay between H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and auxin pathways. In another recent study with <italic>cat2</italic>-deficient plants, it was demonstrated that <italic>myo</italic>-inositol (MI) levels are seriously decreased, independently of salicylic acid (SA) accumulation. These data indicate a role of MI in cell death triggered by peroxisomal H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and suggest that its cellular concentration is a major factor that determines the outcome of defence responses to oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C17">Chaouch and Noctor 2010</xref>).The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> peptide kiss of death (KOD) is another H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-inducible regulator of programmed cell death (PCD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C15">Blanvillain <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). It is induced nine-fold after application of 30 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> to leaf discs and its expression is linked to caspase3 activity, a strong hallmark of PCD. KOD is also involved in embryo development as its mutation reduces PCD of the suspensor cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C15">Blanvillain <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Although the mode of action of KOD is still unclear, it is the first short open reading frame peptide reported to be involved in PCD regulation.Earlier this year, a group in Tsinghua University performed the first apoplast proteome investigation of plant seedlings in response to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C98">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The authors propose a protein network that provides clues for oxidative stress responses in rice root apoplasts. Basically, the 54 differentially regulated H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-responsive proteins described in this study could be divided into two categories: related to redox regulation and related to cellular metabolism. The first group includes 24 proteins which sense stress signals and modulate redox state: many class III peroxidases, malate dehydrogenase, putative receptor-like proteins (RLPs), thiol redox-associated proteins (FMO and PDI), a chitinase and a pathogenesis-related protein (PR-1a). The second group is needed to adjust the metabolic flows in order to alleviate the deleterious effects of stress. Remarkably, 26 of all the reported proteins are involved in carbohydrate metabolism and 17 of these are glycosylhydrolases (GHs). Most of the latter are downregulated after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment, which may lead to rearrangements of cell wall constituents. On the other hand, enzymes like UDP-glucose pyrophosphorylase, pectinesterase and α-arabinofuranosidase are upregulated, and may contribute to strengthening the cell wall by influencing polysaccharide turnover and increasing pectin demethylesterification.Hydrogen peroxide communicates with a variety of other signalling molecules and plant hormones. Together they form an intricate network that is still not completely characterized. Here we present some details on the interaction of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> with Ca<sup>2+</sup>, SA and nitric oxide (NO).Like H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, Ca<sup>2+</sup> is also a ubiquitous second messenger able to orchestrate different physiological reactions. There are numerous data in the literature indicating that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> homeostasis are interdependent, with some cases in which H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> regulates Ca<sup>2+</sup> ion fluxes, while in others Ca<sup>2+</sup> affects H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> metabolism. A classic example of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-mediated Ca<sup>2+</sup> signalling is the cascade leading to stomatal closure in response to drought. In this chain of reactions, the plant hormone abscisic acid (ABA) induces the production of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in guard cells, which results in the opening of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeable channels and an increase in the cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> level ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>) in intact guard cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C69">Pei <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). Moreover, if H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production is blocked, ABA-induced closure of stomata is inhibited. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings, the application of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> triggers a biphasic Ca<sup>2+</sup> elevation, with the first peak located in cotyledons and the second in the root (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C76">Rentel and Knight 2004</xref>). Importantly, the short time needed before the first Ca<sup>2+</sup> rise suggests that Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx may be among the earliest responses to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. The delay in the second calcium peak indicates that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> may catalyse a [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> rise by specific mechanisms in different tissues. More recently, it was shown that spermidine oxidase-derived H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> regulates pollen plasma membrane hyperpolarization-activated Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels in order to induce pollen tube growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C88">Wu <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Pollen from polyamine oxidase (PAO) mutants was unable to cause the opening of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeable channels in the presence of spermidine, which resulted in reduced pollen tube growth and seed number.Cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> is in turn able to trigger changes in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration. Hydrogen peroxide synthesis requires a continuous Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx which activates NADPH oxidases located at the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C48">Lamb and Dixon 1997</xref>). Experiments with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> challenged with <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> demonstrated that the NADPH oxidase inhibitor diphenylene iodonium does not change the Ca<sup>2+</sup> balance, but the Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel blocker LaCl<sub>3</sub> suppresses H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation and the hypersensitive response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C41">Grant <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). Thus, in this case it is again Ca<sup>2+</sup> that acts upstream of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Similarly, it appears that in tobacco cells, the free sphingoid Long Chain Base (LCB) sphinganine induces transient increases in the nuclear and cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration and the downstream production of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C47">Lachaud <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Interestingly, according to the model of sphinganine signalling proposed by the authors, only the nuclear Ca<sup>2+</sup> flow is implicated in subsequent H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-independent cell death mechanisms, while the [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub> current is necessary for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced basal cell defence responses. Therefore, it seems that in this model system, cell death is uncoupled from H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> pathways.The antioxidant system may also be a target of Ca<sup>2+</sup> influence. For example, the efficiency of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> scavenging in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants depends on the peroxisomal Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C24">Costa <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). It appears that the intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> rise significantly accelerates H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> detoxification and this is achieved at least in part with the help of the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive catalase CAT3. Calmodulin (CaM) is a ubiquitous Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding protein, which can regulate a number of different protein targets, thereby affecting many different cellular functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C20">Chin and Means 2000</xref>). One of its targets is the MAP kinase 8 (MPK8) which is mainly operative after mechanical wounding. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C80">Takahashi <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> recently proved that the MPK8 pathway in turn negatively regulates H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> synthesis by controlling the expression of <italic>RbohD</italic>.Calcium-dependent protein kinases (CDPKs) sense the Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration changes in plant cells and play important roles in signalling pathways for disease resistance and a number of stress responses. In some cases, biotic and abiotic stresses are mediated by CDPKs, which are upregulated after an H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> burst. In tomato, <italic>LeCDPK1</italic> expression is rapidly and transiently enhanced in leaves treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C19">Chico <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). Similarly, in wheat, eight out of 20 studied CDPKs respond to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C51">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).Salicylic acid is a key signalling molecule in plants exposed to biotrophic pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C71">Pieterse <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), required for the establishment of the systemic acquired resistance (SAR) response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C29">Dempsey and Klessig 1994</xref>). Hydrogen peroxide can be linked directly to SA, since benzoic acid (the immediate precursor of SA) is converted into SA by the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-mediated activation of benzoic acid 2-hydroxylase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C50">León <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>). At the same time, SA also has the capacity to enhance the endogenous level of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, mainly by inducing the activation of SOD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C75">Rao <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>). Thus, according to this scenario H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and SA can work together as a self-amplifying system.In <italic>cat2</italic> plants, which were mentioned earlier, the effect of oxidative stress also relies on isochorismate synthase 1 (ICS1). This conclusion was drawn after the <italic>cat2</italic> line was crossed with <italic>sid2</italic>, which is defective in ICS1, and it was observed that lesion formation is completely absent in the <italic>cat2 sid2</italic> double mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C18">Chaouch <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). This indicates that the isochorismate pathway of SA synthesis couples intracellular oxidative stress to cell death and disease resistance responses. The <italic>cat2</italic> mutants were also used in a study that addresses the role of glutathione reductase 1 (GR1) in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C57">Mhamdi <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The authors carried out analyses in <italic>cat2 gr1</italic> double mutants and established that the GR1-dependent glutathione status is decisive for multiple responses to an increased H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration, including the accumulation of SA and the subsequent induction of pathogenesis-related genes. In turn, <italic>sid2</italic> plants were utilized to investigate seed germination processes under high salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C49">Lee <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). While the inhibitory effect of salt stress on <italic>sid2</italic> germination is strengthened in the presence of higher SA concentrations, treatment with &lt;50 µM SA significantly alleviates it. This can be partially explained by the fact that the elevation of endogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> levels is hindered after treatment with moderate doses of SA. The germination of <italic>sid2</italic> seeds under such conditions of high salinity is hypersensitive to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, but the physiological concentrations of SA modulate antioxidant activity to prevent oxidative damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C49">Lee <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).Similar results were obtained in tomato, where the effect of SA on root viability during NaCl treatments is also concentration dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C39">Gémes <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Again, the lower quantities of SA reduce the accumulation of ROS and NO, and help the plant withstand the salt stress, while the higher ones provoke an oxidative burst and disorganization of the root meristem. Salicylic acid provokes ameliorative effects during heavy metal stress as well. In a similar manner, the exogenous application of SA relieves Cd toxicity by reducing H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation in root apoplasts of the legumes <italic>Phaseolus aureus</italic> and <italic>Vicia sativa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C96">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). An example of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> antagonizing SA signalling is the nuclear translocation of the SAR-associated transcription activator NPR1. In this case, cytoplasmic H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was shown to inhibit the SA-induced transport of NPR1 to the nucleus and thus block the activation of pathogenesis-related (PR) genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C70">Peleg-Grossman <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).These results demonstrate that the interactions between H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and SA are multi-faceted, and can vary from cooperation to mutual inhibition in different contexts, concentrations and conditions.Nitric oxide is a second messenger in plants which displays both pro-oxidant and antioxidant properties. On the one hand, NO is able to induce scavenging of excess H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and thus inhibit peroxide signalling pathways; on the other hand, NO may also collaborate with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> to switch on SAR, or stress tolerance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C56">Małolepsza and Różlska 2005</xref>). For example, NO and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> have overlapping roles in the acclimation to salinity. Proteomic analysis revealed that 85 proteins vary quantitatively in citrus plants exposed to salt stress. However, pre-treatment with either H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> or sodium nitroprusside (a NO-releasing chemical) prevented changes in the accumulation levels of 45 of them and alleviated the detrimental effects of high salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C81">Tanou <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Another example of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and NO exerting similar functions is their influence on the stimulation or inhibition of root hair growth induced by different concentrations of extracellular nucleotides in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C22">Clark <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). In contrast, NO mediates tolerance to copper toxicity in tomatoes, partly by antagonizing the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> effect, as it efficiently leads to a boost of the antioxidant system activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C85">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010<italic>a</italic></xref>). Similarly, in maize leaves ABA-induced H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> production leads in turn to NO generation, which activates MAPK pathways, to finally result in the upregulation of the expression and activities of antioxidant enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C94">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).It was demonstrated that synergistic interactions between NO and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> can be necessary for induction of PCD. For example, in tobacco Bright Yellow-2 (TBY-2) cells, both molecules are required for the activation of PCD and the addition of an NO scavenger restores the cell viability after treatment with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C27">de Pinto <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Interestingly, the NO synthesis is stimulated only after direct application of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, but not after prolonged exposure to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, supporting the view that distinct signalling mechanisms are activated under different combinations of conditions. Similarly, in soybean cells, PCD can be triggered by high levels of NO, but only when supplemented with sublethal amounts of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Moreover, the SOD inhibitor sodium diethyldithiocarbamate blocks PCD progression in these cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C28">Delledonne <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). This proves that during HR, NO does not require the presence of O<sub>2</sub><sup>−</sup>, but needs H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (produced after the dismutation of O<sub>2</sub><sup>−</sup> catalysed by SOD) in order to activate the PCD machinery. However, in other cases, NO and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> do not seem to cooperate and only one of them is enough to cause PCD. For instance, in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> suspension cultures, high concentrations of NO are sufficient to induce PCD independently of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C23">Clarke <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>).In an intriguing new study, the map-based positional cloning of rice <italic>NOE1</italic>, a gene whose knockout leads to an excess of NO, revealed that this is actually the rice catalase OsCATC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C3">Lin <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Mutant <italic>noe1</italic> plants are characterized by increased leaf H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentrations, which in turn promote the synthesis of NO by the activation of the enzyme NR. This demonstrates that in some scenarios NO is produced downstream of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> as well. Since the removal of NO alleviates the symptoms of cell death in the <italic>noe1</italic> mutants, in this case NO seems to serve as an endogenous mediator of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced cell death.As described earlier, stomatal closure initiated by ABA is realized through an intracellular signalling pathway that includes H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeable channels. However, another major component in this chain of effectors appears to be NO. Indeed, exogenous NO is actually able to induce stomatal closure. Increased H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentrations provoked by ABA may in turn trigger NO generation by NR and nitrogen oxide synthase (NOS)-like enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C67">Neill <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). This presumably occurs through the action of the protein kinase OXI1 and involves Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C77">Rentel <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Another elicitor of stomatal closure is extracellular calmodulin (ExtCaM), which plays an important physiological role in the regulation of stomatal diurnal rhythm. Extracellular calmodulin and ABA can induce some parallel changes in second messenger levels in guard cells, including H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and NO. In the ExtCaM-mediated stomatal closure scenario, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> first accumulates after activation of GPA1—the α subunit of a heterotrimeric G protein, further downstream follows the AtNOA1-dependent NO accumulation, which ultimately leads to stomatal closure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C52">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).In a recent study, genetic screening for mutants defective in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced NO accumulation has identified the prohibitin gene <italic>PHB3</italic> as a player in the NO homeostasis system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS014C86">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010<italic>b</italic></xref>). Remarkably, <italic>phb3</italic> mutations do not appear to affect H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> metabolism or signalling, positioning prohibitin only in the NO pathway. These findings prove that although H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and NO influence and partly complement each other, their downstream networks diverge at some points.In the course of evolution, plants developed mechanisms to utilize potentially toxic ROS for signalling purposes. This turns ROS, and mainly H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, into signalling agents with tremendous impact on plant growth and behaviour. Since accumulation of higher concentrations of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is a potent inducer of cell death, a major scientific challenge is to reveal the regulatory processes that govern H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> metabolism and find a way to prevent excessive H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> synthesis in the field. Although the progress made in the last few years contributed to the overall knowledge concerning H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> physiology and unveiled many components in its signalling network, our knowledge is only scratching the surface. Their answers will have not only fundamental, but also practical importance, since crop yield depends on the capacity of plants to tolerate elevations in ROS. Perhaps the future deciphering of the subtle mechanisms of plants to fine-tune the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration holds the key for improving agriculture and responding to the demands of the ever-growing world population.This work was financially supported by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">EC FP7, 245588 project ‘Biosupport’</grant-sponsor> and by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Multidisciplinary Research Partnership ‘Ghent Bio-economy’</grant-sponsor>.V.P. and F.B. wrote the paper.None declared.We thank Annick Bleys for help in preparing the manuscript and Viktor Ivanov for designing the figures.