Effects of salinity and ascorbic acid on growth, water status and antioxidant system in a perennial halophyteCatalase <italic>in vitro</italic>The effect of combined salinity and waterlogging on the halophyte <italic>Suaeda maritima</italic>: the role of antioxidantsRole of superoxide dismutases (SODs) in controlling oxidative stress in plantsReactive oxygen species: metabolism, oxidative stress, and signal transductionThe role of ascorbic acid in cell metabolism: between gene-directed functions and unpredictable chemical reactionsAscorbic acid: much more than just an antioxidantExogenously applied ascorbic acid alleviates salt-induced oxidative stress in wheatPhysiological adaptations to seawater concentration in <italic>Avicennia marina</italic> from Indus delta, PakistanRapid determination of free proline for water-stress studiesSuperoxide dismutase: improved assays and an assay applicable to acrylamide gelsHow reactive oxygen species and proline face stress togetherPhotosynthetic activity and leaf antioxidative responses of <italic>Atriplex portulacoides</italic> subjected to extreme salinityAntioxidants, oxidative damage and oxygen deprivation stress: a reviewFlora of West Pakistan No. 28: PlumbaginaceaeROS homeostasis in halophytes in the context of salinity stress toleranceA rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye bindingEnvironmental stress sensitivity of an ascorbic acid-deficient <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutantInvolvement of soluble sugars in reactive oxygen species balance and responses to oxidative stress in plantsComparison of the effects of NaCl and KCl at the roots on seedling growth, cell death and the size, frequency and secretion rate of salt glands in leaves of <italic>Limonium sinense</italic>Antioxidant responses of rice seedlings to salinity stressThe effects of foliar application of ascorbic acid (Vitamin C) on antioxidant enzymes activities, lipid peroxidation and proline accumulation of Canola (<italic>Brassica napus</italic> L.) under conditions of salt stressResponse of flax cultivars to ascorbic acid and α-tocopherol under salinity stress conditionsSalt tolerance in <italic>Grevillea robusta</italic> seedlings via foliar application of ascorbic acidSalinity tolerance in halophytesThe presence of glutathione and glutathione reductase in chloroplasts: a proposed role in ascorbic acid metabolismL-ascorbic acid is accumulated in source leaf phloem and transported to sink tissues in plantsA reassessment of the function of the so-called compatible solutes in the halophytic Plumbaginaceae <italic>Limonium latifolium</italic>Ascorbate as seen through plant evolution: the rise of a successful moleculeReactive oxygen species and antioxidant machinery in abiotic stress tolerance in crop plantsProductivity and mineral nutrition of <italic>Limonium</italic> species irrigated with saline wastewatersPopulation characteristics of a coastal halophyte <italic>Arthrocnemum macrostachyum</italic>Comparative salt tolerance of perennial grassesGrowth, sodium uptake and antioxidant responses of coastal plants differing in their ecological status under increasing salinityHalophytes: biology and economic potentialsSalt tolerance of a cash crop halophyte <italic>Suaeda fruticosa</italic>: biochemical responses to salt and exogenous chemical treatmentsOsmoprotective compounds in the Plumbaginaceae: a natural experiment in metabolic engineering of stress tolerancePhotoperoxidation in isolated chloroplasts: I. Kinetics and stoichiometry of fatty acid peroxidationRedox states of glutathione and ascorbate in root tips of poplar (<italic>Populus tremula</italic> × <italic>P. alba</italic>) depend on phloem transport from the shoot to the rootsEffect of NaCl salinity on <italic>Atriplex nummularia</italic> (L.) with special emphasis on carbon and nitrogen metabolismAntioxidative response mechanisms in halophytes: their role in stress defencePlant peroxidases: biomarkers of metallic stressPlant sugars are crucial players in the oxidative challenge during abiotic stress: extending the traditional conceptThe effect of salinity on the growth, water status, and ion content of a leaf succulent perennial halophyte, <italic>Suaeda fruticosa</italic> (L.) ForsskA review of ascorbic acid potentialities against oxidative stress induced in plantsMolecular characterization of cDNAs for two anionic peroxidases from suspension cultures of sweet potatoIs proline accumulation <italic>per se</italic> correlated with stress tolerance or is proline homeostasis a more critical issue?Salinity effects on polyphenol content and antioxidant activities in leaves of the halophyte <italic>Cakile maritima</italic>Tissue specificity of tobacco peroxidase isozymes and their induction by wounding and tobacco mosaic virus infectionEffects of optimal and supra-optimal salinity stress on antioxidative defence, osmolytes and in vitro growth responses in <italic>Sesuvium portulacastrum</italic> LIsoprene produced by leaves protects the photosynthetic apparatus against ozone damage, quenches ozone products, and reduces lipid peroxidation of cellular membranesTocopherol biosynthesis: chemistry, regulation and effects of environmental factorsRole of ascorbate in detoxifying ozone in the apoplast of spinach (<italic>Spinacia oleracea</italic> L.) leavesBiochemistry and molecular biology of antioxidants in the rhizobia-legume symbiosisDifferences in water relations, leaf ion accumulation and excretion rates between cultivated and wild species of <italic>Limonium</italic> sp. grown in conditions of saline stressMechanisms of salinity toleranceHydrogen peroxide is scavenged by ascorbate-specific peroxidase in spinach chloroplastsEffects of salinity on growth, membrane permeability and root hydraulic conductivity in three saltbush speciesEffect of sucrose on ascorbate level and expression of genes involved in the ascorbate biosynthesis and recycling pathway in harvested broccoli floretsGalactinol and raffinose constitute a novel function to protect plants from oxidative damageAscorbate and glutathione: keeping active oxygen under controlReactive oxygen species regulation and antioxidant defence in halophytesSalt tolerance mechanisms in mangroves: a reviewDefense potentials to NaCl in a mangrove, <italic>Bruguiera parviflora</italic>: differential changes of isoforms of some antioxidative enzymesApoplastic ascorbate metabolism and its role in the regulation of cell signallingApoplastic peroxidases and lignification in needles of Norway spruce (<italic>Picea abies</italic> L.)Effects of ascorbic acid and gibberellin A3 on alleviation of salt stress in common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.) seedlingsUptake and fate of ascorbic acid-2-phosphate in infiltrated fruit and vegetable tissueDifferent antioxidant defense responses to salt stress during germination and vegetative stages of endemic halophyte <italic>Gypsophila oblanceolata</italic> BarkIon transport in halophytesExogenous ascorbic acid (vitamin C) increases resistance to salt stress and reduces lipid peroxidationAscorbic acid in plants: biosynthesis and functionLong-distance transport of L-ascorbic acid in potatoSelective and powerful stress gene expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> in response to malondialdehydeIntra- and inter-cellular compartmentation of ionsThe estimation of carbohydrates in plant extracts by anthrone<italic>Sphaerophysa kotschyana</italic>, an endemic species from Central Anatolia: antioxidant system responses under salt stressExogenously applied ascorbic acid ameliorates detrimental effects of NaCl and mannitol stress in <italic>Vicia faba</italic> seedlingsRecent progress of salinity tolerance research in plantsIron deficiency induced changes in ascorbate content and enzyme activities related to ascorbate metabolism in cucumber rootsPlant salt toleranceGrowth and selective ion transport of <italic>Limonium stocksii</italic> under saline conditions<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Tim J. FlowersThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<italic>Limonium stocksii</italic> is a potential commercial cut-flower crop for saline areas using brackish water. We therefore were interested to learn about the mechanism of its salinity tolerance. Plants grew well under lower saline conditions (300 mM NaCl) but higher salinities reduced growth. An increase in leaf osmolality and the management of salinity-induced oxidative stress are the key strategies employed. Exogenous AsA application improved the functioning of the AsA-dependent antioxidant system, leading to better growth.Salinity causes oxidative stress in plants by enhancing production of reactive oxygen species, so that an efficient antioxidant system, of which ascorbic acid (AsA) is a key component, is an essential requirement of tolerance. However, antioxidant responses of plants to salinity vary considerably among species. <italic>Limonium stocksii</italic> is a sub-tropical halophyte found in the coastal marshes from Gujarat (India) to Karachi (Pakistan) but little information exists on its salt resistance. In order to investigate the role of AsA in tolerance, 2-month-old plants were treated with 0 (control), 300 (moderate) and 600 (high) mM NaCl for 30 days with or without exogenous application of AsA (20 mM) or distilled water. Shoot growth of unsprayed plants at moderate salinity was similar to that of controls while at high salinity growth was inhibited substantially. Sap osmolality, AsA concentrations and activities of AsA-dependant antioxidant enzymes increased with increasing salinity. Water spray resulted in some improvement in growth, indicating that the growth promotion by exogenous treatments could partly be attributed to water. However, exogenous application of AsA on plants grown under saline conditions improved growth and AsA dependent antioxidant enzymes more than the water control treatment. Our data show that AsA-dependent antioxidant enzymes play an important role in salinity tolerance of <italic>L. stocksii</italic>.In plants soil salinity causes both osmotic stress and ionic toxicity, which can be lethal under prolonged exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C82">Zhu 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C56">Munns and Tester 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C80">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Halophytes survive salinity by sequestering salts in vacuoles and accumulating organic osmolytes in their cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C25">Flowers and Colmer 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C35">Hameed and Khan 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C58">Nedjimi 2014</xref>), thus reducing ion toxicity while maintaining osmo-balance. Halophytes may also employ shoot succulence, salt exclusion from roots, salt excretion through specialized salt glands and sequestering excess salt in old leaves to complete their life cycle under salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C25">Flowers and Colmer 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C70">Shabala and Mackay 2011</xref>). High salinity typically compromises carbon fixation, leading to the over reduction of light-harvesting complexes that cause production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C62">Ozgur <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C34">Hamed <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). These ROS are managed within a narrow functionally important range by using enzymatic and non-enzymatic antioxidants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C41">Jithesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C15">Bose <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). High salt stress, however, can make these systems inadequate causing severe injury that may lead to death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C35">Hameed and Khan 2011</xref>).Ascorbic acid (AsA) plays a key role in salt tolerance of many halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C41">Jithesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C62">Ozgur <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). It quenches ROS directly as well as through the Asada–Halliwell–Foyer pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C61">Noctor and Foyer 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C29">Gest <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). It also recycles the lipid-soluble antioxidant α-tocopherol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C52">Lushchak and Semchuk 2012</xref>). It may also contribute to maintaining photosynthesis, cell-cycle progression, cell wall expansion, gene expression, synthesis of many hormones, anthocyanin and flavonoids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C72">Smirnoff and Wheeler 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C6">Arrigoni and De Tullio 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C65">Pignocchi and Foyer 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C29">Gest <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). AsA is absorbed readily after exogenous application (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C79">Younis <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and moves within the plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C27">Franceschi and Tarlyn 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C74">Tedone <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C39">Herschbach <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Therefore, foliar application of AsA improves salt tolerance of crop plants in a number of ways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C7">Athar <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C21">Dolatabadian <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C22">ElHariri <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C24">Farahat <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), but little information is available on its role in halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>).<italic>Limonium stocksii</italic>, which is found in the coastal areas of Gujarat (India), Sindh and Balochistan (Pakistan) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C14">Bokhari 1973</xref>), is a salt-secreting perennial halophyte in Plumbaginaceae. This species is characterized by beautiful pink-purple flowers and has the potential to become a commercially important cut-flower like many other <italic>Limonium</italic> (aka Sea Lavender or Statice) species (<uri xlink:href="http://www.teleflora.com/about-flowers/statice.asp" xlink:type="simple">http://www.teleflora.com/about-flowers/statice.asp</uri>). Profit margins could be significantly enhanced if <italic>L. stocksii</italic> could be grown using seawater and on saline land. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C83">Zia <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> reported that it is a highly salt-tolerant species, but the mechanism of its salt tolerance is not very well understood. We hypothesized that AsA would play a key role in improving salt tolerance; therefore, we investigated: (i) the magnitude of oxidative damage, (ii) levels of enzymatic and non-enzymatic antioxidants and (iii) the role of exogenously applied AsA/water, in response to increasing NaCl concentration.Seed-bearing inflorescences of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> were collected during July 2009 from Hawks Bay, Karachi, Pakistan (24°52′21.87″N, 66°51′24.58″E, 17 ft. altitude, ∼1.5 km away from the sea front). Seeds were separated from the inflorescence and surface sterilized using 1 % sodium hypochlorite for a minute followed by rinsing with distilled water, air-dried and stored at room temperature.Seeds were sown in plastic pots (12 cm diameter) containing sandy soil and sub-irrigated with half-strength modified Hoagland's solution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C23">Epstein 1972</xref>) soon after seedling emergence. Salinity treatments [0 (Control), 300 and 600 mM NaCl] were applied at a rate of 150 mM NaCl per day to minimize osmotic shock. Tap water was used daily to compensate for evaporative loss and the irrigation medium was replaced every third day to avoid salt build up. One week after the final salinity concentrations were reached, plant shoots were sprayed until dripping with AsA (20 mM) or distilled water (each containing 0.1 % Tween-20); these treatments continued twice a week until harvest. Unsprayed plants were controls. Five plants per pot with four pots per treatment were used and were harvested after 30 days of salinity treatment.Shoot fresh weight (FW) was measured soon after harvest while dry weight (DW) was determined after placing plant samples in a forced-draft oven at 60 °C for at least 48 h or until constant weight was achieved.Leaf sap osmolality was determined with the help of a vapour pressure osmometer (VAPRO 5520, Wescor Inc., Logan, UT, USA).Free proline and total soluble sugars (TSS) were quantified in hot-water extracts, which were prepared by boiling finely ground dry plant material in distilled water at 100 °C for 1 h (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C44">Khan <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). Proline in hot-water extracts was quantified according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C9">Bates <italic>et al.</italic> (1973)</xref>. Diluted hot-water extract (1 mL) was added to 1 mL of ninhydrin : glacial acetic acid (1 : 1 v/v) mixture in a test tube, followed by heating at 100 °C for 1 h. After cooling in an ice-bath, proline was estimated from the absorbance (at 520 nm; Beckman DU-530 spectrophotometer, Beckman Coulter Inc., Brea, CA, USA) of the chromophore extracted in toluene using a standard curve with pure proline.Total soluble sugars were determined using anthrone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C77">Yemm and Willis 1954</xref>). Diluted hot-water extract was mixed with anthrone reagent and incubated in a water bath at 100 °C for 30 min. The reaction was stopped in an ice bath and absorbance was noted at 630 nm with Beckman DU-530 spectrophotometer.Ascorbic acid concentration was estimated by using a slightly modified method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C53">Luwe <italic>et al.</italic> (1993)</xref>. Freshly harvested plant sample (0.5 g) was ground in liquid nitrogen mortar and then homogenized in ice-cold trichloroacetic acid (TCA, 1 % w/v). The homogenate was then centrifuged at 12 000 × g for 20 min at 4 °C and the supernatant (50 µL) mixed with potassium phosphate buffer (0.95 mL, 100 mM, pH 7.0) and ascorbate oxidase (1 μL of 1 Unit µL<sup>−1</sup>). Oxidation of AsA (<italic>ε</italic> = 14.3 mM<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−1</sup>) was then recoded at 265 nm.Antioxidant enzymes were extracted as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C66">Polle <italic>et al.</italic> (1994)</xref> with some modifications. Fresh plant samples (0.5 g) were powdered in liquid nitrogen mortar and homogenized in potassium phosphate buffer (5 mL of 100 mM, pH 7.0) containing 0.5 % triton X-100, 2 % (w/v) polyvinylpyrrolidone, 5 mM disodium ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid and 1 mM <sc>l</sc>-AsA. Homogenates were then centrifuged at 12 000 × g for 20 min at 4 °C and the supernatants used in enzyme assays carried out at 25 °C. The activity of superoxide dismutase (SOD; EC 1.15.1.1) was measured by the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C10">Beauchamp and Fridovich (1971)</xref>; catalase (CAT; EC 1.11.1.6) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C1">Aebi (1984)</xref>; guaiacol peroxidase (GPX, EC 1.11.1.7) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C81">Zaharieva <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref>; ascorbate peroxidase (APX, EC 1.11.1.11) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C57">Nakano and Asada (1981)</xref> and glutathione reductase (GR, EC 1.6.4.2) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C26">Foyer and Halliwell (1976)</xref>. Enzyme activities were defined as in original methods and expressed as units of enzyme activity per milligram protein, which was estimated according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C16">Bradford (1976)</xref>.Endogenous hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) was measured using the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C51">Loreto and Velikova (2001)</xref>.The extent of lipid peroxidation was estimated by quantifying the malondialdehyde (MDA) content of leaves according to the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C38">Heath and Packer (1968)</xref>.Statistical analysis of the data was carried out using SPSS version 11.0 for windows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C73">SPSS Inc. 2001</xref>). Two-way analysis of variances (ANOVAs) were used to determine whether salinity, exogenous treatments and their interactions as grouping factors had significant effect on response variables such as biomass and biochemical parameters. A post hoc Bonferroni test was performed to find significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) differences among individual means of the treatments.Two-way ANOVA of the effects of exogenous treatments (E), salinity (S) and their interaction (E × S) on different parameters of <italic>Limonium stocksii</italic>. Numbers are the <italic>F</italic>-values with the level of significance given as superscript. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ns, non-significant.Effect of salinity and exogenous treatments on shoot growth of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings. Fresh (A) and dry (B) weight values (in mg plant<sup>−1</sup>) are given as bars representing mean ± standard error of four plants. Different capital letters across salinity treatments and small letters within each salinity level are significantly different from each other (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Bonferroni test).Effect of salinity and exogenous treatments on (A) leaf sap osmolality and (B) water content of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings. Bars represent mean ± standard error. Different capital letters across salinity treatments and small letters within each salinity level are significantly different from each other (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Bonferroni test).Effect of salinity and exogenous treatments on (A) proline, (B) TSS and (C) reduced ascorbate (AsA) concentrations of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> leaves. Bars represent mean ± standard error. Different capital letters across salinity treatments and small letters within each salinity level are significantly different from each other (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Bonferroni test).Effects of salinity and exogenous treatments on SOD (A), CAT (B), GPX (C), APX (D) and GR (E) activities of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> leaves. Bars represent mean ± standard error. Different capital letters across salinity treatments and small letters within each salinity level are significantly different from each other (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Bonferroni test).Effect of salinity and exogenous treatments on hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) concentrations of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> leaves. Bars represent mean ± standard error. Different capital letters across salinity treatments and small letters within each salinity level are significantly different from each other (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Bonferroni test).Effect of salinity and exogenous treatments on lipid peroxidation (MDA concentration) in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> leaves. Bars represent mean ± standard error. Different capital letters across salinity treatments and small letters within each salinity level are significantly different from each other (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Bonferroni test).<italic>Limonium stocksii</italic> gained similar biomass over 30 days in 300 mM NaCl as in the absence of salt; however, a further increase in salinity markedly inhibited biomass production. Although growth inhibition occurred at high salinity, <italic>L. stocksii</italic> appears to be more tolerant than other members of the genus: as growth inhibition was observed in <italic>L. perezii</italic> at 110 mM NaCl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C31">Grieve <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>) and in <italic>L. sinense</italic> at 300 mM NaCl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C19">Ding <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>); growth of <italic>L. pectinatum</italic> was promoted at 100 mM NaCl and was similar to control at 200 mM NaCl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C55">Morales <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). Our results are also similar to growth responses reported for co-occurring halophytes such as <italic>Suaeda fruticosa</italic>, <italic>Arthrocnemum macrostachyum</italic>, <italic>Avicennia marina</italic>, <italic>Aeluropus lagopoides</italic> and <italic>Urochondra setulosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C32">Gul and Khan 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C8">Aziz and Khan 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C44">Khan <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C33">Gulzar and Khan 2006</xref>).Halophytes utilize internal inorganic ions (Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup>) for osmotic adjustment, by sequestering them in vacuoles with associated synthesis and accumulation of organic/compatible solutes in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C76">Wyn Jones and Gorham 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C25">Flowers and Colmer 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C40">Hussin <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The increase in leaf sap osmolality of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings with rise in external salinity could be an indicator of such solute accumulation for osmotic adjustment. The linear increase in shoot Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> ions in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings reported in an earlier study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C83">Zia <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) also supports this assumption. Similar results have been reported for co-occurring species such as <italic>S. fruticosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), <italic>A. marina</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C8">Aziz and Khan 2000</xref>) and <italic>U. setulosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C33">Gulzar and Khan 2006</xref>). Accumulation of compatible solutes such as choline-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate and betaines of β-alanine, proline and hydroxyl-proline, as reported for taxa within Plumbaginaceae, could also be responsible for osmotic adjustment in our test species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C37">Hanson <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C28">Gagneul <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C25">Flowers and Colmer 2008</xref>).Salinity is widely reported to enhance production of ROS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C62">Ozgur <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), which can damage important cell components such as proteins, lipids and nucleic acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C13">Blokhina <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C4">Apel and Hirt 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C30">Gill and Tuteja 2010</xref>). We also observed an increase in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration (a common ROS) in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings in response to increasing salinity, as reported for many other halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C41">Jithesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C62">Ozgur <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Lipid peroxidation, a non-enzymatic autoxidation process due to ROS, is commonly used as a measure of salinity-induced oxidative stress and plant sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C62">Ozgur <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). It is generally measured in terms of MDA contents, which are common end-products of lipid peroxidation. Generally, a positive linear relationship between MDA concentration and salinity is reported for halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C41">Jithesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C62">Ozgur <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). For instance, MDA concentrations increased with increasing salinity in halophytes such as <italic>Cakile maritima</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C48">Ksouri <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), <italic>Sesuvium portulacastrum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C50">Lokhande <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), <italic>Gypsophila oblanceolata</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C69">Sekmen <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and <italic>Sphaerophysa kotschyana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C78">Yildiztugay <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). We also found a linear increase in MDA concentrations with increasing NaCl treatments in <italic>L. stocksii</italic>. Although the relationship between MDA levels and plant performance is complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C2">Alhdad <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), some stress signalling roles of MDA are also emerging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C75">Weber <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Slightly higher MDA concentrations in <italic>S. fruticosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) were associated with better growth.Halophytes employ a number of enzymatic and non-enzymatic antioxidants to prevent oxidative damage and keep ROS concentrations within a narrow functional rage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C41">Jithesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C62">Ozgur <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Superoxide dismutase is considered the first line of defence against ROS under stress conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C3">Alscher <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). <italic>Limonium stocksii</italic> seedlings under saline conditions showed increased activity of SOD, which was similar to that reported for <italic>Bruguiera parviflora</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C64">Parida <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>), <italic>Atriplex portulacoides</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C12">Benzarti <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and <italic>S. portulacastrum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C50">Lokhande <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Catalase activity in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> remained unchanged with the increase in salinity indicating either constitutive expression or importance of other than CAT-based H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> detoxification under salinity stress. Similar CAT activity was also reported for another halophyte <italic>A. portulacoides</italic> in up to 400 mM NaCl salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C12">Benzarti <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Guaiacol peroxidase activity increased significantly in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings under salinity as in <italic>B. parviflora</italic> under saline conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C64">Parida <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Apart from their role in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> detoxification, GPXs are also involved in a number of physio-chemical processes such as growth, auxin metabolism, biosynthesis of ethylene and lignin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C49">Lagrimini and Rothstein 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C20">Dionisio-Sese and Tobita 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C46">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C54">Matamoros <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C42">Jouili <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Activities of APX and GR were reported to increase in <italic>A. portulacoides</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C12">Benzarti <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), <italic>Salicornia brachiata</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C63">Parida and Jha 2010</xref>) and <italic>B. parviflora</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C64">Parida <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) under salinity stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C41">Jithesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). A similar increase in the activities of these enzymes in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> was also observed indicating their role in ROS detoxification under salinity stress.Many low-molecular-weight antioxidant substances such as AsA are also involved in ROS detoxification in halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C41">Jithesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C35">Hameed and Khan 2011</xref>). AsA contents of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> leaves increased under saline conditions similar to <italic>Sphaerophysa kotschyana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C78">Yildiztugay <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Increased AsA concetrations in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> could be due to better recycling via the Asada–Halliwell–Foyer pathway and/or its increased biosynthesis. Soluble sugar concentrations of <italic>L. stocksii</italic> leaves increased under saline conditions and this supports a direct relationship between sugar (sucrose) concentration and AsA biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C59">Nishikawa <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Soluble sugars can also act as ROS scavengers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C18">Couée <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C60">Nishizawa <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C43">Keunen <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).Proline accumulation is often used as stress indicator in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C47">Kishor and Sreenivasulu 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C11">Ben Rejeb <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). However, proline levels remained unchanged in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings under saline conditions. This may indicate adequate stress management and the absence of injury symptoms also supports this assumption.Experiments for studying effects of exogenous application of different chemicals such as AsA involve spray of aqueous solutions and any improvement in growth and salt tolerance by such treatments may be due to water rather than the chemical. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> showed the importance of such water-spray in salinity tolerance of a coastal halophyte <italic>S. fruticosa</italic>. Water-spray improved sub-cellular defence in <italic>S. fruticosa</italic> probably by mitigating osmotic constraint thereby water acquisition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Water-spray on <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings resulted in a significant improvement in growth and levels of antioxidant enzymes. This indicates that the improvement in growth by exogenous AsA treatment could partly be due to water in the solution rather than the AsA itself: an increase in leaf water content and levels of TSS and proline and low oxidative damage support this conclusion. However, the DW was greater in the AsA treatment than the water-spray alone at all salinities (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV004F1">1</xref>), suggesting specific effects of AsA. At high salinity, the TSS concentration and the activities of the antioxidant enzymes were higher with the AsA-treatment than with the water-spray alone (only for GPX the difference was not significant). The proline concentration was higher in the AsA treatment than with the water-spray at the 300 mM treatment, but not at the higher salinity. Based on our results, it appears that AsA does bring about specific improvements to growth and these were associated with biochemical changes in the leaves. Similar results for the treatment with AsA have been reported for <italic>S. fruticosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and in many non-halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C71">Shalata and Neumann 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C21">Dolatabadian <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C79">Younis <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Exogenously applied AsA is easily absorbed, transported and metabolized in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C68">Sapers <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C27">Franceschi and Tarlyn 2002</xref>), where it has a variety of metabolic and physiological functions in antioxidant defence, photosynthesis, transmembrane electron transport, biosynthesis of plant hormones and/or cell expansion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C17">Conklin <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C5">Arrigoni and De Tullio 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C6">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C45">Khan <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).Exogenous application of AsA decreased lipid peroxidation in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings under salinity as reported for <italic>S. fruticosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C36">Hameed <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and in crops such as <italic>Brassica napus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C21">Dolatabadian <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) and <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C67">Saeidi-Sar <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), indicating better antioxidant defence. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C71">Shalata and Neumann (2001)</xref> pointed out that the protective effects of exogenous AsA appeared to be related to its antioxidant activity rather than its possible use as an organic substrate for respiratory metabolism. Exogenous AsA significantly increased levels of endogenous AsA and Asada–Halliwell–Foyer pathway enzymes in <italic>L. stocksii</italic> seedlings compared with both un-sprayed and water-sprayed plants. Likewise, exogenous AsA also increased APX and GR activities in <italic>Vicia faba</italic> seedlings compared with control plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV004C79">Younis <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). These findings show that the exogenous AsA improves salinity tolerance through stimulating antioxidant defence.Pictorial description of key findings.The authors thank <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Higher Education Commission of Pakistan</grant-sponsor> for provision of funds under a research grant entitled ‘Salt-induced Oxidative Stress: Consequences and Possible Management’.Obtaining funds: M.A.K.; experiment designing: A.H., B.G., M.A.K.; execution of experiments: A.H., T.H.; data analyses: A.H., S.G., I.A., B.G.; paper writing: M.A.K., A.H., S.G., I.A.None declared.We thank Ms Aysha Rasheed for her help in some biochemical assays. We also thank anonymous reviewers and Associate Editor Tim Flowers for their valuable comments, which were very helpful.