 Characterization of Na +  uptake in the endangered desert pupfish,  Cyprinodon macularius  (Baird and Girard)  High salinity mortality of desert pupfish,  Cyprinodon macularius   Sodium and chloride transport in soft water and hard water acclimated zebrafish ( Danio rerio )  Comparative characterization of Na +  transport in  Cyprinodon variegatus variegatus  and  Cyprinodon variegatus hubbsi : a model species complex for studying teleost invasion of freshwater  Evaluation of pre- and post-zygotic mating barriers, hybrid fitness and phylogenetic relationship between  Cyprinodon variegatus variegatus  and  Cyprinodon variegatus hubbsi  (Cyprinodontiformes, Teleostei)  Allozymic variation in desert pupfish from natural and artificial habitats: genetic conservation in fluctuating populations  Inhibitory effect of low salinity on growth and reproduction of the estuarine sheepshead minnow,  Cyprinodon variegatus   Mitochondrial DNA variation in pupfishes assigned to the species  Cyprinodon macularius  (Atherinomorpha: Cyprinodontidae): taxonomic implications and conservation genetics  Historical biogeography of the new-world pupfish genus  Cyprinodon  (Teleostei: Cyprinodontidae)  The multifunctional fish gill: dominant site of gas exchange, osmoregulation, acid-base regulation, and excretion of nitrogenous waste  GraphPad Prism  Mechanism of acid adaptation of a fish living in a pH 3.5 lake  Ion regulation in fish gills: recent progress in the cellular and molecular mechanisms  Salinity of Surface Water in the Lower Colorado River-Salton Sea Area  Importance for absorption of Na +  from freshwater of lysine, valine and serine substitutions in the α1a-isoform of Na,K-ATPase in the gills of rainbow trout ( Oncorhynchus mykiss ) and Atlantic salmon ( Salmo salar )  Growth, food intake, and food conversion in a euryplastic fish exposed to different temperature and salinities  Amiloride and its analogs as tools in the study of ion transport  Ammonia excretion via Rhcg1 facilitates Na +  uptake in larval zebrafish,  Danio rerio , in acidic water  Expression regulation of Na + -K + -ATPase α1-subunit subtypes in zebrafish gill ionocytes  Genetic structure of wild populations of the endangered desert pupfish complex (Cyprinodontidae:  Cyprinodon )  Les echanges de sodium chez les poissons  Carassius auratus  L. Action d'un inhibiteur d l'anhydrase carbonique  Desert Pupfish ( Cyprinodon macularius ) Recovery Plan  Ion transport, osmoregulation, and acid-base balance  Relation of desert pupfish abundance to selected environmental variables in natural and manmade habitats in the Salton Sea basin  The Status of  Cyprinodon macularius  and  Cyprinodon nevadensis , Two Desert Fishes of Western North America  Description and conservation status of  Cyprinodon macularius eremus , a new subspeces of pupfish from Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument, Arizona  Physiochemical environments and tolerances of cyprinodontoid fishes found in estuaries and salt marshes of eastern North America  A phylogenetic analysis and taxonomic revision of ricefishes,  Oryzias  and relatives (Beloniformes, Adrianichthyidae)  Ion and acid-base regulation in the freshwater mummichog ( Fundulus heteroclitus ): a departure from the standard model for freshwater teleosts  Gene expression after freshwater transfer in gills and opercular epithelia of killifish: insight into divergent mechanisms of ion transport  SigmaStat 3.5  Investigation of the Salton Sea  Role of SLC12A10.2, a Na-Cl cotransporter-like protein, in a Cl uptake mechanism in zebrafish ( Danio rerio )  Late Holocene lacustrine chronology and archaeology of ancient Lake Cahuilla, California  Ammonium-dependent sodium uptake in mitochondrion-rich cells of medaka ( Oryzias latipes ) larvae  Salinity-dependent expression of the branchial Na + /K + /2Cl −  cotransporter and Na + /K + -ATPase in the sailfin molly correlates with hypoosmoregulatory endurance   Editor:  Steven Cooke  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  This study investigated the mechanism of Na +  uptake in freshwater by the endangered pupfish,  Cyprinodon macularius. Cyprinodon macularius  exhibits a low-affinity uptake system and appears to be relatively inflexibile with respect to mechanisms of Na +  uptake compared with most freshwater species.  This study provided an initial characterization of Na +  uptake in saline freshwater by the endangered pupfish,  Cyprinodon macularius.  This species occurs only in several saline water systems in the southwestern USA and northern Mexico, where salinity is largely controlled by water-management practices. Consequently, understanding the osmoregulatory capacity of this species is important for their conservation. The lower acclimation limit of  C. macularius  in freshwater was found to be 2 mM Na + . Fish acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na +  displayed similar Na +  uptake kinetics, with  K   m   values of 4321 and 3672 μM and  V  max  values of 4771 and 3602 nmol g −1  h −1 , respectively. A series of experiments using pharmacological inhibitors indicated that Na +  uptake in  C. macularius  was not sensitive to bumetanide, metolazone, or phenamil. These results indicate the Na + –K + –2Cl −  cotransporter, Na + –Cl −  cotransporter, and the Na +  channel–H + -ATPase system are likely not to be involved in Na +  uptake at the apical membrane of fish gill ionocytes in fish acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + . However, Na +  uptake was sensitive to 1 × 10 −3  M amiloride (not 1 × 10 −4  or 1 × 10 −5  M), 5-( N -ethyl- N -isopropyl)-amiloride (EIPA), and ethoxzolamide. These data suggest that  C. macularius  relies on a low-affinity Na + –H +  exchanger for apical Na +  uptake and that H +  ions generated via carbonic anhydrase-mediated CO 2  hydration are important for the function of this protein.  The fish genus  Cyprinodon  (Cyprinodontiformes) is thought to have originated in the southwestern USA or northern Mexico ∼7–8 million years ago ( Echelle  et al. , 2005 ). Today, approximately 50 species of  Cyprinodon  have been described, with ∼40 of these species in the arid Southwest. The remaining species are spread along the Gulf of Mexico and Atlantic coastline from Venezuela to Massachusetts, as well as many of the Caribbean Islands. The majority of species live in relatively stenohaline environments (although there may be seasonal variation) ranging from slightly saline springs to athalassic lakes with salinities approximately twice that of seawater.  The desert pupfish,  Cyprinodon macularius , historically ranged from the Gila River in Arizona to the Salton Sea in California and down into the Colorado delta region of Sonora and Baja ( Miller, 1943 ). However, due to various water-management projects (reservoirs, water-diversion canals) and introduced species,  C. macularius  has disappeared from the Gila and lower Colorado rivers, and populations have declined at other locations ( Miller and Fuiman, 1987 ;  Dunham and Minckley, 1998 ). Currently, there are only two populations of  C. macularius , one located in the Salton Sink area and the other located on the Colorado river delta.  Diversion of the Colorado river has periodically flooded the Salton Sink, forming ancient Lake Cahuilla. There have been four historical flooding events in the past 2000 years, with the lake persisting for periods of ∼50–250 years each time ( Waters, 1983 ). The most recent diversion occurred in 1905, forming what is now called the Salton Sea, and  C. macularius  was observed relatively quickly after its formation ( Thompson, 1920 ). The diversion ended in 1907, and salinity has been gradually increasing to its current level of ∼50 g l −1 . Historical monitoring data on salinity in the Colorado river prior to various dam projects indicate that the feed water for the Salton Sea had an Na +  concentration in the range of 3–10 mM ( Irelan, 1971 ), providing an estimate of the minimal salinity to which  C. macularius  may have been exposed in the past century. Populations of  C. macularius  are currently restricted to saline springs and creeks that drain to the Salton Sea, where salinities range from ∼1 to 50 g l −1  ( Kinne, 1960 ;  Martin and Saiki, 2005 ).  A form now recognized as  Cyprinodon eremus  occurs in Quitobaquito Springs, Arizona and in the Rio Sonoyta, Sonora, Mexico ( Echelle  et al. , 2000 ;  Loftis  et al. , 2009 ). Together,  C. macularius  and  C. eremus  are currently listed as a federally endangered species in the USA ( Marsh and Sada, 1993 ).  Despite the impact of various man-made alterations to water flow and salinity regimens in the region, the osmoregulatory capacity of  C. macularius  has received little study.  Barlow (1958)  concluded that  C. macularius  had an upper salinity threshold of 90 g l −1  based on observations made in small hypersaline pools along the shoreline of the Salton Sea.  Kinne (1960)  demonstrated that larvae can survive and grow at salinities ranging from freshwater to 55 g l −1 , with an optimal salinity between 10 and 40 g l −1 .  Our interest was in the osmoregulatory capacity of  C. macularius  in freshwater conditions, and more specifically, in Na +  regulation. Freshwater teleosts must compensate for the diffusive loss of osmolytes through active uptake of ions against their chemical gradients ( Evans  et al. , 2005 ;  Marshall and Grosell, 2006 ). Active Na +  uptake occurs primarily in gill ionocytes and is driven by Na + –K + -ATPase located on the basolateral membrane of these cells. Entry of Na +  from water into the cell across the apical membrane can be accomplished by several different proteins. A putativie Na +  channel linked to H + -ATPase and two Na + –H +  exchanger (NHE) isoforms are the primary mechanisms used by teleosts studied to date ( Hwang  et al. , 2011 ). In slightly saline waters (5–10 mM NaCl), Cl − -dependent Na +  uptake via an Na + –Cl −  cotransporter or Na + –K + –2Cl −  cotransporter (NKCC) has also been demonstrated in some fish ( Wang  et al. , 2009 ;  Yang  et al. , 2011 ).  We have previously characterized osmoregulation in the euryhaline coastal pupfish,  Cyprinodon variegatus variegatus , as well as the subspecies,  Cyprinodon variegatus hubbsi  ( Brix and Grosell, 2012 ).  Cyprinodon v. variegatus  occurs along the Gulf and Atlantic coasts of North America and tolerates salinities ranging from freshwater up to 167 g l −1  ( Nordlie, 2006 ). Previous studies indicate  C. v. variegatus  does not survive (long term), grow, or reproduce in freshwater with &lt;2 mM Na +  ( Dunson  et al. , 1998 ). In contrast,  C. v. hubbsi  occurs in only eight freshwater lakes in central Florida. These lakes have ambient Na +  concentrations of 0.4–1.0 mM Na + , below the level typically tolerated by  C. v. variegatus , suggesting that  C. v. hubbsi  has adapted to this more dilute freshwater environment.  We demonstrated that  C. v. variegatus  and  C. v. hubbsi  bred and raised in common garden conditions (freshwater with 7 mM Na + ) have similar low-affinity Na +  uptake kinetics ( K  m  = 7000–38 000 μM) when acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + , while  C. v. hubbsi  switches to a high-affinity system ( K  m  = 100–140 μM) when acclimated to low-Na +  freshwater (≤1 mM Na + ) characteristic of its native habitat ( Brix and Grosell, 2012 ). We further demonstrated, through a series of experiments with pharmacological inhibitors, that  C. v. variegatus  appears to utilize a combination of an NHE and an NKCC for Na +  uptake across the apical membrane of gill ionocytes at 7 mM Na + , but only an NHE at 2 mM Na + . In contrast,  C. v. hubbsi  appears to utilize only a low-affinity NHE when acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + , and a high-affinity NHE when acclimated to 0.1 or 1 mM Na + . Sodium uptake is not sensitive to bafilomycin (an H + -ATPase inhibitor) in either subspecies in any conditions, but Na +  uptake in  C. v. hubbsi  is sensitive to phenamil, leading to some uncertainty about the possible involvement of a Na +  channel–H + -ATPase system in this subspecies ( Brix and Grosell, 2012 ).  Given the above findings, we hypothesized that  C. macularius , which has evolved in relatively saline water and is rarely or never likely to encounter waters with &lt;3 mM Na + , would exhibit similar Na +  transport kinetics and utilize the same Na +  transport proteins as  C. v. variegatus . In addition to providing useful management information on this endangered species, if this hypothesis proved correct, it would provide weight of evidence regarding the basal Na +  transport characteristics of  Cyprinodon  and a better context in which to evaluate the apparent adaptations in  C. v. hubbsi  to osmoregulate in dilute freshwater.  Adult  C. macularius  were acquired from an in-house culture maintained by the US Geological Survey laboratory in Columbia, MO (US Fish and Wildlife Service Endangered Species Permit #TE2057312). The US Geological Survey had collected their initial stock from the Salton Sea population of  C. macularius  in 2002, and the fish were maintained at 25°C in hard well water (300 mg l −1  hardness) adjusted to a salinity of 5 g l −1  with aquarium sea salts (Instant Ocean). Fish were held at the University of Miami in 110 l glass aquaria at 23–26°C in flow-through conditions, initially with filtered natural seawater (35 g l −1 ) from Bear Cut, FL, USA. Fish were acclimated to near-freshwater conditions (0.3 gl −1 ; 7 mM Na + , pH 7.9) over a period of 4 days and held for &gt;30 days. After this holding period, fish were bred, and offspring were hatched and raised to sexual maturity in the same near-freshwater conditions (0.3 gl −1 ; 7 mM Na + , pH 7.9). Dechlorinated City of Miami tapwater (∼1.0 mM Na + , 1.0 mM Cl − , 0.5 mM Ca 2+ , 0.2 mM Mg 2+ , 0.5 mM SO 4  2−  and 0.8 mM HCO 3  − , pH 7.9) was mixed with filtered natural seawater to achieve the desired salinity. This second generation was then bred in the same conditions to produce fish used for all experiments in this study. Throughout the acclimation and holding period, as well as during all experiments,  C. macularius  were fed  Artemia  nauplii for 2 weeks posthatch and then, over a 1 week period, gradually switched over to flake food (Tetramin™ Tropical Flakes).  The Na +  uptake kinetics of  C. macularius  were determined in juvenile fish (26–240 mg) acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na +  for at least 3 weeks prior to experimentation. In a preliminary experiment, attempts to acclimate juvenile and adult  C. macularius  to 1 mM Na +  over a 4 day period resulted in ∼50% mortality within 96 h, so 2 mM Na +  was considered the lower limit for this species. For each experiment, Na +  uptake rates were measured at seven or eight different ambient Na +  concentrations ranging from 0.174 to 57.1 mM Na +  depending on the Na +  concentration to which they were acclimated. At each Na +  concentration, eight juvenile fish were placed in 50 ml of a defined medium (480 μM CaSO 4 , 150 μM MgSO 4  and 100 μM KHCO 3 , pH 7.0, 23°C), to which a targeted concentration of NaCl was added. Test solutions were continuously aerated to maintain dissolved oxygen levels during the flux period. Fish were allowed to acclimate to this medium for 10 min, after which the medium was replaced with fresh solution of the same ionic composition, and 1–2 μCi of   22  Na (depending on ambient Na +  concentration) was added to the solution. The flux solution (1 ml) was sampled after 1 min for measurements of [Na + ] and   22  Na activity. The total flux exposure period ranged from 0.9 to 2.3 h, depending on the ambient Na +  concentration being tested. In all cases, the internal specific activity was &lt;1% of the external specific activity (assuming 150 mM Na +  in plasma) such that correction for backflux was unnecessary ( Maetz, 1956 ). At the end of the exposure period, water samples for [Na + ] and   22  Na activity were again collected, fish were removed from the exposure media, double rinsed in a 100 mM Na +  solution to displace any loosely bound   22  Na, blotted dry, euthanized with an overdose of MS-222, weighed to nearest 0.1 mg, and then assayed individually for radioactivity.  Juvenile  C. macularius  were acclimated to different Na +  concentrations as described above. Experiments were then performed to measure Na +  uptake in the presence and absence of different pharmacological inhibitors. Initial experiments were conducted using amiloride ( N -amidino-3.5-diamino-6-chloropyrazinecarbromide), which inhibits both Na +  channels and NHEs, with a higher affinity for Na +  channels ( Kleyman and Cragoe, 1988 ). We tested three amiloride concentrations in an attempt to distinguish effects between the Na +  channel and NHE pathways. For the control and amiloride treatments, eight juvenile  C. macularius  were exposed in 48 ml of the water to which they were acclimated. Fish were allowed to acclimate for 10 min to the test system, after which the water was replaced with fresh solution of the same ionic composition. Amiloride dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) was then added to achieve final concentrations of 1 × 10 −5 , 1 × 10 −4 , or 1 × 10 −3  M amiloride and 0.1% DMSO, while for the control group only DMSO was added. After allowing 5 min for the drug to take effect, 0.2 μCi of   22  Na was added to each treatment, and the fish were exposed for 2 h. At the beginning and end of the exposure period, a 1 ml sample was collected for measurement of [Na + ] and   22  Na activity. At the end of the exposure period, fish were treated as described in the Na +  uptake experiments above.  Similar experimental designs were used in subsequent inhibitor experiments, again testing fish acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + .  Cyprinodon macularius  were exposed to 5 × 10 −5  M 5-( N -ethyl- N -isopropyl)-amiloride (EIPA), which is a potent NHE inhibitor with low affinity for Na +  channels, and 1 × 10 −5  M phenamil, a Na +  channel inhibitor with relatively low affinity for NHEs ( Kleyman and Cragoe, 1988 ). In order to investigate the presence/absence of a chloride-dependent Na +  transporter, juvenile fish were exposed to 1 × 10 −4  M bumetanide (NKCC inhibitor) and 1 × 10 −5  M metolazone (Na + –Cl −  cotransporter inhibitor) in separate experiments. Finally, we investigated the potential role of carbonic anhydrase (CA) in Na +  uptake by exposing fish to 10 −4  M ethoxzolamide (6-ethoxy-1,3-benzothiazole-2-sulfonamide), a potent CA inhibitor.  Total Na +  in water samples was measured by atomic absorption spectrophotometry (Varian Spectra AA-220, Mulgrave, Victoria, Australia). Water and fish samples were measured for   22  Na activity using a γ-counter with a window of 15–2000 keV (Packard Cobra II Auto-Gamma, Meriden, CT, USA). Rates of Na +  uptake as measured by the appearance of radioactivity in the fish (in nanomoles per gram per hour) were calculated following  Boisen  et al.  (2003) .  All values are expressed as means ± SEM. Comparison data were analysed by Student's unpaired  t -test (or Mann–Whitney  U -test if normality assumptions were not met) or by ANOVA with a  post hoc  Holm–Sidak test when multiple treatments were evaluated. All comparison analyses were performed using SigmaStat v3.5 ( SPSS, 2006 ). Kinetic data were observed to fit a Michaelis–Menten function, and estimates of  K  m  and  V  max  were determined using non-linear regression in GraphPad Prism v5.0 ( GraphPad Software Inc., 2007 ). Differences in  K  m  and  V  max  estimates for fish acclimated to different Na +  concentrations were tested using an extra sum of squares  F -test ( Zar, 2009 ).  Na +  uptake rates (in nanomoles per gram per hour) as a function of external Na +  concentrations (micromolar) for  Cyprinodon macularius  acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + . Values are means ± SEM (n   = 8). See Table  1  for estimates of  K  m  and  V  max   Na +  uptake kinetics in  Cyprinodon  spp.  Different letters indicate statistically significant differences ( P  &lt; 0.05).  Effect of increasing amiloride concentrations on Na +  uptake rates (in nanomoles per gram per hour) in  C. macularius  acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + . Controls include dimethyl sufoxide (DMSO) carrier. Values are shown as means + SEM ( n  =   8). *Statistical difference compared with the control ( P  ≤ 0.05)  Effect of 5 × 10 −5  M 5-( N -ethyl- N -isopropyl)-amiloride (EIPA) on Na +  uptake rates (in nanomoles per gram per hour) in  C. macularius  acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + . Controls include DMSO carrier. Values are shown as means + SEM ( n    =   8). *Statistical difference compared with the control ( P  ≤ 0.05)  Effects 1 × 10 −5  M phenamil on Na +  uptake rates (in nanomoles per gram per hour) in  C. macularius  acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + . Controls include DMSO carrier. Values are shown as means + SEM ( n    =   8).  Effect of 1 × 10 −4  M bumetanide on Na +  uptake rates (in nanomoles per gram per hour) in  C. macularius  acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + . Controls include DMSO carrier. Values are shown as means + SEM ( n    =   8).  Effect of 1 × 10 −5  M metolazone on Na +  uptake rates (in nanomoles per gram per hour) in  C. macularius  acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + . Controls include DMSO carrier. Values are shown as means + SEM ( n    =   8).  Effect of 1 × 10 −4  M ethoxzolamide on Na +  uptake rates (in nanomoles per gram per hour) in  C. macularius  acclimated to 2 or 7 mM Na + . Controls include DMSO carrier. Values are shown as means + SEM (n = 8). *Statistical difference compared with the control (P ≤ 0.05)  Our objective was to assess Na +  transport characteristics in  C. macularius  and compare them with those previously observed in  C. v. variegatus  and  C. v. hubbsi . We hypothesized that  C. macularius  would be similar to  C. v. variegatus , with previously observed differences between  C. v. variegatus  and  C. v. hubbsi  reflecting adaptations by the latter to its dilute freshwater environment.  With respect to Na +  transport kinetics,  C. macularius  displayed a significantly lower  K  m  than either  C. variegatus  subspecies when acclimated to 7 mM Na + , but was intermediate when acclimated to 2 mM Na +  (Table  1 ). This change in ranking reflects the lack of change in  C. macularius K  m  over this range, while both  C. variegatus  subspecies significantly increased their affinity for Na +  with decreasing ambient Na +  concentrations. The lack of flexibility in apparent  K  m  for  C. macularius  may reflect the relatively stenohaline environment (i.e. not subject to daily fluctuations in salinity due to tidal cycles) in which it has evolved, in comparison to  C. variegatus .  Similar to  C. v. variegatus , lack of phenamil sensitivity in  C. macularius  (Fig.  4 ) indicates that they do not utilize the apical Na +  channel–H + -ATPase system that is used in the majority of freshwater fish studied to date ( Hwang  et al. , 2011 ). Interestingly, the only other species studied to date that lack this system are  Fundulus heteroclitus  ( Patrick and Wood, 1999 ;  Scott  et al. , 2005 ) and the Japanese medaka ( Oryzias latipes ;  Wu  et al. , 2010 ).  Fundulus heteroclitus  is in the order Cyprinodontiformes, while  O. latipes  is in the closely related order Beloniformes ( Parenti, 2008 ). Both orders include a large number of small euryhaline fish, suggesting a possible phylogenetic and/or environmental signal for this difference in Na +  transport protein expression. It would be of interest to study a euryhaline fish outside of these two orders to test whether the absence of the apical Na +  channel–H + -ATPase system is characteristic of these two orders or a trait common to euryhaline fish.   Cyprinodon macularius  Na +  uptake was also insensitive to both bumetanide and metolazone (Figs  5  and  6 ), indicating that this species does not use either NKCC or the Na + –Cl −  cotransporter for apical Na +  acquisition. We previously hypothesized that the very high  V  max  for  C. v. variegatus  was primarily due to the expression of NKCC in the apical membrane of gill ionocytes in this species ( Brix and Grosell, 2012 ). The apparent lack of NKCC expression in  C. macularius  and correspondingly low  V  max , provides further support for this hypothesis. We also hypothesized that the expression of an apical NKCC in  C. v. variegatus  ionocytes was an evolved trait not basal to  Cyprinodon  spp. and may be an adaptation to take up large amounts of Na +  rapidly when it occurs high in estuaries, where &gt;1 mM Na +  concentrations may occur for only a few hours during high tide. The lack of NKCC in the more stenohaline  C. macularius , as well as the loss of NKCC expression from the stenohaline  C. v. hubbsi  ( Brix and Grosell, 2012 ), is consistent with this hypothesis.   Cyprinodon macularius  Na +  uptake was sensitive to both amiloride, a Na +  channel and NHE blocker, and EIPA, a NHE specific inhibitor. Amiloride typically affects Na +  channels at relatively low concentrations (10 −5  M), while inhibiting NHE at higher concentrations (10 −4  to 10 −3  M;  Kleyman and Cragoe, 1988 ). Considering that Na +  uptake is phenamil insensitive, that only 1 × 10 −3  M amiloride inhibited Na +  uptake (Fig.  2 ), and that EIPA had a comparable effect to this amiloride concentration (Fig.  3 ), it appears that  C. macularius  is relying on a relatively low-affinity NHE for apical Na +  uptake. However, it is worth noting that the  K  0.5  for  C. macularius  was &gt;1 × 10 −3  M amiloride, significantly higher than that estimated for  C. v. variegatus  (3 × 10 −4  M). Likewise, EIPA inhibited Na +  uptake only by 12% in  C. macularius  acclimated to 2 mM Na + , while it inhibited Na +  uptake by 51 and 91% in  C. v. variegatus  and  C. v. hubbsi  acclimated to the same water ( Brix and Grosell, 2012 ). This raises the possibility that  C. macularius  is using a different NHE isoform, that there are amino acid differences for the same protein isoform, or that other currently unidentified proteins are involved in Na +  uptake across the apical membrane of gill ionocytes.  The final experiment involved use of the CA inhibitor, ethoxzolamide. In some fish, CA-mediated hydration of CO 2  provides intracellular H +  for the function of NHE in thermodynamically unfavourable conditions ( Hirata  et al. , 2003 ). We hypothesized that inhibition of CA would have little or no effect on Na +  uptake at 7 mM Na + , because this condition is favourable for NHE function, but would potentially affect Na +  uptake at 2 mM Na + , where the Na +  gradient would be less thermodynamically favourable. Surprisingly, we observed that ethoxzolamide did not have a significant effect on Na +  uptake at 2 mM Na + , but did have a significant effect at 7 mM Na +  (Fig.  7 ). These results contrast with  C. v. variegatus , in which treatment with ethoxzolamide stimulated Na +  uptake at 7 mM Na + , but inhibited Na +  uptake at 2 mM Na + . The present results for  C. macularius  are more similar to  C. v. hubbsi , in which ethoxzolamide inhibited Na +  uptake at both 2 and 7 mM Na + , albeit to a lesser extent than observed for  C. macularius  ( Brix and Grosell, 2012 ).  We previously hypothesized that the stimulatory effect observed in  C. v. variegatus  was the result of an unknown signalling pathway activating NKCC, and the lack of stimulation in  C. macularius  is consistent with this hypothesis. The reason for the greater effect of ethoxzolamide in  C. macularius  at 7 mM Na +  compared with 2 mM Na +  is not clear. It suggests that the thermodynamic gradient is less favourable at 7 mM Na + . There are several possible reasons for this; intracellular Na +  may be higher in fish acclimated to 7 mM Na + , requiring a higher production of H +  by CA to maintain a favourable gradient, or an NHE-Rhesus glycoprotein metabolon ( Wu  et al. , 2010 ;  Kumai and Perry, 2011 ) may be active only in fish acclimated to 2 mM Na + , which would be likely to dampen the effects of ethoxzolamide on Na +  uptake. One possibility worth investigating is that  C. macularius  switches Na + –K + -ATPase isoforms ( Jorgensen, 2008 ;  Liao  et al. , 2009 ) between 7 and 2 mM Na + , allowing for a lower intracellular Na +  and therefore less reliance on CA-generated H +  for NHE function. Regardless of the mechanism, the results for  C. macularius  and the two  C. variegatus  subspecies highlight the diverse and complex interplay of CA with proteins involved in Na +  uptake in freshwater, even among closely related species.  In conclusion, this study suggests that the endangered pupfish,  C. macularius , may rely solely on a low-affinity NHE for apical Na +  uptake in freshwater, although we cannot rule out the possibility of novel transport systems being present, given the modest effects observed in the inhibitor experiments. This contrasts with two subspecies of  C. variegatus  that display a more dynamic response to varying Na +  concentrations in freshwater, utilizing either a combination of NKCC and NHE or multiple NHE isoforms for apical Na +  uptake. Similar to  C. variegatus , H +  generated by CA-mediated hydration of CO 2  plays an important role in regulating Na +  uptake by  C. macularius  in freshwater.   Cyprinodon macularius  were generously provided by Chris Ingersoll at the USGS Laboratory in Columbia, MO, USA and held under USFWS Endangered Species Permit #TE2057312. Experiments were approved by the University of Miami animal care committee. This work was supported by a University of Miami Maytag Fellowship (to KVB), a National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship (to KVB), and the National Science Foundation (IOB 0743903 and IOS 1146695 to MG). 