 Molecular detection and species identification of  Alexandrium  (Dinophyceae) causing harmful algal blooms along the Chilean coastline  Six new microsatellite markers for the toxic marine dinoflagellate  Alexandrium tamarense   Identification and characterization of potentially alagal-lytic marine bacteria strongly associated with the toxic dinoflagellate  Alexandrium catenella   Toxic algal blooms and red tides: a global perspective   The ecology and oceanography of harmful algal blooms: multidisciplinary approaches to research and management . UNESCO IOC Technical Series 74  Biogeography of toxic dinoflagellates in the genus  Alexandrium  from the northeastern United States and Canada  Approaches to monitoring, control and management of harmful algal blooms (HABs)  Variación temporal del fitoplancton entre 1993 y 1998 en una estación fija del seno Aysén, Chile (45°26′S 73°00′W)  Use of PCR and partial sequencing of the large-subunit rRNA gene to identify  Alexandrium catenella  (Dinophyceae) from the south of Chile  Basecalling of automated sequencer traces using phred. II. Error probabilities  Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred. I. Accuracy assessment  Bioensayos con mamíferos y ensayos bioquímicos y celulares para la detección de ficotoxinas  The global complex phenomena of harmful algal blooms  Genetic diversity and molecular detection of three toxic dinoflagellate genera  (Alexandrium ,  Dinophysis  and  Karenia)  from French coasts  PhyML: a simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood  Transport of toxic dinoflagellates via ships’ ballast water: bioeconomic risk assessment and efficacy of possible ballast water management strategies  Morphology, toxin composition and LSU rDNA phylogeny of  Alexandrium minutum  (Dinophyceae) from Denmark, with some morphological observations on other European strains   Vibrio parahaemolyticus  infections and algal intoxications as emergent public health problems in Chile  Sequence comparison of toxic and non-toxic  Alexandrium tamarense  (Dinophyceae) isolates from UK waters  A new look at the statistical model identification  Species-specific detection and quantification of toxic marine dinoflagellates  Alexandrium tamarense  and  A. catenella  by real-time PCR assay  The application of a molecular clock based on molecular sequences and the fossil record to explain biogeographic distributions within the  Alexandrium tamarense  ‘species complex’ (Dinophyceae)  Development of specific rRNA probes to distinguish between geographic clades of the  Alexandrium tamarense  species complex  Bivalve filter feeding revisited  Informative characteristics of 12 divergent domains in complete large subunit rDNA sequences from the harmful dinoflagellate genus,  Alexandrium  (Dinophyceae)  Paralytic shellfish poisoning toxins: biochemistry and origin  Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0  Phylogenetic analysis of  Alexandrium  species and  Pyrodinium bahamense  (Dinophyceae) based on theca morphology and nuclear ribosomal gene sequence  Phylogeny and biogeography of the toxic dinoflagellate  Alexandrium   Phylogeny and biogeography of the toxic dinoflagellate  Alexandrium   Species boundaries and global biogeography of the  Alexandrium tamarense  complex (Dinophyceae)  Sequence comparisons link toxic European isolates of  Alexandrium tamarense  from the Orkney Islands to toxic North American stocks  Phylogenetic analysis guided by intragenomic SSU rDNA polymorphism refines classification of ‘ Alexandrium tamarense ’ species complex  Toxin variability in cultured and natural populations of  Alexandrium tamarense  from southern South America—evidence of diversity and environmental regulation  Revisión taxonómica de los dinoflagelados de Chile  Improving the analysis of dinoflagellate phylogeny based on rDNA  Development of microsatelitte markers in the toxic dinoflagellate  Alexandrium catenella  (Dinophyceae)  Probable origin and toxin profile of  Alexandrium tamarense  (Lebour) Balech from southern Brazil  jModelTest: phylogenetic model averaging  Particle capture in the mussel  Mytilus edulis : the role of latero-frontal cirri  Phylogenetic relationship of  Alexandrium monilatum  (Dinophyceae) to other  Alexandrium  species based on 18S ribosomal RNA gene sequences  MrBayes 3.2: efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space  Identification of group and strain-specific genetic markers for globally distributed  Alexandrium  (Dinophyceae). I. RFLP analysis of SSU rRNA genes  LSU rDNA-based RFLP assays for discriminating species and strains of  Alexandrium  (Dinophyceae)  Identification of group and strain-specific genetic markers for globally distributed  Alexandrium  (Dinophyceae) II. Sequence analysis of a fragment of the LSU rRNA gene  Molecular evolution of the  Alexandrium tamarense  ‘species complex’ (Dinophyceae): dispersal in the North American and West Pacific regions  Estimating the dimension of a model  Studies on the various allometric relationships in the intertidal green mussel,  Perna viridis  Linnaeus of Ennore estuary, Madras  An evaluation of LSU rDNA D1-D2 sequences for their use in species identification  Impacto económico de las floraciones de microalgas nocivas en chile y datos recientes sobre la ocurrencia de veneno amnésico de los mariscos   MEGA5:  molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods  Phylogenetic relationship of  Alexandrium tamiyavanichii  (Dinophyceae) to other  Alexandrium  species based on ribosomal RNA gene sequences  High resolution spatio-temporal detection of potentially harmful dinoflagellates in confined waters in the NW Mediterranean  Both authors contributed equally.  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Misleading morphological observations assigned  Alexandrium catenella  as local dinoflagellate responsible for HABs in Southern Chilean coasts. Our work based on molecular methods found that local  Alexandrium  belongs to group I of the  tamarensis  complex composed mainly of  A. tamarense.   On the basis of morphological evidence, the species involved in South American Pacific coast harmful algal blooms (HABs) has been traditionally recognized as  Alexandrium catenella  (Dinophyceae). However, these observations have not been confirmed using evidence based on genomic sequence variability. Our principal objective was to accurately determine the species of  Alexandrium  involved in local HABs in order to implement a real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assay for its rapid and easy detection on filter-feeding shellfish, such as mussels.  For species-specific determination, the intergenic spacer 1 (ITS1), 5.8S subunit, ITS2 and the hypervariable genomic regions D1–D5 of the large ribosomal subunit of local strains were sequenced and compared with two data sets of other  Alexandrium  sequences. Species-specific primers were used to amplify signature sequences within the genomic DNA of the studied species by conventional and real-time PCR.  Phylogenetic analysis determined that the Chilean strain falls into Group I of the  tamarensis  complex. Our results support the allocation of the Chilean  Alexandrium  species as a toxic  Alexandrium tamarense  rather than  A. catenella , as currently defined .  Once local species were determined to belong to Group I of the  tamarensis  complex, a highly sensitive and accurate real-time PCR procedure was developed to detect dinoflagellate presence in  Mytilus  spp. (Bivalvia) samples after being fed (challenged)  in vitro  with the Chilean  Alexandrium  strain. The results show that real-time PCR is useful to detect  Alexandrium  intake in filter-feeding molluscs.  It has been shown that the classification of local  Alexandrium  using morphological evidence is not very accurate. Molecular methods enabled the HAB dinoflagellate species of the Chilean coast to be assigned as  A. tamarense  rather than  A. catenella.  Real-time PCR analysis based on  A. tamarense  primers allowed the detection of dinoflagellate DNA in  Mytilus  spp. samples exposed to this alga. Through the specific assignment of dinoflagellate species involved in HABs, more reliable preventive policies can be implemented.  Harmful algal blooms (HABs) occur throughout the world and are known for their negative economic and sanitary impacts ( Anderson 2009 ). Of particular concern are the paralytic shellfish toxins produced mainly by bloom-forming dinoflagellates in the genus  Alexandrium.  Over the past few decades,  Alexandrium  blooms have extended, covering new territories. In this sense, expansion of dinoflagellate species could be explained by ocean currents, human-induced mechanisms such as water from ballasts and global warming, climate adaptation and colonization of newly generated niches ( Anderson 1989 ). On the other hand, it is also possible that the increasing number of blooms reported today is the result of a worldwide effort to implement new techniques to detect and prevent their negative effects ( Anderson 2007 ). Blooms of different  Alexandrium  species have been reported from Japan ( Kodama 2010 ), northwestern Mediterranean Sea ( Vila  et al.  2001 ), Australia ( Hallegraeff 1998 ), Caribbean Sea, off the Venezuelan coast ( Halstead and Schantz 1984 ), Brazil ( Persich  et al.  2006 ), along the American Pacific coasts, from Alaska to the Strait of Magellan ( Suárez  et al.  2002 ;  Glibert  et al.  2005 ;  Hernández  et al.  2005 ), and from north Atlantic coasts from the Gulf of St Lawrence to North Carolina ( Anderson  et al.  1994 ). Compared with the numerous studies describing Australian, North American and Japanese  Alexandrium  ribotypes and morphotypes, relatively few works describe their South American counterparts from the South Pacific ( Lilly 2003 ).  Historically,  Alexandrium  species were described based on microscopic observations of morphological features including plate patterns, cell size and shape, and secondary characteristics such as chain formation. Unfortunately, these morphological traits have often proven insufficient for identifying species, leading to confusion concerning the distribution, ecology and toxicity within this genus ( Lilly  et al.  2005 ). When morphological features are questionable for taxonomic identification, they must be combined with molecular data for accurate species definition ( Hansen  et al.  2003 ).  Sequence variation analyses have been accepted to be a valid methodology for an accurate species description. This is even clearer in the  Alexandrium  genus, which has been partially reclassified on the basis of molecular genetic data, as the taxonomic value of only morphological characters proved to be insufficient for the  tamarensis  complex ( Leaw  et al.  2005 ). A good example is the taxonomic trait ‘presence or absence of the ventral pore’, used to discriminate between  A. affine  and  Alexandrium tamarense.  This trait would not be deemed useful for species identification considering that it is homoplastic ( Leaw  et al.  2005 ).  Using the classical species definition for lineage formation ( Mayr 1982 ),  Lilly  et al . (2007)  recognize  Alexandrium tamarense  (Lebour) Balech,  Alexandrium catenella  (Whedon and Kofoi) Balech and  Alexandrium fundyense  Balech as different species. On the other hand, phylogenies of  Alexandrium  species have been established based on genomic sequences of the large and small subunits of ribosomal DNA (LSU and SSU rDNA, respectively) ( Guillou  et al.  2002 ;  Usup  et al.  2002 ;  John  et al . 2003 ,  2005 ;  Murray  et al.  2005 ;  Rogers  et al.  2006 ). Of these sequences, the D1/D2 region of the LSU rDNA has been proved to be the most suited for discrimination of closely related  Alexandrium  species ( Ki and Han 2007 ). Thus, this hypervariable region has been proposed as a suitable candidate to discriminate between species with similar fidelity as Cytochrome Oxidase I gene ( Sonnenberg  et al.  2007 ).  Scholin and Anderson (1994 ,  1996 ) and  Scholin  et al.  (1994 ,  1995 ), based on DNA sequencing of the divergent D1/D2 LSU rDNA region and restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) analysis of the small subunit rDNA genes, consider that they could be strains of the same species, naming them the  tamarensis  complex. Using these results as a starting point,  Lilly  et al.  (2007)  further established the  tamarensis  complex as a valid cluster, derived from a phylogenetic analysis comparing more than 126 different  Alexandrium  D1/D2 region sequences. Their detailed examination revealed the presence of five clades, defined as: Group I (North American), Group II (Mediterranean), Group III (Western European), Group IV (Temperate Asian) and Group V (Tasmanian).  In this study, we sequenced local  Alexandrium  intergenic spacer 1 (ITS1), 5.8S rDNA, ITS2 and D1–D5 hypervariable LSU rDNA regions in order to incorporate molecular data that could help define more clearly the  Alexandrium  species responsible for HABs in Chilean coasts. This is considering that the local South American Pacific  Alexandrium  species were classified as  A. catenella  ( Muñoz 1985 ), mainly based on morphological traits, but without a further assessment of sequence variation. In this sense, species-specific assignment allows the implementation of a polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assay for accurate monitoring along Chilean coasts in order to prevent public health hazards and economic losses.  Three different clonal  Alexandrium  cell cultures (ACC01, ACC02, ACC07) were kindly provided by Professor Benjamín Suárez from the Laboratorio de Toxinas Marinas, Universidad de Chile. These were collected from Canal Costa in Aysén region, Chile (45°37′60 S, 73°32′60 W), between April 1994 and March 1995, and maintained in f/2 medium ( Guillard 1975 ) at 12 °C under a 16 : 8 h light:dark cycle and 60 μmol m −2  s −1  photon flux density. These three strains belong to the Chilean algae repository collection used in various national and international studies ( Córdoba and Müller 2002 ;  Amaro  et al . 2005 ;  Lilly  et al.  2007 ;  Montoya  et al.  2010 ).  Cells for analysis (100 mL) were collected from each clonal culture at mid-logarithmic phase and centrifuged at 3000  g  for 5 min at 4 °C. The supernatant was removed, the pellet resuspended in 500 μL of Milli-Q water, and transferred to a 1.5-mL microfuge tube. Microfuge tubes were placed in liquid nitrogen for 30 s and the cells subsequently disrupted for 1 min using an Axygen polypropylene pestle (PES-15-B-SI, Union City, CA, USA). Genomic DNA was then extracted from the pellet using the DNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen ,  Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer's instructions.  DNA concentration was measured using a fluorometer (Qubit, Sunnyvale, CA, USA) together with the Qubit dsDNA BR Assay Kit (Invitrogen, Eugene, OR, USA). The quality was evaluated based on its integrity by comparison with a 23-kb band of λ-HindIII ladder (Invitrogen, USA) in 1 % agarose (Ultrapure, Invitrogen, Barcelona, Spain) gel electrophoresis stained with ethidium bromide.  Primer sequences used in amplifying the ITS1-D5 region in  Alexandrium  species.  The annealing temperature for each primer and the study from which the sequences were obtained are listed.  Primer sequences used in amplifying species-specific microsatellite genomic regions in  A. catenella  and  A. tamarense .  The annealing temperature for each primer, the species and the study from which the sequences were obtained are listed.  TD, touchdown.  All selected  Alexandrium  sequences were obtained using the keywords ‘Alexandrium LSU rDNA’ or ‘Alexandrium 28S in the GenBank database (  http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov  ) [ see ADDITIONAL INFORMATION ]. For a detailed species-specific analysis, two data sets were generated. The first was composed of 81 unique sequences at least 641 bp long, covering the D1/D2 region of the LSU rDNA. This group incorporated 79  Alexandrium  genus species (including the local strain), and two  Prorocentrum micans  strains that were used as outgroups. The second set had 18 sequences at least 1776 bp long, of which 16 corresponded to  tamarensis  complex (including the local strain), one to  A. minutum  and one to  A. affine ; the last two were used as outgroups. For both data sets, alignments were carried out in the ClustalX2 V2.0 ( Larkin  et al.  2007 ) graphical platform.  jModeltest ( Posada 2008 ) was used to find the best substitution model and associated parameters for phylogenetic analysis in both data sets using the Akaike ( Hirotugu 1974 ) and Bayesian ( Schwarz 1978 ) information criteria.  Bayesian analysis was implemented with MrBayes V3.2 ( Ronquist  et al.  2012 ) for the first and second data sets, and was carried out with 1 500 000 runs, with five separate initial trees, with the Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) process set to four chains and 25 % of initial trees discarded as ‘burn-in’. Within each chain, samples were obtained every 100 iterations, and the values of the average deviation of split frequencies (AVSF) and potential scale reduction factor (PSRF) were obtained. These values were used to evaluate convergence of the generated trees. Additionally, maximum likelihood analysis was carried out in PhyML V3.0 ( Guindon and Gascuel 2003 ) in order to further support taxon assignment. Analysis was started with a random tree sample (Subtree pruning and regrafting method) and 1000 bootstrap replicate runs.  Figtree V1.3.1 (Andrew Rambaut. FigTree v1.3.1 2006–2009.   http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree  ) was used for a graphical visualization and representation of PhyML and MrBayes output trees.  In order to estimate the nucleotide differences within the  tamarensis  complex in each data set, the values for the average number of differences per pair of sequences aligned within each group and the number of parsimonious informative sites were calculated in the MEGA 5.05 program ( Tamura  et al . 2011 ).  An  in situ  experimental protocol for dinoflagellate challenge was developed in order to implement it subsequently for  Alexandrium  detection in filter-feeding shellfish and water columns. The experiments were performed in quadruplicate using four experimental aquaria of 15 L, containing five mussels each (one mussel from each aquarium for each of the 5 days was used for DNA extraction).  Individuals of the edible mussel  Mytilus  were transported to the laboratory, where they were acclimatized for 1 week at 14 °C and seawater salinity of 30 practical salinity units. During this period, mussels were continuously fed with the microalga  Isochrysis galbana  at 1.5 mg L −1  using a peristaltic pump and providing constant aeration. The seawater was changed every 48 h. Following acclimation, the mussels were exposed to a contaminated diet (1.7–2.0 mg L −1 ; dry weight) containing 50 % toxic dinoflagellate  Alexandrium  strain ACC02 and 50 %  I. galbana  (by weight) for a period of 12 days, followed by a detoxification period of 15 days where they were fed with  I. galbana . Every day the aquaria received an amount of food representing 2 % of the dry body weight of the experimental mussels ( Shafee 1976 ), delivered continuously using a Masterflex 7519-05 peristaltic pump at the temperature and salinity cited above. One mussel from each replicate aquarium was taken on Days 2, 3, 4 and 5 of the toxic feeding cycle and on Day 15 of the detoxification cycle. Animals were immediately processed for purification of gill DNA.   Amplification of local  Alexandrium  strains ACC01, ACC02 and ACC07 using species - specific primers;  A. tamarense  (lanes 1, 2 and 3) and  A. catenella  (lanes 4, 5 and 6).  M = 100-bp DNA size marker. Species-specific amplification in the rDNA region using  A. catenella  and  A. tamarense  primers were carried out in a MaxiGene Gradiente thermocycler (Axygen) in 1× PCR buffer, 20–50 ng of genomic DNA template, 3 mM MgCl 2,  100 µM each dNTP, 0.1 µM each primer and 0.4 U of TopTaq DNA polymerase (Fermentas) in a 10-µL reaction volume. Five microlitres of each PCR product were analysed in a 2 % agarose gel. A Fermentas GeneRuller™ 100-bp DNA ladder was used for size estimation of amplified fragments.  Mussels were randomly taken from each of the four aquaria (replicates) on each day of sampling. Animals were dissected alive and 30 g of drained gill tissue were used as the starting material for DNA purification with DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Each sample of purified DNA was stored at −20 °C. As explained below, the gill was considered as a useful source of  Alexandrium  DNA as particulate materials, such as unicellular organisms, tend to accumulate in this organ ( Jørgensen 1996 ;  Riisgard  et al . 1996 ) and other tissues such as the hepatopancreas do not provide DNA with the integrity needed for this type of study.    Alexandrium tamarense  microsatellite amplifications of the three local strains with (A) specific primers ATB8 (lanes 1, 2 and 3) and ATD8 (lanes 4, 5 and 6).  Lanes 7 and 8 correspond to controls with primers ATB8 without DNA. (B) Specific amplification with primers ATB1 (lanes 1, 2 and 3) and ATF11 (lanes 6, 7 and 8). Lanes 4–5 and 9–10 are controls without DNA for primer sets ATB1 and ATF11, respectively. M = 100-bp DNA size marker. Species-specific microsatellite amplifications using  A. catenella  and  A. tamarense  primers were carried out in a MaxiGene Gradiente thermocycler (Axygen) in 1× PCR buffer, 20–50 ng of genomic DNA template, 3 mM MgCl 2,  100 µM each dNTP, 0.1 µM each primer and 0.4 U of TopTaq DNA polymerase (Fermentas) in a 10-µL reaction volume. Five microlitres of each PCR product were analysed in a 2 % agarose gel. A Fermentas GeneRuller TM  100-bp DNA ladder was used for size estimation of amplified fragments.  Electropherogram profiles from the ITS1-D5 region of the rDNA of strains ACC01, ACC02 and ACC03 were analysed with the phred algorithm in order to discard the presence of pseudogenes or intragenomic rDNA polymorphisms (IRP). Only bases with scores over 30 (sequencing error probability 1/1000) were considered for further analysis. As no nucleotide differences were obtained for this region between the three local  Alexandrium  strains, only one sequence, Ach01, was used as a representative of them (NCBI accession no. JN657223).  Analysis by jModeltest estimated that the GTR + Γ was the best substitution model for later Bayesian and maximum likelihood analysis. If a given model was not an option in MrBayes, the following least restrictive model was used (e.g. GTR).   Phylogenetic tree of 80  Alexandrium  species and strains (Atm,  A. tamarense ; Act,  A. catenella ; Afu,  A. fundyense ; Amn,  A. minutum ; Aaf,  A. affine ; Atr,  A. tropicale ; Aty,  A. tamiyanavichii ;  P. micans ,  Prorocentrum micans ) and local  Alexandrium  species Ach01.  Sequences were obtained from the GenBank database using the keywords ‘Alexandrium LSU rDNA’ or ‘Alexandrium 28S’. Phylogenetic trees were generated for an alignment of 81 sequences of 641 bp in the D1/D2 region through Bayesian inference in MrBayes V3.2 and maximum likelihood (ML) in PhyML. Bayesian analysis was carried out with 1 500 000 runs, with five separate initial trees. Convergence was checked through PSRF and AVSF. FigTree V1.3.1 was used as a visual representation of output trees. For ML analysis these were carried out with 1000 bootstrap replicates.   Phylogenetic tree of 17  Alexandrium  species and strains (Atm,  A. tamarense ; Act,  A. catenella ; Afu,  A. fundyense ; Amn,  A. minutum ; Aaf,  A. affine ) and local  Alexandrium  species Ach01.  Sequences were obtained from the GenBank database using the keywords ‘Alexandrium LSU rDNA’ or ‘Alexandrium 28S’. Phylogenetic trees were generated for an alignment of 18 sequences of 1776 bp in the ITS1-D5 region through Bayesian inference in MrBayes V3.2 and maximum likelihood (ML) in PhyML. Bayesian analysis was carried out with 1 500 000 runs, with five separate initial trees. Convergence was checked through PSRF and AVSF. FigTree V1.3.1 was used as a visual representation of output trees. For ML analysis these were carried out with 1000 bootstrap replicates.  For maximum likelihood analysis, the logarithm of the likelihood score of the optimal tree was −6591.25984. As expected, the results were again consistent and the local  Alexandrium  strain was allocated to Group I of the  tamarensis  complex.  Topologies for trees generated through maximum likelihood and Bayesian inference were the same, and had high bootstrap and posterior probability values (Figs  3  and  4 ). Group generation was carried out analysing clades formation and the previous literature. Comparing the structure of both trees, using 18 or 81 sequence alignments, the same clades were formed.  In order to obtain information on the variability of the amplified region for both data sets, the average number of differences per pair of sequences aligned and the number of parsimonious sites were measured. For the first data set, values were 8.37 bp and 130, respectively. On the other hand, for the second data set, the average number of differences per pair of sequences aligned was 52.03 bp and the number of parsimonious sites was 298. Considering the 1185-bp segment covering only the LSU rDNA region, the amount of parsimonious informative sites and the average number of differences per pair of sequences aligned decreases from 298 to 174 and from 52.02 to 35 bp, representing a fall of 42 and 32 %, respectively, with respect to the whole amplified region.  Detection of  Alexandrium  DNA in gill tissue samples from challenged  Mytilus  through days 2 to 27 by q-PCR.   Mytilus  were exposed to a contaminated diet (1.7–2.0 mg L −1 ; dry weight) containing 50 % toxic dinoflagellate  Alexandrium  strain ACC02 and 50 %  I. galbana  (by weight) for a period of 12 days, followed by a detoxification period of 15 days, where they were fed with  I. galbana . Animals were dissected alive on Days 2, 3, 4 and 5 of the toxic phase and Day 15 of the detoxification phase, and 30 g of drained gill tissue were used as the starting material for DNA purification with the DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Real-time PCR assays using species-specific  A. tamarense  primers were carried out in extracted DNA from  Mytilus  in order to determine the possibility of detecting  Alexandrium  DNA in challenged mussel tissue. NA, no amplification.   a Days in toxic phase.   b Days in detoxification phase.  The study of HABs has become increasingly important given the recent rise in the number and frequency of toxic events, and associated adverse impacts on public health, fisheries and ecosystem services ( Anderson 1989 ;  Cassis  et al . 2002 ). This threat has led to extensive investigation on how to develop international standards for the detection of toxins in seafood and on the implementation of expanded monitoring programmes for toxic algae. One of the most frequently used methods for the evaluation of toxins in HAB episodes worldwide has been the mouse bioassay. Unfortunately, this technique does not always provide accurate estimates of toxicity ( Fernández  et al . 2002 ) and requires considerable resources and time. Moreover, this technique has been questioned with regard to animal welfare and is prohibited in some countries. In this context, increasing efforts have been focused on monitoring the toxic algae directly to predict their occurrence and better allocate sampling effort, particularly with regard to toxin analysis.  In this paper, we present phylogenetic analyses using ITS1-D5 rDNA sequence data which demonstrate that the Chilean strains analysed belong to Group I in the  tamarensis  complex, rather than to the  A. catenella  grouping ( Scholin  et al.  1994 ;  Medlin  et al.  1998 ;  Higman  et al.  2001 ;  Lilly  et al.  2007 ). The first studies concerning Chilean HABs carried out 40 years ago, based on morphological observations, identified  A. catenella  as the dominant  Alexandrium  species ( Muñoz 1985 ). This identification has never been questioned or assessed by more accurate methods such as genomic sequencing. The phylogenetic analysis carried out in this study clearly indicates that the local  Alexandrium  species belongs to the Group I ribotype. This group is mainly composed of  A. tamarense , in contrast to Group IV in which the predominant species is  A. catenella . Similarly, phylogenetic trees based on  Alexandrium  toxin variability showed that strains from Argentina, Brazil, Chile and Uruguay belonged to the same clade, paralleling the Group I results ( Montoya  et al.  2010 ) .  As red tide blooms have been present since the 19th century in Chile and Brazilian, Uruguayan and Argentinian events are more recent, it has been proposed that toxic episodes in Eastern South America could be due to the expansion of Chilean  Alexandrium  species ( Lilly  et al.  2007 ). Even more, Uruguayan and Brazilian strains have been classified as  A. tamarense  in Group I, consistent with our findings in relation to the fact that Chilean species, supporting the hypothesis that the local strain was missclassified as  A. catenella .  Very recently,  Miranda  et al.  (2012)  discussed the validity of using direct amplification sequences of the rDNA subunits as a suitable method for strain differentiation in  Alexandrium  species, due to the existence of paralogue genes. In this respect, base quality discrimination did not give evidence of paralogue sequences. On the other hand,  Ki and Han (2007) , eliminating paralogue sequences for their analysis, found 39 parsimony informative sites within the D1–D5 LSU rDNA region in five different  Alexandrium  species. Our study found a much higher value of parsimony variable sites (174) when our local sequence was aligned with published sequences, which probably contained paralogue DNA regions. It is unlikely that this considerable difference could be explained by increased mutation rates in the sequenced regions. Thus, this result agrees with Miranda  et al.  (2012), who suggest that the great diversity in Group I of the  tamarensis  complex could be due to the lack of an accurate discrimination of paralogue sequences.  The sequence analysis facilitated the use of a specific and highly sensitive real-time PCR assay to detect local  Alexandrium . Owing to the ability of filter-feeding molluscs to capture and concentrate phytoplankton, by pumping water through their gill filaments, we tested the possibility of detecting dinoflagelate DNA in this organ of challenged mussels. Preliminary experimental results showed, for the first time, the implementation of a practical test to detect these algae in gill tissue extracted from mussels challenged under laboratory conditions. Currently, we are working on the implementation of this test in field samples in order to detect traces of  Alexandrium  in seawater. It would be very useful to count with methods to detect traces of dinoflagellates, in order to predict massive algal blooming through constant monitoring of red tide episodes, thus preventing human consumption of toxic filter-feeding shellfish.  Traditionally, South American Pacific HABs have been assigned to  A. catenella , based only on morphological evidence that has proven to be an unreliable indicator of species identification within the  A. tamarense  complex ( Lilly  et al.  2007 ).  This study was focused on the molecular identification of the  Alexandrium  species that causes paralytic shellfish poisoning in Chilean coasts ( Hernández  et al.  2005 ). Phylogenetic analyses based on sequence data and species-specific PCR assays targeting LSU rDNA and microsatellite regions, all demonstrate that cultures isolated from Chilean coasts belong to the  tamarensis  complex Group I and are not  A. catenella  (Figs  1  and  2 , Tables  1  and  2 ,  Hosoi-Tanabe and Sako 2005 ).  As not all  A. tamarense  are toxic, we are currently developing a real-time PCR assay based on primer pairs that target signature nucleic acid sequences of genes involved in toxin production. Our goal is to set up a new technique for early, sensitive and accessible HAB detection in order to avoid the important financial damage and public health issues.   The following additional information is available in the online version of this article –   Sequences used for phylogenetic analyses.  File 1: DNA sequences used in this study. Strain assignment, morphospecies, origin and accession number in GenBank are given when available.  The Ach01 (NCBI accession no. JN657223) sequence was uploaded to GenBank.  This work was funded by the  Corporación del fomento de la producción (Corfo) of Chile  through the INNOVA Chile Project  #07CN13PPD-240 .  A.J. and G.F. did the sequence analysis, phylogenetic analysis, PCR experiments and writing of the manuscript. M.A., P.O., J.E.T. and J.M.N. contributed with the challenge of the  Mytilus  spp. samples with local  Alexandrium  species. V.M. developed the idea, provided further inputs during the project and contributed to the financial means for carrying out the project.  We thank M. Córdova and B. Suárez-Isla for providing  Alexandrium  cultures.  None declared. 