 Honing in on phenotypes: comprehensive two-dimensional gas chromatography of herbivory-induced volatile emissions and novel opportunities for system-level analyses  Identification of the SAAT gene involved in strawberry flavor biogenesis by use of DNA microarrays  Insects betray themselves in nature to predators by rapid isomerization of green leaf volatiles  Plant volatiles  Herbivore-associated elicitors: FAC signaling and metabolism  The new Automated Mass Spectrometry Deconvolution and Identification System (AMDIS)  Volatile compound fingerprinting of mixed-culture fermentations  Herbivore-infested plants selectively attract parasitoids  Chemical ecology of host-plant selection by herbivorous arthropods: a multitrophic perspective  Metabolomics—the link between genotypes and phenotypes  Molecular interactions between the specialist herbivore  Manduca sexta  (Lepidoptera, Sphigidae) and its natural host  Nicotiana attenuata . VIII. An unbiased GC×GC-ToFMS analysis of the plant's elicited volatile emissions  SuperSAGE analysis of the  Nicotiana attenuata  transcriptome after fatty acid–amino acid elicitation (FAC): identification of early mediators of insect responses  Molecular interactions between the specialist herbivore  Manduca sexta  (Lepidoptera, Sphingidae) and its natural host  Nicotiana attenuata . III. Fatty acid–amino acid conjugates in herbivore oral secretions are necessary and sufficient for herbivore-specific plant responses  Silencing of hydroperoxide lyase and allene oxide synthase reveals substrate and defense signaling crosstalk in  Nicotiana attenuata   Variation in herbivore and methyl jasmonate-induced volatiles among genetic lines of  Datura wrightii   Elucidation of gene-to-gene and metabolite-to-gene networks in  Arabidopsis  by integration of metabolomics and transcriptomics   Nicotiana attenuata  SIPK, WIPK, NPR1, and fatty acid–amino acid conjugates participate in the induction of jasmonic acid biosynthesis by affecting early enzymatic steps in the pathway  C 12  derivatives of the hydroperoxide lyase pathway are produced by product recycling through lipoxygenase-2 in  Nicotiana attenuata  leaves  Data processing for mass spectrometry-based metabolomics  MZmine: toolbox for processing and visualization of mass spectrometry based molecular profile data  Defensive function of herbivore-induced plant volatile emissions in nature  Silencing the jasmonate cascade: induced plant defenses and insect populations  Pectin methylesterase NaPME1 contributes to the emission of methanol during insect herbivory and to the elicitation of defence responses in  Nicotiana attenuata   CAMERA: an integrated strategy for compound spectra extraction and annotation of LC/MS data sets  MetAlign: interface-driven, versatile metabolomics tool for hyphenated full-scan mass spectrometry data preprocessing  An untargeted metabolomics approach to contaminant analysis: pinpointing potential unknown compounds  Green leaf volatiles: hydroperoxide lyase pathway of oxylipin metabolism  beta-Glucosidase: an elicitor of herbivore-induced plant odor that attracts host-searching parasitic wasps  Combined transcript and metabolite analysis reveals genes involved in spider mite induced volatile formation in cucumber plants  Decoding genes with coexpression networks and metabolomics—‘majority report by precogs  Polymorphism in jasmonate signaling partially accounts for the variety of volatiles produced by  Nicotiana attenuata  plants in a native population  SNF1-related kinases allow plants to tolerate herbivory by allocating carbon to roots  The volatile compound BinBase mass spectral database  XCMS: processing mass spectrometry data for metabolite profiling using nonlinear peak alignment, matching, and identification  Highly sensitive feature detection for high resolution LC/MS  Practical approaches to plant volatile analysis  A novel approach for nontargeted data analysis for metabolomics. Large-scale profiling of tomato fruit volatiles  A role for differential glycoconjugation in the emission of phenylpropanoid volatiles from tomato fruit discovered using a metabolic data fusion approach  The induction of volatile emissions in maize by three herbivore species with different feeding habits: possible consequences for their natural enemies  Why plant volatile analysis needs bioinformatics—detecting signal from noise in increasingly complex profiles  Rapid modification of the insect elicitor  N -linolenoyl-glutamate via a lipoxygenase-mediated mechanism on  Nicotiana attenuata  leaves  Indirect defence of plants against herbivores: using  Arabidopsis thaliana  as a model plant  Caterpillar-elicited methanol emission: a new signal in plant–herbivore interactions?  Tuning the herbivore-induced ethylene burst: the role of transcript accumulation and ethylene perception in  Nicotiana attenuata   Herbivory rapidly activates MAPK signaling in attacked and unattacked leaf regions but not between leaves of  Nicotiana attenuata   Web-based inference of biological patterns, functions and pathways from metabolomic data using MetaboAnalyst  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Here we discuss opportunities for system-wide analysis of plant volatiles provided by the implementation of non-supervised data processing. We illustrate the value of such approaches by presenting recent findings on wild tobacco volatile emissions using two-dimensional gas chromatography.  Plant volatile organic compound (VOC) production requires a complex network of biochemical pathways, which, although well mapped from a biochemical point of view, remains only partly understood with regard to its physiological and genetic regulation. Additionally, although analytical procedures for plant VOC measurement have become increasingly faster and more sensitive in recent years, pinpointing relevant shifts in VOC production from the thousands of molecular fragments that are generated by modern mass spectrometer instruments remains challenging. Here we discuss novel opportunities for system-wide analysis provided by the implementation of non-targeted data processing and multivariate statistics in VOC analysis. We illustrate the value of implementing non-targeted data processing with examples of recent findings from our group on the interactive control exerted by salivary components of a lepidopteran herbivore,  Manduca sexta , on herbivory-induced VOC emissions in the wild tobacco  Nicotiana attenuata . Finally, we briefly discuss the use of multi-platform data integration for probing the nature of metabolic and regulatory systems underlying VOC emissions.  Plants continuously emit large quantities of chemically highly diverse volatile organic compounds (VOCs). More than 1700 VOCs have, for instance, been detected in floral scents and many more are emitted from other tissues. These VOC blends mainly consist of products of the phenylpropanoid pathway, terpenoids and fatty acid (FA) and amino acid derivatives (reviewed in  Baldwin 2010 ). Green leaf volatiles (GLVs), the best structurally characterized FA-based VOCs, are synthesized by all higher plants during mechanical damage. Their emission originates from the degradation of C 18  FAs—linolenic and linoleic acids—when hydroperoxidated by a lipoxygenase (LOX) and cleaved into C 12  and C 6  units by a hydroperoxide lyase (HPL) ( Halitschke  et al.  2004 ;  Matsui 2006 ). In contrast, terpenoids, which are produced by the mevalonic acid pathway in the cytosol or the 2-methylerythritol 4-phosphate/1-deoxy-xylulose 5-phosphate pathway located in the plastids, provide much of the structural diversity in plant VOC blends.  Volatile organic compounds are central to multiple aspects of a plant fitness in nature, notably by providing information to pollinators or competitors and by protecting plant tissues from biotic and abiotic stresses. The release of VOCs from vegetative organs following insect herbivore attack is a general property of plant species (reviewed in Turlings and Wäckers 2004) and has been the topic of numerous studies addressing their biosynthesis and release, as well as the eco-physiological functions of these emissions. Early studies and many others since then, conducted under optimized laboratory conditions ( De Moraes  et al.  1998 ;  Turlings 1998  and for a review,  Dicke 2000 ) or under field conditions ( Kessler and Baldwin 2001 ), on this induced response have demonstrated that parasitoids and predators make effective use of herbivory-induced volatiles to locate their prey.   Tholl  et al.  (2006)  recently reviewed currently available methods for plant volatile collection and analysis. As highlighted by the authors of the review, the number of analytes that can be detected in a single sample has increased considerably in recent years owing to impressive advances in the resolution and signal detection of modern gas chromatography coupled to mass spectrometers (GC–MS). However, our capacity to pinpoint relevant shifts in these large data-sets has not increased in tandem. This schism has been discussed in a review article by  van Dam and Poppy (2008) . The authors of this excellent review encourage the implementation of multivariate statistics and meta-analysis of plant VOCs, and notably its integration with insect behavioural data to increase the impact of modern instrumentation in understanding the ecological function of plant volatiles. Here, we describe the tools and resources already available for the untargeted post-processing and comparison of plant VOC profiles, and illustrate its value with examples of recent findings from our group on the interactive levels of control on herbivory-induced plant VOC (HIPV) emissions in  Nicotiana attenuata . Finally, we briefly discuss novel avenues offered by multi-platform data integration.  Plant VOC emissions are indicative of the physiological and metabolic status of the emitter. A better characterization of the plethora of homeostatic controls shaping plant VOC emissions is therefore essential for understanding their eco-physiological functions. To do so, one has first to discriminate between ecologically informative signals emitted by the plant and the surrounding noise. To succeed in this task, the implementation of rigorous data processing approaches and statistical analyses in VOC research is required. Here, we provide an overview of existing and readily implementable tools for the untargeted processing of GC–MS plant VOC data-sets. Such tools originate from the field of metabolomics—the omics approach interested in the comprehensive study of chemical fingerprints that specify cellular processes ( Fiehn 2002 )—for which numerous commercial and freeware programs have recently been developed. Commonly used programs perform raw file translation, pre-processing of mass chromatograms—including peak picking and deconvolution—and export peak tables suitable for statistical treatments. A non-exhaustive list of suitable programs is available at the web page of the Fiehn lab at UC Davis ( http://fiehnlab.ucdavis.edu/staff/kind/Metabolomics/ ). Most of these programs can be readily applied to normal GC–MS data as they make use of the NetCDF file format (ASTM E2078-00, Standard Guide for Analytical Data Interchange Protocol for Mass Spectrometric Data), which can be produced from most, if not all, commercial file formats. File translation is usually performed by using platform-specific GC–MS operating software. Converters to a more recently developed exchangeable file format, such as mzXML, have been developed by both academic institutions and companies.  Typical post-processing pipelines for large MS data-sets proceed through multiple stages, with feature detection and alignment being the two most critical ones ( Katajamaa and Oresic 2007 ). Feature detection, also referred to as ‘peak picking’, corresponds to the detection and extraction of the representations of measured ions from a GC–MS or a liquid chromatography coupled to mass spectrometer (LC–MS) raw signal. Alignment methods cluster extracted feature traces across different samples. This requires correcting for peak drifts to accurately determine the concentration of analytes in an automated fashion to produce peak tables suitable for cross-sample statistical comparisons. Many of the commercial or freeware programs developed in recent years attempt to bridge the gap existing between analytical chemistry and biology, and thereby to facilitate the rapid extraction of ecologically relevant signals from complex matrices. Among these programs are AMDIS, MetAlign ( Lommen 2009 ), MZmine (and its update MZmine2;  Katajamaa  et al.  2006 ) and XCMS ( Smith  et al.  2006 ; and its online server, XCMS online,  https://xcmsonline.scripps.edu/ ). The application of these programs to VOC profile analysis is discussed below.  AMDIS—an acronym that stands for Assisted Mass Deconvolution Identification Solution—is a computer program that extracts spectra for individual components in a GC–MS data file and identifies target compounds by matching these spectra against a reference library ( Davies 1998 ). Deconvolution means grouping fragments corresponding to one mass spectrum, and thus a single compound, into clusters. This step in data processing is not only critical for database searches, but also reduces the redundancy of a peak table prior to multivariate statistics. MetAlign is another efficient data processing freeware for the pre-processing and comparison of full scan nominal or accurate mass LC–MS and GC–MS data. The new version of metAlign is available as a free download at  www.metalign.nl . This program is capable of automatic file format conversions, accurate mass isolation, baseline corrections, peak picking and  m / z  feature artefact filtering, as well as alignment of up to 1000 data-sets. MetAlign has been effectively applied to the post-processing of GC–MS and LC–MS data-sets obtained from the quality control of fruits ( Tikunov  et al.  2005 ,  2010 ), fermentation studies ( De Bok  et al.  2011 ) and drinking water ( Lommen  et al.  2007 ). MZmine2 is another open-source project software dedicated to MS data processing. It is based on the original MZmine toolbox, described in  Katajamaa  et al.  (2007) , and proposes a user-friendly and flexible set of modules covering the entire work-flow pipeline, including visualization, peak picking, peak list processing, alignment and searching in a custom library or by connecting the PubChem Compound database as well as basic statistical tools. Unfortunately, MetAlign and MZmine2, like most peak picking programs, do not include options for mass spectrum deconvolution. Mass spectra must therefore be reconstructed from individually extracted molecular fragments.  Tikunov  et al.  (2005)  demonstrated, by investigating polymorphisms in fruit VOC emissions from tomato cultivars, that mass spectra reconstruction can be performed by confounding co-eluting molecular fragments sharing significant co-regulation across the data-set. In recent years, XCMS has become the most commonly used program to post-process LC–MS-based metabolomics data-sets ( Smith  et al.  2006 ;  Tautenhahn  et al.  2008 ). This bioconductor R package can be applied to GC–MS data analysis and the recently developed web-server (XCMS online) provides a set of parameters optimized for the processing of GC-based data. XCMS imports chromatographically or non-chromatographically separated and single-spectra and tandem mass spectral data from AIA/ANDI NetCDF, mzXML, mzData and mzML files. The XCMS analysis methodology involves peak picking/filtering and matching these peaks across samples for retention time correction. Differential  m/z  features—extracted ion chromatograms are automatically generated for a given number of them—or the complete  m/z  matrix are then exported as a tab-delimited file. XCMS can be used in combination with CAMERA, a bioconductor package that isolates compound-specific mass spectra according to the quality of the fit between extracted ion currents from co-eluting molecular fragments ( Kuhl  et al.  2011 ). BinBase represents another open-source program well suited for between-treatment comparative processing and automated identification of VOCs in complex mixtures ( Skogerson  et al.  2011 ).  All these MS processing programs export processed results into file formats suitable for most statistical packages. The application of multivariate statistics—a branch of exploratory statistics allowing the reduction of a large data-set on several mutually dependent variables—to the analysis of HIPV emissions has been comprehensively reviewed in  van Dam and Poppy (2008) . Noteworthy are the important advances made in recent years in the development of statistical web-servers, such as MetaboAnalyst ( Xia 2011 ), that guide users through a step-by-step statistical analysis pipeline rich in a variety of menus, information hyperlinks and check boxes. The next paragraph demonstrates the value of mutualizing high chromatographic resolution and clustering statistics to access the complexity of the signalling events translating into HIPV emissions.   An approach for non-targeted processing of GC × GC plant volatile maps.  Two-dimensional counter maps are generated after the analysis of volatile extracts by GC × GC–ToF-MS. Peak lists are produced using the peak picking and deconvolution tools of the instrument operating software and subsequently aligned separately (1) to a reference matrix issued from the analysis of an equimolar mixture of all samples (2). Peaks providing matches with metabolites from the reference matrix (4) are then retained for univariate and multivariate statistical analysis (5).   Statistical analysis of non-targeted GC × GC–ToF-MS volatile profiles of  M. sexta  OS and FAC elicited leaves pinpoint insect-specific reconfigurations of the wound response.  Data used for the network analysis have been published in  Gaquerel  et al.  (2009) .  Nicotiana attenuata  leaf VOCs were collected 1–13 and 25–37 h after mechanical wounding and direct application of a buffer mimicking the pH of  M. sexta  OS (wounding alone), raw  M. sexta  OS diluted in distilled water or FACs,  M. sexta  OS elicitors activating, at physiological concentrations, many of the early responses observable during insect feeding. (1) Correlation-based network analysis using the overall sample set ( n  = 50 samples, issued from a compendium of six eliciting treatments, cf.  Gaquerel  et al.  2009 ) shows dependences in the regulation of VOC levels partly overlapping with large compound class definitions. Peaks obtained by non-targeted processing were reported at a signal-to-noise ratio of 10—since we estimated this value as the minimum required for integration and accurate identification during alignments with the NIST and homemade libraries—and matched across samples using the approach described in Fig.  1 . Network visualization of correlation data was obtained with the Pajek software package ( http://vlado.fmf.uni-lj.si/pub/networks/pajek/ ). Nodes represent identified metabolite belonging to the main VOC classes. The distance between two nodes is based on 1 − the absolute value of the Pearson correlation coefficient ( r ) with the Fruchtermann–Reingold three-dimensional algorithm. Nodes connected by an edge share a significant ( P  &lt; 0.05) correlation coefficient  r  &gt; 0.75. Significance levels for correlation coefficients were determined by following the number of metabolite pairs ( n ) using the equation  t  =  r  × ( n −2) 0.5 /(1− r  2 ) 0.5  and the associated  P  value obtained from the  t  distribution table. (2) Mapping significant changes in VOCs released (compared to wounding alone) by  M. sexta  OS and FAC treatments onto the network highlights the dramatic control exerted by FACs over volatile terpenoid production and release. A VOC was considered significantly (unpaired  t -test,  P  &lt; 0.05) differentially emitted after treatment ( M. sexta  OS or FAC application) if its fold change (FC: ratio of means for treatment vs. control) was greater than 2 or lower than 0.5. Asterisks denote the position in the network of three VOCs reported in the main text.   Current knowledge of the modulations of the wound volatile response triggered by  M. sexta  OS cues in  N. attenuata .  When  M. sexta  larvae chew on a leaf, OS contaminate wounds to elicit specific reconfigurations of the initial wound response (blue sector of the pie chart). Oral secretions activate the release of new VOCs and enhance or repress the initial wound response for other VOCs (light and dark orange of the pie chart). Jasmonic acid-based signalling plays a pivotal role in the activation of transcription-dependent terpenoid releases. Both the nature of the jasmonate signal(s) and the downstream elements controlling this response remain largely elusive. (1) Oral secretions  probably also contain yet to be identified additional factors qualitatively and quantitatively shaping VOC emissions. Fatty acid–amino acid conjugates are central to the enhancement of the wound response and for OS-specific releases of terpenoid compounds ( Gaquerel  et al.  2009 ). (2) Fatty acid–amino acid conjugates are additionally processed into active and inactive oxidized forms when penetrating wounded tissues. Among the active metabolites, one has been shown to have a moderating effect on monoterpene emissions ( van Doorn  et al.  2010 ). (3) An unknown enzyme present in  M. sexta  OS catalyses the ( Z )–( E ) isomerization of GLVs produced directly upon wounding of  N. attenuata  leaves. ( E )-isomers are produced from plant-derived ( Z )-isomers and increase the foraging efficiency of predators ( Allmann and Baldwin 2010 ).  Non-targeted analysis of plant VOC emissions offers new research opportunities in functional genomics, as we next discuss to highlight the value of integrating multiple omics approaches. Research in this direction might notably benefit from the development of multi-instrumental analytical platforms used to trace both the biogenesis of VOCs  in planta  and their emission into the air. For instance,  Tikunov  et al.  (2010)  combined GC–MS-based VOC measurements with non-targeted LC–ToF-MS profiling of tomato fruit cultivars. Intriguingly, the so-called ‘metabolic data fusion’ approach revealed that the reduced levels of emission, in certain tomato cultivars, of three phenylpropanoid volatiles translated from specific conversions of traditional hexose–pentoside precursors into glycoconjugates of higher complexity which were not cleaved upon fruit tissue disruption ( Tikunov  et al.  2010 ). The application of similar multi-instrumental approaches to HIPV emissions could theoretically pave the way for a better understanding of the mechanisms associated with VOC accumulation and release during plant–insect interactions.  Innovative research on the functional genomics of plant VOCs will undoubtedly benefit from convergences in high-throughput transcriptomics and metabolomics. A large body of recent literature reports (for a review, see  Saito  et al.  2008 ) has demonstrated the value of integrating these two omics approaches by means of data-mining informatics. This strategy represents an excellent tool for the prediction and identification of novel genes involved in complicated metabolic pathways. Originally applied to  Arabidopsis  stress responses, detailed informatics mining of gene expression profiling data and targeted metabolite measurements induced by deficiency of sulfur and nitrogen led to the identification of previously unknown molecular players involved in glucosinolate biosynthesis ( Hirai  et al.  2005 ). The approach used in this study and many others that have followed is largely based on the ‘guilt-by-association’ principle, which assumes that a shared regulatory control is exerted over genes involved in a core biological process. The application of this strategy for gene function prediction has been excellently reviewed by  Saito  et al.  (2008) . Gene-to-metabolite integrative analyses have been applied in a few cases for VOC biosynthetic gene annotation, notably for the genes controlling developmentally regulated VOC releases by strawberry ( Fragaria  sp.;  Aharoni  et al.  2000 ) and spider mite-induced responses in cucumber ( Cucumis sativus ;  Mercke  et al.  2004 ) or for those responsible for polymorphisms in VOC emissions detected in different accessions and introgression lines of wild and cultivated tomato ( Lycopersicon hirsutum  and  Solanum lycopersicum ;  Tikunov  et al.  2005 ,  2010 ). The latter study also underlines the power of exploiting natural variation in identifying the genes responsible for VOC production. Unfortunately, only a few such studies have addressed natural variations in the HIPV emissions from non-domesticated species, for example in  Datura wrightii  ( Hare  et al.  2007 ) or  N. attenuata  ( Schuman  et al.  2009 ). We have identified large variations, probably genetically determined, in the release of most HIPV in a native population of  N. attenuata  plants growing in Utah (USA) ( Schuman  et al.  2009 ). These quantitative variations in HIPV emissions were only partially associated with expression-level polymorphisms detected for JA biosynthetic and perception genes, suggesting that significant polymorphisms in VOC biosynthetic genes accounted for the VOC genetic diversity of  N. attenuata  native populations.  In conclusion, the implementation of unsupervised processing and statistics has the power to increase the impact of modern instrumentation in understanding the chemical ecology of plant VOCs. Succeeding in this task implies rigorous data processing and statistical mining following standards established in the last decade for microarray analysis. Here, we provided a rapid overview on open access and commercial programs to perform these analyses. The choice of one of these programs depends on the type of data produced, on users' computational experience but also on later processing steps (including statistical analysis) to be conducted with the output matrix. In this respect, the R platform offers an extremely large and versatile statistical environment for mining analyte matrices produced in a first step by packages such as XCMS. Like most automated data processing procedures, peak picking and alignment steps are prone to false-positive and false-negative assignments, materialized, for instance, by non-extracted true analyte peaks, over-representation of noise-associated features and non-correctly aligned mass features. The selection of the best algorithm, but also of the best associated parameters, is therefore not an easy task since different settings strongly affect peak detection/alignment performance. Thus, quality control tests—some of these procedures being documented as part of software/package manuals—as well as manual inspection of the output data are important steps to understand and optimize data-processing and to conduct rigorous statistical analysis.  Embedding the processing and statistical analysis results within the context of existing biological knowledge represent another main challenge of metabolomics studies. Global metabolic profiles or fingerprints can be a very powerful means of comparing biological samples; however, metabolite identity and data integration (different metabolomics platforms, metabolomics–genomics data) remain indispensable for providing mechanistic insight into a biological phenomenon. In this direction, integration of metabolomics data obtained from different analytical platforms is becoming crucial to get a broad overview on biochemical shifts associated with HIPV emissions, for instance by assessing stress- or developmentally-regulated modulations of  non-volatile precursor pools using LC-based analytics ( Tikunov  et al.  2010 ). Recent work on plant–insect interaction has also shown the importance of conducting real-time measurements of low-molecular-weight compounds such as ethylene (laser-based infrared photo-acoustic detection) ( Von Dahl  et al.  2007 ) or methanol (proton transfer reaction–mass spectrometry) ( Von Dahl  et al.  2006 ;  Körner  et al.  2009 ) in parallel with the assessment of traditional herbivory-induced metabolic pathways (including HIPV) to understand the complexity of plant defence against insects. For all these reasons, parallel genetic analyses of physiological, transcriptional and analytical measures of HIPV emissions are needed to enhance our ability to pinpoint some of the causal genes in plant signalling and metabolic cascades shaping HIPV bouquets.  This research was supported by the  Max Planck Society .  E.G. and I.T.B. wrote the manuscript. Both authors have seen and agreed to the final submitted manuscript.  None declared. 