Limited plasticity of shoot preformation in response to light by understorey saplings of common walnut (<italic>Juglans regia</italic>)Plant architecture: a dynamic, multilevel and comprehensive approach to plant form, structure and ontogenyCrown architecture of valuable broadleaved speciesQuelques modalités de la croissance rythmique endogène des tiges chez les végétaux ligneux. Comptes rendus du Colloque International sur l'Arbre, MontpellierHydraulic architecture correlates with bud organogenesis and primary shoot growth in beech (<italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic>)Effects of canopy opening on height and diameter growth in naturally regenerated beech seedlingsDoes shade improve light interception efficiency? A comparison among seedlings from shade-tolerant and -intolerant temperate deciduous tree speciesPreformation in vegetative buds of <italic>Prunus persica</italic>: factors influencing number of leaf primordia in overwintering budsRelative extents of preformation and neoformation in tree shoots: analysis by a deconvolution methodInter- and intraspecific relationships between shade tolerance and shade avoidance in temperate treesEvaluation of irradiance metrics with respect to predicting sapling growthDevelopmental plasticity in plants: implications of non-cognitive behaviorChanges in crown development patterns and current-year shoot structure with light environment and tree height in <italic>Fagus crenata</italic> (Fagaceae)Structural and physiological plasticity in response to light and nutrients in five temperate deciduous woody species of contrasting shade toleranceBud and growth-unit structure in seedlings and saplings of <italic>Nothofagus alpina</italic> (Nothofagaceae)Plasticity in leaf traits of 38 tropical treespecies in response to light: relationships with light demand and adult statureAnnual shoot morphology and architecture in Persian WalnutBud structure in relation to shoot morphology and position on the vegetative annual shoots of <italic>Juglans regia</italic> LPeriods of organogenesis in mono- and bicyclic annual shoots of <italic>Juglans regia</italic> L. (Juglandaceae)Seedling survival responses to irradiance are differentially influenced by low-water availability in four tree species of the Iberian cool temperate-Mediterranean ecotoneShade tolerance, a key plant feature of complex nature and consequencesEcological limits to plant phenotypic plasticityEffects of suppression and release on sapling growth for 11 tree species of northern, interior British ColumbiaThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Analysis of the variability of primary growth is needed to improve our understanding of architectural plasticity in trees. From measurements of light and the growth of understory saplings of common walnut (<italic>Juglans regia</italic>), we show that shoot pre-formation within buds does not contribute to the subsequent phenotypical plasticity in shoot dimensions.Analysis of the variability of organogenesis and extension (two basic processes of primary growth) is needed to improve our understanding of architectural plasticity in trees. An example of such plasticity is the difference in size between fully grown shoots found at different positions on the tree. The contribution of preformation processes to these differences was explored by determining the intraspecific variability of shoot preformation of main stems of understorey saplings of <italic>Juglans regia</italic>.In 2007, two samples of annual shoots that differentiated in 2006 were taken from saplings growing in a Mediterranean mixed forest in the south of France. At the first sampling, the terminal winter bud of each parent shoot was dissected and the nodes of these buds were counted. For the second sampling, annual shoot growth was measured after the 2008 growing season. The percentage of light transmitted through the understorey was determined by hemispherical photographs.The effect of plant development (ontogeny) on the number of preformed leaves and the annual shoot extension was strong. Light availability also contributed to explaining differences in the length of annual shoots. The impact of light on the number of preformed leaves was minimal.Ontogeny (onset of branching) and reduced irradiance both affected leaf preformation in buds of annual shoots, with ontogeny being the more influential. The results suggest that the shoot preformation did not contribute to the plasticity of morphology of annual shoots. Light availability was more influential and promoted annual shoot extension.The composition and dynamics of tree canopies cause spatial and temporal heterogeneity of light availability for understorey vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C22">Valladares and Niinemets 2008</xref>). During establishment in the forest, small trees must necessarily cope with shade and wait for an opportunity, such as that created by a forest gap, to reach the forest canopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C24">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). During this early phase, the plant makes physiological compromises to deal with low irradiance levels, but must also retain the ability to respond quickly to any increase in light availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C10">Henry and Aarssen 2001</xref>). The ability of individuals to respond to environmental changes by adjustments to phenotype (i.e. phenotypic plasticity; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C13">Novoplansky 2002</xref>) has consequences for plant survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C21">Sanchez-Gomez <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>).The relationship between shade tolerance and leaf anatomy and morphology is well known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C25">Rozendaal <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). At a higher scale, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C6">Delagrange <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> have shown that crown structure, viewed as the spatial arrangement of leaves, has a large effect on light interception efficiency. The importance of crown architecture in responses to shade is well recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C22">Valladares and Niinemets 2008</xref>).To study crown architecture, we used a method that allows identification of the endogenous components of development. These include growth in length and girth, branching, sexuality and reiteration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C1">Barthélémy and Caraglio 2007</xref>). Growth by stems is the result of two complementary processes: node organogenesis and extension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C3">Champagnat <italic>et al.</italic> 1986</xref>). For a particular organ, differentiation and extension may take place simultaneously or at different times. Organs that differentiate during one growing flush but extend only after a resting period are described as preformed organs, while organs that differentiate and extend in the same growing flush are described as neoformed organs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C1">Barthélémy and Caraglio 2007</xref>). Neoformation is uncommon in temperate species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C12">Kozlowski, 1971</xref>) and linked with favourable growth conditions and some architectural constraints due to bud position in the plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C9">Guédon <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C16">Puntieri <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Known variability of shoot preformation is related to the period of bud differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C20">Sabatier <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>), the architectural position of the bud (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C19">Sabatier and Barthélémy 2001<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C16">Puntieri <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), the architectural stage of tree development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C16">Puntieri <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) and hydraulic architecture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C4">Cochard <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). The involvement of shoot preformation in the plastic responses of trees is little understood. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C8">Gordon <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> reported that, in orchard conditions, light availability within the crown has no effect on the number of leaves preformed each year. It is well known that in the forest understorey, shade changes leaf morphology, anatomy and physiology, and tree architecture in ways that optimize light capture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C22">Valladares and Niinemets 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C2">Barthélémy <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). However, few studies have investigated shoot preformation of annual shoots in shaded conditions. Studies of common walnut (<italic>Juglans regia</italic>) indicate that most annual shoots are exclusively preformed in winter buds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C19">Sabatier and Barthélémy 2001<italic>b</italic></xref>). Visible shoots consist of leaves that became differentiated the previous spring at the time the previous shoot was extending and remain enclosed in buds from summer to early spring the following year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C20">Sabatier <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>).The present study assesses relationships between shoot preformation, tree ontogeny and the light environment in walnut saplings under a mixed forest canopy. We allocated the total variability in size and growth either to differences in light availability or to ontogeny. The work tested effects on bud composition and annual shoot extension.The studied stand is located in a mixed forest near Montpellier (43°40′33″N; 3°51′53″E) in the south of France. Mean stand elevation is 57 m and the climate is typical Mediterranean (e.g. dry summer, rainfall mainly in autumn and spring), with a mean annual cumulative rainfall of 732 mm, an annual mean daily maximum temperature of 20.2 °C and an annual mean daily minimum temperature of 9.4 °C for the period 1977–2006. The forest canopy mainly comprised <italic>Quercus ilex</italic>, <italic>Quercus pubescens</italic>, <italic>Pinus halepensis</italic> and <italic>Tilia platyphyllos</italic>. The understorey consisted of saplings of <italic>Q. ilex</italic>, <italic>Q. pubescens</italic>, <italic>T. platyphyllos</italic>, <italic>Celtis australis</italic>, <italic>Prunus avium</italic>, <italic>J. regia</italic>, <italic>Hedera heli</italic>x and <italic>Ruscus aculeatus</italic>. Light transmitted down to the understorey ranged from 5 to 35 % of full sunlight.<bold>Period of leaf differentiation and extension in understorey walnut saplings and times of measurement.</bold> Broken lines: differentiation of spring leaves; unbroken lines: extension of spring leaves (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C20">Sabatier <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Arrows indicate when measurements were made.In March 2008 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ022F1">1</xref>), before spring budburst, the terminal bud of each main stem was fixed in 70 % ethanol and dissected using an Olympus SZx9 stereomicroscope at up to × 57 magnification. Bud content and structure were described following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C20">Sabatier <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref>. This extended from bud periphery to the meristematic dome and comprised cataphylls, embryonic green leaves and primordia. Embryonic green leaves were distinguished from cataphylls by the presence of well-differentiated leaflets. Primordia were distinguished from embryonic green leaves by the absence of leaflets. The total number of nodes per bud was obtained by adding together the numbers of cataphylls, embryonic green leaves and primordia.In October 2008, when shoot growth had ceased (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ022F1">1</xref>), the length and number of leaves of the annual shoot of the main stem were recorded for each tree.Light availability in the understorey was quantified by hemispherical photography, a widely used technique for exploring forest structure and understorey light conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C11">Kobe and Hogarth 2007</xref>). Photographs were taken above the terminal bud of the main stem of each sampled tree using a horizontally levelled digital camera (Coolpix 8400, Nikon) mounted on a tripod and oriented towards the zenith, using a fish-eye lens of 180° field of view (Coolpix FC-E9, Nikon). Photographs were analysed for the percentage of transmitted light from April to October using the program GLA2 of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C7">Frazer <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref>. For Sample 1, photographs of each tree were taken in May 2007 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ022F1">1</xref>), at the end of growth unit extension. The percentage of transmitted light in the understorey forest was estimated during the period when those buds that would generate shoots the following year (2008) were forming. For Sample 2, photographs of each tress were taken in October 2008 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ022F1">1</xref>), before leaf fall. The percentage of transmitted light was estimated during the period in 2008 when shoots were extending.A simple linear model was chosen that describes three quantitative variables (number of embryonic green leaves per bud, number of nodes per bud and length of annual shoots) using the following quantitative dendrometric variables: height, diameter, age and architectural stage of development (i.e. unbranched tree vs. branched tree). The model we selected limited the extent of over-fitting and used analysis of deviance incorporating chi-square testing. Our selection of the most suitable model began with the most complete model that incorporated height, diameter, age of trees, architectural stage of tree, and interactions between the architectural stage of tree and the three quantitative variables. However, interactions between quantitative variables rendered the model overly complex and generated inconveniently large data sets. Of the three models we compared, the most appropriate one incorporated tree height, architectural stage of development and their interaction.To assess the effect of percentage of transmitted light on annual growth, the percentage of transmitted light was added as a covariable. In selected models to avoid collinearity the effects were assessed through type I analysis of variance (ANOVA). The tested hypothesis was: does transmitted light have an effect on the quantitative variables of interest after assessing any effect of tree development? Data were analysed with software R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C17">R Development Core Team 2008</xref>).<bold>Analysis of height, basal diameter, age, number of branches and number of embryonic green leaves in understorey walnut saplings at two separate sampling times</bold>. Measurements were made on shoots that emerged in 2008 on saplings that were either branched or unbranched. Sample 1 included terminal buds. Sample 2 included fully extended terminal shoots derived from buds similar to those analysed in Sample 1Means are shown with standard deviations in parentheses. Means sharing a letter within a row are not statistically different (Tukey's test at <italic>P</italic> = 0.05).<bold>Relationships between transmitted light and height, basal diameter and age for unbranched (white circle) or branched (black circle) understorey walnut saplings for each of two samples.</bold> Light was measured in May 2007 for Sample 1 and in October 2008 for Sample 2. Significant correlations (Spearman rank-test <italic>P</italic>= 0.05) are indicated with lines. All the correlations are for unbranched trees; correlations were never significant for branched trees.<bold>Relationships between light availability and bud content in understorey walnut saplings.</bold> Relationships are shown between (A) stem height, basal diameter, age of saplings, transmitted light and (B) number of nodes, cataphylls, embryonic green leaves or primordia in terminal buds of unbranched (open circles) and branched (closed circles) saplings. Dashed lines for unbranched trees and bold lines for branched trees are inserted where significant correlations were detected (Spearman rank-test <italic>P</italic>= 0.05).<bold>Relationships between the length of annual shoots and the height, basal diameter, age or percentage of transmitted light for unbranched (open circles) and branched (closed circles) saplings of understorey walnut.</bold> Significant correlations (Spearman rank-test <italic>P</italic>= 0.05) are indicated with lines. Only unbranched saplings gave significant correlations.Analysis of variance relating height and architectural stage of development (branched or unbranched) of understorey walnut saplings to number of nodes within buds, number of embryonic leaves within buds and annual shoot lengthType I ANOVA tested the effects of transmitted light (bold-valued line), knowing the effects of tree height and architectural stage. Degrees of freedom (Df), <italic>F-</italic>values and level of significance (<italic>P</italic>) are shown. Significance levels: ns: <italic>P</italic>&gt; 0.05; *<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.001.The number of leaves on annual shoots was similar to the number of embryonic green leaves found in winter buds. This result confirms that the leaves of annual shoots of <italic>J. regia</italic> trees are all preformed in buds that developed the previous year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C19">Sabatier and Barthélémy 2001<italic>b</italic></xref>).For unbranched trees, the number of embryonic green leaves within buds, and to a lesser extent the number of cataphylls, increased with tree height and stem diameter. The number of embryonic green leaves per bud also increased if trees had branched. The results confirm that meristem characteristics change as the plant grows larger and it develops branches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C1">Barthélémy and Caraglio 2007</xref>). Thus, during early development, the main stem of the walnut produces more and more leaves each year as the plants increase in size. This effect is linked with increasing capacity to transport assimilates as the amount of sapwood expands stem diameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C4">Cochard <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). The basal diameter gives information not only on the conduction capacity of the main stem but also on integrated branch conduction. When the tree becomes branched, the relationship between leaf number and basal diameter of the main stem changes. The results suggest that the architectural stage of development should be taken into account in the analyses of dimension allometries in trees.We found no effect of light availability during the organogenesis period on the number of embryonic green leaves or on the number of nodes per bud. As in <italic>Prunus persica</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C8">Gordon <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), the extent of preformation in buds of <italic>J. regia</italic> was independent of the proportion of total sunlight reaching shoots during bud organogenesis. Nevertheless, available light may have an indirect and delaying effect on shoot preformation. For example, in <italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic> the light environment has a 1-year-delayed effect on secondary growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C5">Collet <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). This, in turn, affects shoot preformation in the following year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C4">Cochard <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). The delayed effect of the response places an important limit to the adaptive value of trait plasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C23">Valladares <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).Otherwise, light availability had a positive and immediate effect on annual shoot length. This relation was also found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C14">Osada <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref>. Annual shoot length is the sum of extension growth by each internode of the shoot. As light has no effect on the number of nodes, only extension seems to contribute to the plastic response of primary growth of walnut to light availability. These results suggested that the walnut saplings respond to an increase of available light with an increased annual shoot length. This can be interpreted as a mechanism for the effective exploitation of recently formed gaps in the forest canopy. It is also the case that leaf morpho-anatomical and physiological properties may also respond strongly to changes in light availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ022C15">Portsmuth and Niinemets 2007</xref>). This highlights the need to take a multiscale and integrative perspective when studying plant plasticity.A positive response of walnut saplings to increasing availability of light (i.e. less shading) strongly affected the amount of annual shoot extension. The number of preformed leaves was not changed by the light regime and therefore was not involved in this phenotypic plastic response. The onset of branching on young saplings markedly increased the number of embryonic green leaves per bud. Analysis of the causality of branching expression will now be needed to understand better the effect of variability of annual shoot morphology on whole tree architecture.This study was funded by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">AMAP (Botany and Computational Plant Architecture)</grant-sponsor>, which is a joint research unit that associates <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">CIRAD (UMR51), CNRS (UMR5120), INRA (UMR931), IRD (R123) and Montpellier 2 University (UM27) France</grant-sponsor>; <uri xlink:href="http://amap.cirad.fr/" xlink:type="simple">http://amap.cirad.fr/</uri>.O.T. carried out the tree growth and light measurement, data analysis and statistical analyses, drafted the manuscript and participated in the sampling protocol. S.A.S. conceived the study and the sampling and measurement protocols, participated in tree growth measurement and helped to draft the manuscript. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript.None declared.We thank M. Guéroult for help in collecting field samples and G. Le Moguedec for statistical help. Y. Caraglio and J. Puntieri gave fruitful comments on earlier drafts of this paper.