Body condition predicts energy stores in apex predatory sharksThe effects of prolonged fasting of the body composition and reproductive success of female polar bears (<italic>Ursus maritimus</italic>)Jaws: the inside story. The metabolism of elasmobranch fishesStable isotope ratios indicate that body condition in migrating passerines is influenced by winter habitatPatterns of lipid storage and utilization in birdsReproduction and energy reserves of a predatory carabid beetle relative to agroecosystem complexityThe need to reconsider the use of condition indices in fishery scienceConservation physiology today and tomrrowWhat is conservation physiology? Perspectives on an increasingly integrated and essential scienceThe relationship between reproductive and foraging energetics and the evolution of the PinnipediaTravelling light: white sharks (<italic>Carcharodon carcharias</italic>) rely on body lipid stores to power ocean-basin scale migrationTwo-year migration of adult female white sharks (<italic>Carcharodon carcharias</italic>) reveals widely separated nursery areas and conservation concernsReproductive energy allocation and long-term energy stores in a viviparous lizard (<italic>Eulamprus tympanum</italic>)Occurrence of tiger shark (<italic>Galeocerdo cuvier</italic>) scavenging on avian prey and its possible connection to several large-scale bird die-offs in the Florida KeysEcological risk assessment and its application to elasmobranch conservation and managementPhysiological stress response, reflex impairment, and survival among five sympatric shark species following experimental capture and releaseBody fat influences departure from stopover sites in migratory birds: evidence from whole-island telemetryMass/length residuals: measures of body condition or generators of spurious results?Killing for conservation: the need for alternatives to lethal sampling of apex predatory sharksA review of shark satellite tagging studiesDon't bite the hand that feeds: assessing ecological impacts of provisioning ecotourism on an apex marine predatorA revised estimate of daily ration in the tiger shark with implication for assessing ecosystem impacts of apex predatorsThe condition conundrum: application of multiple condition indices to the dusky shark <italic>Carcharhinus obscurus</italic>A new metric for measuring condition in large predatory sharksEstimating fitness: a comparison of body condition indicesHigh plasma triglyceride levels in small birds during migratory flight: a new pathway for fuel supply during endurance locomotion at very high mass-specific metabolic rates?Capital and income breeding as alternative tactics of resource use in reproductionMetabolic constraints on long-distance migration in birdsLength-weight relationships for 13 species of sharks from the western North AtlanticIndexes of condition for small mammalsCan simple condition indices be used to monitor and quantify seasonal changes in the energy reserves of cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic>)?Spatial and temporal influences on the physiological condition of invasive silver carpReproductive ecology and abundance of the sand tiger shark, <italic>Carcharias taurus</italic>, from the southwestern AtlanticAre fat reserves in migratory birds affected by condition in early life?Using allometry to predict body mass from linear measurements in the white sharkA review of selected physiological characteristics unique to elasmobranchsConditionR: A Language and Environment for Statistical ComputingThe function of the plasma triglycerides in fatty acid transportLife History EvolutionMigrating birds stop over longer than usually thought: an improved capture–recapture analysisEvaluating body condition in small mammalsThe Evolution of Life HistoriesCondition indices for conservation: new uses for evolving toolsFlight energetics in birdsEnzyme activities support the use of liver lipid-derived ketone bodies as aerobic fuels in muscle tissues of active sharksMeasurement versus estimation of body condition in snakesReproductive biology of the tiger shark (<italic>Galeocerdo cuvier</italic>) in HawaiiThe physiology of life history trade-offs in animals<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We measured and took blood samples from large tiger sharks in the wild to determine if their body condition (a metric of health) was related to energy stores (fatty acids). Our results revealed that body condition and fatty acids were positively and significantly correlated. This is important for understanding how large, highly mobile apex predators such as tiger sharks store and use energy required for migration and mating.Animal condition typically reflects the accumulation of energy stores (e.g. fatty acids), which can influence an individual's decision to undertake challenging life-history events, such as migration and reproduction. Accordingly, researchers often use measures of animal body size and/or weight as an index of condition. However, values of condition, such as fatty acid levels, may not always reflect the physiological state of animals accurately. While the relationships between condition indices and energy stores have been explored in some species (e.g. birds), they have yet to be examined in top predatory fishes, which often undertake extensive and energetically expensive migrations. We used an apex predatory shark (<italic>Galeocerdo cuvier</italic>, the tiger shark) as a model species to evaluate the relationship between triglycerides (energy metabolite) and a metric of overall body condition. We captured, blood sampled, measured and released 28 sharks (size range 125–303 cm pre-caudal length). In the laboratory, we assayed each plasma sample for triglyceride values. We detected a positive and significant relationship between condition and triglyceride values (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.02). This result may have conservation implications if the largest and highest-condition sharks are exploited in fisheries, because these individuals are likely to have the highest potential for successful reproduction. Our results suggest that researchers may use either plasma triglyceride values or an appropriate measure of body condition for assessing health in large sharks.Animals in nature typically encounter substantial constraints on growth due to trade-offs between the ability to obtain food vs. the ability to reproduce and survive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C42">Stearns, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C39">Roff, 2001</xref>). Balancing these trade-offs can determine how natural selection acts on life-history traits, such as age at maturity and reproductive output (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C42">Stearns, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C39">Roff, 2001</xref>). The concept of accumulating energy stores for future use is a well-documented strategy for mitigating the effects of spatial or temporal resource scarcity as well as the costs of reproduction and migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C27">Klaassen, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C26">Jönsson, 1997</xref>; Zera and Harsham, 2001). The strategies that animals employ to accumulate these stores have been examined in a range of animals, from beetles to polar bears (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C1">Atkinson and Ramsay, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C5">Bommarco, 1998</xref>). Most often, researchers examine an index of condition to estimate body fat stores, and indirectly, an index of animal ‘health’ (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C29">Krebs and Singleton, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C24">Jakob <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C46">Weatherhead and Brown, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C17">Green, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C41">Schulte-Hostedde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C3">Bearhop <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C16">Goymann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Condition metrics come in many different forms, but are generally measured as some relationship between body mass and body length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C24">Jakob <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C17">Green, 2001</xref>). However, values of condition may not always accurately reflect the physiological state of animals, and there is a need to determine whether values of condition accurately reflect more direct measures of health, such as fatty acid levels.Establishing these relationships is especially important for animals that migrate over long distances, which is known to be energetically exhausting for many animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C44">Tucker, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C27">Klaassen, 1996</xref>) and for longer-lived species, in which the costs of reproduction are generally higher due to longer gestation and more developed young (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C12">Doughty and Shine, 1998</xref>). Fats are a major source of fuel for animals during long periods of metabolic demand. Three primary plasma lipids used in fuel transport are free fatty acids, cholesterol and triglycerides, the last of which has been documented as a primary energy store crucial for fuelling migrations in many taxa, such as bird species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C4">Blem, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C40">Schaub <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Triglycerides are high-energy molecules, which consist of a glycerol molecule connected to three fatty acid chains. Triglycerides typically accumulate from the diet and are stored in the fat vacuoles of adipose cells in vertebrates. Plasma triglycerides mostly originate directly or via synthesis in the liver, and their presence in the plasma indicates lipid transport to surrounding tissues (i.e. liver and peripheral tissues), with high triglyceride values suggesting a high rate of fat deposition and utilization, although the transit of these products is likely to change with nutritional state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C38">Robinson, 1970</xref>). Furthermore, the nutritional state of individual animals is important for events such as extensive migrations, and ultimately, to enable animals to survive and reproduce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C29">Krebs and Singleton, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C16">Goymann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).For several reasons, sharks represent a good system in which to test the relationship between condition and metrics of physiological state. Many shark species are threatened and undergoing population declines due to synergistic anthropogenic impacts (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C14">Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), and therefore, there is substantial interest in their overall health and population demographics. Moreover, many large sharks undergo extensive ocean-wide migrations over thousands of kilometres, which are related to foraging and/or reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C19">Hammerschlag <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C11">Domeier and Nasby-Lucas, 2013</xref>). Finally, most sharks exhibit long gestation periods, have few offspring and exhibit long periods between reproductive events, which are likely to be linked to the high energetic requirements for fuelling their developing precocious embryos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C32">Lucifora <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Taken together, these factors indicate a need to understand the relationship between condition and physiological state and suggest that energy stores are crucial in the movement, reproduction and survival among shark species.Sharks generally store fat in the large bi-lobed liver, which is believed to play a significant role in lipid metabolism during migrations and throughout gestation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C35">Oguri, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C45">Watson and Dickson, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C22">Hussey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C10">Del Raye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). However, to our knowledge, there are no published studies investigating plasma lipid reserves in live large sharks and how these energy stores change with size or body condition, despite their documented importance in catalysing or sustaining movement and reproduction in many vertebrate species. We set out to determine the relationship between a metric of condition and an independent measure of physiological state (plasma lipid metabolites) in a wide-ranging apex predator (the tiger shark, <italic>Galeocerdo cuvier</italic>). Like other sharks, tiger sharks have long gestation periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C47">Whitney and Crow, 2007</xref>) and are known to migrate long distances (&gt;3000 km) between the Caribbean and the mid-Atlantic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C20">Hammerschlag <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Recently, a metric of condition was developed for large sharks that uses measurements of overall body shape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C23">Irschick and Hammerschlag, 2014</xref>). We hypothesized that we would find a positive relationship between this metric of condition (described below) and levels of plasma lipid metabolites. We make this prediction on the premise that a larger, bulkier (i.e. ‘fatter’) shark should possess relatively larger fat stores in the liver, and therefore, higher levels of circulating plasma lipid metabolites, a prediction which has some support in other analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C30">Lambert and Dutil, 1997</xref>). An alternative possibility (i.e. the null hypothesis) is that there is no relationship between these variables, and that body girth is either not a good metric of body condition and/or the levels of plasma lipid metabolites are not correlated with the size of the liver in sharks. The novelty in our study resides in ascertaining whether researchers can determine shark ‘health’ from simple overall metrics of body shape (body condition), which would provide significant insights into the greater ecology of large mobile predators. We discuss our results in the context of how condition and energy stores could impact critical phases of life history in sharks.Tiger sharks were sampled for this study in two subtropical locations: off the west end of Grand Bahama Island in the Bahamas (∼26.59°N, 79.08°W; ‘Tiger Beach’) in July 2012 and October 2013, and along a latitudinal gradient from Solider Key, Biscayne Bay, FL, USA (25.59°N, 80.16°W) to the reef edge in the middle Florida Keys in US federal waters (∼24.69°N, 80.85°W) from March to October 2013. All sharks were captured using standardized circle-hook drumlines (for specifics see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C15">Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). When a shark was captured, it was brought in swiftly (average time 1 min) and restrained and secured on a partly submerged platform on the boat. A water-pump was placed in the shark's mouth to permit irrigation of gills throughout sampling. While hooking durations ranged from 20–100 min for all individuals examined, it is unlikely that plasma metabolite values were influenced by an individual stress response to fishing, because tiger sharks have a dampened stress response to fishing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C15">Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).There is a rich literature on quantifying condition in fish (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C6">Cone, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C43">Stevenson and Woods, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C36">Pope and Kruse, 2007</xref>), including a very comprehensive analysis of condition in 2120 dead dusky sharks (<italic>Carcharhinus obscurus</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C22">Hussey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). These metrics typically involve either some relationship between length and mass or a direct measure of liver mass. Several reviews have discussed the advantages and pitfalls of such length–mass metrics of condition, and their remains debate as to whether they represent animal health accurately (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C24">Jakob <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C17">Green, 2001</xref>). Given that we captured and released massive (&gt;300 kg) tiger sharks, obtaining body masses or liver masses was not possible. While some studies have attempted to generate estimated body masses from sharks from various length–weight relationships (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C34">Mollet and Cailliet, 1996</xref>), it would not be appropriate for us to use masses calculated from length–weight models, using measured lengths and then dividing those estimates of mass by the same lengths that generated those masses to calculate intra-specific variation in shark condition. Such an approach would be inaccurate and circular. Rather, we opted to use a metric that employs independent measurements of body girth at different points along the body axis to estimate the overall body form of the shark (following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C23">Irschick and Hammerschlag, 2014</xref>; described below).We did, however, estimate the body mass of each shark (in kilograms) from the measured fork length (FL) by using the published length–weight relationship for tiger sharks presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C28">Kohler <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref>.A diagram of a tiger shark identifying the morphological variables used in measuring condition. All four variables shown (CKC, caudal keel circumference; FS, frontal span; LS, lateral span; and PS, proximal span) were measured across the body.We collected 20 ml of mixed venous blood from the caudal vein of each shark using 18 gauge needles and 10 ml syringes. Approximately 7 ml of whole blood was aliquoted and centrifuged at 1300 <bold><italic>g</italic></bold> for 5 min to separate whole blood from plasma. Plasma was flash frozen in a dry shipper charged with liquid nitrogen. These samples were then transported to the Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Science and stored at −80°C. A subset of plasma samples (six sharks from the July 2012 Bahamas trip and three Florida sharks) were frozen at &lt;− 20°C before processing. We analysed plasma triglycerides (in millimoles per litre) using the EnzyChrom Triglyceride Assay Kit (ETGA-200; BioAssay Systems, Haywood, CA, USA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C31">Liss <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).To ensure that there was no influence of freezing temperature on triglyceride values from samples frozen at different temperatures, we statistically compared the means from a set of paired samples frozen at −20 and −80°C from the Bahamas 2013 trip and found no significant differences (Student's paired <italic>t</italic> test assuming equal variances, <italic>t</italic> = −1.21, <italic>n</italic> = 11, <italic>P</italic> = 0.24); therefore, samples were pooled for analysis. Samples were run in triplicate across two plates with intra- and inter-assay coefficients of variation of 9.3 and 21.1%, respectively. The inter-assay variation is likely to be attributable to the very low (approaching zero in some cases) triglyceride values found in these animals. Data were normalized to meet the assumptions of normality. We evaluated the relationships between triglycerides and length, estimated weight and body condition, as well as the relationships between body condition and length and estimated body mass, using linear regression. Statistical significance was declared at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, and all analyses were conducted using the R statistical program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C37">R Development Core Team, 2009</xref>).Biological, morphological, condition and triglyceride values for 28 tiger sharks sampled in the Bahamas and Florida in 2012 and 2013Abbreviations: F, female; FL, fork length; M, male; PCL, pre-caudal length; and TL, total length.Relationships between plasma triglycerides (in mmol l<sup>−1</sup>) and condition (<bold>A</bold>), as well as weight (<bold>B</bold>; in kilograms, based on a published species-specific length–weight equation from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C28">Kohler <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>), in 28 free-ranging tiger sharks (black circles, females; and red circles, males) sampled in the subtropical Atlantic.Animal condition has widely been viewed as a window into animal ‘health’, and thus, potentially impacts the ability of animals to feed, reproduce and migrate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C29">Krebs and Singleton, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C24">Jakob <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C46">Weatherhead and Brown, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C17">Green, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C41">Schulte-Hostedde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C3">Bearhop <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C16">Goymann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). However, as mentioned earlier, common metrics of animal condition are not always simply related to independent metrics of physiological state. Therefore, understanding the relationships between animal condition and other metrics of energetic state is important for animals of conservation concern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C43">Stevenson and Woods, 2006</xref>), especially for animals that migrate long distances and that require large energetic stores to reproduce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C31">Liss <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).The vast majority of research on the energetic limitations of migration has occurred in birds. This work has revealed that individuals vary in individual condition and fuel reserves, which in turn influences their migration success, as well as the total fuel reserves available to birds once migration is completed (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C33">Merlla and Svensson, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C3">Bearhop <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C16">Goymann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>); however, findings for birds may not be applicable to other kinds of animals. Plasma metabolite concentrations of triglycerides have been correlated with higher rates of lipid catabolism and body mass (condition) before and during energetically demanding life-history phases in birds (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C25">Jenni-Eiermann and Jenni, 1992</xref>).(<bold>A</bold>) An example of a high-condition/high-triglyceride value tiger shark with large girth from the present study, captured and sampled in October 2013. (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>) An example of a low-condition/low-triglyceride individual captured on the same day, exhibiting physical trauma that is likely to have resulted from males biting the face and tail during mating.The liver is the largest organ in most shark species and is likely to play an important role during lipid metabolism by driving a change in blood triglyceride levels during different phases of life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C35">Oguri, 1990</xref>). During reproduction in sharks, the liver is involved in yolk production via vitellogenin production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C32">Lucifora <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Moreover, female sharks store large amounts of lipids in the liver prior to the pre-vitellogenic phase of the reproductive cycle, to be consumed during vitellogenesis and gestation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C32">Lucifora <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> found a negative correlation between liver weight and maximal diameter of ovarian follicles in sand-tiger sharks (<italic>Carcharhinus taurus</italic>). A recent study of white sharks (<italic>Carcharadon carcharias</italic>) satellite tagged in the Eastern Pacific found that sharks undergoing extensive migrations (4000 km) displayed a consistent increase in vertical drift rate, speculated to be due to a decrease in buoyancy caused by depleted lipid reserves during migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C10">Del Raye <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Our data suggest that measuring condition in white sharks may provide a stronger test of this hypothesis.We noted a large amount of variation in both condition and triglyceride values in our sample of tiger sharks. Some of this variation may be related to differential use of liver energy reserves among individuals throughout movement phases and reproductive stages. While elasmobranch fishes seem to have, in general, much lower circulating levels of triglycerides than most other vertebrates, triglycerides have been well documented as a potential primary energy source, which often comprise a large proportion of the total lipid content in the liver (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C2">Ballantyne, 1997</xref>). At this point it remains unknown whether circulating plasma triglycerides are linked to either exogenous (external factors, such as recent ingestion) or endogenous processes (utilization within the body). However, the lack of high-fat prey at the Bahamas ecosystem (i.e. long time lags in high-energy resource input) and evidence from published data on tiger shark movement at the site likely suggest a within-individual variation of utilization of triglycerides which, in turn, may underscore a potential physiology/life-history trade-off between energy allocation to either soma or reproductive construction and maintenance costs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C48">Zera and Harshman, 2001</xref>). While the observed variation among individual triglyceride values is likely to be a driving factor of a low <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU022F2">2</xref>), this finding underscores the fact that life-history traits are often variable in natural populations and that negative associations (i.e. trade-offs) are generally a crucial assumption of life-history evolution.In a study of the same population of tiger sharks at the Bahamas site (but none of the same individuals we sampled here), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C20">Hammerschlag <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> found that sharks exhibited a combination of two primary habitat use patterns, namely large-scale migrations (3500 km) with an activity space of 8549 km<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C2">2</xref></sup> and high-residency patterns (&gt;60 days) within 350 km<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C2">2</xref></sup> of the tagging site. Furthermore, the majority of the individuals seen at the Bahamas site are sexually mature size classes and bear strong evidence of recent mating year-round, and especially in the spring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C20">Hammerschlag <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; A. J. Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic>, unpublished observations; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU022F3">3</xref>B and C). It would therefore be valuable to compare condition and triglyceride values for these two groups of individuals and between sexes to determine whether energy accumulation during migrations precedes mating and gestation at high-residency sites. If this pattern is indeed occurring, tiger sharks may resemble ‘capital breeders’, in which provisioning of offspring is not limited by the travel time to and from foraging grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C9">Costa, 1993</xref>). The movement data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C20">Hammerschlag <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>, documented generalist dietary patterns and low daily ration of this species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C13">Gallagher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C21">Hammerschlag <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) support this hypothesis. Future research expanding to include additional nutritional parameters (e.g. cholesterol and free fatty acids) and adding reproductive hormone assay, ultrasounds and movement data is needed to evaluate further these patterns and energy use in large elasmobranchs.It is worth noting that, prior to normalization, raw triglyceride values were slightly left skewed (i.e. few individuals at the highest energy states). If this is pattern is truly representative, it could have important conservation implications. For example, if a high threshold level of energy stores is required for onset of pregnancy in tiger sharks, then their populations could be more vulnerable to anthropogenic threats that alter energetic intake.In conclusion, our study highlights the potential role of physiology for organismal behaviour, fitness and demography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C8">Cooke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C7">Cooke, 2014</xref>). Additionally, it underscores the utility of coupling investigations of body form with physiology to explore possible limitations on migration and other energetically challenging life-history phases in top marine predators using non-lethal techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU022C18">Hammerschlag and Sulikowski, 2011</xref>). As researchers studying large predatory fish migration and behavioural ecology evolve to shift their attention from the ‘where’ to the ‘why’ and the ‘how’, studies using physiological measures of energy stores and condition may become increasingly valuable.We thank the staff and interns of the University of Miami's R.J. Dunlap Marine Conservation Program for assistance collecting data, specifically C. Slonim, F. Graham, K. Harthog, E. Nelson and J. Abernethy, J. Castellano of Jim Abernethy's Scuba Adventures. We also thank J. Sulikowski, B. Prohaska, C. Wheeler and C. P. Hammerschlag for their field assistance. We also appreciate the three anonymous reviewers who provided sound recommendations for improving this manuscript. This work was supported by the Disney Worldwide Conservation Fund and the Batchelor Foundation.