Waterlogging-induced changes in root architecture of germplasm accessions of the tropical forage grass <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic>Oxygen distribution and movement, respiration and nutrient loading in banana roots (<italic>Musa</italic> sp. L) subjected to aerated and oxygen-depleted environmentsAtmospheric warming and the amplification of precipitation extremesAeration in higher plantsRoot growth and metabolism under oxygen deficiencyOxygen diffusion in pea. II. The oxygen status of the primary root as affected by growth, the production of laterals and radial oxygen lossMeasurement and modelling of oxygen release from roots of <italic>Phragmites australis</italic>Flooding stress: acclimations and genetic diversityResponses to drought and flooding in tropical forage grasses. I. Biomass allocation, leaf growth and mineral nutrientsRoot growth of lupins is more sensitive to waterlogging than wheatDesynapsis and precocious cytokinesis in <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic> (Poaceae) compromise meiotic divisionMorpho-anatomical adaptations to waterlogging by germplasm accessions in a tropical forage grassLong distance transport of gases in plants: a perspective on internal aeration and radial oxygen loss from rootsOxygen transport, respiration, and anaerobic carbohydrate catabolism in roots in flooded soilsIon transport in seminal and adventitious roots of cereals during O<sub>2</sub> deficiencyFlooding tolerance: suites of plant traits in variable environmentsWaterlogging and plant nutrient uptakeEthylene and responses of plants to soil waterlogging and submergenceThe anatomical characteristics of roots and plant response to soil floodingNatural variation in <italic>Brachiaria</italic> and existing germplasm collectionRice root properties for internal aeration and efficient nutrient acquisition in submerged soilLatin America. Climate change 2007: impacts, adaptation and vulnerabilityThe physical basis for increases in precipitation extremes in simulations of 21st-century climate changeDiagnostic methods for the measurement of root activity in rice plantResponse of the different root system components of sorghum to incidence of waterloggingThe chemistry of submerged soilSomaclonal variation in plant adaptation to acid soil in the tropical forage legume <italic>Stylosanthes guianensis</italic>Ecophysiology of wetland plant roots: a modelling comparison in aeration in relation to species distributionChanges in precipitation with climate changePlant adaptations to anaerobic stressAerenchyma formation in crop species: a review<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Michael B. JacksonThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic>, a tropical forage grass, develops aerenchyma in nodal roots to adapt to waterlogging. A large body of work has focused on the functional role of aerenchyma in nodal roots under waterlogged soil conditions. On the other hand, quantification of responses of lateral roots to waterlogging has been often overlooked in past work. Our data indicated that although waterlogging reduced the overall proportion of lateral roots, its proportion significantly increased in the top 10 cm of the soil. This suggests that soil flooding increases lateral root proliferation of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> in upper soil layers. This may compensate the reduction of root surface area brought by the restriction of root growth at depths below 30 cm into waterlogged soil.Waterlogging is one of the major factors limiting the productivity of pastures in the humid tropics. <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic> is a forage grass commonly used in zones prone to temporary waterlogging. <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic> accessions adapt to waterlogging by increasing aerenchyma in nodal roots above constitutive levels to improve oxygenation of root tissues. In some accessions, waterlogging reduces the number of lateral roots developed from main root axes. Waterlogging-induced reduction of lateral roots could be of adaptive value as lateral roots consume oxygen supplied from above ground via their parent root. However, a reduction in lateral root development could also be detrimental by decreasing the surface area for nutrient and water absorption. To examine the impact of waterlogging on lateral root development, an outdoor study was conducted to test differences in vertical root distribution (in terms of dry mass and length) and the proportion of lateral roots to the total root system (sum of nodal and lateral roots) down the soil profile under drained or waterlogged soil conditions. Plant material consisted of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions from the gene bank of the International Center for Tropical Agriculture, Colombia. Rooting depth was restricted by 21 days of waterlogging and confined to the first 30 cm below the soil surface. Although waterlogging reduced the overall proportion of lateral roots, its proportion significantly increased in the top 10 cm of the soil. This suggests that soil flooding increases lateral root proliferation of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> in the upper soil layers. This may compensate for the reduction of root surface area brought about by the restriction of root growth at depths below 30 cm. Further work is needed to test the relative efficiency of nodal and lateral roots for nutrient and water uptake under waterlogged soil conditions.Daily news reflects the extremes in water availability around the world and modelling predicts that extreme events, including heavy precipitation, will increase in the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C21">Magrin <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C2">Allan and Soden 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C22">O'Gorman and Scheneider 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C29">Trenberth 2011</xref>). The term waterlogging is used to refer to flooding of the soil. This occurs when the infiltration of water from rainfall or flooding exceeds the rate of subsurface drainage and evapotranspiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C9">Bramley <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Diffusion of gases, notably of oxygen, is ∼10 000 times slower in water than in air, leading to oxygen depletion in waterlogged soils as diffusive influx fails to keep pace with demand from root and microbial respiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C16">Elzenga and Veen 2010</xref>). Oxygen deficiency in the soil rooting zone might affect plant growth directly by limiting root aerobic respiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C17">Jackson 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C30">Vartapetian and Jackson 1997</xref>). Many species well adapted to waterlogging have aerenchyma formed in root tissues that allows the internal transport of oxygen within the roots. This can at least partly compensate for oxygen shortage in the soil and support root aerobic respiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C3">Armstrong 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C12">Colmer 2003</xref>).A limitation for plant growth in tropical grasslands is temporary or permanent waterlogging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C8">Baruch 1994</xref>). <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic> (Rendle) Schweickerdt is a stoloniferous perennial grass that grows well in areas of infertile acid and poorly drained soils subject to temporary waterlogging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C19">Keller-Grein <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>) and thus an important forage option under these conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C10">Calisto <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). In a previous study, it was found that while <italic>B. humidicola</italic> developed aerenchyma in nodal roots even when well drained, aerenchyma increased further under waterlogging. This presumably allowed internally transported oxygen to sustain root aerobic respiration and elongation under soil oxygen shortage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C11">Cardoso <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The same study also found that lateral roots (i.e. roots developed from nodal roots) showed negligible aerenchyma and that a reduction in the number of lateral roots occurred in some <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions under waterlogged soil conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C11">Cardoso <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). It has been proposed that a reduction in the number of lateral roots developed from an aerenchymatous root axis might be an advantage under oxygen-deficient conditions as lateral roots consume O<sub>2</sub> from the aerenchyma of the parent root, thus decreasing O<sub>2</sub> diffusion to the elongation zone of the parent root (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C5">Armstrong <italic>et al.</italic> 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C28">Sorrell <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C1">Aguilar <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). However, reductions in lateral root development would, inevitably, reduce the surface area needed for nutrient and water absorption in waterlogged soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C20">Kirk 2003</xref>).A large body of work has focused on the development and functional role of aerenchymatous roots under waterlogged soil conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C7">Bailey-Serres and Voesenek 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C15">Colmer and Voesenek 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C14">Colmer and Greenway 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C31">Yamauchi <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). On the other hand, despite being highly responsive to their environment, quantification of responses of lateral roots to waterlogging has been often overlooked in past work. Furthermore, there appears to be no published information regarding the relative contribution of the lateral root system (in dry mass or length) to the total root system in <italic>B. humidicola</italic> under any conditions. The present study is a follow-up to one showing significant reductions in root dry mass and penetration when 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> germplasm accessions were waterlogged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C11">Cardoso <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The main objective was to quantify differences in vertical root distribution (in terms of dry mass and length) and the contribution of the lateral root system (%) to the total root system (i.e. the sum of nodal and lateral roots) across soil depth. A detailed knowledge of morphological responses and intra-specific variation of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> will contribute to the development of efficient screening procedures for evaluating waterlogging tolerance of hybrids generated from the ongoing <italic>Brachiaria</italic> breeding programme of the International Center for Tropical Agriculture (CIAT).The methodology used in this study was similar to the one described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C11">Cardoso <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>. <italic>Brachiaria humidicola</italic> is a deep-rooted C<sub>4</sub> grass of African origin. Twelve germplasm accessions of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> (CIAT 679, CIAT 6013, CIAT 6133, CIAT 6707, CIAT 16182, CIAT 16866, CIAT 16886, CIAT 16888, CIAT 26152, CIAT 26181, CIAT 26416 and CIAT 26570) were selected from a total of 66 accessions held in the gene bank of CIAT. Three <italic>Brachiaria</italic> grasses (<italic>B. brizantha</italic> cv. Toledo, <italic>B. ruziziensis</italic> 44-02 and a <italic>B.</italic> hybrid cv. Mulato II) with poorer adaptation to waterlogging than <italic>B. humidicola</italic> were included for reference (checks) but were excluded from analysis.The soil used in this study was an Oxisol collected from Santander de Quilichao, Department of Cauca in Colombia (lat. 3°60′N; long. 76°310′W; altitude 990 m), 0–20 cm from the soil surface. All genotypes were grown from vegetative propagules and visually selected for homogeneity from 87-day-old plants growing in propagation pots. Each propagule had a single expanding leaf and a differentiated node for rooting <bold>[see</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu017/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information</bold></ext-link><bold>]</bold>. Propagules arose from stolons. Propagation pots consisted of plants (vegetative stage) that were growing in pots filled with 4 kg of a mixture of soil and sand (2 : 1 w/w) under pot capacity and fertilized conditions (milligrams added per kilogram of a soil–sand mixture: N 21, P 26, K 52, Ca 56, Mg 15, S 10, Zn 1.0, Cu 1.0, B 0.05 and Mo 0.05). Selected propagules were then washed for 1 min in 0.1 % commercial sodium hypochlorite before re-planting. A 1 : 1 (w/w) mixture of soil and sand was used to facilitate root growth and separation from soil for root analysis. Before re-planting of propagules, the soil mixture was thoroughly mixed with the following nutrient application (milligrams of element per kilogram of a soil–sand mixture: N 40, P 50, K 100, Ca 101, Mg 28, S 20, Zn 2.0, Cu 2.0, B 0.1 and Mo 0.1). This level of nutrient application represented the recommended fertility level for crop–pasture establishment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C27">Rao <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>). The soil mixture (4.5 kg) was packed in transparent plastic cylinders (80 cm high × 7.5 cm diameter) inserted into beige polyvinyl chloride (PVC) pipes. Three similarly sized propagules (∼6 cm length) were planted 2 cm below the soil surface in each soil cylinder, watered daily and thinned to one after 7 days. After thinning, propagules were watered daily and allowed to grow for another 21 days. A factorial combination of 15 genotypes by two drainage conditions (drained or waterlogged) was established in a four-replicate randomized complete block. Waterlogging treatment was imposed by sealing the lower end of the PVC pipes with a cap and maintaining a water level of 3 cm above the soil surface <bold>[see</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu017/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information</bold></ext-link><bold>]</bold>. Plants grown under drained soil were watered daily to maintain soil humidity at field capacity. The number of fully expanded leaves, leaf greenness and maximum rooting depth (cm) for each plant were recorded before the start of the experiment. Leaf greenness was measured in two fully expanded young leaves in SPAD (soil plant analysis development) units using a hand-held chlorophyll meter (SPAD-502, Konica Minolta, Japan). Maximum rooting depth was estimated from roots growing next to the wall of the transparent plastic cylinders.The experiment was conducted in an open area at CIAT (Cali, Colombia). During the experiment, the average temperature was 31.5/23.0 °C (day/night), the relative air humidity was 41.2/56.8 % (day/night) and the maximum photosynthetic photon flux density was 1910 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>.Redox potentials were monitored in four cylinders filled with a soil mixture (two for drained soil and two for waterlogged soil) using a platinum electrode and a calomel reference electrode connected to a micro-voltmeter (ODR meter, Eijkelkamp, The Netherlands) at three soil depths (∼5, 15 and 25 cm from the soil surface). Recording of measurements was taken after 3–5 min of equilibration before the start of the experiment (0 days) and after 21 days of treatment.Before harvesting, the number of fully expanded leaves and maximum rooting depth (cm) for each plant were recorded. Maximum rooting depth was estimated from roots growing next to the wall of the transparent plastic cylinders that looked white and healthy. Plants were harvested after 21 days of growth under drained or waterlogged soil conditions. Previous work identified a period of ∼30 days of establishment plus 21 days of treatment as optimal to minimize limitations of root growth due to the container size of plants grown in soil cylinders of 80 cm height × 7.5 cm diameter. Shoot dry mass was determined after drying leaves and stems in an oven at 60 °C for 72 h. Each soil cylinder was sliced into four layers representing different depths from the soil surface (0–10, 10–20, 20–30 and 30–77 cm). To help remove rhizosphere soil from roots, each soil profile was placed in a container with a few drops of wetting agent (polysorbate 20) for 10–15 min and rinsed again with tap water to remove loosened soil. After washing, roots from each soil profile were stored separately in 50 % ethanol and stored at 4 °C for later analysis.Using a dissecting microscope, the brighter and turgid live roots were easily distinguished from the darker and deflated dead ones, which were discarded. The number of live nodal roots was recorded. Thereafter, roots of each soil profile were placed in a tray filled with water and nodal and lateral roots were separated using a surgical scalpel blade. Lateral roots that appeared dead (blackish colour) together with organic matter debris were removed from the tray with an eyedropper. Images of nodal and lateral roots for each soil depth were recorded separately at 600 dpi using a flatbed dual scanner (EPSON Expression 1680, Japan). The length of nodal and lateral roots for each soil profile was estimated using the scanned images and WinRhizo software (Regent Instruments, Canada). After scanning, all roots were carefully collected to minimize loss of material, and oven dried at 60 °C for 72 h for the separate determination of dry mass of nodal and lateral roots down the soil profile. The overall proportion (%) of lateral roots (in terms of dry mass and length) to the total root system (sum of nodal and lateral roots) was determined. The proportions of lateral roots to the total root system for each soil profile were also calculated.Means, standard errors and analyses of variance (ANOVA) were calculated using the open source Agricolae Package of R (v. 2.15.2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C26">R Development Core Team 2012</xref>). Data were log transformed to ensure normality about the means. Differences between accessions were analysed using the least significant difference (LSD) at <italic>α</italic> = 0.05.Soil redox potentials (mV) under (A) drained or (B) waterlogged conditions. Measurements were taken at ∼5, 15 and 25 cm from the soil surface. Columns represent means and error bars their standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 2). The dashed line represents the value where oxygen is undetectable (330 mV) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C25">Ponnamperuma 1972</xref>).Leaf greenness (SPAD units) and dead leaf dry mass of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown under drained or waterlogged soil. Data shown are means of four replicates ± SE. An asterisk (*) represents significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the *0.05, **0.01 and ***0.001 probability levels). <italic>P</italic><sub>anova</sub> and LSD values exclude checks.Number of leaves of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks): (A) before the start of the experiment and (B) after 21 days of growth under drained or waterlogged soil conditions. Columns represent means and error bars their standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 4). All accessions showed an increase in the number of leaves under both treatments from the beginning of the experiment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Asterisks (*) represent significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the *0.05, **0.01 and ***0.001 probability levels). Least significant difference values exclude checks.(A) Shoot and (B) root dry mass of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown for 21 days under drained or waterlogged soil conditions. Columns represent means and error bars their standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 4). Asterisks (*) represent significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the *0.05, **0.01 and ***0.001 probability levels). Least significant difference values exclude checks.Number of nodal roots and maximum rooting depth of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown under drained or waterlogged soil. Nodal roots of plants grown under drained soil reached the bottom of the cylinders (77 cm). Data shown are means of four replicates ± SE. NS, not significant. <italic>P</italic><sub>anova</sub> and LSD values exclude checks.Total root length (m plant<sup>−1</sup>) of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown for 21 days under drained or waterlogged soil conditions. Columns represent means and error bars their standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 4). Asterisks (*) represent significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the ***0.001 probability levels). Least significant difference values exclude checks.Root dry mass distribution across soil depth of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown under drained or waterlogged soil for 21 days. Data shown are means of four replicates ± SE. Asterisks (*) represent significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the *0.05, **0.01 and ***0.001 probability levels). NS, not significant. <italic>P</italic><sub>anova</sub> and LSD values exclude checks.Root length distribution across soil depth of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown under drained or waterlogged soil for 21 days. Data shown are means of four replicates ± SE. Asterisks (*) represent significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the *0.05, **0.01 and ***0.001 probability levels). NS, not significant. <italic>P</italic><sub>anova</sub> and LSD values exclude checks.Proportion (%) of lateral root dry mass to total root dry mass across soil depth of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown under drained or waterlogged soil for 21 days. Data shown are means of four replicates ± SE. Asterisks (*) represent significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the *0.05, **0.01 and ***0.001 probability levels). NS, not significant. <italic>P</italic><sub>anova</sub> and LSD values exclude checks.Proportion (%) of lateral root length to total root length across soil depth of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown under drained or waterlogged soil for 21 days. Data shown are means of four replicates ± SE. Asterisks (*) represent significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the *0.05, **0.01 and ***0.001 probability levels). NS, not significant. <italic>P</italic><sub>anova</sub> and LSD values exclude checks.Overall proportion of (A) lateral root dry mass to total root weight and (B) lateral root length to total root length of 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown for 21 days under drained or waterlogged soil conditions. Columns represent means and error bars their standard error (<italic>n</italic> = 4). Asterisks (*) represent significant differences between treatments for each accession (statistical significance at the *0.05, **0.01 and ***0.001 probability levels). Least significant difference values exclude checks.Schematic representation of the relative contribution of lateral root length across soil depth in 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown for 21 days under drained or waterlogged soil conditions. Horizontal lines represent lateral roots. Vertical lines represent nodal roots. Distribution of lateral roots at 30–77 cm of soil depth under drained soil conditions was assumed to be even.Waterlogging for 21 days reduced the shoot dry mass of accessions CIAT 16866 and CIAT 16888 together with a decrease in the number of leaves. This reflects the importance of leaf production in maintaining shoot growth (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F3">3</xref>). In the present study, reduction of leaf number in CIAT 16866 and CIAT 16888 when waterlogged was not the outcome of faster leaf senescence (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU017TB1">1</xref>), but rather a result of slower leaf production (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F2">2</xref>). Total root dry mass and total root length were both significantly reduced in <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (except CIAT 16886) under waterlogging conditions (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F3">3</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F4">4</xref>). In contrast, total root dry mass and total root length of CIAT 16886 were not reduced, possibly a reflection of its inherently slower growth rate as indicated by the lower production of leaves throughout the period of study (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F2">2</xref>A and B). For any accession, there was no reduction in the number of nodal roots per plant under waterlogging conditions. Thus, the decreases in total root dry mass and total root length are attributable to a restriction of nodal root penetration below 30 cm in anoxic soil (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F4">4</xref>; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU017TB2">2</xref>). The maximum rooting depth into waterlogged and anoxic soils depends on the amount of oxygen that reaches the root tip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C12">Colmer 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C13">Colmer and Greenway 2005</xref>). This is greatly facilitated by aerenchyma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C18">Justin and Armstrong 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C4">Armstrong and Drew 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C12">Colmer 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C13">Colmer and Greenway 2005</xref>). Previous research showed that nodal roots of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> responded to waterlogging by increasing root aerenchyma (to around 30 % of cross-sectional area); this is presumably to improve root aeration and sustain elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C11">Cardoso <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).Our data showed that waterlogged soil reached anoxic conditions (&lt;330 mV; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F1">1</xref>). Although the importance of aerenchyma in supporting root elongation under oxygen-deficient conditions is widely recognized, it was shown that even roots with very high porosities (over 30 %) rarely penetrate more than 30 cm of soil (e.g. wetland species; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C18">Justin and Armstrong 1987</xref>). On this basis, roots of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> would also be expected to be limited to 30 cm in flooded soil. This in turn will restrict total root surface area to one that restricts nutrient and water uptake to maintain shoot growth. Therefore, we suggest that other adaptations acting together with aerenchyma development sustain the shoot growth of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> under waterlogging conditions.The present study shows that lateral roots comprise a large component of the root system. In all the <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions we tested, lateral roots represented around 50 % of total root weight and 62–88 % of total root length under drained conditions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F5">5</xref>A and B). Under waterlogging conditions, an overall reduction of the proportion of lateral roots (in terms of both dry mass and length) to total root length was found (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F5">5</xref>A and B). A reduction of lateral roots under oxygen shortage has previously been recorded for some accessions of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C11">Cardoso <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and other species such as rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C23">Ota 1970</xref>), pea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C5">Armstrong <italic>et al.</italic> 1983</xref>), sorghum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C24">Pardales <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>) and banana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C1">Aguilar <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). It has been argued that a reduction of lateral roots developed from the parent root is of adaptive value as more oxygen could reach the tip of the parent root to sustain root elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C5">Armstrong <italic>et al.</italic> 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C28">Sorrell <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C1">Aguilar <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). However, this will probably result in a reduction of root surface area, already restricted by the maximum penetration attained by roots into waterlogged soil.The present study showed that there was a significant increase in the proportion of lateral root length in the upper 10 cm of waterlogged soil (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU017TB6">6</xref>; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F6">6</xref>). An increase in the proportion of lateral roots in the top 10 cm of soil suggests an enhanced development of lateral roots closer to the root base of nodals under waterlogging conditions. Increased lateral root development closer to the root base might be a consequence of slower nodal root elongation under waterlogging conditions. Another possibility is that lateral root development near the root base was facilitated by a closer proximity to the oxygen provided by aerenchyma from the nodal root. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C6">Armstrong <italic>et al.</italic> (1990)</xref>, O<sub>2</sub> consumed by lateral roots developed from the base of parent roots with high porosity will have little impact on the O<sub>2</sub> concentration in the root base and thus in the O<sub>2</sub> diffusion path to the root tip. Therefore, it is possible that the bulk of lateral roots of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions were initiated within the first 10 cm of the waterlogged soil. This could be considered advantageous under waterlogged conditions since they would not detrimentally affect the penetration of the parent root (i.e. nodal roots with aerenchyma).Although the focus of this study was on <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions, it is instructive to note the responses of <italic>B. brizantha</italic>, <italic>B. ruziziensis</italic> and a <italic>Brachiaria</italic> hybrid that were used to confirm the superior waterlogging tolerance of the selected <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions. Their relatively poor adaptation when compared with <italic>B. humidicola</italic> was revealed as a more strongly reduced shoot growth and increased leaf senescence (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU017TB1">1</xref>; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU017F3">3</xref>). This greater damage above ground was associated with confinement of the roots to the top 10 cm of waterlogged soil (the maximum rooting depth was ∼2-fold below that of the <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU017TB2">2</xref>). Shallower root systems were presumably a consequence of less aerenchyma in roots of the three check species since this has previously been found to be approximately half that in <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions and comprise ∼16 % of cross-sectional area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU017C11">Cardoso <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).The present study shows that the overall proportion of lateral roots developed from the parent root axes of 12 accessions of <italic>B. humidicola</italic> was decreased by 21 days of soil waterlogging. However, in the top 10 cm of the soil the reverse was the case, with waterlogging increasing the proportion of the roots that comprised lateral roots. An increased proportion of lateral roots in the upper layers is thought to be of adaptive value by compensating for the reduction of absorptive root surface resulting from the inhibition of root growth at depths below 30 cm.Variation among the accessions was found for all plant attributes and proportions measured. However, it was not possible to establish associations between root traits and the reduction of shoot growth under waterlogging conditions for two accessions (CIAT 16866 and CIAT 16888). Further research is therefore needed to establish the differences in the efficiency of nutrient and water uptake by both nodal (aerenchymatous) and lateral (non-aerenchymatous) roots and test their relationships with the observed differences in shoot growth among <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions. A causal connection between lack of rooting depth and extent of aerenchyma is indicated by the shallow rooting depth of waterlogging-intolerant <italic>Brachiaria</italic> species that characteristically have much less extensive aerenchyma in their main root axes.This work was partially funded by FONTAGRO (USA) (project number: FTG-8060/08).J.A.C. was involved in designing the experiments, data collection and analysis, manuscript preparation and submission. J.C.J. contributed to the set-up of experiments and manuscript preparation. I.M.R. was involved in designing and supervision of experiments, manuscript preparation and submission.None declared.We thank S. Gómez, E. Cuarán and H. Mina for their help during the course of the study. We thank the associate editor and two anonymous reviewers for useful comments that improved this manuscript.The following <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu017/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link> is available in the online version of this article –<bold>File 1.</bold> Schematic representation of system used to evaluate waterlogging tolerance in <italic>Brachiaria</italic> spp.<bold>File 2.</bold> Number of nodal roots across soil depth in 12 <italic>B. humidicola</italic> accessions (plus three checks) grown under drained or waterlogged soil for 21 days. Data shown are means of four replicates ± SE. Number of nodal roots for each soil profile was reduced with increasing depth.