Crassulacean acid metabolism-cycling in <italic>Euphorbia milii</italic>Photosynthetic pathways and ecological distribution of <italic>Euphorbia</italic> species in EgyptOn the ecophysiology of the Clusiaceae in Trinidad: expression of CAM in <italic>Clusia minor</italic> L. during the transition from wet to dry season and characterization of tree endemic speciesCarbon-isotope composition of biochemical fractions and the regulation of carbon balance in leaves of the C<sub>3</sub>-CAM <italic>Clusia minor</italic> L. growing in TrinidadThe quantitative analysis of chlorophylls a and b in plant extractsC<sub>3</sub> plants enhance rates of photosynthesis by reassimilating photorespired and respired CO<sub>2</sub>Why are non-photosynthetic tissues generally <sup>13</sup>C enriched compared with leaves in C<sub>3</sub> plants? Review and synthesis of current hypothesesCrassulacean acid metabolism. A plastic photosynthetic adaptation to arid environmentsIsotopic composition of plant carbon correlates with water-use efficiency of wheat genotypesEnvironmental influences on carbon recycling in a terrestrial CAM bromeliad, <italic>Bromelia humilis</italic> JacqPatterns of gas exchange and organic acid oscillations in tropical tress of the genus <italic>Clusia</italic>Comparative ecophysiology of five species of <italic>Sedum</italic> (Crassulaceae) under well-watered and drought-stressed conditionsDiscrimination in the dark. Resolving the interplay between metabolic and physical constraints to phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase activity during the crassulacean acid metabolism cycleRecycling of CO<sub>2</sub> during induction of CAM by drought in <italic>Talinum paniculatum</italic> (Portulacaceae)The occurrence and phylogenetics of CAM in the PortulacaceaeCorrelation between CAM-cycling and photosynthetic gas exchange in five species of <italic>Talinum</italic> (Portulacaceae)Crassulacean acid metabolism and fitness under water deficit stress: if not for carbon gain, what is facultative CAM good for?Occurrence of facultative crassulacean acid metabolism in leaves of <italic>Talinum triangulare</italic> (Portulacaceae)Induction by drought of crassulacean acid metabolism in the terrestrial bromeliad, <italic>Puya floccosa</italic>Effect of varying CO<sub>2</sub> partial pressure on photosynthesis and on carbon isotope composition of carbon-4 of malate from the crassulacean acid metabolism plant <italic>Kalanchoe daigremontiana</italic> Hamet et PerrCrassulacean acid metabolism in the ZZ plant, <italic>Zamioculcas zamiifolia</italic> (Araceae)C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis and CAM in a Kansas rock outcrop succulent, <italic>Talinum calycinum</italic> (Portulacaceae)Ecophysiological significance of CO<sub>2</sub>-recycling via CAM in <italic>Talinum calycinum</italic> Engelm. (Portulacaceae)Comparative rates of dark CO<sub>2</sub> uptake and acidification in the Bromeliaceae, Orchidaceae, and EuphorbiaceaeEcophysiology and distribution of the endemic leafless spurge <italic>Euphorbia aphylla</italic> and the introduced <italic>E. tirucalli</italic> (Euphorbiaceae, <italic>Euphorbia</italic> sect. <italic>Tirucalli</italic>) in the Canary IslandsCarbon isotope ratio measurements of succulent plants in southern AfricaWhy do Euphorbiaceae tick as medicinal plants? A review of Euphorbiaceae family and its medicinal featuresFunctional constraints of CAM leaf anatomy: tight cell packing is associated with increased CAM function across a gradient of CAM expressionPhotosynthetic characteristics and chloroplast ultrastructure of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> tree species grown in high- and low-light environmentsEcology and ecophysiology of tree stems: corticular and wood photosynthesisCarbon isotope ratio and the extent of daily CAM use by BromeliaceaeOperation of the xanthophyll cycle and degradation of D1 protein in the facultative CAM plant, <italic>Talinum triangulare</italic>, under water deficitThe occurrence of C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis in <italic>Euphorbia</italic> subgenus <italic>Chamaesyce</italic> (Euphorbiaceae)Crassulacean acid metabolism 1975–2000, a check listDistribution of crassulacean acid metabolism in orchids of Panama: evidence of selection for weak and strong modesSystematics of photosynthetic carbon fixation pathways in <italic>Euphorbia</italic>δ<sup>13</sup>C values of some succulent plants from MadagascarHow closely do the δ<sup>13</sup>C values of crassulacean acid metabolism plants reflect the proportion of CO<sub>2</sub> fixed during day and night?Further support for the phylogenetic relationships within <italic>Euphorbia</italic> L. (Euphorbiaceae) from nrITS and trnL–trnF IGS sequence dataThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Photosynthetic characteristics of <italic>Euphorbia milii</italic> are reported for the first time. The occurrence of CAM-cycling is shown to serve as a mechanism of water conservation. This is a detailed and novel report of such CAM mode in the genus, which is abundant in constitutive CAM and C<sub>4</sub> species. Anatomical evidence for the possible operation of a CO<sub>2</sub>-concentrating mechanism around the vascular bundle, the C<sub>2</sub> route, is provided. Findings are important for our understanding of evolution of CAM in the genus.Crassulacean acid metabolism (CAM) occurs in many Euphorbiaceae, particularly <italic>Euphorbia</italic>, a genus with C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species as well. With the aim of contributing to our knowledge of the evolution of CAM in this genus, this study examined the possible occurrence of CAM in <italic>Euphorbia milii</italic>, a species with leaf succulence and drought tolerance suggestive of this carbon fixation pathway. Leaf anatomy consisted of a palisade parenchyma, a spongy parenchyma and a bundle sheath with chloroplasts, which indicates the possible functioning of C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis. No evidence of nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> fixation was found in plants of <italic>E. milii</italic> either watered or under drought; watered plants had a low nocturnal respiration rate (<italic>R</italic>). After 12 days without watering, the photosynthetic rate (<italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub>) decreased 85 % and nocturnal <italic>R</italic> was nearly zero. Nocturnal H<sup>+</sup> accumulation (ΔH<sup>+</sup>) in watered plants was 18 ± 2 (corresponding to malate) and 18 ± 4 (citrate) μmol H<sup>+</sup> (g fresh mass)<sup>−1</sup>. Respiratory CO<sub>2</sub> recycling through acid synthesis contributed to a night-time water saving of 2 and 86 % in watered plants and plants under drought, respectively. Carbon isotopic composition (δ<sup>13</sup>C) was −25.2 ± 0.7 ‰ in leaves and −24.7 ± 0.1 ‰ in stems. Evidence was found for the operation of weak CAM in <italic>E. milii</italic>, with statistically significant ΔH<sup>+</sup>, no nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> uptake and values of δ<sup>13</sup>C intermediate between C<sub>3</sub> and constitutive CAM plants; ΔH<sup>+</sup> was apparently attributable to both malate and citrate. The results suggest that daily malate accumulation results from recycling of part of the nocturnal respiratory CO<sub>2</sub>, which helps explain the occurrence of an intermediate value of leaf δ<sup>13</sup>C. <italic>Euphorbia milii</italic> can be considered as a CAM-cycling species. The significance of the operation of CAM-cycling in <italic>E. milii</italic> lies in water conservation, rather than carbon acquisition. The possible occurrence of C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis merits research.Carbon isotopic composition of species of <italic>Euphorbia</italic> with high to intermediate values of δ<sup>13</sup>C and CAM mode assigned by authors on the basis of leaf gas exchange, acid accumulation, δ<sup>13</sup>C and enzyme activity.NA, no mode assigned; ND, not determined.Since values of δ<sup>13</sup>C alone are not sufficient to distinguish between C<sub>3</sub> species and plants that obtain up to one-third of their carbon during the night, which include weak CAM plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C40">Winter and Holtum 2002</xref>), measurements of physiological and biochemical variables are necessary. In order to demonstrate the operation of CAM, routine determinations include, among others, ΔH<sup>+</sup>, δ<sup>13</sup>C and nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> fixation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C12">Griffiths <italic>et al</italic>. (2007)</xref> devised an ingenious method of ascertaining the occurrence of nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> fixation by examining the response of the night-time CO<sub>2</sub> exchange rate to intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>).Intermediate values of δ<sup>13</sup>C can also suggest the occurrence of C<sub>3</sub> metabolism with high water-use efficiency, as the data of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C8">Farquhar and Richards (1984)</xref> on wheat indicate, or of C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis, as in the case of <italic>Euphorbia acuta</italic>. In wheat and maize, C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis is responsible for an increase of 8–11 % in photosynthetic rate through re-assimilation of photorespired CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C5">Busch <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>).Plants of <italic>Euphorbia milii</italic> subgenus <italic>Euphorbia</italic>, Section <italic>Goniostema</italic>, common name crown of thorns, originally from Madagascar, are cultivated worldwide for their ornamental value. Plants are perennial armed shrubs as tall as 1 m, with fleshy stem and branches, and partly succulent leaves. According to observations by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C27">Mooney <italic>et al</italic>. (1977)</xref>, CAM is present in the weak mode in leafy species of the genus. The medicinal and molluscicidal properties of the latex in <italic>E. milii</italic> have been extensively investigated (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C28">Mwine and Van Damme 2011</xref>); in contrast, literature on the physiology of the species is practically non-existent.In spite of the succulence of its leaves and the various reports of CAM in the genus, <italic>E. milii</italic> has been reported as non-CAM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C38">Webster <italic>et al</italic>. 1975</xref>). Nevertheless, recalculation of the data of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C25">McWilliams (1970)</xref> gives a ΔH<sup>+</sup> of 100 μmol (g fresh mass)<sup>−1</sup> and a dark CO<sub>2</sub> fixation rate of 0.1 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, suggesting that CAM in <italic>E. milii</italic> operates in the cycling mode, i.e. nocturnal H<sup>+</sup> accumulation and daytime but nearly no night-time CO<sub>2</sub> fixation (for the definition of CAM modes, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C7">Cushman 2001</xref>).With the aim of contributing to our knowledge of the evolution of CAM in <italic>Euphorbia</italic>, this study re-examined the possible occurrence of CAM in <italic>E. milii</italic> through daily leaf gas exchange, including <italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> and <italic>R</italic>/<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> curves (where <italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub> is the photosynthetic rate and <italic>R</italic> is the respiration rate), measurements of dawn and dusk H<sup>+</sup> content, and determinations of δ<sup>13</sup>C.Plants of <italic>E. milii</italic> were propagated from one plant purchased at a nursery by inserting cuttings into the soil of 2-L pots filled with silty clay loam (Viveros Exotica Raphia, S.R.L., Caracas); plants were fertilized monthly with N : P : K 15 : 15 : 15 and grown in the garden for 1 year before the beginning of experiments. Plants, ∼50 cm tall, were maintained in the greenhouse under natural light, fully watered every other day and fertilized weekly. Day length was 12 h (06:00–18:00 h), mean maximum daily photosynthetic photon flux density (PPFD) between 09:00 and 14:30 h 507 ± 22 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, mean air temperature 32 ± 5/18.4 ± 0.5 °C (day/night) and relative humidity 60 ± 10 %. Water deficit was imposed by withholding watering.Free-hand cross-sections of stems (average thickness 5 mm) and leaves were observed under the microscope at ×40 (stem) and ×400 (leaf). Leaf sections were stained with toluidine blue.Leaf and stem water content was determined as the difference between the fresh mass (FM) and the mass after drying for 72 h at 60 °C [dry mass (DM)], divided by the area in the case of leaves (FM/A) and by DM in the case of stems. Leaf thickness was measured with precision calipers. Chlorophyll (Chl) content was determined after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C4">Bruinsma (1963)</xref> in 80 % cold acetone extracts of leaf or stem sections collected at 18:00 h. The mesophyll succulence index was calculated as <italic>S</italic><sub>m</sub> = g water (mg Chl)<sup>−1</sup> after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C21">Kluge and Ting (1978)</xref>.The δ<sup>13</sup>C was determined with a precision of 0.15 ‰ using a ThermoFinnigan DeltaPlusXL Isotope Ratio Mass Spectrometer (San Jose, CA, USA) and PDB as the standard.Whole leaves were weighed fresh and set to boil in 50 mL distilled water for 10 min in a microwave oven at maximum power; samples were sieved through a plastic colander, leaf segments and the colander were rinsed, and the solution was made up to 100 mL. Samples were titrated to pH 7.0 for the estimation of H<sup>+</sup> corresponding to malate according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C30">Nobel (1988)</xref>, and to pH 8.4 for citrate. Since <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C10">Franco <italic>et al</italic>. (1990)</xref> noted that there was a strong linear relationship between concentrations of malate and citrate determined enzymatically and by titration, in the absence of an enzymatic method for the determination, titration is an adequate alternative. Latex was collected from cut stems and leaves, suspended in distilled water and titrated likewise. The ΔH<sup>+</sup> was calculated as the difference between dawn and dusk H<sup>+</sup> contents.The <italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub>, <italic>R</italic>, stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) and transpiration rate (<italic>E</italic>) were measured in the laboratory with a CIRAS 2 IRGA connected to a PLC(B) assimilation chamber (PP Systems, Amesbury, MA, USA) at an incoming CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>a</sub>) of 380 μmol mol<sup>−1</sup>, a chamber temperature tracking ambient (24 ± 1 °C) and an incident PPFD of 200 (the first morning hours) or 1000 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> (the rest of the daytime). Records were automatically taken every 30 min. Response curves were done in six different leaves of <italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> between 10:00 and 11:00 h, and of nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> exchange to <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> between 20:00 and 05:00 h.Values are mean ± SE (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Statistical significance was assessed where indicated through one- or two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) with the Statistica package.Cross-sections of the leaf of <italic>E. milii</italic>. UE, upper epidermis; PP, palisade parenchyma; VB, vascular bundle; BS, bundle sheath; SP, spongy parenchyma; LE, lower epidermis. Arrowheads point at chloroplasts.In watered plants, <italic>S</italic><sub>m</sub> in both leaves and stem green cortex was 2.7 ± 0.2 g water (mg Chl)<sup>−1</sup>; δ<sup>13</sup>C was −25.2 ± 0.7 ‰ in leaves and −24.7 ± 0.1 ‰ in stems. In the stem green cortex of watered plants, malate- and citrate-H<sup>+</sup> content was 48 ± 9 and 29 ± 5 μmol H<sup>+</sup> (g FM)<sup>−1</sup>, respectively, without daily oscillation. Water suspensions of latex showed no acid content.Time course of changes with drought in leaves of <italic>E. milii</italic> in (A) H<sup>+</sup> content titrated to pH 7.0 (empty circles, dawn; filled circles, dusk); (B) H<sup>+</sup> content titrated to pH 8.4 (empty circles, dawn; filled circles, dusk); (C) nocturnal H<sup>+</sup> accumulation (empty triangles, pH 8.4; filled triangles, pH 7.0), and (D) dawn leaf FM per area (circles) and chlorophyll content (triangles). Values are mean ± SE (<italic>n</italic> = 12). Different letters indicate significant differences at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 after a two-way ANOVA (time under drought × hour of day for each pH in A and B) and a one-way ANOVA (time under drought for each pH in C).Response curve of the leaf photosynthetic rate to (A) photosynthetic photon flux density and (B) leaf intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in watered plants of <italic>E. milii</italic>. Values are mean ± SE (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Filled circles, <italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub>; empty symbols, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>. Measurements were made at a CO<sub>2</sub> concentration of 380 μmol mol<sup>−1</sup> in (A) and a PPFD of 1000 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> in (B).Daily course of the leaf photosynthetic rate, stomatal conductance and transpiration rate in plants of <italic>E. milii</italic> under drought for 0, 7, 12 and 16 days. Measurements were made at a CO<sub>2</sub> concentration of 380 μmol mol<sup>−1</sup>, leaf temperature of 24.0 ± 1.0 °C and PPFD of 200 (06:00–10:00 h) and 1000 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> (10:00–18:00 h). The dark bar on the abscissa indicates the length of the dark period.Photosynthetic and respiration rate of stem cross-sections inserted into the IRGA assimilation chamber.Values are mean ± SE (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Incident photosynthetic photon flux density is indicated.Response curves to leaf intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration of nocturnal respiration rate and stomatal conductance in watered plants of <italic>E. milii</italic>. Filled symbols, <italic>R</italic>; empty symbols, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>. Values are mean ± SE (<italic>n</italic> = 6).Change in nocturnal leaf transpiration rate of plants of <italic>E. milii</italic> watered and under different degrees of drought as a function of nocturnal respiration rate. Values are data points. The regression line (solid), 95 % confidence intervals (broken lines) and determination coefficient (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are shown.Evidence was found for the operation of weak CAM in <italic>E. milii</italic>, with statistically significant ΔH<sup>+</sup> in watered plants and plants under drought, low δ<sup>13</sup>C and no nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> uptake; ΔH<sup>+</sup> was apparently attributable to both malate and citrate. Results suggest that daily malate and citrate accumulation results from recycling of part (watered plants) or all (plants under drought) of the nocturnal respiratory CO<sub>2</sub>. Recycling of CO<sub>2</sub> through malate synthesis, together with the absence of nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> uptake, helps explain the occurrence of values of leaf δ<sup>13</sup>C intermediate between C<sub>3</sub> and constitutive CAM plants.Values of nocturnal acid accumulation and carbon isotopic composition reported for CAM species.Some values were re-calculated from the data in references. ND, not determined.Values of mesophyll succulence index reported for constitutive, facultative- and cycling-CAM species.The presence in <italic>E. milii</italic> of bundle sheath cells with chloroplasts is indicative of the possible operation of C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis, as reported in <italic>E. acuta</italic>. This species shares with <italic>E. milii</italic> low, C<sub>3</sub>-like values of δ<sup>13</sup>C (−25.5 ‰ according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C38">Webster <italic>et al</italic>. 1975</xref>, and −28.5 ‰ according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C35">Sage <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and an intermediate value of CO<sub>2</sub> compensation concentration (32 mmol mol<sup>−1</sup>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C35">Sage <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). The occurrence of CAM, Kranz anatomy and C<sub>4</sub> photosynthesis in the same leaf has been reported in Portulacaceae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C14">Guralnick and Jackson 2001</xref>), but to date no report on CAM together with C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis has been published. Given that the C<sub>2</sub> route of carbon fixation has been proposed as an intermediate evolutionary step from C<sub>3</sub> to C<sub>4</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C35">Sage <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), investigating the functioning of C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis in <italic>E. milii</italic> would bring interesting viewpoints on the evolution of CAM and C<sub>4</sub> plants, particularly in <italic>Euphorbia</italic>.A significant oscillation in H<sup>+</sup> content corresponding to citrate was found, equivalent to 12 μmol citrate (g FM)<sup>−1</sup> after 12 days of drought, comparable with the lower end, ∼22 μmol (g FM)<sup>−1</sup>, of the range in species of <italic>Clusia</italic>, a genus abundant in CAM species performing different modes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C22">Lüttge 2007</xref>). The role of citrate accumulation in carbon or water balance during CAM remains unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C22">Lüttge 2007</xref>); citrate does not provide net CO<sub>2</sub> gain, as does malate, but should prove more effective than malate in increasing <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> during the day because its breakdown produces three molecules of CO<sub>2</sub> as opposed to one in the case of malate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C22">Lüttge 2007</xref>). Increased <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> during the day is a photoprotective mechanism well recognized in CAM plants, as shown in plants of the facultative CAM species <italic>Talinum triangulare</italic> under drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C34">Pieters <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>).Photosynthetic characteristics in <italic>E. milii</italic> were consistent with those of a sun plant: high apparent quantum yield, saturating PPFD and Chl a/b ratio (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C31">Pearcy and Franceschi 1986</xref>).The absence of net dark CO<sub>2</sub> fixation was consistent with the proportion of dark CO<sub>2</sub> uptake calculated using the regression equations of the proportion of CO<sub>2</sub> fixed during the night against δ<sup>13</sup>C found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C40">Winter and Holtum (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C33">Pierce <italic>et al</italic>. (2002)</xref>. In many facultative CAM species, δ<sup>13</sup>C tends towards low values. In a review of 23 facultative CAM species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C16">Herrera 2009</xref>), the mean, maximum and minimum δ<sup>13</sup>C were −23.9, −14.0 and −30.0 ‰, respectively, indicating that the variability in δ<sup>13</sup>C values may lead researchers to classify a species as a C<sub>3</sub>, facultative or constitutive CAM plant. In <italic>Euphorbia aphylla</italic>, δ<sup>13</sup>C ranged from −27.1 ‰ for the youngest cladode in the dry season during summer to −24.5 ‰ for the oldest cladode in the rainy season during winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C26">Mies <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>), reflecting the effects on δ<sup>13</sup>C of day/night temperatures, water availability and developmental stage.Values of δ<sup>13</sup>C higher in stems than in leaves suggest the occurrence of nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> fixation, although this could not be demonstrated in intact plants. The occurrence of an assimilation rate in the dark amounting to a third of PPFD-saturated leaf <italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub> strongly suggested that stems are capable of nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> fixation. Stem internal CO<sub>2</sub> re-fixation in young twigs and branches possessing a green cortex may compensate for 60–90 % of the potential respiratory carbon loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C32">Pfanz <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). If stem recycling in <italic>E. milii</italic> occurred through phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase (PEPC) activity, that would explain the apparent <sup>13</sup>C enrichment. There are two alternative explanations for higher δ<sup>13</sup>C in the stems of <italic>E. milii</italic>. One explanation is that this variable was determined in sections comprising all tissues, green as well as non-autotrophic; non-autotrophic organs of C<sub>3</sub> plants, such as stems, have been found to be enriched in δ<sup>13</sup>C by ∼1–3 ‰ relative to leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C6">Cernusak <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Another, simpler, explanation is that barriers to CO<sub>2</sub> diffusion into the stem are larger than into leaves, hindering entrance of the heavier <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub>. Actual nocturnal CO<sub>2</sub> fixation by stems of <italic>E. milii</italic> remains to be determined accurately by methods such as carbon labelling, involving all stem tissues.The response of leaf dark respiration to <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> suggests the operation of a carboxylation system, most likely PEPC, which makes recycling of respiratory CO<sub>2</sub> possible. In the constitutive CAM plant <italic>Kalanchoe daigremontiana</italic>, a <italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> curve during phase I of the CAM cycle showed a pronounced increase at low <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> and saturation at a <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> of ∼250 μmol mol<sup>−1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C12">Griffiths <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). Our results show that the response of dark respiration to <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> was not an artefact caused by changes in <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>, because <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> remained constant in spite of increasing <italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>.Water saving through respiratory CO<sub>2</sub> recycling was significant, as in the case of <italic>T. paniculatum</italic>, a facultative CAM species, in which the amount of water saved was 5–12 times that lost by transpiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C13">Güerere <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>). Similarly, in <italic>T. calycinum</italic>, 5–44 % of water was potentially conserved by CAM-cycling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT014C24">Martin <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</xref>).Leaf water balance in <italic>E. milii</italic> seems to rest on both recycling of respiratory CO<sub>2</sub> and strict stomatal control, rather than on water supply from the succulent stem, as leaf FM/A remained unchanged after 16 days of drought and stem water content did not vary significantly during this time.In view of the observations presented here, <italic>E. milii</italic> can be considered as a CAM-cycling species that in watered plants shows diurnal, but not nocturnal, CO<sub>2</sub> uptake and low ΔH<sup>+</sup>; plants under drought have very low <italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub>, equally low ΔH<sup>+</sup> and no net dark CO<sub>2</sub> exchange. The significance of the operation of such a low CAM in <italic>E. milii</italic> resides in water conservation, rather than carbon acquisition. The occurrence of C<sub>2</sub> photosynthesis remains to be demonstrated.Experiments were done with equipment acquired through <grant-num xlink:type="simple">grant PG-03.00.6524.2006</grant-num> and technical assistance provided by <grant-num xlink:type="simple">grant PG 03.7381.2011-1</grant-num> (CDCH-UCV).None declared.Thanks are due to the PaleoLab at the College of Marine Science of the University of South Florida and to Dr Enrique Montes for the determinations of δ<sup>13</sup>C. Help with leaf section preparation and the provision of photographs by L. Hermoso, M. Escala and A. Menéndez are gratefully acknowledged.