 The group IV-A cyclic nucleotide-gated channels, CNGC19 and CNGC20, localize to the vacuole membrane in  Arabidopsis thaliana   Expression of plant cyclic nucleotide-gated cation channels in yeast   Arabidopsis  protein disulfide isomerase-5 inhibits cysteine proteases during trafficking to vacuoles before programmed cell death of the endothelium in developing seeds  Salt tolerance conferred by overexpression of a vacuolar Na + /H +  antiport in  Arabidopsis   Vacuolar cation/H +  exchange, ion homeostasis, and leaf development are altered in a T-DNA insertional mutant of  AtNHX1 , the  Arabidopsis  vacuolar Na + /H +  antiporter  A high-affinity calmodulin-binding site in a tobacco plasma-membrane channel protein coincides with a characteristic element of cyclic nucleotide-binding domains  HLM1, an essential signaling component in the hypersensitive response, is a member of the cyclic nucleotide-gated channel ion channel family  Identification of a functionally essential amino acid for  Arabidopsis  cyclic nucleotide gated ion channels using the chimeric  AtCNGC11/12  gene  The cyclic nucleotide-gated calmodulin-binding channel AtCNGC10 localizes to the plasma membrane and influences numerous growth responses and starch accumulation in  Arabidopsis thaliana   Early effects of salinity on water transport in  Arabidopsis  roots. Molecular and cellular features of aquaporin expression  A putative calcium-permeable cyclic nucleotide-gated channel, CNGC18, regulates polarized pollen tube growth  Protein disulfide isomerase-2 of  Arabidopsis  mediates protein folding and localizes to both the secretory pathway and nucleus, where it interacts with maternal effect embryo arrest factor  The cyclic nucleotide gated cation channel AtCNGC10 traffics from the ER via Golgi vesicles to the plasma membrane of  Arabidopsis  root and leaf cells  The  Arabidopsis dnd1  ‘defense, no death’ gene encodes a mutated cyclic nucleotide-gated ion channel  Salt and osmotic stress cause rapid increases in  Arabidopsis thaliana  cGMP levels  AT_CHLORO, a comprehensive chloroplast proteome database with subplastidial localization and curated information on envelope proteins  A cyclic nucleotide-gated channel is essential for polarized tip growth of pollen   Arabidopsis thaliana  cyclic nucleotide gated channel 3 forms a non-selective ion transporter involved in germination and cation transport  The cyclic nucleotide-gated channel, AtCNGC10, influences salt tolerance in  Arabidopsis   The cyclic nucleotide-gated channel AtCNGC10 transports Ca 2+  and Mg 2+  in  Arabidopsis   The use of protoplasts to study innate immune responses  Plants do it differently. A new basis for potassium/sodium selectivity in the pore of an ion channel   Arabidopsis  tonoplast proteins TIP1 and TIP2 interact with the cucumber mosaic virus 1a replication protein  Characterisation of calmodulin binding to cyclic nucleotide-gated ion channels from  Arabidopsis thaliana   Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: application to complete genomes  Salt-dependent regulation of a CNG channel subfamily in  Arabidopsis   Cloning and first functional characterization of a plant cyclic nucleotide-gated cation channel  Electrophysiological analysis of cloned cyclic nucleotide-gated ion channels   Arabidopsis  AtCNGC10 rescues potassium channel mutants of  E. coli , yeast and  Arabidopsis  and is regulated by calcium/calmodulin and cyclic GMP in  E. coli   Characterization of plant phenotypes associated with loss-of-function of AtCNGC1, a plant cyclic nucleotide gated cation channel  Ca 2+ , cAMP, and transduction of non-self perception during plant immune responses  The role of monovalent cation transporters in plant responses to salinity  Phylogenetic relationships within cation transporter families of  Arabidopsis   The role of cyclic nucleotide-gated ion channels in plant immunity  A multicolored set of  in vivo  organelle markers for co-localization studies in  Arabidopsis  and other plants  An extended AE-rich N-terminal trunk in secreted pineapple cystatin enhances inhibition of fruit bromelain and is post-translationally removed during ripening  Identification of prokaryotic and eukaryotic signal peptides and prediction of their cleavage sites  Identification of the protein storage vacuole and protein targeting to the vacuole in leaf cells of three plant species  A complex and mobile structure forms a distinct subregion within the continuous vacuolar membrane in young cotyledons of  Arabidopsis   The occurrence of ‘bulbs’, a complex configuration of the vacuolar membrane, is affected by mutations of vacuolar SNARE and phospholipase in  Arabidopsis   Physiological roles of cyclic nucleotide gated channels in plants  Expression of a truncated tobacco  NtCBP4  channel in transgenic plants and disruption of the homologous  Arabidopsis CNGC1  gene confer Pb 2+  tolerance  CNGCs: prime targets of plant cyclic nucleotide signalling  The chimeric cyclic nucleotide-gated ion channel ATCNGC11/12 constitutively induces programmed cell death in a Ca 2+  dependent manner  Plastid proteomics in higher plants: current state and future goals  Second messengers mediate increases in cytosolic calcium in tobacco protoplasts  The chimeric  Arabidopsis  cyclic nucleotide-gated ion channel 11/12 activates multiple pathogen resistance responses  Gene-for-gene disease resistance without the hypersensitive response in  Arabidopsis dnd1  mutant  The role of cyclic nucleotide-gated channels in cation nutrition and abiotic stress  Protein storage vacuoles are transformed into lytic vacuoles in root meristematic cells of germinating seedlings by multiple, cell type-specific mechanisms  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  The cyclic nucleotide-gated channels, CNGC19 and CNGC20, are the sole members of the highly isolated evolutionary group IV-A in Arabidopsis plants. Prior studies have shown that the expression of both CNGC19 and CNGC20 genes are induced by salinity and biotic stress. In this report, CNGC19 and CNGC20 were determined to localize to the vacuolar membrane. Co-expression of CNGC19 and CNGC20 increased the efficiency of vacuolar localization. CNGC19 and CNGC20 are, therefore, vacuolar membrane channels that are hypothesized to mediate plant response to salinity and biotic stress.  Plant cyclic nucleotide-gated channels (CNGCs) are implicated in the uptake of both essential and toxic cations, Ca 2+  signalling, and responses to biotic and abiotic stress. The 20 CNGC paralogues of  Arabidopsis  are divided into five evolutionary groups. Group IV-A is highly isolated and consists only of two closely spaced genes,  CNGC19  and  CNGC20 . Prior studies have shown that both genes are induced by salinity and biotic stress. A unique feature of CNGC19 and CNGC20 is their long hydrophilic N-termini. To determine the subcellular locations of CNGC19 and CNGC20, partial and full-length fusions to GFP(S65T) were generated. Translational fusions of the N-termini of CNGC19 (residues 1–171) and CNGC20 (residues 1–200) to GFP(S65T) were targeted to punctate structures when transiently expressed in leaf protoplasts. In the case of CNGC20, but not CNGC19, the punctate structures were co-labelled with a marker for the Golgi. The full-length CNGC19-GFP fusion co-localized with markers for the vacuole membrane (αTIP- and γTIP-mCherry). Vacuole membrane labelling by the full-length CNGC20-GFP fusion was also observed, but the signal was weak and accompanied by numerous punctate signals that did not co-localize with αTIP- or γTIP-mCherry. These punctate structures diminished, and localization of full-length CNGC20-GFP to the vacuole increased, when it was co-expressed with the full-length CNGC19-mCherry. Vacuole membrane labelling was also detected  in planta  via immunoelectron microscopy using a CNGC20-antiserum on cryopreserved ultrathin sections of roots. We hypothesize that the role of group IV-A CNGCs is to mediate the movement of cations between the central vacuole and the cytosol in response to certain types of abiotic and biotic stress.  Plants have evolved several distinct classes of transporters and channels to facilitate the movement of cations across cellular membranes ( Mäser  et al.  2001 ). The members of the plant cyclic nucleotide-gated channel (CNGC) family are evolutionarily and structurally related to Shaker-type K +  channels, but are typically permeable to a range of monovalent cations ( Leng  et al.  2002 ;  Balagué  et al.  2003 ;  Hua  et al.  2003 ;  Gobert  et al.  2006 ;  Christopher  et al.  2007 ). Several CNGCs have also been shown to translocate divalent cations such as Ca 2+  and Mg 2+  ( Leng  et al.  1999 ;  Ali  et al.  2006 ;  Frietsch  et al.  2007 ;  Urquhart  et al.  2007 ;  Guo  et al.  2010 ), and there is a growing body of evidence that the molecular function of some CNGCs is to mediate Ca 2+  signalling ( Talke  et al.  2003 ;  Ma  et al.  2009 ). Cyclic nucleotide-gated channels are oppositely regulated by two distinct second messengers, cyclic nucleotides and Ca 2+ /calmodulin, through partially overlapping ligand-binding domains located near the C-terminus ( Leng  et al.  1999 ,  2002 ;  Arazi  et al.  2000 ;  Köhler and Neuhaus 2000 ;  Balagué  et al.  2003 ;  Li  et al.  2005 ;  Yoshioka  et al.  2006 ). In general, cyclic nucleotides activate CNGCs, whereas Ca 2+ /calmodulin inhibit them. The phenotypic characterization of  cngc  mutants and antisense lines implicates members of this channel family in the uptake and distribution of monovalent and divalent cations ( Sunkar  et al.  2000 ;  Li  et al.  2005 ;  Gobert  et al.  2006 ;  Ma  et al.  2006 ;  Christopher  et al.  2007 ;  Guo  et al.  2008 ,  2010 ;  Yuen and Christopher 2010 ), plant defence responses ( Yu  et al.  1998 ;  Clough  et al.  2000 ;  Balagué  et al.  2003 ;  Yoshioka  et al.  2006 ;  Moeder  et al.  2011 ), gravitropism ( Ma  et al.  2006 ;  Borsics  et al.  2007 ) and pollen tube elongation ( Chang  et al.  2007 ;  Frietsch  et al.  2007 ).  Plant CNGCs are divided into five phylogenetic subfamilies, designated as groups I, II, III, IV-A and IV-B ( Mäser  et al.  2001 ). Of the 20 CNGCs in  Arabidopsis , only two genes,  CNGC19  and  CNGC20 , constitute group IV-A. These tandem genes are closely spaced on chromosome 3. Whereas  CNGC19  is expressed within the vasculature of roots and leaves,  CNGC20  is expressed in the root cortex, the carpel and sepals of flowers, guard cells and in leaf mesophyll cells proximal to veins ( Kugler  et al.  2009 ). Although salt stress influences the expression of both genes ( Maathuis 2006 ;  Kugler  et al.  2009 ;  Yuen and Christopher 2010 ), knockout mutations in either gene do not result in hypersensitivity to Na + , or altered accumulation of Na +  within plant tissues ( Maathuis 2006 ;  Kugler  et al.  2009 ). Null mutants of  CNGC19  and  CNGC20  exhibit reduced resistance to avirulent pathogen infection, indicating a role for these genes in plant defence responses ( Moeder  et al.  2011 ). Furthermore,  CNGC19  is induced by bacterial infection and the bacterial elicitor, flg22, and T-DNA insertion mutants of  CNGC19  display increased susceptibility to the fungal pathogen,  Botrytis cinerea  ( Moeder  et al.  2011 ).  To understand how individual CNGCs contribute to cation fluxes in plants, it is crucial to define their distribution patterns within cells. In plants, CNGCs are present at both the plasma membrane (PM) and the membrane of vacuoles. The subcellular localization of CNGCs has primarily been accomplished through the use of chimeric fluorescent reporter proteins. Fluorescent protein fusions indicate that at least four of the six CNGCs belonging to group I are targeted to the PM: CNGC3 ( Gobert  et al.  2006 ), CNGC10 ( Christopher  et al.  2007 ) and CNGC11 and CNGC12 ( Baxter  et al.  2008 ). CNGC18, a pollen-specific member of group III, was shown to localize to a region of the PM near the tip of expanding pollen tubes ( Chang  et al.  2007 ;  Frietsch  et al.  2007 ). The group II members, CNGC7 and CNGC8, are also expressed exclusively in pollen, but localize to the tonoplast ( Chang  et al.  2007 ). The subcellular distribution of CNGCs has been studied in a few cases by immunolocalization. Using paralogue-specific antibodies, CNGC5 (group II) was detected at the PM of leaf protoplasts by immunofluorescence microscopy, and CNGC10 was shown by high-resolution immunoelectron microscopy to pass through the secretory pathway and localize to the PM ( Christopher  et al.  2007 ). In contrast, no experimental information is available on the subcellular localizations of CNGC19 or CNGC20. Protein sorting algorithms predict that CNGC20 resides in the chloroplast ( Sherman and Fromm 2009 ). However, no CNGC-related sequences were identified in two comprehensive, experimentally derived datasets of the  Arabidopsis  chloroplast proteome, AT_CHLORO ( Ferro  et al.  2010 ) and the Plastid Proteome DataBase ( van Wijk and Baginsky 2011 ).  In this report, we utilized fluorescent reporter protein fusions and immunolelectron microscopy to determine the subcellular destinations of CNGC19 and CNGC20. We demonstrated that both channels are targeted to vacuolar membranes. Our findings suggest that group IV-A CNGCs mediate plant responses to salinity and pathogen infection by facilitating the movement of cations between the central vacuole and the cytosol.  Subcellular localization predictions for  Arabidopsis  CNGCs were performed using TargetP v1.1 ( Nielsen  et al.  1997 ). Transmembrane domain predictions were performed using TMHMM v1.0 ( Krogh  et al.  2001 ). Genes encoding putative group IV-A CNGCs were identified from the sequenced genomes of  Oryza sativa ,  Populus trichocarpa , and  Physcomitrella patens  by BLASTP searches, with CNGC19 and CNGC20 serving as the query sequences. The poplar homologues, designated here as PtCNGC-IVa1, PtCNGC-IVa2 and PtCNGC-IVa3 (GenBank: EEE95941.1, EEF07751.1 and EEF07752.1, respectively), and the rice homologue OsCNGC-IVa1 (GenBank: BAD16877.1) were obtained using the NCBI BLAST server, while the moss homologue PpCNGC-IVa1 (COSMOSS v1.6: Pp1s204_120V6) was identified by a Phytozome BLAST search. Phylogenetic analysis with all 20 CNGCs from  Arabidopsis  confirmed that these CNGCs belong to group IV-A (data not shown).  All constructs used for protoplast transfection in this study were generated in cloning vector pBluescript KS(+). The generation of pBL(35S :GFP(S65T) ) was described previously ( Cho  et al.  2011 ). The constructs pBL(35S: CNGC19  FL - GFP ) and pBL(35S: CNGC20  FL - GFP ) were created by replacing the  EGFP  coding sequence of plasmid pBL(35S: CNGC10 - EGFP ) ( Christopher  et al.  2007 ) with  GFP ( S65T ), and the  CNGC10  genomic DNA sequence with the full-length genomic DNA sequences of  CNGC19  ( At3g17690 ) or  CNGC20  ( At3g17700 ), respectively. The GFP(S65T) fragment was amplified from plasmid HBT95::sGFP(S65T)-NOS with primers GFP/NdeI (5′-CACCGACTAGT CATATG GTGAGCAAGGGCGAG-3′) and GFP/BstEII (5′-TACAG GGTCACC TTACTTGTACAGCTCGTCCATG-3′).  CNGC19  was amplified from  Arabidopsis thaliana  (ecotype Col-0) genomic DNA using the PCR primer pair CNGC19/NcoI.F (5′-TAAA CCATGG CTCACACTAGGACTTTCACT-3′) and CNGC19/NdeI.R (5′-ATCA CATATG ACGGTTGGAATTGGAGTGAG-3′), while  CNGC20  was amplified using primers CNGC20/NcoI.F (5′-TGGTCAAG CCATGG CTTCCCACAACGA-3′) and CNGC20/NdeI.R (5′-AATAC CATATG AAGGCTATAACTAGACTGAG-3′). The  GFP(S65T)  fragment was cloned between the NdeI and BstEII restriction sites of pBL(35S: CNGC10 - EGFP ), and the CNGC19 and CNGC20 fragments between NcoI and NdeI. It was necessary to ligate the  CNGC20  amplicon sequentially as two separate fragments due to the presence of an internal NdeI site. Green fluorescent protein fusions to the N-terminal regions of CNGC19 and CNGC20 were developed as described above, except that the CNGC19 N1  fragment was obtained using the primer pair CNGC19/NcoI.F and CNGC19(D86)/NdeI.R (5′-TTGAA CATATG ATCATCTTCAGGTGGAAC-3′), CNGC19 N2  using primers CNGC19/NcoI.F and CNGC19(V166)/NdeI.R (5′-GTCCA CATATG AACAAATTTGGAATGAGGA-3′), CNGC20 N1  using primers CNGC20/NcoI.F and CNGC20(E117)NdeI.R (5′-TTCAA CATATG CTCATCCTCTGAGGAGTT-3′) and CNGC20 N2  using primers CNGC20/NcoI.F and CNGC20(V200)/NdeI.R (5′-GTCCA CATATG AACCTCTTTGGCATGAGGA-3′). The fusion construct pBL(35S: CNGC19  FL - mCherry ) was generated by ligation of a PCR fragment containing both the coding sequence for mCherry and the nopaline synthase (nos) 3′ untranslated region (UTR) between the NdeI and SacI sites of pBL(35S: CNGC19  FL - GFP ). This fragment was amplified from plasmid pt-rk ( Nelson  et al.  2007 ), using the primers GFP/NdeI.F and Nos/SacI.R (5′-TAGTT GAGCTC CCGATCTAGTAACATAGA-3).  The constructs used for the transient expression of fluorescent markers for the Golgi [pBL(35S: Man49-mCherry )], peroxisomes [pBL(35S: mCherry- SKL)] and tonoplast [pBL(35S: γTIP-mCherry )] are derivatives of the organelle markers developed by  Nelson  et al.  (2007) . The new plasmids were generated by digesting the binary plasmids G-rk, PX-rk and vac-rk (respectively) with SacI and HindIII, and mobilizing the reporter gene cassettes between the corresponding restriction sites of pBluescript KS(+). The tonoplast marker construct, pBL(35S: αTIP - mCherry ), was generated by amplification of the full-length genomic DNA sequence of  AtαTIP  ( At1g73190 ; also referred to as  AtTIP3;1 ) with primers αTIP/XbaI.F (5′-AAGT TCTAGA TCATAATGGCAACATCAGCTC-3′) and αTIP/BamHI.R (5′-GTTC GGATCC GTAATCTTCAGGGGCCAAG-3′), and subsequent ligation of the PCR product between the SpeI and BamHI sites of pBL(35S: γTIP-mCherry ). The plastid envelope marker pBL(35S: NTT2 - mCherry ) was created in a similar manner, using primers NTT2/SpeI.F (5′-GTGCT ACTAGT GAGATAGAGAGATGGAAGGT-3′) and NTT2/BamHI.R (5′-ATCAT GGATCC AATGCCAGTAGGAGTAGATTTCT-3′) to amplify the genomic DNA sequence of  AtNTT2  ( At1g15500 ).  pBL(35S:NTT2-GFP)  was created by digesting  pBL(35S:NTT2-mCherry)  with KpnI and NcoI, and cloning the 3.1-kb fragment containing the cauliflower mosaic virus (CaMV) 35S promoter and  AtNTT2  genomic DNA sequence between the KpnI and NcoI sites of  pBL(35S:GFP(S65T)) . The construct pBL(35S: BiP1-mCherry -HDEL) contains, in order, the CaMV 35S promoter, the  AtBiP1  ( At5g28540 ) genomic DNA sequence, the coding sequence of mCherry-HDEL and the nos terminator, inserted between the KpnI and SacI sites of pBluescript KS(+). The CaMV 35S promoter region was amplified with primers 35S/KpnI.F (5′-TTCAA GGTACC TTCATGGAGTCAAAGATTCA-3′) and 35S/XhoI.R (5′-ATCTA CTCGAG TCAAGAGTCCCCCGTG-3′), the  AtBiP1  gene sequence was amplified from  A. thaliana  (ecotype Col-0) genomic DNA with primers BiP1/XhoI.F (5′-GAG CTCGAG CGCAAAAGTTTCCGATATGGCTCGCTC-3′) and BiP1/XmaI.R (5′-AGA CCCGGG GAGCTCATCGTGAGACTCATCTTC-3′), and the mCherry-HDEL coding sequence and nos 3′ UTR were amplified from plasmid ER-rk with primers GFP/XmaI.F (5′-AAA CCCGGG CTTGTACAGCTCGTCCATGC-3′) and Nos/SacI.R.  Protoplasts were isolated from 3- to 4-week-old  Arabidopsis  leaves and transfected with plasmid DNA using the protocol described by  He  et al . (2006) . For standard transfections involving only one reporter construct, 20 μL of ∼1 μg μL −1  plasmid DNA were added per 200 μL of protoplasts suspended in MMg solution (0.4 M mannitol, 15 mM MgCl 2 , 4 mM MES, pH 5.7). In cases where protoplasts were simultaneously co-transfected with two reporter constructs, a 20-μL mixture containing ∼10 μg of each plasmid was utilized. After transfection, the protoplasts were incubated in W5 solution (154 nM NaCl, 125 mM CaCl 2 , 5 mM KCl, 2 mM MES, pH 5.7). Samples were analysed 18+ hours post-transfection with an Olympus FV-1000 laser scanning confocal microscope. For mitochondria staining, the protoplasts were incubated in W5 solution containing 0.5 µM MitoTracker Orange CMTMRos (Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, USA) 30 min prior to analysis. The excitation/emission filters utilized for fluorescence detection were 488/505–525 nm for GFP(S65T), 543/585–615 nm for mCherry and MitoTracker Orange, and 633/650 nm for chlorophyll autofluorescence. Confocal microscopy was performed at the Biological Electron Microscope Facility (University of Hawaii, Manoa, HI, USA).  An affinity-purified rabbit polyclonal antibody was raised against a unique region of CNGC20 (residues 664–678, sequence Ac-CLERSSVNPDGTRIR-amide) by New England Peptide (Gardner, MA, USA). For immunogold labelling, developing roots and leaves were preserved by high-pressure freezing/freeze-substitution techniques as described previously ( Andème Ondzighi  et al.  2008 ). The resin-embedded sections were placed on formvar-coated nickel slot grids and blocked for 30 min with 3 % (w/v) non-fat dried milk solution in 0.01 M phosphate-buffered saline pH 7.2 containing 0.1 % Tween-20 (PBST). The sections were washed in PBST and then incubated with a 10-fold dilution of the CNGC20 primary antiserum or the rabbit pre-immune serum (negative control). After washing, a 25-fold dilution of secondary antibody, goat anti-rabbit IgG conjugated to 15 nm gold particles (Ted Pella, Inc.), was added for 2 h at room temperature. Sections were washed and stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate. All observations were performed using a Philips CM10 microscope (Philips, Hillsboro, OR, USA). The CNGC20 antiserum was tested by immunoblot analysis  [ as shown in   Supporting Information   ]  by the method described in  Neuteboom  et al.  (2009 ).  N-terminal length and predicted subcellular localization of  Arabidopsis  CNGCs. The 20 CNGCs of  Arabidopsis  are arranged by subfamily, with group IV-A orthologues from other plants included for comparison. Deduced N-terminal lengths are based on the predicted positions of the S1 transmembrane segments by TMHMM v1.0. Here, %19Nterm and %20Nterm indicate percentage identity with the N-terminal regions of CNGC19 and CNGC20; the absence of similarity is denoted by ‘not applicable’ (n.a.). Four predictive scores are obtained using TargetP: cTP, chloroplast transit peptide; mTP, mitochondrial targeting peptide; SP, secretory pathway signal peptide; and others. The highest score among the four categories is indicated in italics.  Domain arrangement of CNGC19 and CNGC20. Shaded boxes indicate the positions of the N-terminal 19-aa motif, the six transmembrane segments (S1–S6) of the hydrdophobic core region and the C-terminal overlapping cyclic nucleotide-binding (CNBD) and calmodulin-binding domains (CaMBD). FL corresponds to the full-length versions of CNGC19 and CNGC20, and N1 and N2 represent portions of the N-terminal region utilized in GFP fusion constructs.  Sequence alignment of group IV-A CNGCs from  Arabidopsis , poplar, rice and moss. Three putative members of group IV-A are present in poplar (GenBank: EEE95941.1, EEF07751.1 and EEF07752.1), one in rice (GenBank: BAD16877.1) and one in  P. patens  (COSMOSS v1.6: Pp1s204_120V6). Residues matching the consensus (five or more sequences) are shaded in black, and similar residues are shaded in grey. Amino acids strictly conserved among all sequences are denoted by an asterisk below the alignment. The 19-aa conserved interval (LxxSGxLGxCxDPxCxxCP) and first transmembrane domain (S1) are boxed in red. The indicated position of S1 is based on TMHMM 1.0 predictions for both CNGC19 and CNGC20.  Subcellular localization pattern of GFP fused to N-terminal segments of CNGC19 or CNGC20. Confocal laser scanning microscope images of leaf protoplasts transiently expressing (A) GFP(S65T), (B) CNGC19 N1 -GFP, (C) CNGC20 N1 -GFP, (D) CNGC19 N2 -GFP or (E) CNGC20 N2 -GFP. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, chlorophyll autofluorescence (red); column 3, merged GFP and chlorophyll signals. Scale bars represent 5 µm.  Subcellular localization pattern of GFP fused to full-length CNGC19 or CNGC20. Confocal laser scanning microscope images of leaf protoplasts transiently expressing (A–C) CNGC19 FL -GFP or (D, E) CNGC20 FL -GFP. The arrows indicate contiguous membranes labelled by CNGC19 FL -GFP (C) or CNGC20 FL -GFP (E) that wrap around multiple chloroplasts. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, chlorophyll autofluorescence (red); column 3, merged GFP and chlorophyll signals. Scale bars represent 5 µm.  Comparison of CNGC19 FL - and CNGC20 FL -GFP localization with a marker for the chloroplast envelope. Confocal microscopy images of leaf protoplasts transiently expressing (A) CNGC19 FL -GFP or (B) CNGC20 FL -GFP, co-transfected with the chloroplast envelope marker, NTT2-GFP. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, RFP signal (red); column 3, merged GFP and RFP signals; column 4, merged GFP and RFP signals with chlorophyll autofluorescence (blue). Scale bars represent 5 µm.  Comparison of CNGC19 FL -GFP localization with markers for the tonoplast. Confocal laser scanning microscope images of leaf protoplasts co-transfected with CNGC19 FL -GFP and (A–C) αTIP-mCherry or (D, E) γTIP-mCherry. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, RFP signal (red); column 3, merged GFP and RFP signals; column 4, merged GFP and RFP signals with chlorophyll autofluorescence (blue). Scale bars represent 5 µm.  Comparison of CNGC20 FL -GFP localization with markers for the tonoplast. Confocal laser scanning microscope images of leaf protoplasts co-transfected with CNGC20 FL -GFP and (A, B) αTIP-mCherry or (C) γTIP-mCherry. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, RFP signal (red); column 3, merged GFP and RFP signals; column 4, merged GFP and RFP signals with chlorophyll autofluorescence (blue). Scale bars represent 5 µm.  Simultaneous expression of CNGC19 FL -mCherry and CNGC20 FL -GFP. (A, B) Confocal laser scanning microscope images of leaf protoplasts co-transfected with CNGC19 FL -mCherry and CNGC20 FL -GFP. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, RFP signal (red); column 3, merged GFP and RFP signals; column 4, merged GFP and RFP signals with chlorophyll autofluorescence (blue). Scale bars represent 5 µm.  Comparison of CNGC19 N2 -GFP and CNGC20 N2 -GFP with a marker for Golgi. Confocal laser scanning microscope images of leaf protoplasts co-transfected with the Golgi marker Man49-mCherry and (A) CNGC20 FL -GFP, (B) CNGC19 N2 -GFP or (C) CNGC20 N2 -GFP. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, RFP signal (red); column 3, merged GFP and RFP signals; column 4, merged GFP and RFP signals with chlorophyll autofluorescence (blue). Scale bars represent 5 µm.  The punctate distribution patterns of partial fusion constructs, CNGC19 N2 -GFP and CNGC20 N2 -GFP, were also compared with the Golgi marker. Interestingly, whereas CNGC19 N2 -GFP did not co-localize with Man49-mCherry (Fig.  9 B), CNGC20 N2 -GFP fluorescence overlapped with the Golgi marker (Fig.  9 C). Not all of the punctate structures labelled by the Golgi marker were co-labelled by CNGC20 N2 -GFP (Fig.  9 C), possibly indicating that CNGC20 N2 -GFP is only targeted to, or accumulates within, a subset of Golgi.  Detection of CNGC20 at vacuolar membranes by immunoelectron microscopy. (A, D) Transverse ultrathin sections of  Arabidopsis  root tips were labelled with anti-AtCNGC20 antiserum and then examined by TEM. (B, C) Higher magnification of the boxed regions in (A). cy, cytoplasm; er, endoplasmic reticulum; v, vacuole; tp, tonoplast. A 15 nm gold–anti-rabbit secondary antibody is used in all labelling.  In  Arabidopsis , the CNGC phylogenetic tree consists of 20 members, of which CNGC19 and CNGC20 are the sole members of subgroup IV-A. They are distinguished among CNGCs by their long and novel conserved N-termini, yet retain key features common to all CNGCs such as the overlapping cyclic nucleotide- and calmodulin-binding domains of the C-terminus, six predicted membrane spanning domains and a close resemblance to Shaker-type K +  channels. To better understand the roles that CNGC19 and CNGC20 play in regulating cation fluxes in plants, we investigated their subcellular locations using the leaf mesophyll protoplast transient expression system. Although the conserved hydrophilic N-termini of CNGC19 and CNGC20 are predicted to contain chloroplast transit peptides, translational fusions of GFP with CNGC19 or CNGC20 did not localize to chloroplasts. We instead found that CNGC19 FL -GFP and CNGC20 FL -GFP co-localized with markers for the vacuole membrane (αTIP-mCherry; γTIP-mCherry) when simultaneously expressed in protoplasts.  Under our experimental conditions, αTIP- and γTIP-mCherry typically did not appear to label the limiting membrane of the large central vacuole. This is consistent with previous studies showing that epitope-tagged or fluorescent protein-tagged versions of αTIP, δTIP and γTIP strongly label relatively small elliptical structures when transiently expressed in protoplasts or cultured cells ( Park  et al.  2004 ;  Kim  et al.  2006 ;  Saito  et al.  2011 ). These structures may represent either small vacuoles or ring-like extensions of the central vacuole membrane that are referred to as vacuole ‘bulbs’. Vacuolar bulbs were first identified in  Arabidopsis  transgenic plants stably expressing γTIP-GFP under the CaMV 35S promoter ( Saito  et al.  2002 ). The intensity of γTIP-GFP fluorescence in bulbs is ∼3-fold higher than that in the limiting membrane of the central vacuole ( Saito  et al.  2002 ), and their formation is correlated with the fusion of small vacuoles ( Saito  et al.  2011 ). It is speculated that vacuolar bulbs may serve as a reservoir of membranes to facilitate the rapid expansion or transformation of vacuoles or plant response to salt stress ( Saito  et al . 2002 ;  Boursiac  et al.  2005 ), or as specialized subregions of the vacuole where hydrolytic activities are localized ( Saito  et al.  2002 ;  Zheng and Staehelin 2011 ). In addition to labelling bulb-like structures, CNGC19 FL -GFP and CNGC20 FL -GFP occasionally co-localized with short, non-elliptical membranes of intense vacuole marker fluorescence. We hypothesize that these co-labelled membranes correspond to regions of the tonoplast where vacuole bulbs were unfolded to expand the limiting membrane of the central vacuole.  Protoplasts expressing CNGC20 FL -GFP frequently exhibited punctate GFP fluorescence that partially co-localized with the Golgi marker Man49-mCherry. Thus, CNGC20 FL -GFP may have a lower efficiency in trafficking to the vacuole than CNGC19 FL -GFP under our experimental conditions, resulting in the accumulation of CNGC20 FL -GFP in Golgi and possibly other undefined punctate subcellular structures. We observed a decrease in punctate labelling when CNGC20 N2 -GFP was co-expressed with CNGC19 FL -mCherry, with 70–80 % more of the cells exhibiting some vacuolar labelling, possibly indicating an increased efficiency in CNGC20 FL -GFP trafficking to the vacuolar membrane in the presence of co-expressed CNGC19 FL -mCherry. Since plant CNGC polypeptides most likely assemble as tetramers to form functional cation channels ( Hua  et al.  2003 ), we speculate that the simultaneous expression of CNGC19 FL -mCherry and CNGC20 FL -GFP causes the chimeric proteins interacting with each other to form CNGC19/CNGC20 hetero-multimers, which are transported together to the vacuole membrane.  Protoplasts expressing GFP fused to the entire hydrophilic N-terminal region of CNGC19 or CNGC20 (CNGC19 N2 -GFP; CNGC20 N2 -GFP) do not display diffuse cytosolic labelling, but instead exhibit punctate labelling. This suggests that the N-terminal regions of CNGC19 and CNGC20 contain information that influences protein sorting, but are not sufficient to direct proteins to the vacuole. Interestingly, the N-terminal regions of group IV-A CNGCs contain a novel 19-aa conserved motif (LxxSGxLGxCxDPxCxxCP). Since GFP fusions harbouring shortened versions of the N-terminal region truncated just prior to this motif (CNGC19 N1 -GFP; CNGC20 N1 -GFP) exhibit diffuse labelling of the cytosol, we speculate that the 19-aa interval may play a role in protein sorting. Interestingly, in protoplast co-transfection experiments, the Golgi marker Man49-mCherry co-localized with CNGC20 N2 -GFP, but not with CNGC19 N2 -GFP. This suggests that differences exist between the protein sorting information contained within the N-terminal hydrophilic regions of CNGC19 and CNGC20. These differences may contribute, at least in part, to the dissimilar localization patterns of our full-length CNGC19 FL -GFP and CNGC20 FL -GFP fusions with regard to the absence or presence of punctate labelling (respectively).  The presence of CNGC19 and CNGC20 at vacuolar membranes suggests that these channels serve as pathways for the passive transport of cations between the vacuole and cytosol. Since the genes encoding CNGC19 and CNGC20 are upregulated by salt stress ( Maathuis, 2006 ;  Kugler  et al.  2009 ;  Yuen and Christopher 2010 ), one possible function of these channel proteins is to ameliorate the effects of deleterious levels of Na +  in the cytosol by facilitating Na +  redistribution between the cytosol and vacuole. It is unlikely, however, that CNGC19 and CNGC20 play a direct role in the sequestration of Na +  to the central vacuole since Na +  must be actively transported against its electrochemical gradient, a function performed by vacuolar Na + /H +  (NHX) antiporters ( Apse  et al.  1999 ,  2003 ). An alternative possibility is that CNGC19 and CNGC20 facilitate the plant's response to salinity by mediating Ca 2+  signalling. Salt stress induces a rapid rise in cGMP levels, and a transient increase in free cytosolic [Ca 2+ ]; at moderate salt concentrations (50 mM), suppressing cGMP accumulation with an inhibitor of guanylyl cyclases also diminishes the Ca 2+  spike ( Donaldson  et al.  2004 ). Cyclic nucleotide-gated channels, which are activated by cyclic nucleotides ( Li  et al.  2005 ), could function as a link between cGMP accumulation and the influx of Ca 2+  into the cytosol ( Donaldson  et al.  2004 ). The potential involvement of vacuolar CNGCs in Ca 2+  signalling is circumstantially supported by experiments in tobacco protoplasts that have demonstrated that cAMP and cGMP can trigger the influx of Ca 2+  to the cytosol from both intracellular and extracellular Ca 2+  stores ( Volotovski  et al.  1998 ). In addition to being upregulated by salt stress,  CNGC19  and  CNGC20  have been implicated in the  Arabidopsis  response to infection by bacterial and fungal pathogens ( Moeder  et al.  2011 ). If CNGC19 and CNGC20 are indeed Ca 2+  channels, they may serve a similar molecular function in the response to both abiotic and biotic stress by mediating calcium signalling through the release of vacuolar Ca 2+  into the cytosol.  CNGC19 and CNGC20 are components of vacuole membranes. Under the protoplast transient expression system, CNGC20 is weakly trafficked to the vacuole.  However, co-expression of CNGC19 and CNGC20 results in efficient transport of CNGC20 to the vacuolar membrane, possibly due to the formation of heteromultimeric channels. How CNGC19 and CNGC20 influence cation fluxes within plant cells in response to salt stress and biotic stress remains unclear. Future experiments defining the permeability of these channels to various cations will clarify whether CNGC19 and CNGC20 are directly involved in the subcellular redistribution of Na +  or function as mediators of Ca 2+  signalling.  This research was supported by a  Hatch project award  ( HAW00507-H ) and the  Advances in Biosciences Education programme  funded by the  National Science Foundation  (grant no.  MCB-09-58107 ).  D.A.C. conceived the project, and D.A.C. and C.C.Y.Y. designed the protoplast transient expression experiments and developed all the new fusion constructs utilized in this study. D.A.C. performed all the immunoelectron microscopy experiments. C.C.Y.Y. conducted protoplast transfections and analysed the samples through confocal microscopy. D.A.C. and C.C.Y.Y. wrote the manuscript, and read and approved the final version for submission.  None declared.   The following Supporting Information is available in the online version of this article.    File 1 : Figure. Comparison of CNGC19 FL - and CNGC20 FL -GFP localization with a marker for the ER. Confocal laser scanning microscope images of leaf protoplasts co-transfected with the ER marker BiP1-mCherry-HDEL and (A) CNGC19 FL -GFP or (B) CNGC20 FL -GFP. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, RFP signal (red); column 3, merged GFP and RFP signals; column 4, merged GFP and RFP signals with chlorophyll autofluorescence (blue). Scale bars represent 5 µm.   File 2 : Figure. Comparison of CNGC19 FL - and CNGC20 FL -GFP localization with a marker for mitochondria. Confocal microscopy images of leaf protoplasts transiently expressing (A) CNGC19 FL -GFP or (B) CNGC20 FL -GFP, and stained with MitoTracker Orange. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, MitoTracker Orange signal (red); column 3, merged GFP and MitoTracker Orange signals; column 4, merged GFP and MitoTracker Orange signals with chlorophyll autofluorescence (blue). Scale bars represent 5 µm.   File 3 : Figure. Comparison of CNGC19 N2 - and CNGC20 N2 -GFP localization with a marker for peroxisomes. Confocal laser scanning microscope images of leaf protoplasts co-transfected with the peroxisome marker mCherry-SKL and (A) CNGC19 N2 -GFP or (B) CNGC20 N2 -GFP. Column 1, GFP signal (green); column 2, RFP signal (red); column 3, merged GFP and RFP signals; column 4, merged GFP and RFP signals with chlorophyll autofluorescence (blue). Scale bars represent 5 µm.   File 4 : Figure. Pre-immune serum staining of roots. Immunolabelling of  Arabidopsis  cryo-fixed thin root tissue sections with rabbit pre-immmune serum and anti-rabbit 15 nm gold-conjugated secondary antiserum as a negative control. Samples were viewed via TEM as described in the Methods. No labelling was observed. G, Golgi apparatus, Cy, cytoplasm; Vc, vacuole; ER, rough endoplasmic reticulum; Pm, plasma membrane; M, mitochondrion.   File 5 : Figure. Immunolabelling of leaves. Immunolabelling of  Arabidopsis  cryo-fixed thin leaf tissue sections with anti-CNGC20 antiserum and anti-rabbit 15 nm gold-conjugated secondary antiserum. Samples were viewed via TEM as described in the Methods. No labelling was observed in the chloroplasts (CT); some labelling was observed in the edges of vacuoles (V).   File 6 : Figure. Immunoblot analysis of CNGC20 in  Arabidopsis  total cellular proteins. Immunoblot analysis was performed using the anti-CNGC20-specific peptide antiserum on 40 μg of total seedling proteins (14-day-old) from wild type (WT) and the CNGC20 T-DNA mutant (MUT). The homozygous T-DNA insert (SALK_129133.22.05) is in the fourth exon of the CNGC20 locus (At3g17700). The antiserum detects a single band of ∼84 kDa in the wild-type protein sample, which is the predicted size of CNGC20, whereas no CNGC20 protein is detected in the mutant. This indicates that the antiserum is specific to CNGC20. Coomassie-stained proteins (COOM) are shown from a duplicate gel. 