Photosynthetic capacity is negatively correlated with the concentration of leaf phenolic compounds across a range of different speciesSecondary metabolites in plant defence mechanismsResource availability hypothesis of plant antiherbivore defenses tested in a South African savannah ecosystemInternal filters: prospects for UV-acclimation in higher plantsThe ecology of leaf life spansRethinking the role of many plant phenolics—protection from photodamage not herbivores?Intra-specific variation in herbivory on two tropical tree speciesEffects of plant growth rate and leaf lifetime on the amount and type of anti-herbivore defenseResource availability and plant antiherbivore defenseGlobal patterns of foliar nitrogen isotopes and their relationships with climate, mycorrhizal fungi, foliar nutrient concentrations, and nitrogen availabilityThe plant traits that drive ecosystems: evidence from three continentsThe Resource Availability Hypothesis revisited: a meta-analysisPhotosynthesis and nitrogen relationships in leaves of C<sub>3</sub> plantsThe photosynthesis–nitrogen relationship in wild plantsBenefits of plant diversity to ecosystems: immediate, filter and founder effectsCosts of defense and their effects on plant productivityGeneral procedures and measurement of total phenolicsFlavonoid antioxidants: chemistry, metabolism and structure–activity relationshipsThe dilemma of plants: to grow or defendMechanisms underlying interspecific variation in photosynthetic capacity across wild plant speciesCoordination between leaf and stem traits related to leaf carbon gain and hydraulics across 32 drought-tolerant angiospermsAntioxidant defence responses: physiological plasticity in higher plants under abiotic constraintsTRY – a global database of plant traitsInherent variation in growth rate between higher plants: a search for physiological causes and ecological consequencesThe role of flavonol glycosides and carotenoids in protecting soyabean from ultraviolet-B damageCarbon and nitrogen economy of 24 wild species differing in relative growth rateCauses and consequences of variation in leaf mass per area (LMA): a meta-analysisLeaf lifespan in relation to leaf, plant and stand characteristic among diverse ecosystemsFrom tropics to tundra: global convergence in plant functioningStructure–antioxidant activity relationships of flavonoids and phenolic acidsSeduced by the dark side: interacting molecular and ecological respectives on the influence of light on plant defence against pests and pathogensPlant phenolic antioxidant and prooxidant activities: phenolics-induced oxidative damage mediated by metals in plantsδ<sup>15</sup>N values of tropical savanna and monsoon forest species reflect root specializations and soil nitrogen statusFundamental trade-offs generating the worldwide leaf economics spectrumLand-plant ecology on the basis of functional traitsLeaf specific mass confounds leaf density and thicknessConvergence towards higher leaf mass per area in dry and nutrient-poor habitats has different consequences for leaf life spanThe worldwide leaf economics spectrumThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.This study reveals a negative relationship between leaf phenolic compounds and photosynthetic A<sub>max</sub> among different plant species. This indicates a functional integration among carbon gain and the concentration of leaf phenolic compounds that reflects the trade-off between growth and defence/protection demands.Phenolic compounds are the most commonly studied of all secondary metabolites because of their significant protective–defensive roles and their significant concentration in plant tissues. However, there has been little study on relationships between gas exchange parameters and the concentration of leaf phenolic compounds (total phenolics (TP) and condensed tannins (CT)) across a range of species. Therefore, we addressed the question: is there any correlation between photosynthetic capacity (<italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>) and TP and CT across species from different ecosystems in different continents?A plethora of functional and structural parameters were measured in 49 plant species following different growth strategies from five sampling sites located in Greece and Australia. The relationships between several leaf traits were analysed by means of regression and principal component analysis.The results revealed a negative relationship between TP and CT and <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> among the different plant species, growth strategies and sampling sites, irrespective of expression (with respect to mass, area or nitrogen content). Principal component analysis showed that high concentrations of TP and CT are associated with thick, dense leaves with low nitrogen. This leaf type is characterized by low growth, <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> and transpiration rates, and is common in environments with low water and nutrient availability, high temperatures and high light intensities. Therefore, the high TP and CT in such leaves are compatible with the protective and defensive functions ascribed to them.Our results indicate a functional integration between carbon gain and the concentration of leaf phenolic compounds that reflects the trade-off between growth and defence/protection demands, depending on the growth strategy adopted by each species.Data for various leaf traits encompassing many species are important in order to understand the different plant strategies and the adaptation of each species in a particular environment. The correlations between leaf traits provide insights into the selective pressures that have shaped the evolution of vegetation, and can help with the calibration of models predicting vegetation and productivity dynamics with respect to climate and land-use change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C30">Reich <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C40">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C35">Shipley <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C37">Westoby and Wright 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C22">Kattge <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).A great variation in photosynthetic capacity (<italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>) is evident both within and between species. Within-species variation in <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> has been ascribed to variations in leaf nitrogen concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C13">Field and Mooney 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C12">Evans 1989</xref>), due to the large fraction of leaf nitrogen that is invested in the photosynthetic apparatus. This is the reason that generally a strong positive correlation between <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> and leaf nitrogen concentration within species has been observed. Between-species variation in <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> occurs even among C<sub>3</sub> species, although they share the same photosynthetic metabolism. A global survey dealing with 1 % of vascular plant species on Earth revealed that <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> varied by 120- and 40-fold when expressed on a dry mass and a leaf area basis, respectively (Glopnet; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C40">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Such a large variation is believed to be related to the growth strategy and/or the niche of a specific species. Regarding growth strategies, higher <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> is found in fast-growing species and in species with a shorter leaf lifespan than in slow-growing ones and species with a long lifespan. Regarding niches, higher <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> is found in sun than in shade species, and in early successional than in late successional species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C4">Chabot and Hicks 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C15">Gulmon and Mooney 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C27">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C23">Lambers and Poorter 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C29">Reich <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C30">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C40">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C19">Hikosaka 2010</xref>). The magnitude of <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> of a species is associated with other functional and structural characteristics of the leaves. Therefore, strong relationships between <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> and other key leaf parameters among species are observed globally. For example, net photosynthetic capacity with respect to mass (<italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub>) is positively correlated with nitrogen content with respect to mass (<italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub>) and negatively correlated with leaf mass per area (LMA). Probably, these relationships are a consequence of the growth strategy of each species, e.g. rapid- versus slow-growing species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C8">Coley <italic>et al.</italic> 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C7">Coley 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C23">Lambers and Poorter 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C29">Reich <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>).Phenolic compounds are the most commonly studied of all secondary metabolites because of their significant concentration and their significant roles in plant tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C36">Waterman and Mole 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C16">Harborne 1997</xref>). The term ‘phenolic’ is used to define substances that possess one or more hydroxyl (OH) substituents bonded onto an aromatic ring. This highly diverse group of secondary metabolites includes mainly simple phenols, lignans, coumarins, flavonoids, tannins and quinines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C36">Waterman and Mole 1994</xref>). These compounds fulfil at least three functions: (i) as defensive compounds—they inhibit the activity of herbivores or pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C1">Bennett and Wallsgrove 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C32">Roberts and Paul 2006</xref>); (ii) as sun-screens—they reduce UV and visible-light penetration to sensitive tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C3">Caldwell <italic>et al.</italic> 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C25">Middleton and Teramura 1993</xref>); and (iii) as antioxidants—they are involved in reducing damage by reactive oxygen species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C31">Rice-Evans <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C5">Close and McArthur 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C17">Heim <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C33">Sakihama <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C21">Jaleel <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The biosynthesis of phenolic compounds requires energy, carbon skeletons and investment of additional nutrients such as nitrogen, which are diverted from primary metabolism. Therefore, allocation of photosynthetic products and nutrients must be balanced between normal growth processes and defense/protection demands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C18">Herms and Mattson 1992</xref>).Since there have been relatively few studies of the associations between photosynthesis and the concentration of total phenolic (TP) compounds and condensed tannins (CT) across species (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C22">Kattge <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), it would be interesting to examine whether there is any correlation between <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> (and probably other gas exchange parameters) and TP and CT among species. In order to test such a general concept it is important to include common plant species thriving in different climate zones and ecosystems. In the present study, we tested this hypothesis using 49 common plant species of different life forms from different sampling sites located in the east Mediterranean basin (Greece) and Australia.Study site coordinates and climatic data.Studied plant species (per year and study site). The life form of the species is also presented.For each species, sampling and measurements were conducted on three adult individuals and two fully expanded, current growth season's leaves per individual. All three individuals were within an area of 100-m radius and had a similar age with leaves accessible for <italic>in planta</italic> measurements (regarding the limitations of the instruments). Measurements were conducted on fully expanded and sun-morphotype leaves: south-east facing (in the Northern Hemisphere) and north-east facing (in the Southern Hemisphere). There were no indications of temporary shading during their expansion. Leaves with obvious symptoms of herbivore or pathogen attack and senescent leaves of the previous growth period were excluded. Laboratory measurements were conducted on the same six leaves that were used for gas exchange measurements. The leaves were collected after measurements of gas exchange had been completed (see below), wrapped in sealed plastic bags and immediately transported to the laboratory in a portable coolbox.For calculation of the LMA (g m<sup>−2</sup>), leaves were oven-dried at 70 °C for 48 h. Leaf lamina area was determined from photographs of the leaves by image analysis using Image-Pro Plus (version 3.01, Media Cybernetics, Silver Spring, MD, USA). Image spatial calibration was ensured by the incorporation of a ruler and samples were photographed from a position perpendicular to the sample plane to avoid geometric distortion of the images. Leaf mass per area was estimated as the ratio of leaf dry mass to leaf area (g m<sup>−2</sup>). For total leaf thickness (LT) measurements, hand-cut cross-sections were made on fresh leaves (replicates as above) of all samples. Leaf density (LD; g cm<sup>−3</sup>) was calculated according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C38">Witkowski and Lamont (1991)</xref> as the ratio between LMA and LT.Measurements of gas exchange were conducted between 0900 and 0012 h. Gas exchange parameters were: photosynthetic capacity (<italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>), transpiration (<italic>E</italic>) and stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) were measured in two leaves per individual; three individuals (six samples) using a portable photosynthesis system LI-6400 (Li-Cor Inc., Lincoln, NE, USA). <italic>A</italic><sub>max,a</sub> was measured at ambient CO<sub>2</sub> atmospheric concentration under saturating photosynthetic photon flux density (∼1850 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> PPFD). Leaves were acclimated to the saturating light intensity until rates of <italic>A</italic><sub>max,a</sub> stabilized. <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> was calculated as the ratio of <italic>A</italic><sub>max,a</sub> to LMA. <italic>E</italic> was also expressed with respect to mass (<italic>E</italic><sub>m</sub>).After weighing, dried plant material of two leaves per individual for three individuals (six samples) was ground to a fine powder with a ball mill. Nitrogen and carbon concentrations were determined by Dumas combustion. Aliquots of 50 mg of the finely ground foliage samples were combusted to N<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> in the presence of O<sub>2</sub>, and quantified by means of thermo-conductivity (LECO CHN2000, St Joseph, MI, USA).The total nitrogen concentration of samples from Greek species was measured by the micro-Kjeldahl digestion method, properly modified for accurate measurements of small amounts of leaf samples and analysed colorimetrically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C26">Mills and Jones 1996</xref>).To assess the variability due to analysis with two different methods, comparisons were made between selected samples from Greece and Australia. The difference between the two analytical methods was constant (∼1.5 %) and thus values were adjusted accordingly. Total nitrogen concentration was expressed per total leaf area (<italic>N</italic><sub>a</sub>) and per dry mass (<italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub>).Total phenolic compounds were measured in two leaves per individual for three individuals (six samples) according to the Folin–Ciocalteu method as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C36">Waterman and Mole (1994)</xref>. Tannic acid (Sigma, USA) was used for a reference curve. Although the reagent also reacts with substances other than phenolic compounds, we used this method because it is recommended for corresponding field studies, it is the most popular and therefore, the results are comparable to the majority of studies (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C41">Harborne 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C36">Waterman and Mole 1994</xref>). Condensed tannins were determined according to the proanthocyanidin method as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C36">Waterman and Mole (1994)</xref>. Delphinidin (Extrasynthese S.A., Genay, France) was used for the reference curve. The concentrations of TP compounds, CT and their sum (TP + CT) were expressed per total leaf area, per dry mass and per nitrogen content (TP<sub>N</sub>, CT<sub>N</sub>).where <italic>X</italic> is the δ<sup>13</sup>C or δ<sup>15</sup>N value and <italic>R</italic> = <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>12</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N/δ<sup>14</sup>N, respectively.The isotopic analyses were performed in the Stable Isotope Unit of the Institute of Materials Science (NCSR Demokritos), accredited according to EN ISO/IEC 17025:2005. Repeated measurements were made for each of the samples. Analytical precision was 0.1 ‰ for δ<sup>13</sup>C and 0.2 ‰ for δ<sup>15</sup>N values.Abbreviations and units of the eight leaf traits examined.Regression analyses were performed to determine the type of relationship that exists between pairs of defined parameters, the strength of the curve and coefficients of determination (<italic>r</italic>), and the statistical significance of correlation coefficients was recorded. Regression analysis was performed using Statgraphics Plus v. 4, (StatPoint Technologies, Inc., Warrenton, VA, USA) at a 95 % level of significance on the means of six samples per species. Correlations were displayed graphically as scatter graphs using SigmaPlot 11.0 (Systat Software, Inc., San Jose, CA, USA).The principal component analysis (PCA) for eight parameters was conducted with CANOCO (version 7.0.61.0, StatSoft, Inc., Tulsa, USA) after log transformation.Spearman rank correlations for each pair of the eight traits examined.Correlations with coefficient <italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub> &gt; 0.5 are in bold.*<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.<bold>Fit of reciprocal model and regression coefficients</bold>. (A) For net photosynthetic capacity with respect to mass (<italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub>) and concentration of phenolic compounds with respect to mass (TP<sub>m</sub>); <italic>r</italic> = 0.52, at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, (B) for net photosynthetic capacity with respect to mass (<italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub>) and concentration of condensed tannins with respect to mass (CT<sub>m</sub>); <italic>r</italic> = 0.59, at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, (C) for net photosynthetic capacity with respect to mass (<italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub>) and LMA; <italic>r</italic> = 0.57, at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.The matrix of rank correlation and coefficients of determination (<italic>r</italic><sub>s</sub>) among all possible pairings of the eight examined traits (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS025TB4">4</xref>) confirmed some already known positive correlations, such as the ones between <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> and <italic>E</italic>, between <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> and <italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub>, and the negative correlation between <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> and LMA (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS025TB4">4</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS025F1">1</xref>C). The results from the regression analyses showed that the relationship between LMA and <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m,</sub> (<italic>r</italic> = 0.57, at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) was also reciprocal (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS025F1">1</xref>C). Nitrogen isotopic composition (δ<sup>15</sup>N) was negatively correlated with leaf structural traits (LMA, LD) and positively correlated with <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS025TB4">4</xref>).Eigenvector values of eight leaf traits on the first two PCA axes in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS025F2">2</xref>.Values are ranked in the order of absolute magnitude along the first PC. The higher value for each parameter between the two axes is in bold.<bold>Principal component analysis biplot of plant samples (Greece: <italic>n</italic> = 32, Australia: <italic>n</italic> = 17) and eight analysed leaf traits.</bold> The percentage of total variance explained by each PC (first PC: 59 %; second PC: 18.9 %) and eigenvector values of the leaf traits are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS025TB5">Table 5</xref>.Increasing values on the first PC indicated a trend for higher water saving and defensive/protective demands (high LMA, LD, TP<sub>m</sub> and CT<sub>m</sub>). Therefore, Australian plants that have higher LMA values are clearly separated from Greek plants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS025F2">2</xref>).The most important findings of the present study concern the negative correlations between <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> and TP and/or CT, irrespective of expression. Although the two curves <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub>–TP and <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub>–CT are described by the same model, the different strengths of these correlations may indicate a differentiation in the functional roles of TP and CT within plant tissues. The direct relationship between <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub> and TP has not been detected earlier, probably since ecological studies using a large number of species did not include the measurement of phenolic compounds, whereas studies in which TP or CT was measured did not include an efficient number of species or life forms. In a recent study, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C20">Ishida <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> found that leaf TP<sub>N</sub> or CT<sub>N</sub> was positively correlated to LMA and negatively correlated to <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> and <italic>A</italic><sub>max,a</sub>. However, the correlations were weak (<italic>r</italic> &lt; 0.5), probably because all the plants examined were drought tolerant and no herbs were included. Our results confirmed these correlations.The results of the PCA indicate an interaction between growth (parameters associated with C and N gain, such as <italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>, <italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub>, <italic>E</italic> and δ<sup>15</sup>N, which is an indicator of soil N availability; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C34">Schmidt and Stewart 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C9">Craine <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>) and defense/protection demands (parameters associated with mechanical and chemical reinforcement, such as LMA, LD and phenolic compounds), which is in accordance with the hypothesis of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C18">Herms and Mattson (1992)</xref>. Additionally, the implication of growth strategy limitations in the interaction between structure and the concentration of phenolic compounds is also indicated since the analysis showed that high TP and CT are associated with thick, dense leaves with low N. Species with this leaf type are slow growing and are common in environments with low water and nutrient availability, and high temperatures and light intensities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C39">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C40">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C28">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), conditions that may also increase both the risk of photodamage and herbivory, and subsequently justify high TP and CT. This particular leaf type represents an indicator of the growth strategy of each species, and this is of use from the curves between <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> and TP and CT. Indeed, the majority of herbs are positioned on the left part of the curve TP<sub>m</sub><italic>–A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS025F1">1</xref>A). On the other hand, species that are characterized by low <italic>A</italic><sub>max,m</sub> and high TP and CT (mainly evergreen trees and shrubs) are positioned on the right part of the curve. This is in accordance with the alreadyknown trend that fast-growing species (mainly herbs) possess low levels of leafdefensive compounds, including TP, whereas slow-growing species show high levels of TP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C6">Coley 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C7">1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C8">Coley <italic>et al.</italic> 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C2">Bryant <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C18">Herms and Mattson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C11">Endara and Coley 2011</xref>).Our results indicate a functional integration between carbon gain and the concentration of phenolic compounds concentration that reflects the trade-off between growth and defence/protection demands, depending on the growth strategy adopted by each species. Further investigation is needed in terms of sample size and/or meta-analysis in order to obtain a more integrated picture of the relationship between the concentration of phenolic compounds and carbon gain. It would also be interesting to investigate whether this relationship is strengthened in the case of species of the same genus. This remains to be answered in a future study.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/pls025/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">The following additional information is available in the online version of this article:</ext-link><bold>File 1. Table 1.</bold> List of abbreviations for all 20 leaf traits initially examined.<bold>File 2. Table 2.</bold> Spearman rank correlations for each pair of the 20 traits initially examined.This work was conducted within a Greek–Australian bilateral co-operation project, funded by the Greek Ministry of Development, General Secretariat of Research and Technology. Financial support from the Greek Scholarship Foundation to S.S. as a post-graduate student is gratefully acknowledged.The project was conceived and planned by G.K. in collaboration with all co-authors. In Australia, the main experimental part of the study was carried out by M.N.F., G.T., V.L. and M.A.A. In Greece, the main experimental part of the study was carried out by S.S., as part of her PhD thesis, D.N., G.L. and E.D. The final data analysis was done by P.B. G.K. was the supervisor of S.S.The authors thank Dr Tyrron Turnball and Dr Tina Bell for their assistance during field and lab measurements in Australian sites, and Professor Diamantopoulos for the use of CANOCO software.None declared.The complete references with the full list of authors for <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C10">Diaz <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C22">Kattge <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS025C40">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> are as follows:<bold>Diaz S, Hodgson JG, Thompson K, Cabido M, Cornelissen JHC, Jalili A, Montserrat-Martí G, Grime JP, Zarrinkamar F, Asri Y, Band SR, Basconcelo S, Castro-Díez P, Funes G, Hamzehee B, Khoshnevi M, Pérez-Harguindeguy N, Pérez-Rontomé MC, Shirvany FA, Vendramini F, Yazdani S, Abbas-Azimi R, Bogaard A, Boustani S, Charles M, Dehghan M, de Torres-Espuny L, Falczuk V, Guerrero-Campo J, Hynd A, Jones G, Kowsary E, Kazemi-Saeed F, Maestro-Martínez M, Romo-Díez A, Shaw S, Siavash B, Villar-Salvador P, Zak MR. 2004.</bold> The plant traits that drive ecosystems: evidence from three continents. <italic>Journal of Vegetation Science</italic> <bold>15</bold>: 295–304.<bold>Kattge J, Díaz S, Lavorel S, Prentice IC, Leadley P, Bönisch G, Garnier E, Westoby M, Reich PB, Wright IJ, Cornelissen JHC, Violle C, Harrison SP, v. Bodegom PM, Reichstein M, Enquist BJ, Soudzilovskaia NA, Ackerly DD, Anand M, Atkin O, Bahn M, Baker TR, Baldocchi D, Bekker R, Blanco C, Blonder B, Bond WJ, Bradstock R, Bunker DE, Casanoves F, Cavender-Bares J, Chambers JQ, Chapin FS, Chave J, Coomes D, Cornwell WK, Craine JM, Dobrin BH, Duarte L, Durka W, Elser J, Esser G, Estiarte M, Fagan WF, Fang J, Fernández-Méndez F, Fidelis A, Finegan B, Flores O, Ford H, Frank D, Freschet GT, Fyllas NM, Gallagher RV, Green WA, Gutierrez AG, Hickler T, Higgins S, Hodgson JG, Jalili A, Jansen S, Joly C, Kerkhoff AJ, Kirkup D, Kitajima K, Kleyer M, Klotz S, Knops JMH, Kramer K, Kühn I, Kurokawa H, Laughlin D, Lee TD, Leishman M, Lens F, Lenz T, Lewis SL, Lloyd J, Llusia` J, Louault F, Ma S, Mahecha MD, Manning P, Massad T, Medlyn B, Messier J, Moles AT, Müller SC, Nadrowski K, Naeem S, Niinemets Ü, Nöllert S, Nüske A, Ogaya R, Oleksyn J, Onipchenko VG, Onoda Y, Ordoñez J, Overbeck G, Ozinga WA, Patino S, Paula S, Pausas JG, Penuelas J, Phillips OL, Pillar V, Poorter H, Poorter L, Poschlod P, Prinzing A, Proulx R, Rammig A, Reinsch S, Reu B, Sack L, Salgado-Negret B, Sardans J, Shiodera S, Shipley B, Siefert A, Sosinski E, Soussana J-F, Swaine E, Swenson N, Thompson K, Thornton P, Waldram M, Weiher E, White M, White S, Wright SJ, Yguel B, Zaehle S, Zanne AE, Wirth C. 2011.</bold> TRY – a global database of plant traits. <italic>Global Change Biology</italic> <bold>17</bold>: 2905–2935.<bold>Wright IJ, Reich PB, Westoby M, Ackerly DD, Baruch Z, Bongers F, Cavender-Bares J, Chapin FS, Cornelissen JHC, Diemer M, Flexas J, Garnier E, Groom PK, Gulias J, Hikosaka K, Lamont BB, Lee T, Lee W, Lusk C, Midgley JJ, Navas M-L, Niinemets U, Oleksyn J, Osada N, Poorter H, Poot P, Prior L, Pyankov VI, Roumet C, Thomas SC, Tjoelker MG, Veneklaas E, Villar R. 2004.</bold> The worldwide leaf economics spectrum. <italic>Nature</italic> <bold>428</bold>: 821–827.