 Network epidemiology and plant trade networks  Visual analytics decision support environment for epidemic modeling and response evaluation.  2011 IEEE Conference on Visual Analytics Science and Technology (VAST)   Model predictions and evaluation of possible control strategies for the 2009 A/H1N1v influenza pandemic in Italy  Effects of vaccination and population structure on influenza epidemic spread in the presence of two circulating strains  Using network properties to predict disease dynamics on human contact networks  What you see is not what you get: how sampling affects macroscopic features of biological networks  The Paleolithic disease-scape, the hygiene hypothesis, and the second epidemiological transition  Dynamical patterns of cattle trade movements  Human mobility networks, travel restrictions, and the global spread of 2009 H1N1 pandemic  Invasion threshold in structured populations with recurrent mobility patterns  Multiscale mobility networks and the spatial spreading of infectious diseases  When individual behaviour matters: homogeneous and network models in epidemiology  Identifying the community structure of the international-trade multi-network  Measuring contact patterns with wearable sensors: methods, data characteristics and applications to data-driven simulations of infectious diseases  Spatial networks  On spatially explicit models of cholera epidemics  Local structure of directed networks  Bayesian modeling to unmask and predict influenza A/H1N1pdm dynamics in London  Complex networks: structure and dynamics  Influence of contact definitions in assessment of the relative importance of social settings in disease transmission risk  Bridging taxonomic and disciplinary divides in infectious disease  Structure of pathways in ecological networks: relationships between length and number  Global change, global trade, and the next wave of plant invasions  Sudden larch death  The biosecurity threat to the UK and global environment from international trade in plants  Community structure of  Phialocephala fortinii s. lat. in European tree nurseries, and assessment of the potential of the seedlings as dissemination vehicles  The physics of where to go  The hidden geometry of complex, network-driven contagion phenomena  Disease dynamics in a dynamic social network  Small-world topology of UK racing: the potential for rapid spread of infectious agents  Efficient immunization strategies for computer networks and populations  Measuring social networks in British primary schools through scientific engagement  Infectious diseases under the influence of changing environmental factors  Erratic flu vaccination emerges from short-sighted behavior in contact networks  Network models: an underutilized tool in wildlife epidemiology?  From graphs to spatial graphs  Networks and the epidemiology of infectious disease  Social encounter networks: characterizing Great Britain  The world trade network  Structural change in the international horticultural industry: some implications for plant health  The potential spread of highly pathogenic avian influenza virus via dynamic contacts between poultry premises in Great Britain  Topology of the Erasmus student mobility network  Analysis of a vaccine model with cross-immunity: when can two competing infectious strains coexist?  Resilience as a universal criterion of health  Indices, graphs and null models: analyzing bipartite ecological networks  A random walk model for infection on graphs: spread of epidemics rumours with mobile agents  Integrating contact network structure into tuberculosis epidemiology in meerkats in South Africa: implications for control  Introduction to network analysis and its implications for animal disease modelling  Modeling dynamic and network heterogeneities in the spread of sexually transmitted diseases  Uncovering space-independent communities in spatial networks  How disease models in static networks can fail to approximate disease in dynamic networks  Strategies for mitigating an influenza pandemic  Emerging fungal threats to animal, plant and ecosystem health  Excluding access to invasion hubs can contain the spread of an invasive vertebrate  Edge direction and the structure of networks  Shortest paths in probabilistic graphs  Pandemic potential of a strain of influenza A (H1N1): early findings  Modelling the influence of human behaviour on the spread of infectious diseases: a review  Commuting network models: getting the essentials  Mathematical models in the evaluation of health programmes  Information networks for disease: commonalities in human management networks and within-host signalling networks  Internet sales of plants for planting—an increasing trend and threat?  Accuracy of mean-field theory for dynamics on real-world networks  Understanding individual human mobility patterns  Mathematical models of infectious disease transmission  Tools to study trends in community structure: application to fish and livestock trading networks  Evolving graphs: dynamical models, inverse problems and propagation   Hymenoscyphus pseudoalbidus , the causal agent of European ash dieback  International plant trade associated risks: laissez-faire or novel solutions  The changing disease-scape in the third epidemiological transition  Epidemiological risk assessment using linked network and grid based modelling:  Phytophthora ramorum  and  Phytophthora kernoviae  in the UK  A brief history of R 0  and a recipe for its calculation  Rust fungi and global change  Disease in metapopulation models: implications for conservation  Modelling epidemics on networks  Insights from unifying modern approximations to infections on networks  Computational methods for social network analysis  Little Italy: an agent-based approach to the estimation of contact patterns-fitting predicted matrices to serological data  Close encounters in a pediatric ward: measuring face-to-face proximity and mixing patterns with wearable sensors  Optimal networks of nature reserves can be found through eigenvalue perturbation theory of the connectivity matrix  Risk assessment in support of plant health  Modelling disease spread and control in networks: implications for plant sciences  Introductions of non-native plant pathogens into Great Britain, 1970–2004  Global trends in emerging infectious diseases  The complex network of global cargo ship movements  Demographic and behavioural change during epidemics  Untangling the interplay between epidemic spread and transmission network dynamics  Competing epidemics on complex networks  Small but slow world: how network topology and burstiness slow down spreading  Modelling the initial phase of an epidemic using incidence and infection network data: 2009 H1N1 pandemic in Israel as a case study  The implications of network structure for epidemic dynamics  Networks and epidemic models  Individual identity and movement networks for disease metapopulations  A measure of individual role in collective dynamics  Sexual network structure and sexually transmitted disease prevention: a modeling perspective  Integrative invasion science: model systems, multi-site studies, focused meta-analysis and invasion syndromes  Structure and formation of ant transportation networks  Inferring epidemic contact structure from phylogenetic trees  Live plant imports: the major pathway for forest insect and pathogen invasions of the US  A pandemic influenza modeling and visualization tool  Evolution of the international regulation of plant pests and challenges for future plant health  Genetic epidemiology of the Sudden Oak Death pathogen  Phytophthora ramorum  in California  Network structure and the biology of populations  Parasites, people and policy: infectious diseases and the Millennium Development Goals  The changing global context of public health  Human mobility and population heterogeneity in the spread of an epidemic  The role of population heterogeneity and human mobility in the spread of pandemic influenza  Determinants of the spatiotemporal dynamics of the 2009 H1N1 pandemic in Europe: implications for real-time modelling  Predicting epidemics on directed contact networks  Edge-based compartmental modelling for infectious disease spread  Plant disease diagnostic capabilities and networks  Concurrent partnerships and transmission dynamics in networks  Disease spread in small-size directed networks: epidemic threshold, correlation between links to and from nodes, and clustering  Networks in plant epidemiology: from genes to landscapes, countries and continents  SIS along a continuum (SISc) epidemiological modelling and control of diseases on directed trade networks  Social contacts and mixing patterns relevant to the spread of infectious diseases  Network analysis of Italian cattle trade patterns and evaluation of risks for potential disease spread  Evaluation of risk and vulnerability using a disease flow centrality measure in dynamic cattle trade networks  Spread of epidemic disease on networks  The structure and function of complex networks  Modularity and community structure in networks  Why social networks are different from other types of networks  Random graphs with arbitrary degree distributions and their applications  Generating social network data using partially described networks: an example informing avian influenza control in the British poultry industry  Network analysis of cattle and pig movements in Sweden: measures relevant for disease control and risk based surveillance  Shift of percolation thresholds for epidemic spread between static and dynamic small-world networks  An overview of social network analysis  Path lengths, correlations, and centrality in temporal networks  Epidemic spreading in scale-free networks   Phytophthora ramorum —a pathogen linking network epidemiology, landscape pathology and conservation biogeography  Plant health and global change—some implications for landscape management  The number of links to and from the starting node as a predictor of epidemic size in small-size directed networks  Disease spread in small-size directed trade networks: the role of hierarchical categories  Plant health challenges for a sustainable land use and rural economy  Social contact networks and disease eradicability under voluntary vaccination  Biodiversity loss affects global disease ecology  Estimating within-household contact networks from egocentric data  A systematic review to identify areas of enhancements of pandemic simulation models for operational use at provincial and local levels  Cryptic speciation in  Hymenoscyphus albidus   A program to increase the number of family physicians in rural and underserved areas. Impact after 22 years  Coupled information diffusion–pest dynamics models predict delayed benefits of farmer cooperation in pest management programs  Invasive pathogens in plant biosecurity. Case study:  Phytophthora ramorum  Werres  et al. : cause of Sudden Oak Death, ramorum leaf blight and ramorum dieback  Epidemionics. From the host–host interactions to the systematic analysis of the emergent macroscopic dynamics of epidemic networks  Controlling the spread of disease in schools  The dynamics of sexual contact networks: effects on disease spread and control  Dynamics of infectious diseases  Contact network structure explains the changing epidemiology of pertussis  The relevance of social network concepts to sexually transmitted disease control  Stochastic oscillations in models of epidemics on a network of cities  Complex networks and symmetry II: reciprocity and evolution of world trade  Perception of epidemic's related anxiety in the general French population: a cross-sectional study in the Rhône-Alpes region  A high-resolution human contact network for infectious disease transmission  Population history and pathways of spread of the plant pathogen  Phytophthora plurivora   Economic networks: the new challenges  Commercial trade of federally listed threatened and endangered plants in the United States  The impacts of network topology on disease spread  Models of epidemics: how contact characteristics shape the spread of infectious diseases  Influence of the network topology on epidemic spreading  Social networks and health  Limits of predictability in human mobility  Modelling the scaling properties of human mobility  Dynamical and bursty interactions in social networks  High-resolution measurements of face-to-face contact patterns in a primary school  Critical behavior of disease spread on dynamic small-world networks  Comparative effects of avoidance and vaccination in disease spread on a dynamic small-world network  Subnets of scale-free networks are not scale-free: sampling properties of networks  Identifying highly connected counties compensates for resource limitations when evaluating national spread of an invasive pathogen  Biosecurity in the movement of commodities as a component of global food security  Representing the UK's cattle herd as static and dynamic networks  Modelling dynamical processes in complex socio-technical systems  Synchrony, waves, and spatial hierarchies in the spread of influenza  Epidemic threshold in dynamic contact networks  Knowledge sharing: a review and directions for future research  Collective dynamics of ‘small-world’ networks  Social and environmental risk factors in the emergence of infectious diseases  Statistical inference to advance network models in epidemiology  Competition among memes in a world with limited attention  Ecological origins of novel human pathogens  Epidemiological implications of the contact network structure for cattle farms and the 20–80 rule  Complexity in human transportation networks: a comparative analysis of worldwide air transportation and global cargo-ship movements  Disentangling the genetic origins of a plant pathogen during disease spread using an original molecular epidemiology approach  Spatio-temporal analysis of an invasive plant pathogen ( Phytophthora ramorum ) in England and Wales  Exploring critical uncertainties in pathway assessments of human-assisted introductions of alien forest species in Canada  Unravelling transmission trees of infectious diseases by combining genetic and epidemiological data  Relating phylogenetic trees to transmission trees of infectious disease outbreaks  The network structure of knowledge sharing among physicians  Community extraction for social networks  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Epidemic models in complex networks are helping us better understand infectious disease outbreaks. This review focuses on the application of new developments in network epidemiology to the study and management of plant diseases. The main aspects covered are: 1) surveys of social networks, 2) models and data about human mobility, 3) epidemic models in directed and hierarchical networks, 4) studies of dynamic networks, and 5) spatial epidemic simulations integrating network data. Because of the increasing amounts of traded plant commodities and the associated rise in introduced plant pests and pathogens, network theory has a great potential in plant science.  Models of epidemics in complex networks are improving our predictive understanding of infectious disease outbreaks. Nonetheless, applying network theory to plant pathology is still a challenge. This overview summarizes some key developments in network epidemiology that are likely to facilitate its application in the study and management of plant diseases. Recent surveys have provided much-needed datasets on contact patterns and human mobility in social networks, but plant trade networks are still understudied. Human (and plant) mobility levels across the planet are unprecedented—there is thus much potential in the use of network theory by plant health authorities and researchers. Given the directed and hierarchical nature of plant trade networks, there is a need for plant epidemiologists to further develop models based on undirected and homogeneous networks. More realistic plant health scenarios would also be obtained by developing epidemic models in dynamic, rather than static, networks. For plant diseases spread by the horticultural and ornamental trade, there is the challenge of developing spatio-temporal epidemic simulations integrating network data. The use of network theory in plant epidemiology is a promising avenue and could contribute to anticipating and preventing plant health emergencies such as European ash dieback.  A selection of key terms in network epidemiology (see  Newman 2003  and the references in the table for further definitions and details).  Temporal trend in the proportion of epidemiological publications mentioning networks (obtained by dividing the number of papers retrieved each year searching at the same time for the keywords ‘networks’ and ‘epidemic’ by the number of papers retrieved that year with the keyword ‘epidemic’), in Google Scholar and Web of Science (1991–2010, as abstracts are searched in Web of Science starting from 1991 only; some papers published after 2010 may still need to be indexed).  One of the main results of network epidemiological studies is that network structure can have a strong influence on epidemic dynamics ( Morris and Kretzschmar 1995 ;  Christley and French 2003 ;  Shirley and Rushton 2005 ;  Bansal  et al.  2007 ;  Drewe  et al.  2011 ;  Smilkov and Kocarev 2012 ). Depending on the way links connect nodes, various network types can be distinguished (e.g. local, small-world, random and scale-free). Local networks show neighbouring connectivity, small-world networks add some rewiring of local links into long-distance connections, random networks have nodes connected with a certain probability, and scale-free networks are characterized by the presence of hubs (super-connected nodes) ( Watts and Strogatz 1998 ;  Keeling and Eames 2005 ;  May 2006 ;  House 2012 ). The presence of hubs, other things being equal, drastically reduces the epidemic threshold compared with non-scale-free network structures.  A selection of key network theory insights about disease management.  defining contact networks related to epidemics,  assessing the consequences for diseases of modern mobility,  studying disease spread and control in directed, hierarchical networks,  moving from static to dynamic network models, and  developing spatio-temporal network simulations of diseases.  The review concludes by pointing out challenges due to the interdisciplinarity of the field and the need to ensure long-term funding for research and review in the network epidemiology of plant diseases.  Network structures are a key factor in epidemics ( Eames and Keeling 2002 ;  Christensen  et al.  2010 ). Much effort is thus being invested to improve our understanding of real-world contacts between human beings ( Ames  et al.  2011 ;  Potter  et al.  2011 ;  Oliveira and Gama 2012 ). Contacts are interactions between individuals which create a network (Table  1 ). Methods used to gather these data and key challenges in their application in modelling infectious diseases have been reviewed by  Barrat  et al.  (2014) .  For example, a diary-based survey of close interactions of a sample of the human population in different European countries showed a high degree of age assortativity, i.e. the tendency of individuals of a given age range to interact with other individuals of the same age range ( Mossong  et al.  2008 ). Not taking into account age assortativity in epidemic models of pertussis has been shown to lead to misleading policy recommendations ( Rohani  et al.  2010 ). High-resolution contact patterns were recently obtained from a French school using sensing technology over 2 days (with an average of 323 contacts per day per participant;  Stehlé  et al.  2011 ) and from an Italian paediatrics hospital ward during a 1-week period (with a median of 20 contacts per day per participant;  Isella  et al.  2011 ).  Heterogeneities in the number of links are fundamental not just within a population, but also among different population subgroups ( Conlan  et al.  2011 ). Also the duration of a contact matters, for example because an infected individual will not be able to infect a new individual if it keeps staying in contact with those that have already been infected ( Miller  et al.  2012 ). A postal and online survey of the contacts of 5000 citizens in England, Scotland and Wales found high levels of clustering (the extent to which contacts are transitive; Table  1 ), which increased with the frequency and duration of contacts ( Danon  et al.  2013 ). Data on the frequency and duration of individual-to-individual interactions were recorded at scientific conferences, with a tendency for most interactions to be ephemeral ( Zhao  et al.  2011 ). In the European diary-based survey, the majority of daily contacts lasted an hour or more, but this length was reduced to &lt;15 min for the majority of contacts with previously unknown people ( Mossong  et al.  2008 ). This implies that contacts tend to be longer within clusters of human individuals than across them.  It is now accepted that the number of different contacts (the degree of a node) is one of the key indicators of the risk to acquire and further spread a disease ( Salathé  et al.  2010 ), but other network metrics, e.g. repeated exposure, can be just as important ( Iozzi  et al.  2010 ). A major challenge remains in inferring network properties from sampling data obtained from a limited part of contact networks ( Stumpf  et al.  2005 ;  Annibale and Coolen 2011 ;  Nickbakhsh  et al.  2011 ). Variation in sampling effort among studies mapping networks is a source of uncertainty also outside epidemiology, e.g. in anthropology, food web ecology and geography ( Dormann  et al.  2009 ). Different types of contacts (e.g. family, healthcare, sexual, social, travel, virtual contacts) will tend to be associated with different probabilities of disease transmission across these contacts for different types of disease ( Rothenberg and Narramore 1996 ;  Smith and Christakis 2008 ;  Smieszek 2010 ;  Bolton  et al.  2012 ).  Different types of contacts are found in plant trade networks too, if only because of the diversity of traded plant species and types (cut flowers, plants for planting, bare-rooted saplings, ornamental twigs, fruits, etc.) ( Dehnen-Schmutz  et al.  2010 ). Inferring the properties of a whole network when only sampling parts of it is an issue for plant trade networks—just as for human social networks—because of the arbitrariness of social and trade network boundaries, and also due to the general lack of standardized data on plant trade networks. It is likely that contacts among plant traders (e.g. nurseries, garden centres and supermarkets) are more long-lasting than contacts among researchers at a conference, but collaboration of researchers with plant health authorities and traders is needed to prove that this is so.  Plant epidemiologists can only aspire to the data currently gathered on human contact patterns. For reasons of commercial sensitivity, plant trade networks are indeed still poorly characterized. This lack of knowledge on the structure of horticultural and ornamental trade networks makes it difficult to prevent the inadvertent dispersal of plant pathogens and pests together with the traded plant material ( Helfer 2014 ;  Schoebel  et al.  2014 ). Regional and international surveys are needed to achieve reconstructions of the networks of plant shipments among plant nurseries and their customers, as well as the networks of informal plant and seed exchanges among farmers, gardeners or urban dwellers.  To assess how likely each commodity is to spread various plant diseases, we then need to overlap the trade network with interception data, which are already recorded (although not always made publicly available) at international borders. Very helpful from a plant health risk assessment perspective would be the systematic inspection of intercepted consignments, e.g. at EU borders, so as to gather data on the proportion of plant material infested by a particular pest or pathogen. But these would be costly measures and border inspectors are already overwhelmed by the increasing amounts of traded plant material ( van der Graaf and Khoury 2010 ).  Of concern is also the lack of studies on the networks of plants and plant commodities traded on the internet ( Giltrap  et al.  2009 ;  Pautasso  et al.  2012 ;  Shirey  et al.  2013 ). We need to map the presence of heterogeneities in contact numbers among internet plant traders, so as to establish whether super-connected nodes are present and, in that case, targeting control at them, because this approach has been shown, for livestock diseases and vertebrate invasive species, to be more efficient and effective than other control strategies ( Natale  et al.  2009 ;  Florance  et al.  2011 ).  Current human mobility is massive, unprecedented, still increasing and has important consequences for the potential and actual spread of diseases over multiple scales. Not only people, but a range of associated goods, ideas and organisms are moving around the planet along modern transportation and communication networks (see reviews in  Brockmann 2010 ;  Kaluza  et al.  2010 ;  Woolley-Meza  et al.  2011 ;  Fisher  et al.  2012 ).  One of the challenges of including human mobility data in epidemic models is given by the multiple types of human movements. Although regional commuting flows (e.g. train, car, bus and cycling journeys) do not make the planet a small-world (i.e. a network with a low average number of steps between two randomly chosen individuals) on their own, they are about one order of magnitude larger than airline flows. Thus, taking into account regional commuters in epidemic models leads to increased synchronization of epidemics in different parts of the planet ( Balcan  et al.  2009 ). This synchronization may in turn decrease opportunities for health officers, policy makers and the public in regions where a pathogen is still unreported to learn from epidemic developments in regions first hit by that pathogen.  Human mobility data are being obtained from various sources, from consecutive sightings of banknotes to mobile phone records. While banknote sightings have been useful in establishing the predictability of movement patterns on broader scales, mobile phone trajectories operating in space–time provide detailed insights on individual mobility patterns ( González  et al.  2008 ).  A key implication of current human mobility patterns is that epidemics of infectious diseases will spread more rapidly than in previous centuries or decades, other things being equal ( Merler and Ajelli 2010 a  ). However, for many human diseases other things are not equal: hygiene levels have steadily improved, and people's awareness of infectious diseases, their causes and what can be done to prevent and cure them is not what it was in the past ( Smith 2007 ;  Ashenburg 2008 ;  Armelagos 2009 ). At the same time, there are factors other than globalization facilitating the emergence of new diseases. For example, many more people inhabit the planet (and its urbanized areas) than at any time in the past, antibiotic resistance has arisen repeatedly and the climate has started to warm ( McMichael and Beaglehole 2000 ;  May 2007 ;  Jones  et al.  2008 ;  Harper and Armelagos 2010 ;  Conraths and Mettenleiter 2011 ).  Each of these developments has consequences for epidemic development: for example, many pathogens tend to reach urban areas earlier than rural ones ( Weiss and McMichael 2004 ;  Woolhouse and Gaunt 2007 ;  Pongsiri  et al.  2009 ;  Merler and Ajelli 2010 b  ), so that a more urbanized planet will tend to have less time to respond to new epidemics of human diseases. A counteracting factor here is that care tends to be more accessible in urbanized regions compared with rural areas ( Rabinowitz  et al.  1999 ). A key research issue is how the heterogeneity of mobility (and disease management) networks can be influenced in a timely (and long-term) manner to reduce the risk posed by epidemics ( Miller  et al.  2009 ;  Draief and Ganesh 2011 ).  Increasing mobility is a key issue in the network epidemiology of plant diseases, because ideally information about how to handle a new invasive plant pathogen needs to reach farmers and plant health authorities before the pathogen is introduced ( Rebaudo and Dangles 2011 ;  Garrett 2012 ). Often this is not the case. For example, the concurrent emergence of the epidemic of  Phytophthora ramorum  in the west coast of the USA and in Europe took place when both regions lacked epidemiological knowledge on this aggressive, generalist and new plant pathogen ( Brasier and Webber 2010 ;  Pautasso 2013 ;  Redlin  et al.  2014 ).  Plant passporting schemes and their associated trace-forward and trace-back data hold much potential to reconstruct plant mobility patterns, but this potential still waits to be exploited. Also in the case of plant health, molecular advances and international regulations are developing tools to counterbalance the risks posed by globalization, but there is a need to improve the uptake of network approaches by plant health authorities ( Brasier 2008 ;  MacLeod  et al.  2010 ;  Jeger  et al.  2012 ;  Hantula  et al.  2014 ). Research is needed to test whether there is heterogeneity in the average commuting distances of plants-for-planting of different species and in various regions. A potentially confounding factor in such studies is the variation among rural and urbanized regions (as well as among industrialized and developing countries) in resources to track and fight plant epidemics. Even if new plant pathogens tend to be recorded first in urbanized regions ( Yemshanov  et al.  2013 ), the bulk of the cultivated area is located in rural areas, so that there might be a longer lag between first report and epidemic, thus providing some more time for rural economies to prepare for new plant health risks.  Taken together, these changes in the global health landscape imply that there is a need for further integration of human and plant mobility data in plant disease epidemic models. The growing complexity of mobility data can potentially enable more detailed epidemiological models, but these may also be more difficult to interpret and generalize, so that a compromise between realism and parsimoniousness is needed.  One key assumption that is often taken in models of epidemic spread in networks is the symmetrical nature of contacts ( Bianconi  et al.  2008 ). This greatly simplifies simulations of epidemics in networks, but may or may not be appropriate depending on the system (reviewed in  Newman  et al.  2001 ;  Meyers  et al.  2006 ). For example, while disease transmission on transportation networks is often asymmetric, airborne infection can be thought of as symmetric without loss of generality (although asymmetry can be present for airborne dispersal depending on the prevailing wind direction and speed).  Even in the case of symmetric contact patterns (i.e. where the probability of transmission is equivalent in both directions), transmission trees (the routes followed by infection) are directed ( Welch  et al.  2011 ). Pathogen transmission tends to occur from one node to another, e.g. from the country of first detection to elsewhere in the world (although subsequent re-infection from elsewhere in the world to the country of first detection can well take place). For example, as a likely consequence of its special position as a transatlantic bridge between the USA and continental Europe, the UK was the only European country to experience a summer peak of the H1N1 flu in 2009 ( Merler  et al.  2011 ). Epidemic transmission trees are in many cases unknown, but can be reconstructed from phylogenetic information on the pathogen at various locations in the putative contact network ( Mascheretti  et al.  2009 ;  Leventhal  et al.  2012 ;  Xhaard  et al.  2012 ;  Ypma  et al.  2012 ).  The directedness of networks results in hierarchical systems where nodes can be divided into main classes. For example, nodes can have (i) more outgoing than incoming connections, (ii) more incoming than outgoing connections, or (iii) a balance between the two ( Pautasso  et al.  2010 c  ). Networks relevant to disease spread which show hierarchical features in their structure include the world trade web ( Ruzzenenti  et al.  2010 ;  Barigozzi  et al.  2011 ;  De Benedictis and Tajoli 2011 ) and subsets of it such as the horticultural and ornamental plant trade networks ( Dehnen-Schmutz  et al.  2010 ;  Bradley  et al.  2012 ;  Liebhold  et al.  2012 ). Food webs of producers, consumers and parasites are also inherently asymmetric and hierarchical ( Foster  et al.  2010 ), and so are many networks diffusing health information from researchers to physicians, policy makers and patients ( Wang and Noe 2010 ;  Zappa 2011 ).  In directed networks of small size (hundreds of nodes), the presence of super-connected nodes only lowers the epidemic threshold if these nodes have a high number of both incoming and outgoing links ( Moslonka-Lefebvre  et al.  2009 ). An open question is how small the size of networks can be for significant differences in the epidemic threshold among network structures to be present (for a given number of network replicates). In hierarchical, directed networks with node status (infectious vs. susceptible) along a continuum, the epidemic final size correlates well with the number of outgoing links of the starting node of the epidemic, regardless of network structure (local, random, small-world and scale-free) and connectance level ( Pautasso  et al.  2010 b  ). Since we do not know which network structure applies to plant trade networks, the out-degree of a node can thus be a useful indicator of its risk.  A continuum between infectivity and susceptibility makes sense when nodes are composed of multiple units (e.g. pupils in school classes, patients in hospital wards, plants in plant nurseries), but such an approach has been rarely used in network epidemiology ( Moslonka-Lefebvre  et al.  2012 ). There is thus a challenge in inferring whether results obtained from models assuming that nodes are binary, i.e. either entirely susceptible or entirely infectious, can be transferred to plant trade networks, as only a proportion of the plants in nurseries and garden centres are typically infected. The same problem applies in plant pathology when using results obtained from epidemic simulations in symmetric networks, given that networks of plant movements are inherently directed. When plants (and their associated organisms) are moved from location  x  to location  y , the reverse movement from location  y  to location  x  does not usually occur ( Brenn  et al.  2008 ). Information is needed about the frequency and dynamics, in various countries, of subgroups such as plant producers, wholesalers, retailers and end users, because their relative proportion has been shown to be related to the likelihood that an epidemic will spread ( Pautasso  et al.  2010 c  ).  The influence of network topology on epidemic spread is not mono-directional, because, as the epidemic unfolds and individuals become infected or recover from infection, the patterns of contacts from infected to susceptible individuals will be modified ( Kamp 2010 a  ,   b  ;  House 2012 ). In addition, dynamic networks can result from the mobility of hosts ( Song  et al.  2010 a  ;  Gargiulo  et al.  2012 ) and active behavioural changes in response to an epidemic ( Saadatian-Elahi  et al.  2010 ;  Ridenhour  et al.  2011 ). A review focusing on this area is provided by  Funk  et al.  (2010) .  Temporal fluctuations in the contacts of an animal farm in Italy (neighbourhoods at distance = 3 of the same node (shown in light blue) in three consecutive monthly networks; modified from  Bajardi  et al.  (2011 a ) , with kind permission of the Public Library of Science). The assessment of the epidemiological consequences of such network dynamics is a challenge for human, animal and plant diseases.  In small-world networks, dynamically rewiring long-distance links during an epidemic leads to a higher probability of disease spread (equivalent to adding 20 % more short-cuts;  Ochab and Gora 2011 ). Incidentally, a dynamic small-world network is computationally more tractable than a fixed one, because adjacency matrices are no longer required; all that is needed is the probability for a short-cut to be present ( Stone and McKay 2011 ). This can be a disadvantage though, if the aim is to model adaptive rewiring (the transformation of local connections into long-distance ones in an adaptive way) in response to an epidemic, because with that approach the long-distance connections are chosen randomly ( Stone  et al.  2010 ).  Some epidemic models taking into account human mobility are dynamically quenched, which means that if an individual visits a new location, the same individual will be more likely than not to return to that place in the future ( Song  et al.  2010 b  ). Even if this is the case, the topological distance (the shortest path separating nodes; Table  1 ) may differ in static vs. temporal networks. Temporal networks are those taking into account changes in the contacts through time. For example, an alternative way to create a dynamic (small-world) network is to simulate disease spread on 365 static (but different) networks, one for each day of the year ( Vernon and Keeling 2009 ). Nodes that appear to be central in static networks may be of limited importance in spreading disease when the temporal fluctuations in contact patterns are considered ( Pan and Saramäki 2011 ). Whether this result also applies to plant trade networks is to the best of our knowledge still to be tested.  For both human and plant diseases, a challenge in modelling disease spread in dynamic networks is the use of metrics that can account for dynamic properties ( Natale  et al.  2011 ), given that most network metrics are based on static networks ( Bajardi  et al.  2011 b  ;  Nöremark  et al.  2011 ;  Klemm  et al.  2012 ). In addition, it would be interesting to know whether temporal preferential attachment mechanisms (the longer a node is connected to another node, the more the two nodes are likely to be connected in the future;  Stehlé  et al.  2010 ) apply also to plant traders.  Nowadays, traded plants and plant parts are no less mobile than human beings, and changes in the behaviour of the industry in response to plant epidemics are observed also in the trade of plants (e.g. switching from susceptible to resistant plant hosts). Research on how long-distance plant trade connections emerge in practice and whether they tend to be maintained through time would be needed. For example, dynamic network models of the epidemic of soybean rust ( Phakopsora pachyrhizi ) in the USA, with counties as nodes and links weighted in proportion to host cultivated area and wind speed and direction, resulted in a reduction of the resources needed to track and predict the crop epidemic ( Sutrave  et al.  2012 ). This is a good example of how network models can be used without an underlying trade network.  For disease control to be informed and to benefit from epidemic simulations in networks, these need to be grounded in realistic spatial and temporal settings ( Viboud  et al.  2006 ;  Harwood  et al.  2009 ;  Dent  et al.  2011 ). A review of the effects of spatial structure on infectious disease dynamics is provided by  Rock  et al.  (2014) .  Networks have traditionally been treated as abstract constructs, given their origin in mathematical topology ( Dale and Fortin 2010 ;  Rozhnova  et al.  2011 ). However, where a group of contacts is located and how it evolves in time can make epidemic outcomes differ from what would have been predicted at an abstract network level ( Bertuzzo  et al.  2010 ). Similarly, superimposing contact networks on spatial epidemic models can improve overall predictions. For example, the peak in influenza-like incidence reported in Italy in 2009 was shown to have occurred earlier in regions with a higher number of arriving international air-bound passengers ( Ajelli  et al.  2011 ).  The key role of space does not just apply to epidemics in networks, because many biological and social networks are also spatially embedded ( Barthélemy 2011 ;  Expert  et al.  2011 ). However, for epidemics, more so than for other systems, there is often the necessity to assess in real time (while the epidemic is ongoing) the potential impact over geographical regions ( Birrell  et al.  2011 ). This is difficult also for human diseases given the frequent lack of good data at the beginning of an epidemic ( Katriel  et al.  2011 ). Network approaches can help trace back the origin of epidemics. For example, an airline network perspective makes it possible to recover an expanding wave of infection around the airport from which an epidemic started spreading, whereas that origin would not be easily traceable when following the same epidemic on a spatial map of the world ( Brockmann and Helbing 2013 ).  A step forward would be the development of software for contemporaneous temporal comparison of different policy measures ( Maciejewski  et al.  2011 ). There is the need to test the effectiveness of the use of such visual tools by researchers and public health officials in the evaluation of measures to respond to epidemic outbreaks ( Afzal  et al.  2011 ). Together with better data at the early epidemic stages, spatio-temporal simulations are needed to make progress in assessing how behavioural changes and the spread of health information affect the resilience of networks ( Birrell  et al.  2011 ;  Döring  et al.  2014 ). Also control measures tend to differ in space and time, so that an important issue to be explored is the interplay of dynamic disease control measures in network epidemic models ( Green  et al.  2011 ).  Epidemic simulations and adaptive disease management modelling in real time are still unrealistic for plant epidemics occurring in trade networks for which there is no information about the network structure, particularly when disease monitoring is patchy and reporting is slower than the epidemic. However, molecular advances (e.g. real-time PCR) and citizen-science approaches (e.g. in the mapping of emerging diseases across whole countries) could make real-time simulations possible for plant epidemics too. A spatio-temporal approach is already inherent in empirical analyses of plant pathogens introduced by trade networks into the wider environment. For example, a study of first records of plant pathogens in the UK (1970–2004) showed that the Netherlands was the origin of introductions (when known) nearly half of the time, and the South-East of England was the region of first report (when known) for 38 % of newly recorded pathogens ( Jones and Baker 2007 ). For historical and geographical reasons, the Netherlands and the South-East of England have more trade connections than other European countries and British regions, respectively.  This kind of analysis can provide useful data to parameterize spatial epidemic network models. Similarly, a temporal study of the spatial association in England and Wales (2003–06) between  P. ramorum  reports in the trade and in the wild found that infected premises (garden centres and nurseries) were significantly associated with infected sites (woodlands and historic gardens) at short distances (&lt;1 km) over the studied period, thus suggesting a role of the trade in spreading the epidemic ( Xu  et al.  2009 ). Given that various  Phytophthora  species are found in plant nurseries, and that some of these species have hybridized to produce new emerging pathogens, plant epidemiology too may benefit from models of the interactions between different pathogen strains spreading in spatial networks ( Alexander and Kobes 2011 ;  Dorigatti and Pugliese 2011 ;  Karrer and Newman 2011 ;  Weng  et al.  2012 ).  A major issue for spatially explicit modelling of diseases spreading in networks is the communication of its inherent uncertainty and simplifications to end users (policy makers, health providers, journalists, patients) ( Prieto  et al.  2012 ). Despite the growing sophistications, spatial models of epidemics in networks are still simplifications of a complicated system ( Reppas  et al.  2010 ). Only rarely is this acknowledged in the discussion of papers reporting results from models of epidemics in spatial networks, so that there is a danger of take-home messages being read without keeping in mind all the various caveats and assumptions of the mathematical models behind policy recommendations ( Ferguson  et al.  2006 ;  Fraser  et al.  2009 ;  Garnett  et al.  2011 ).  Nevertheless, networks provide a flexible framework that can link disciplines and practitioners working in different domains, for example human and plant pathologists, as well as epidemiologists and invasion biologists ( Borer  et al.  2011 ;  Kueffer  et al.  2013 ). Network theory is a useful addition to the set of tools available to understand and manage (plant) diseases, particularly when pathogens are dispersed by human movements over long distances ( Jeger  et al.  2007 ). This review has focused on the use of networks to model the plant trade, but network theory in plant epidemiology can also be applied at the genetic, molecular, meta-population and landscape levels ( Moslonka-Lefebvre  et al.  2011 ).  One important research area where network theory is likely to prove fruitful is the integration of plant health models predicting climate change impacts with those assessing the likely effects of globalization on emerging plant diseases ( Pautasso  et al.  2010 a  ). Long-term funding for plant health modellers, experimenters and practitioners would be needed to develop this research programme. Nevertheless, an improved understanding of the structure and dynamics of plant trade networks can already provide useful insights before the expected climate changes of the coming decades take place. For example, the recent establishment of European ash dieback (caused by  Hymenoscyphus pseudoalbidus ;  Queloz  et al.  2011 ) throughout Europe was facilitated by local and long-distance trade in infected ash saplings, which continued to be planted in forests and plantations for several years despite the growing evidence that tree nurseries were a pathway for the spread of this emerging disease ( Gross  et al.  2014 ).  Our work was partly funded by the Rural Economy and Land Use (RELU) programme and the French Foundation for Research on Biodiversity (FRB) through its Centre for Analysis and Synthesis of Biodiversity Data (CESAB).  All authors have made a substantial contribution to the manuscript. Each author has seen and agreed to the submitted manuscript.  None declared.  Many thanks to T. Harwood, O. Holdenrieder, M. Moslonka-Lefebvre, L. Pellis, M. Shaw and X. Xu for insights and discussions, and to O. Holdenrieder, T. Matoni and anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on a previous draft. 