Flooding and fragment size interact to determine survival and regrowth after fragmentation in two stoloniferous <italic>Trifolium</italic> speciesFlooding stress: acclimations and genetic diversityDifferences in flooding tolerance between species from two wetland habitats with contrasting hydrology: implications for vegetation development in future floodwater retention areasClonal growth strategies along flooding and grazing gradients in Atlantic coastal meadowsResponse of aquatic plants to abiotic factors: a reviewStressful ‘memories’ of plants: evidence and possible mechanismsFitness consequences of natural variation in flooding-induced shoot elongation in <italic>Rumex palustris</italic>Flooding tolerance: suites of plant traits in variable environmentsHow internode length, position and presence of leaves affect survival and growth of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> after fragmentation?Burial depth and stolon internode length independently affect survival of small clonal fragmentsEffects of fragmentation on the survival and growth of the invasive, clonal plant <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>On the evolution of clonal plant life historiesNo long-term costs of meristem allocation to flowering in stoloniferous <italic>Trifolium</italic> speciesShade avoidance in the clonal herb <italic>Trifolium fragiferum</italic>: a field study with experimentally manipulated vegetation heightTiming of disturbance changes the balance between growth and survival of parent and offspring ramets in the clonal forest understory herb <italic>Uvularia perfoliata</italic>Variation in flooding-induced morphological traits in natural populations of white clover (<italic>Trifolium repens</italic>) and their effects on plant performance during soil floodingPlasticity as a plastic response: how submergence-induced leaf elongation in <italic>Rumex palustris</italic> depends on light and nutrient availability in its early life stageMorphological plasticity in <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> L.: the effects of clone genotype, soil nutrient level, and the genotype of conspecific neighboursCLO-PLA: the database of clonal and bud bank traits of Central European floraBud banks and their role in vegetative regeneration—a literature review and proposal for simple classification and assessmentConsequences of more extreme precipitation regimes for terrestrial ecosystemsSpatial genetic structure of aquatic bryophytes in a connected lake systemPhysiological integration for carbon in mayapple (<italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic>), a clonal perennial herbThe measurements of selection on correlated charactersSubmergence-induced morphological, anatomical, and biochemical responses in a terrestrial species affect gas diffusion resistance and photosynthetic performanceSubmergence-induced leaf acclimation in terrestrial species varying in flooding toleranceResprouting response of aquatic clonal plants to cutting may explain their resistance to spate floodingPhenotypic plasticity and mechanical stress: biomass partitioning and clonal growth of an aquatic plant speciesAbiotic stresses increase plant regeneration abilityPlant invasiveness is not linked to the capacity of regeneration from small fragments: an experimental test with 39 stoloniferous speciesThe role of stolen internodes for ramet survival after clone fragmentation in <italic>Potentilla anserina</italic>On the ecological and evolutionary significance of storage in clonal plantsIs tolerance to summer flooding correlated with distribution patterns in river floodplains? A comparative study of 20 terrestrial grassland speciesClonal integration in <italic>Ranunculus reptans</italic>: by-product or adaptation?Acclimation to soil flooding—sensing and signal-transductionFlooding-induced adventitious rooting in Rumex: morphology and development in an ecological perspectivePlant hormones regulate fast shoot elongation under water: from genes to communitiesEarly developmental responses to seedling environment modulate later plasticity to light spectral qualityAFLP—a new technique for DNA-fingerprintingIntegrated physiological units in plantsResource storage and the expression of clonal plant life historiesVariation in petiole and internode length affects plant performance in <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> under opposing selection regimesPhenotypic plasticity early in life constrains developmental responses laterIntraspecific variation of a desert shrub species in phenotypic plasticity in response to sand burial<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Michael B. JacksonThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Clonal plants are common in frequently flooded habitats because of their resilience to disturbance. We investigated if submergence prior to fragmentation of clones of two clover species reduced survival and regrowth of clonal fragments, and if these fitness parameters were different between genotypes from highly disturbed river forelands and less disturbed coastal dune slacks. We found that soil flooding severely decreased survival and regrowth, and that plants from the more disturbance-prone habitat were less negatively affected by fragmentation. However, internode size was, surprisingly, often negatively correlated with survival after fragmentation, but positively correlated with regrowth. Apparently, contrasting selection pressures exist on internode size in stoloniferous species growing in disturbed habitats.Clonal plants, which reproduce by means of stolons and rhizomes, are common in frequently flooded habitats. Resilience to disturbance is an important trait enabling plants to survive in such highly disturbed habitats. Resource storage is thought to enable clonal plants to resume growth after clonal fragmentation caused by disturbance. Here we investigated if submergence prior to disturbance reduces survival and regrowth of clonal fragments and whether or not genotypes originating from highly disturbed riverine habitats are more resistant to mechanical disturbance than genotypes from less disturbed coastal dune slack habitats. We further tested if variation in survival and regrowth was affected by internode size. Clones from contrasting habitats of two closely related <italic>Trifolium</italic> species were first genotypically characterized by amplification fragment length polymorphism and then subjected to soil flooding and subsequent clonal fragmentation. These species differ with respect to their abundance in riverine and dune slack habitats, with <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> mainly occurring in riverine grasslands and <italic>Trifolium fragiferum</italic> in coastal dune slacks. Soil flooding decreased survival and regrowth by up to 80 %. Plants originating from riverine grasslands were less negatively affected by fragmentation than plants from dune slack habitats. Surprisingly, ramets did not always benefit from being attached to a larger internode, as internode size was often negatively correlated with survival after fragmentation. Regrowth, on the other hand, was generally positively correlated with internode size. These unexpected results indicate that there may be contrasting selection pressures on internode size in stoloniferous species growing in severely disturbed habitats.Flooding is an increasingly common stress affecting plant growth and vegetation composition in flood-prone areas. Recent global change scenarios predict that the incidence of flooding events will increase in the coming decades due to changes in rainfall patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C20">Knapp <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Flooding affects plant growth and survival in various ways, as it is a compound stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C1">Bailey-Serres and Voesenek 2008</xref>). Oxygen deficiency, light limitation, toxic soil compounds and mechanical disturbance may all act at the same time during flooding. These stresses may each select for specific plant traits, but it is remarkable that plant communities in flood-prone habitats are often characterized by a high prevalence of vegetatively reproducing plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C3">Benot <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), i.e. forming stolons, rhizomes or root suckers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C11">Fischer and Van Kleunen 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C18">Klimesova and de Bello 2009</xref>). Stolons and rhizomes play an important role in transport of resources between connected ramets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C39">Watson 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C22">Landa <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C33">Van Kleunen <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>), and also have an important storage function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C31">Suzuki and Stuefer 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C40">Watson 2008</xref>). It has been argued that the presence of parts of the stolon can positively affect plant survival after clone fragmentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C30">Stuefer and Huber 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C8">Dong <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C9">2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C10">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C29">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). This may be beneficial after a flooding event when part of the clone has become disconnected due to mechanical stress as a result of strong water currents or mortality of the remainder of the clone. Clonal species can quickly resprout from dormant meristems after clone fragmentation, by reallocating resources stored in the stolons and rhizomes to the sites of new leaf and root production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C19">Klimesova and Klimes 2007</xref>). Apart from the negative effects of flooding-induced disturbance, flooding may also play an important role as a long-distance dispersal agent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C21">Korpelainen <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Clonal fragments may be spread along the riverine systems during flooding events, thereby allowing plants to invade new habitats or already established populations. Survival after clone fragmentation is therefore not only important for the maintenance of existing populations, but may also have important consequences for gene flow among populations or establishment of new populations.The ability to regrow after clone fragmentation may depend on the environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C28">Puijalon <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C4">Bornette and Puijalon 2011</xref>). Moreover, different stresses may interact and the conditions experienced earlier may affect responsiveness to subsequent stress factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C42">Weinig and Delph 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C16">Huber <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C37">von Wettberg <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Stress events may precondition plants and prime them to respond to subsequent stresses, even if the stresses are of different nature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C5">Bruce <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). It has, for example, been shown that both limited nutrient availability and mechanical stress caused by high water velocity increased plant survival after fragmentation in the aquatic species <italic>Berula erecta</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C27">Puijalon and Bornette 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C28">Puijalon <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). A general response of increased allocation to clonal structures in plants experiencing environmental stress may explain this result. However, repeated environmental stress may also reduce plant growth and survival. This can especially occur if environmental stress negatively affects storage, either by reducing allocation to storage due to limited resource uptake or by depleting previously stored resources (e.g. caused by investment in increased elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C16">Huber <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C43">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The direction and nature of the effects of prior stresses on the response to subsequent fragmentation, however, largely remain unclear.Plants have evolved different mechanisms to alleviate the negative effects of flooding events. Translocation of resources to leaf growth, production of adventitious roots, aerenchyma formation and elongation of petioles or leaf tissues may enable plants to restore oxygen supply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C34">Visser and Voesenek 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C1">Bailey-Serres and Voesenek 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C7">Colmer and Voesenek 2009</xref>). It has been shown that the ability of plant species to express these adaptations strongly differs along flooding gradients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C35">Visser <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C36">Voesenek <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C2">Banach <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Strong selection pressures driven by a different frequency or likelihood of flooding have resulted in a distinctly different set of species within a narrow geographical range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C32">van Eck <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Also within flood-prone habitats, different types and frequencies of flooding may impose distinctly different selection pressures on plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C36">Voesenek <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C6">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Coastal dune slacks and riverine grasslands are both prone to flooding. However, both habitat types are exposed to different flooding regimes, with rapidly rising water levels and strong currents during the growing period of plants in riverine grasslands, as opposed to mainly winter and early spring flooding with a much more gradual rise of the water level and no streaming water in coastal dune slacks. It is likely that plants in these contrasting flood-prone areas have evolved different mechanisms to cope with the flooding stress. In this manuscript we ask to what extent prior flooding affects the ability of plants to survive and regrow after mechanical disturbance, and whether different flooding regimes have led to the selection of locally adapted ecotypes that differ in their responses to fragmentation after flooding. Accordingly, we performed an experiment with the two closely related stoloniferous clover species <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> and <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> to test the following hypothesis: (i) As commonly observed in other species, internode size was expected to be positively linked to survival and regrowth after fragmentation. (ii) Previous flooding was expected to affect survival and regrowth after fragmentation, either positively by preconditioning of plant responses to further fragmentation, or negatively due to reserve depletion and negative effects of internode size. (iii) As <italic>T. repens</italic> often occurs in disturbed riverine habitats and <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> favours less disturbed dune slack grasslands, we expected <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> to be less tolerant to fragmentation following a flooding episode than <italic>T. repens</italic>. (iv) It was anticipated for both species that genotypes originating from the disturbance-prone river floodplains would be more disturbance tolerant than genotypes originating from the more sheltered dune slack environments.Two closely related stoloniferous clover species <italic>T. repens</italic> and <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> were used for the experiments. These species have a similar developmental pattern: they both grow by means of aboveground stolons composed of ramets and each ramet consists of one internode, one leaf, one meristem located in the leaf axil (potentially differentiating into a flower or a side branch) and root primordia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C13">Huber and Wiggerman 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C12">Huber and During 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C15">Huber <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The species differ, however, in their ecological niches. While <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> mainly occurs in coastal habitats and occasionally spreads to riverine grasslands and grasslands along motorways, <italic>T. repens</italic> has a much wider ecological niche and occurs in a wide variety of grassland habitats and roadside verges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C12">Huber and During 2000</xref>). For the present experiment, we collected 20–29 clonal fragments consisting of one unbranched stolon with 5–10 ramets in four grasslands where both species co-occurred, namely in two coastal dune slack and two riverine grasslands in The Netherlands (Oost-Voorne (51°85′N, 4°07′E) and Goedereede (51°84′N, 3°99′E), and Waardenburg (51°83′N, 5°28′E) and Pannerdensche Kop (51°89′N, 6°02′E), respectively). The distance between sampled plants was at least 1–2 m. These coastal dune slack and riverine habitats differ greatly in the frequency and type of disturbance. While the dune slack habitats are mainly characterized by flooding during winter and early spring caused by slowly rising water levels, the riverine grasslands can be flooded for several shorter times during the year but with faster inundation and higher final water tables. The latter situation is considered to cause greater physical disturbance.Principal coordinates analysis and ΦPT values computed from AMOVA on individuals of <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> (A) and <italic>T. repens</italic> (B) populations. Principal coordinates analysis plots and ΦPT values are based on 63 AFLP markers for <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> and on 47 AFLP markers for <italic>T. repens</italic>. The symbols represent riverine (filled uptriangle, Pannerdensche Kop, PK; cross, Waardenburg, W) and coastal dune slack (filled square, Oost-Voorne, V; filled diamond, Goedereede, G) populations. Percentages of total variance explained by each axis are noted in brackets. The inlaid box shows the ΦPT values for the pairwise population comparisons. Higher ΦPT values indicate a higher degree of differentiation between populations.Illustration of how clonal fragments were created after the flooding treatment. Increasing numbers indicate developmental stages of the ramets; ramet 3 was selected for testing regrowth. Note that this ramet did not develop roots yet.Survival was analysed by means of logistic regression, testing for the effects of species, habitat, treatment, population nested within habitat and genotype nested within population and habitat on ramet survival. Leaf number, stolon dimensions and biomass of the different compartments were analysed by means of three-way nested ANOVA, with species, habitat and treatment as the main factors, and the random factors population nested within habitat and genotype nested within population and habitat. A temporal block was added to the ANOVA model to account for differences between the two temporal blocks but not to the logistic regression. Whether or not initial internode volume affected survival and regrowth was analysed with linear regression analyses for each species×treatment×habitat combination separately. In order to be able to compare the magnitude of the effects of initial internode volume on regrowth between species and treatments and habitat of origin, we standardized the data prior to analyses following commonly used approaches to calculate standardized regression coefficients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C23">Lande and Arnold 1983</xref>). Internode volume was standardized by subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation. The performance parameters survival, leaf number and plant weight (excluding old stolon material) were relativized by dividing by the mean in order to be able to compare the different species and traits. Means and standard deviations were calculated for each species × treatment × habitat combination separately. As we assessed initial internode volume for each fragment separately, we were able to perform the regression analysis on the level of the individual plant. The regression analysis was performed for each treatment, species and habitat type separately, using the means and standard deviations for the respective groups. For each species and treatment, all plants originating from one habitat type were pooled for these regression analyses. The program package SAS (SAS 9.1; SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA) was used for all analyses.Results from a four-way nested ANOVA testing for the effect of species (S; <italic>T. repens</italic> or <italic>T. fragiferum</italic>), treatment (T; soil flooded or drained), habitat of origin (H; riverine or coastal dune slacks), population (P) and genotype (Gen) on initial internode characteristics (length, diameter, volume), plant survival, leaf number, internode and plant weight at harvest. Survival was tested by means of logistic regression. <italic>F</italic>-values and their significance are given, except for survival where <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> values and their significance are given. Only surviving plants were analysed for the data at harvest, resulting in lower df values (given in brackets). Significantly different values are indicated in bold, and marginally significant differences in italics. Significance levels are as follows: ***<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.001, **0.001 &lt; <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.01, *0.01 &lt; <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05, <sup>$</sup>0.05 &lt; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.1, ns <italic>P</italic> ≥ 0.1.Characteristics of the attached internode after fragmentation (mean ± 1 SE) of plants that were previously subjected to drained (dark bars) or soil-flooded (light bars) conditions. Plants from the two populations within a given habitat of origin were pooled for the sake of clarity.Plant growth and survival (mean ± 1 SE) 2 weeks after fragmentation. Plants were previously subjected to drained (dark bars) or soil-flooded (light bars) conditions. Plant weight indicates the biomass of new leaves and roots and excludes the original internode. Internode dry weight indicates the final dry weight of the internode that had remained attached to the plants after fragmentation. Plant weight, leaf number and internode weight are only given for those plants that actually survived. Plants from the two populations within a given habitat of origin were pooled for the sake of clarity.The internodes of drained plants of <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> were almost twice as heavy as those of drained <italic>T. repens</italic> plants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU024F4">4</xref>G and H, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU024TB1">1</xref>). Soil flooding decreased internode weight by up to 30 % in <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> and by 5–20 % in <italic>T. repens</italic> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.086).There was no difference among genotypes with respect to survival and leaf production after fragmentation. However, plant weight (leaf and roots) and weight of the attached distal internode differed significantly among genotypes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU024TB1">1</xref>).Correlation between internode volume and the performance parameters, i.e. survival, number of leaves and dry weight of the new plant (excluding the old internode). Standardized regression coefficients and their significance are given. Negative values indicate that performance parameters were negatively affected by increasing internode volume and positive values indicate that performance was positively affected by increasing internode volume. The analysis was performed for each species, treatment and habitat combination separately. Significantly different values are indicated in bold, and marginally significant differences in italics. Significance levels are as follows: ***<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.001, **0.001 &lt; <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.01, *0.01 &lt; <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05, <sup>$</sup>0.05 &lt; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.1, <sup>ns</sup><italic>P</italic> ≥ 0.1.Plants in their natural environment are subjected to a multitude of environmental cues throughout their development, and conditions experienced at early developmental stages may affect response to subsequent cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C42">Weinig and Delph 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C5">Bruce <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C37">von Wettberg <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). The effects may be direct if early conditions limit resource uptake and storage, or indirect through physiological changes such as to hormone balance or chemical composition of stored resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C28">Puijalon <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Our results show that flooding strongly reduced survival and regrowth in response to subsequent fragmentation. This may have been due to reduced allocation of resources into storage in flooded plants, as under flooded conditions resources are, among others, allocated to morphological responses such as adventitious roots and increased leaf elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C15">Huber <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C6">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). In addition, the cuticle of flooded leaves is often thinner, which makes the plants prone to desiccation as soon as the water recedes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C24">Mommer <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C25">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C6">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). A similar process may have led to a reduction of cuticle thickness of submerged stolon internodes, thereby increasing water loss. Such water loss could explain the reduced survival of clonal fragments that were previously flooded in our experiment.Fragmentation during natural flooding events may provide an important dispersal mechanism in clonal plants. It can thus be expected that genotypes characterized by reduced survival after flooding-induced fragmentation are selected against in highly disturbed riverine habitats. This is consistent with the relatively lower effects of flooding in the survival and regrowth in <italic>T. repens</italic>, a species common in such severely disturbed habitats, than in <italic>T. fragiferum</italic>, a species more common in less disturbed dune slack habitats.The type and frequency of flooding constitutes an important selection agent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C6">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C26">Mony <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). We hypothesized that genotypes originating from disturbance-prone riverine habitats experience different selection pressures than genotypes from less disturbed dune slacks, leading to different resistances to fragmentation. Within species our experiment revealed only weak differences in internode dimensions and general resistance to fragmentation between genotypes originating from dune slack and riverine grasslands with the exception of the comparatively slower regrowth of coastal populations of <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> after fragmentation. However, while this habitat-induced difference was relatively large, it was only marginally significant statistically. This lack of differentiation, particularly in <italic>T. repens</italic>, may be due to relatively large gene flow. <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> is widely distributed and occurs in a wide variety of habitats, making it likely that seeds or clonal fragments disperse relatively easily among populations.Internode size is a trait subject to selection and the optimal size of internodes can depend on a multitude of environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C17">Hutchings <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C41">Weijschede <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). While internode length and diameter may be largely determined by optimal ramet spacing and morphological features associated with the transport function, increasing internode size may also positively affect the amount of resources stored in the internodes, and in turn increase survival and regrowth after clone fragmentation. Our current study tested the hypothesis that, comparable to results on the presence or absence of internodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C30">Stuefer and Huber 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C8">Dong <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C10">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C29">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), investment in larger internodes increases survival and regrowth after fragmentation. In contrast to this prediction, we found that survival probability markedly reduced with increasing internode size. The two species used in this experiment had a similar growth form and developmental rate. However, <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> produced internodes that were almost twice as long with an on average 2.5 times greater volume than internodes produced by <italic>T. repens</italic>. Despite this higher investment in internodes, <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> could not cope well with fragmentation, as fragmented plants had a much lower survival rate compared with <italic>T. repens</italic>. Generally, <italic>T. repens</italic> has a much broader distribution and ecological niche than <italic>T. fragiferum</italic> and can also occur in severely disturbed habitats. <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> may thus have evolved a high resistance to physical disturbance. Even under the extreme fragmentation regime applied in our experiment, close to 100 % of the fragments survived and continued growth in several genotypes of <italic>T. repens</italic>, indicating the great capacity of this species to establish even in strongly disturbed habitats.Interestingly, comparison within species revealed that internode volume was negatively correlated with survival for <italic>T. fragiferum</italic>, indicating again that larger internodes may not be unequivocally beneficial in disturbed habitats. This result is surprising, as it contradicts the generally accepted notion that higher resource storage increases resistance to fragmentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C31">Suzuki and Stuefer 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C14">Huber <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C8">Dong <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Unfortunately, we cannot provide an unambiguous explanation of these surprising results. Several factors may have contributed to the decreased survival in plants with larger internodes. Carbohydrates stored in internodes may have attracted pathogens leading to a decay of the clonal fragment, an effect that is likely to be stronger in larger internodes. This interpretation is also supported by the fact that in previously flooded plants the effect of internode size was weaker. Flooded plants have probably invested less into resource storage in newly produced internodes, leading to the observed lower weight of internodes. Differences in desiccation after fragmentation may provide an alternative interpretation. Larger internodes were characterized by a higher surface-to-volume ratio, as variation in internode size was mainly due to variation in internode length. This may have led to higher evaporation in larger internodes and subsequent desiccation of the clonal fragment. Further research is needed to understand the specific mechanisms leading to reduced survival of larger clonal fragments.It is, however, important to note that if plants were able to survive clonal fragmentation, the size of internodes was positively correlated with biomass gain after fragmentation. This is in line with results on a wide range of species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C9">Dong <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C29">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), since larger internodes are likely to contain more resources that can be reallocated to growth after fragmentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU024C30">Stuefer and Huber 1999</xref>). In line with this expectation, we found, in an unpublished experiment, that internode volume explains 47 % of the variation in carbohydrate content in the third youngest internode of <italic>T. repens</italic> subjected to control conditions (<italic>n</italic> = 15; <italic>F</italic> = 12,63; <italic>P</italic> = 0.003; J. Kassenberg and H. Huber, Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands, unpubl. res.). Our present results thus provide evidence for a more complex role of internode size in the ability of plants to withstand severe disturbance. While producing larger internodes may lower survival probability, it contributes positively to future growth and performance. This indicates that there may be contrasting selection pressures on internode size in stoloniferous species growing in severely disturbed habitats.H.H., E.J.W.V. and J.L.P. designed the experiments and wrote the paper, and H.H., E.J.W.V., J.L.P. and G.C. performed the experiments and analyses.None declared.We gratefully acknowledge Harry van de Steeg and Heinjo During for help with collecting plant material, and Nelleke Cornips, Gerard van der Weerden and the staff of the Experimental Garden and Genebank of the Radboud University for providing practical support during plant growth and maintenance during the experiment. Jan Zethof helped with the molecular analyses. Onno Calf produced the drawing in Fig. 2.