 Phenotypic traits of  Phragmites australis  clones are not related to ploidy level and distribution range  Genetic diversity, ecophysiology and growth dynamics of reed ( Phragmites australis )  Changes in activities of antioxidative system and monoterpene and photochemical efficiency during seasonal leaf senescence in  Hevea brasiliensis  trees  The correct name of the common reed  Taxonomy, chromosome numbers, clonal diversity and population dynamics of  Phragmites australis   Geographic variation in growth responses in  Phragmites australis   Genetic diversity and dispersal of  Phragmites australis  in a small river system  Responses of ecotypes of  Phragmites australis  to increased seawater influence: a field study in the Danube Delta, Romania  Clone-specific differences in  Phragmites australis : effects of ploidy level and geographic origin  Some aspects of the life history and autecology of  Phragmites communis  Trin. A review  Clone specific differences in a  Phragmites australis  stand. I. Morphology, genetics and site description  Relationship between photosynthesis and chlorophyll content during leaf senescence of rice seedlings  A phylogeographic study of the cosmopolitan genus  Phragmites  (Poaceae) based on AFLPs  Genetic diversity patterns in  Phragmites australis  at the population, regional and continental scales  Effect of climatic gradients on the photosynthetic responses of four  Phragmites australis  populations  Chlorophylls and carotenoids—pigments of photosynthetic biomembranes  Effects of salinity on the growth of  Phragmites australis   Effect of climate on the salt tolerance of two  Phragmites australis  populations. I. Growth, inorganic solutes, nitrogen relations and osmoregulation  Mechanisms of salinity tolerance  Tolerance and physiological responses of  Phragmites australis  to water deficit  Osmotic and ionic effects of NaCl and Na 2 SO 4  salinity on  Phragmites australis   An evolutionary approach to understanding the biology of invasions: local adaptation and general-purpose genotypes in the weed  Verbascum thapsus   Phenotypic differences among ploidy levels of  Phragmites australis  growing in Romania  Recognition of  Phragmites australis  subsp.  americanus  (Poaceae: Arundinoideae) in North America: evidence from morphological and genetic analyses  Comparison of morphological variation indicative of ploidy level in  Phragmites australis  (POACEAE) from Eastern North America  Ecological genetics of plant invasions: what do we know?  Causes and consequences of invasive plants in wetlands: opportunities, opportunists, and outcomes  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  The present study reveals significant genetically determined differences in a range of growth and ecophysiological traits between different  Phragmites australis  genotypes, and provides evidence that the differences are neither related to ploidy level  per se  nor to the phylogeographic relationships of the genotypes.   Phragmites australis  is a wetland grass with high genetic variability, augmented by its cosmopolitan distribution, clonal growth form and large variation in chromosome numbers. Different ploidy levels and ecotypes differ in morphology and ecophysiological traits, and may possess different levels of phenotypic variation. The aim of this study was to quantify the natural variation in ecophysiological characteristics of  P. australis , and to explore whether differences in ecophysiological traits can be related to ploidy levels or to the geographic origin of the clones.  Fifteen clones of  P. australis  from Europe and Asia/Australia, representing five ploidy levels (4 x , 6 x , 8 x , 10 x  and 12 x ), were grown in a common garden design for 119 days. Plant growth and light-saturated rate of photosynthesis ( P  max ), stomatal conductance ( g  s ), water use efficiency (WUE) and concentrations of photosynthetic pigments and mineral ions in the leaves were measured.  The growth of the plants and most ecophysiological parameters differed significantly between clones. The mean maximum shoot height varied from 0.9 to 1.86 m,  P  max  from 9.7 to 27 µmol m −2  s −1 ,  g  s  from 0.22 to 1.41 mol m −2  s −1  and WUE from 13 to 47 µmol mol −1 . The concentrations of chlorophylls did not vary significantly between clones, but the chlorophyll  a / b  ratio and the concentrations of total carotenoids did. The observed differences were not explained either by the ploidy level  per se  or by the geographic origin or phylogenetic relationships of the clones.  Phylogeographic relationships in  P. australis  on a global scale do not mirror the environment where the adaptations have evolved, and high phenotypic variation among and within clones complicates comparative studies. Future studies aimed at explaining differences in plant behaviour between  P. australis  populations should be careful in the selection of target genotypes and/or populations, and should avoid generalizing their findings beyond the genotypes and/or populations studied.  Genetic diversity among individuals within a species is reflected in the presence of alleles in the gene pool, and hence different genotypes within populations ( Ward  et al . 2008 ). Such diversity can be identified by phenotypic traits, such as morphology or size. The wetland grass – common reed ( Phragmites australis ) – is a species with very high genetic variability ( Lambertini  et al.  2006 ,  2008 ) that is augmented by its cosmopolitan distribution, clonal growth form and the large variation in chromosome numbers ( Brix 1999 ;  Clevering and Lissner 1999 ). The species includes several ploidy levels with tetraploids (4 x ) being the predominant ploidy level in Europe, while octoploids (8 x ) are predominant in Australia and Asia ( Clevering and Lissner 1999 ). Polyploids often occur together within the same population. A well-known mixed cytotype population is in the Danube Delta in Romania, with 2 n  = 4 x , 6 x , 8 x  and 12 x  ( Clevering and Lissner 1999 ;  Hansen  et al . 2007 ;  Lambertini  et al . 2008 ). Another mixed cytotype population is in Far East Russia, in Sakhalin Island, with 2 n  = 4 x , 6 x , 8 x  and 10 x  ( Clevering and Lissner 1999 ).  Polyploidy often leads to an overall increase in plant size ( Stebbins 1971 ), and the Romanian octoploid  P. australis  has been reported to have taller and thicker shoots and larger leaves than the tetraploids ( Hanganu  et al . 1999 ;  Pauca-Comanescu  et al . 1999 ;  Clevering  et al . 2001 ). The length of stomatal guard cells also increases with increasing ploidy level, suggesting a correlation between cell and plant size; however, these differences do not affect photosynthetic gas exchange at different ploidy levels ( Hansen  et al . 2007 ). On the contrary,  Saltonstall  et al . (2007)  found significant differences in guard cell size and stomatal density between American native and Europeanintroduced  P. australis  clones that could not be explained by differences in genome size. Also, significant differences in ecophysiological characteristics between populations with different ploidy levels, as well as within a ploidy level, have been reported ( Kühl  et al . 1999 ;  Clevering  et al . 2001 ;  Lessmann  et al . 2001 ;  Hansen  et al . 2007 ). Hence, there is plenty of evidence that large genetically determined differences in morphology and physiology exist among populations and clones of  P. australis .  In  P. australis , reproduction occurs both by vegetative spreading of shoots and rhizomes and long-distance dispersal of seeds ( Haslam 1973 ), and several studies have documented large genetic variability within local  P. australis  populations ( Lambertini  et al . 2008 ;  Fer and Hroudova 2009 ). However, at a global scale,  P. australis  can be grouped into a number of genetically related groups ( Lambertini  et al . 2006 ). The North American native population of  P. australis , formally recognized as  P. australis  ssp.  americanus  ( Saltonstall  et al . 2004 ), constitutes one well-defined group. Another distinctive  P. australis  group extends throughout East Asia and Australia, and is predominantly comprised of octoploids ( Lambertini  et al . 2006 ). Tetraploids are also present in the Far East, but these are genetically more closely related to European  P. australis  than to the Asiatic/Australian group ( Lambertini  et al . 2006 ). The European  P. australis  ssp.  australis  ( Clayton 1968 ) belongs genetically to a very diverse group with large cytological variation and an almost cosmopolitan distribution ( Lambertini  et al . 2006 ).  This study focuses on a comparison of ecophysiological traits between seven European clones and eight Asiatic/Australian clones with different ploidy levels. Unlike previous studies, we have considered all cytotypic variation present in Europe and Asia/Australia, and compared the two geographic ranges dominated by tetraploids and octoploids, respectively. The aim was to assess the natural variation in ecophysiological characteristics that occurs between them, and to explore whether consistent differences in ecophysiological traits can be related to the ploidy level and/or the geographic distribution range. Differences in ecophysiological traits might have evolved as a result of adaptation to the environmental conditions in the different geographic ranges, eventually in concert with polyploidization.  List of  P. australis  clones used in the study, their origin, ploidy level and phylogeographic relationships. Sample labels are the same as in  Lambertini  et al . (2006) , but the prefix ‘Pa’, standing for  P. australis , has been replaced by ‘E’ and ‘A’, indicating the geographic distribution of the clones in Europe (E) or Asia/Australia (A).  * Lambertini  et al . (2006) .  In order to produce similar-sized, genetically identical plants for use in the experiment, shoots of the 15 clones were cut at their base and laid on a sand substrate in a 20- to 30-mm water layer, in a heated greenhouse for 1 month, until new shoots with roots were produced at the stem nodes of the layered shoots. The shoots were taken from a live collection of  P. australis  clones kept at the Department of Bioscience, Aarhus University, Denmark (56°13N; 10°07E), for at least 5 years prior to the study. Ten genetically identical shoots of each clone were then planted in five 3.5-L plastic pots in commercial compost, with two plants in each pot. The pots were watered with a fertilizing solution prepared from tap water and a commercial nutrient solution (100 mg L −1  Pioner NPK Makro 19-2-15+Mg and 0.1 ml L −1  Pioner Mikro+Fe, Brøste, Lyngby, Denmark). In order to maintain equal water levels in all pots, each pot was placed in a 6-L outer container filled with fertilizing solution to a height of ∼100 mm. The smallest plant was removed from the pots after the first 14 days of establishment in the greenhouse. The whole experimental set-up comprised 15 clones, each represented by five replicates. The clones were grown for 119 days under identical environmental conditions in a greenhouse. The plants were watered every third or fourth day as needed, and their relative position in the greenhouse was changed weekly to minimize the effects of environmental gradients within the greenhouse.  Air temperature, relative humidity and photosynthetically active radiation in the greenhouse were monitored by a combined temperature and humidity sensor (Rotronic MP100TS-000; Bassersdorf, Switzerland) and an LI-190 Quantum Sensor (Li-Cor Biosciences, Lincoln, NE, USA), and all data were stored by an LI 1400 datalogger (Li-Cor Biosciences). The monthly average air temperature fluctuated from a maximum of 22 °C at noon to 14 °C at midnight in July and August, and from 20 to 11 °C in September and October. The relative air humidity fluctuated between 30 and 95 %, with strongest variations in July. Relative humidity values below 50 % were rare and occurred only in July. The average light intensity during the daytime was highest in July, with a maximum of 934 µmol m −2  s −1  on 26 July. Thereafter, the light intensity decreased, reaching peak values of 635, 427 and 183 µmol m −2  s −1  in August, September and October, in concert with the decrease in day length.  Plant height (i.e. distance from the soil surface to the apical node of the tallest shoot in each pot) was measured at the beginning of the experiment and every second or third week. The shoot elongation rate (in millimetres per day) was calculated from the height difference between two successive samplings until shoot elongation stopped.  After 42–49 days, when all plants were in an active growth phase, the light-saturated rate of photosynthesis ( P  max ), transpiration and stomatal conductance ( g  s ) were measured on the third or fourth youngest fully developed leaf of each plant, using an LI-6400XT Portable Photosynthesis System (Li-Cor Biosciences). Leaves were acclimated in the leaf chamber for 3–5min until steady-state gas exchange properties were observed. The leaf chamber was air conditioned at 20 °C with a relative humidity of 35–50 %, and placed on a tripod to ensure stability during readings. The leaf chamber was supplied with atmospheric air drawn from a height of 5 m from outside the greenhouse. Light was supplied by an LI-6400-02B LED light source (Li-Cor Biosciences) set at 1800 µmol m −2  s −1  intensity. The leaf width was measured prior to infra-red gas-exchange analysis (IRGA) measurements to estimate the leaf area in the chamber.  P  max  was registered when the IRGA showed stable readings, usually after 2–5 min. The intrinsic water use efficiency (WUE) was calculated as  P  max  divided by  g  s . The potential quantum yield of photosystem II (PSII),  F  v / F  m , was measured in a dark-acclimated leaf from each replicate with a Portable Chlorophyll Fluorometer (PAM-2000, Walz Mess- und Regeltechnik, Germany). The saturation pulse method was used. The leaf was wrapped in aluminium foil for at least 15 min before a Walz Dark Leaf Clip (DLC-8) was used, together with the PAM, to take the readings of the  F  v / F  m  ratios.  The leaves used in photosynthetic gas exchange measurements were frozen, and then lyophilized. Concentrations of chlorophylls (Chl  a , Chl  b ) and total carotenoids (Total-car) were measured in a spectrophotometer after extraction of ∼5 mg of leaf dry weight (dw) in 8 mL of 96 % ethanol according to  Lichtenthaler (1987) . Total-car is xanthophyll (x) plus carotenes (c). Pigment concentrations were expressed as milligrams per gram dry weight, and the ratios between the concentration of total chlorophylls and carotenoids, [( a  +  b )/( x  +  c )], were calculated.  At the end of the experiment, plants were harvested and the leaves frozen and lyophilized. The freeze-dried leaves were ground and ∼0.1 g dw of ground plant material was extracted in 30-mL centrifuge tubes with 15 mL of Milli-Q water (Millipore) at 80 °C for 20 min. After cooling, 15 mL of Milli-Q water were added and the samples centrifuged for 5 min at 1700  g . The concentrations of chloride (Cl) in the extractions were determined by titration with AgNO 3  (ABU52 Biburette Titrator, TitraMaster 85, Radiometer Analytical SAS, France). Concentrations of sodium (Na), potassium (K), calcium (Ca) and magnesium (Mg) in the extracts were analysed by ICP-OES (Optima 2000 DV, Perkin Elmer Instruments Inc., CT, USA).  Differences in the measured parameters due to geographic range (GR), ploidy level (PL) and clonal variation were analysed by a nested ANOVA using the GLM procedure of the software Statgraphics Centurion XV (Manugistics Inc., MD, USA). Geographic range and ploidy level were treated as independent factors, whereas clonal variation was nested within GR × PL. Outliers were identified by the unusual residual procedure. Values with residuals &gt;3.5 were eliminated. Differences among clones in the measured parameters were identified by one-way ANOVAs. Data were tested for variance homogeneity using Levene's test, and if necessary log transformed. The post hoc Tukey's HSD (honestly significant difference) test was used to identify significant differences among the clones at the 95 % confidence level. A rotated principal component analysis (PCA) was conducted on the measured ecophysiological characteristics of the 15 clones, in order to reduce the number of variables into a smaller number of principal components that account for most of the variance in the data.  Summary of a two-way ANOVA showing the effects of geographic range (GR) and ploidy level (PL) on the measured ecophysiological parameters in  P. australis  clones. The factor ‘clone’ was nested in ‘GR × PL’ in the ANOVA. Variance within each factor was tested against the total variation of the clones, each represented by its five replicates. SS % = sum of squares as a percentage; df = degrees of freedom. Numbers in boldface indicate  P  values &lt;0.05.  Average final shoot height, light-saturated rate of photosynthesis ( P  max ), stomatal conductance ( g  s ), intrinsic water use efficiency (WUE) and potential quantum yield of PSII ( F  v / F  m ) of  P. australis  clones with different ploidy levels, and from two different geographic ranges as indicated by the first letter in the clone name (‘E’, Europe; ‘A’, Asia/Australia).  Means ± SD are shown; different letters within columns indicate significant differences ( P &lt; 0.05) between clones.   Average shoot height (A) and shoot elongation rate (B) of four significantly different  P. australis  clones over time.  The clones were propagated from stem nodes of layered shoots and grown in a greenhouse for 119 days. Clones shown in the figure represent  P. australis  from Europe and Asia/Australia and two ploidy levels (4 x  and 8 x ). Data for only four clones are shown to simplify the graphs.  Significant differences in  P  max ,  g  s  and WUE, as well as  F  v / F  m  ratio were found among the clones (Table  3 ). The  P  max  varied from 9.7 µmol CO 2  m −2  s −1  in a hexaploid European clone (E656RO6x) to 27 µmol CO 2  m −2  s −1  in a tetraploid Asiatic clone (A205RU4x). Consistent differences in  P  max  between European and Asiatic/Australian clones, as indicated by the distribution of variance (Table  2 ), could not be directly observed in the data. Two Asiatic clones with high  P  max  values appeared to explain the non-significant difference between the two geographic ranges (Table  3 ). The  g  s  ranged from 0.22 to 1.41 mol m −2  s −1 , and WUE ranged between 13.6 and 47.2 µmol CO 2  mol −1  H 2 O (Table  3 ). The highest and lowest  g  s , and correspondingly lowest and highest WUE, were found in European octoploids (E666CZ8x and E624RO8x). Although significant differences in the  F  v / F  m  ratio were observed among clones, the ratios were relatively constant, i.e. restricted to a range of 0.74–0.82.  Average chlorophyll and carotenoid (Total-Car) concentrations, ratio of Chl  a  to Chl  b , and the Chl  a    +   b   to total carotenoid ratio [( a  +  b )/( x  +  c )] of  P. australis  clones with different ploidy levels, and from two different geographic ranges as indicated by the first letter in the clone name (‘E’, Europe; ‘A’, Asia/Australia).  Means ± SD are shown; different letters within columns indicate significant differences ( P &lt; 0.05) between clones.  Average water-extractable ion concentrations in leaves of  P. australis  clones with different ploidy levels, and from two different geographic ranges as indicated by the first letter in the clone name (‘E’, Europe; ‘A’, Asia/Australia).  Means ± SD are shown; different letters within columns indicate significant differences ( P &lt; 0.05) between clones.  Results of PCA of the 12 measured parameters that differed significantly between the 15  P. australis  clones in the post hoc Tukey test. Factor 1 is a ‘pigment-related factor’, factor 2 a ‘growth-related factor’, factor 3 a ‘monovalent ion-related factor’ and factor 4 a ‘divalent ion-related factor’.  Variables with high loadings are shown in bold.   Factor score plots from a rotated PCA on the measured ecophysiological characteristics of 15  P. australis  clones.  Factor 1 is a ‘pigment-related factor’, factor 2 a ‘growth-related factor’, factor 3 a ‘monovalent ion-related factor’ and factor 4 a ‘divalent ion-related factor’. Red dots represent Asiatic/Australian clones, and white dots European clones. Shaded circles delineate the Asiatic/Australian clones, except for clone A120JP8x. The similarities among the Asiatic/Australian clones do not fully match their phylogeographic relationships, as clone A205RU4x is more closely related to the European group than to the Asiatic/Australian group, whereas clone A120JP8x belongs to the Asiatic/Australian group ( Lambertini  et al . 2006 ).  The aim of this study was to evaluate the extent to which differences in the ploidy level and geographic range within the cosmopolitan grass  P. australis  are reflected in phenotypic traits, such as plant size and ecophysiological characteristics, and if the predominance of octoploids in Asia and Australia could be explained by a superior phenotype that may have evolved within the highly genetically and cytotypically diverse  P. australis  species. Hence, we grew clones of different cytotypes collected in Europe (where 2 n  = 4 x  is the dominant ploidy level) and in Asia and Australia (where octoploids predominate) under identical environmental conditions to avoid environmental effects on phenotype development. Furthermore, the clones had been grown in a common outdoor environment under similar conditions in terms of soil, water, nutrition and climate for at least 5 years prior to the experiment. It is therefore justified to assume that any difference in growth, morphology and physiological characteristics between the clones is genetically determined.  Previous studies have reported significant variations in stand height, plant morphology and salinity tolerance related to the ploidy level ( Hanganu  et al . 1999 ;  Pauca-Comanescu  et al . 1999 ;  Hansen  et al . 2007 ). In the Danube delta, Romania, tetra- (4 x ), hexa- (6 x ) and octoploids (8 x ) co-exist, and tetra- and octoploids can be identified by their phenotype as shoots of octoploids are longer and thicker with more nodes than those of tetraploids, and panicles and leaves of octoploids are also larger than those of tetraploids ( Pauca-Comanescu  et al . 1999 ). Also,  Hansen  et al . (2007)  found that different ploidy levels had different morphologies, with Romanian octoploids generally being taller and thicker than other ploidy levels. In the present study, another Romanian octoploid (E624RO8x) was also among the tallest clones, although not significantly taller than a Russian tetraploid, a Japanese octoploid or an Australian decaploid. Hence, it does not seem to be a general characteristic that octoploids are larger than other ploidy levels. Also, our results did not show any statistically significant differences between ploidy levels. For example, the Czech octoploid (E666CZ8x) was shorter than the corresponding Czech tetraploid (E620CZ4x), and in plants from the Danube delta, where different ploidy levels co-exist, there were no significant differences between the different ploidy levels (E646RO4x, E624RO8x, E625RO6x, E656RO6x and E660RO12x). Although European clones appeared very different in size and ecophysiological traits, the Asiatic and Australian clones were very similar. However, similarities were independent of ploidy level and phylogenetic relationships. Not all Asiatic/Australian clones analysed in the present study belonged to the predominantly octoploid group identified by  Lambertini  et al . (2006) . The clone A205RU4x was genetically closer to the European clones than to the Asian/Australian octoploids, but it did not cluster far from the Asiatic/Australian clones in the PCA. Although other European clones clustered together with the Asiatic/Australian clones, the Japanese octoploid clone clustered far away from its close relatives in Sakhalin Island and Australia, revealing large variation in ecophysiological traits also within the predominantly octoploid group that evolved in Asia and Australia.  Differences among clones could not be explained by the ploidy level, geographic range or phylogenetic relationships, but appeared to be genotype dependent. However, the variation was remarkably higher within the European group of clones than within the Asiatic/Australian group, considering that European clones were from a restricted geographic area (Romania and the Czech Republic), whereas the Asiatic/Australian clones covered a much larger geographic range represented by Sakhalin Island, Japan and Australia.  It has been suggested that growth and expansion rates are a combined effect of genotype and the native environment ( Parker  et al . 2003 ;  Ward  et al . 2008 ). This interaction underlines the possible features of successful invaders, which correlate with the length of the growing season – one of the opportunistic traits of invasive species ( Zedler and Kercher 2004 ). The tetraploids analysed in the present study seemed, in general, to invest predominantly in the first stage of the growing season, with intensive growth in spring to reach the maximum height after 2–3 months. In contrast, growth rates of octoploids were moderate in spring, but growth extended over a longer period of time. This difference in growth pattern suggests that the clones are adapted to growing seasons of different length, and also that tetraploids possess more opportunistic traits than octoploids. Other studies also found differences in the length of the growing season among clones that could be related to the geographic origin of the clones ( Clevering  et al . 2001 ).  The 15  P. australis  clones analysed in this study had high phenotypic variation in  P  max ,  g  s  and WUE. The variations observed were genotype dependent, but they could not be clearly attributed to the ploidy level or to the geographic range of origin. This was due to the high variability between representatives of the same ploidy level and variability between clones from the same geographic range, as well as variation between replicas of the same clone. Although all clones had origins at similar latitudes (lowest 35°, highest 50°) and had been acclimated to the same environment for at least 5 years prior to the experiment, significant differences in  P  max ,  g  s  and WUE were observed between clones. Hence, the clones did not acclimate to the growth environment to the same extent. Physiological processes have earlier been reported to acclimate to new growth environments ( Lessmann  et al . 2001 ). However, the native habitat of the clones and differential expression of photosynthesis-related genes may also be some of the reasons for the observed differences in gas exchange characteristics of the clones we studied. Environmentally induced differences in physiological parameters have been found to be generally larger than the genetically determined differences between populations of  P. australis  ( Lessmann  et al . 2001 ). Since in our experiment the premise of similar environmental conditions is ensured, the differences observed between clones can be assumed to be genetic.  The fact that the concentrations of the light-absorbing chlorophylls did not differ among clones is not surprising since the content of chlorophylls is expected to be rather stable within species under common environmental conditions. However, the observed difference in the Chl  a / b  ratio between the clones indicates variations of the functional pigment complex, as well as possible physiological differences in the photosynthetic apparatus. The concentration of total carotenoids as well as the chlorophyll to carotenoid ratio, [( a + b )/( x  +  c )], also differed among the clones. These differences may be related to differences in environmental conditions and the length of the growing season in the native habitat of the clones, since these parameters are often associated with senescence ( Kurahotta  et al . 1987 ;  Chen and Cao 2008 ).  The concentrations of Cl, Na, K, Ca and Mg in the leaves of the plants also differed significantly among the clones, and the differences could not be related either to the ploidy level or to the geographic origin of the clones. The concentrations of these elements in the leaves may be related to the osmotic balance of the cells, and hence to mechanisms and possible strategies adopted by the clones in stress conditions. A differential ability to regulate ions like Cl −  and Na +  in the plant tissue may be related to differences in salt tolerance ( Lissner and Schierup 1997 ;  Lissner  et al . 1999 ;  Munns and Tester 2008 ;  Pagter  et al . 2009 ) and drought resistance ( Pagter  et al . 2005 ). The significant differences observed here support the hypothesis that stress tolerance in  P. australis  is genotype dependent.  The present study reveals significant genetically determined differences in a range of growth and ecophysiological traits between different  P. australis  genotypes, and provides evidence that the differences are not related either to the ploidy level  per se  or to the phylogeographic relationships of the genotypes. This finding is important in the context of those studies based on just a single genotype or population of a species, as well as studies comparing different species based on only one population of each, as results may have been different if another set of populations was chosen. In addition to the genetically determined differences between the clones, the individual genotypes also showed high phenotypic variation, which further complicates studies with this species. The genotype-related variability in growth and ecophysiological traits may be a consequence of different strategies in relation to particular types of stress that have arisen as a result of selection, and the creation of local ecotypes with associated genetically determined ecophysiological characteristics. Our results broaden insights into the correlation between euploidy and ecophysiological traits within  P. australis , as we found no general relationship. Hence, future studies aimed at explaining differences in plant behaviour need to be careful in the selection of target genotypes and/or populations, and should avoid generalizing their findings beyond the genotypes and/or populations studied.   The Danish Council for Independent Research, Natural Sciences , via a grant to H.B.  L.A. carried out the controlled growth experiment and drafted the manuscript. C.L. and H.B. participated in the design of the study and helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.  None declared.  We thank colleagues who sent  Phragmites  leaves, seeds or rhizomes from different parts of the world to help establish our live  Phragmites  collection. Dr Brian K. Sorrell is thanked for linguistic corrections. 