The behavioural ecology of climbing plantsInduced twining in Convolvulaceae climbing plants in response to leaf damageEffect of water availability on tolerance of leaf damage in tall morning glory, <italic>Ipomoea purpurea</italic>Drought limits induced twining by leaf damage in the climbing plant <italic>Ipomoea purpurea</italic> (L.) Roth (Convolvulaceae)Drought and leaf damage limit the search for support in the climbing plant <italic>Ipomoea purpurea</italic> (L.) Roth (Convolvulaceae)Induced twining in <italic>Ipomoea purpurea</italic> (L.) Roth.: response threshold and induction by volatiles and snail damageLes mouvements d'exploration et d'enroulement des plantes volubilesEarly detection of neighbour plants by phytochrome perception of spectral changes in reflected sunlightAlways on the bright side: the climbing mechanism of <italic>Galium aparine</italic>Twining of the hop (<italic>Humulus lupulus</italic> L.)Liana co-occurrence patterns in a temperate rainforestGelatinous fibers are widespread in coiling tendrils and twining vinesCircumnutations: from Darwin to space flightsThe dynamic nature of antipredator behavior: prey fish integrate threat-sensitive antipredator responses within background levels of predation riskPhylogenetic influence on twining chirality in lianas from Amazonian PeruThe behavioral ecology of nutrient foraging by plantsLianas in a subtropical Atlantic Forest: host preference and tree growthEcological relationships between lianas and trees in lowland rain forest in Sabah, East MalaysiaAbundance of climbing plants in a southern temperate rain forest: host tree characteristics or light availability?Host associations of lianas in a south-east Queensland rain forestVine photosynthesis and relationships to climbing mechanics in a forest understoryClimbing plants in relation to their supports in a stand of dry rainforest in the Hunter Valley, New South WalesOptimal foraging, the marginal value theoremMapping QTL for climbing ability and component traits in common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.)Liana diversity and host relationships in a tropical evergreen forest in the Indian Eastern GhatsThe availability of external support affects allocation patterns and morphology of herbaceous climbing plantsDensity and diversity of lianas along a chronosequence in a central Panamanian lowland forestMinute observations and theoretical framework of Darwin's studies on climbing plantsKin recognition in an annual plantCarbon stocks in tropical forests decrease with liana densityGlobal distribution of root climbers is positively associated with precipitation and negatively associated with seasonalityDistribution and traits of climbing plants in subtropical and temperate South AmericaThe global trend in plant twining directionThe role of time and energy in food preferenceMethyljasmonate and α-linolenic acid are potent inducers of tendril coilingJasmonates and related oxylipins in plant responses to pathogenesis and herbivoryGrowth relationships of leaves and internodes in viny angiosperms with different modes of attachmentExperience teaches plants to learn faster and forget slower in environments where it mattersSubordinate, not dominant, woody species promote the diversity of climbing plantsIs the climbing habit of poison oak ecotypic?The distribution and evolution of climbing plantsHow the cucumber tendril coils and overwindsLife history diversity among six species of canopy lianas in an old-growth forest of the eastern Brazilian AmazonLack of differential plasticity to shading of internodes and petioles with growth habit in <italic>Convolvulus arvensis</italic> (Convolvulaceae)Maternal environmental effects on the phenotypic responses of the twining vine <italic>Ipomoea purpurea</italic> to support availabilityPhenotypic responses of the twining vine <italic>Ipomoea purpurea</italic> (Convolvulaceae) to physical support availability in sun and shadeEvolution of a climbing habit promotes diversification in flowering plantsLeaf mimicry in a climbing plant protects against herbivoryEffect of support availability, mother plant genotype and maternal support environment on the twining vine <italic>Ipomoea purpurea</italic>Leaf damage induces twining in a climbing plantPhenotypic selection on leaf functional traits of two congeneric species in a temperate rainforest is consistent with their shade toleranceInteractive effects of leaf damage, light intensity and support availability on chemical defenses and morphology of a twining vineEcophysiological traits may explain the abundance of climbing plant species across the light gradient in a temperate rainforestLife history trade-offs in tropical trees and lianasDamage and shade enhance climbing and promote associational resistance in a climbing plantMechanics of climbing and attachment in twining plantsVine–host interactionsForaging in plants: the role of morphological plasticity in resource acquisitionWays to test stochastic dynamic programming models empiricallyMoving with climbing plants from Charles Darwin's time into the 21st centuryThe physiology of tendrilsPhysiological studies on pea tendrils. V. Membrane changes and water movement associated with contact coilingApplying behavioral-ecological theory to plant defense: light-dependent movement in <italic>Mimosa pudica</italic> suggests a trade-off between predation risk and energetic rewardHost infestation patterns of the massive liana <italic>Hydrangea serratifolia</italic> (Hydrangeaceae) in a Chilean temperate rainforestPlant behaviour and communicationContext dependence in foraging behaviour of <italic>Achillea millefolium</italic>Responses of <italic>Trachelospermum asiaticum</italic> (Apocynaceae) seedlings to growth in a light intensity gradientShoot circumnutation and winding movements require gravisensing cellsA phytogeographical characterization of the vine flora of the Sonoran and Chihuahuan desertsCircumnutation behavior of an exotic honeysuckle vine and its native congener: influence on clonal mobilityHeteroblastic development in vinesLiana habitat and host preferences in northern temperate forestsStress and decision making under the risk of predation: recent developments from behavioral, reproductive, and ecological perspectivesBehavioral decisions made under the risk of predation: a review and prospectusClimbing strategies determine light availability for both vines and associated structural hostsActin and myosin in pea tendrilsOn optimal use of a patchy environmentMate choice in plants: an anatomical to population perspective<italic>Hedera helix</italic> LCircumnutation in <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>. I. Growth, osmotic potential and cell ultrastructure in the free-moving part of the shootNutation in plantsDiversity and host tree preferences of vascular epiphytes and vines in a temperate rainforest in southern ChileDiversity and distribution of lianas in a neotropical rain forest, Yasuní National Park, EcuadorDo vine species in neotropical forests see the forest or the trees?Smallseed dodder (<italic>Cuscuta planiflora</italic>) phototropism toward far-red when in white lightNotes on the origins of Australian desert vinesMorphological specialization and attachment success in two twining lianasShoot dynamics and adaptive morphology of <italic>Ipomoea phillomega</italic> (Vell.) House (Convolvulaceae), a tropical rainforest lianaIncreasing dominance of large lianas in Amazonian forestsResponse of ivyleaf morning glory (<italic>Ipomoea hederacea</italic>) to neighboring plants and objectsThe effects of physical support and density on biomass production and size hierarchies of <italic>Galium aparine</italic> populationsLianas vs. treesThe natural history of lianas on Barro Colorado Island, PanamaEcological studies of lianas in Lambir National Park, Sarawak, MalaysiaBiomechanical studies of vinesOptimal foraging theory: a critical reviewCounteractive biomass allocation responses to drought and damage in the perennial herb <italic>Convolvulus demissus</italic>Über die VorläuferspitzeCyclic heterophylly in <italic>Syngonium</italic> (Araceae)Foraging behaviour in tropical herbaceous climbers (Araceae)Peut-on expliquer les mouvements dirigés des végétaux?Diversity of mechanical architectures in climbing plants: an evolutionary perspectiveVines in arid and semi-arid ecosystemsVolatile chemical cues guide host location and host selection by parasitic plantsNatural selection on ecophysiological traits of a fern species in a temperate rainforestInsect herbivory in climber-host shrubs associations: benefit or detriment?Temporal and spatial patterns of twining force and lignification in stems of <italic>Ipomoea purpurea</italic>The ecology of lianas and their role in forestsIncreasing liana abundance and biomass in tropical forests: emerging patterns and putative mechanismsGreater morphological plasticity of exotic honeysuckle species may make them better invaders than native speciesThe importance of frictional interactions in maintaining the stability of the twining habitAxial forces and normal distributed loads in twining stems of morning gloryStandardized support to measure biomass and fruit production by the invasive climber (<italic>Asparagus asparagoides</italic>)Quantifying the attachment strength of climbing plants: a new approachCircumnutation as a visible plant action and reactionHost tree location behavior of a tropical vine (<italic>Monstera gigantea</italic>) by skototropismHost associations of two adventitious-root-climbing vines in a North Queensland tropical rain forestPhysiological ecology of mesic, temperate woody vinesLe comportement des vrilles en présence de tuteursSuite de nos observations sur le comportement des vrilles en présence de tuteursClimbing plants in a temperate rainforest understorey: searching for high light or coping with deep shade?Infestation of trees by lianas in a tropical forest in Amazonian PeruJasmonate-signalled plant gene expressionEvidence for the involvement of jasmonates and their octadecanoid precursors in the tendril coiling response of <italic>Bryonia dioica</italic>The probability of attack and patterns of constitutive and induced defense: a test of optimal defense theory<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> James F. CahillThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Climbing plants require an external support to grow vertically and thus achieve better access to sunlight. Climbing plants that find a suitable support have greater performance, size and reproduction than those that remain prostrate. Plant behaviour involves rapid morphological or physiological responses to events or environmental changes. Theoretical frameworks from behavioural ecology, traditionally applied to animals, have been successfully used to study plant behaviour. I herein review studies addressing ecological causes and consequences of support finding and use by climbing plants. I also propose the use of behavioural ecology theoretical frameworks to study climbing plant behaviour.Climbing plants require an external support to grow vertically and enhance light acquisition. Vines that find a suitable support have greater performance and fitness than those that remain prostrate. Therefore, the location of a suitable support is a key process in the life history of climbing plants. Numerous studies on climbing plant behaviour have elucidated mechanistic details of support searching and attachment. Far fewer studies have addressed the ecological significance of support-finding behaviour and the factors that affect it. Without this knowledge, little progress can be made in the understanding of the evolution of support-finding behaviour in climbers. Here I review studies addressing ecological causes and consequences of support finding and use by climbing plants. I also propose the use of behavioural ecology theoretical frameworks to study climbing plant behaviour. I show how host tree attributes may determine the probability of successful colonization for the different types of climbers, and examine the evidence of environmental and genetic control of circumnutation behaviour and phenotypic responses to support availability. Cases of oriented vine growth towards supports are highlighted. I discuss functional responses of vines to the interplay between herbivory and support availability under different abiotic environments, illustrating with one study case how results comply with a theoretical framework of behavioural ecology originally conceived for animals. I conclude stressing that climbing plants are suitable study subjects for the application of behavioural–ecological theory. Further research under this framework should aim at characterizing the different stages of the support-finding process in terms of their fit with the different climbing modes and environmental settings. In particular, cost–benefit analysis of climbing plant behaviour should be helpful to infer the selective pressures that have operated to shape current climber ecological communities.Climbing plants need to attach themselves to an external support—typically neighbouring plants—in order to grow vertically to a significant extent and enhance light acquisition. Trellis availability influences climber diversity in forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C40">Garbin <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>), and climbers that fail to encounter a trellis often show reduced growth and/or reproduction compared with those successfully climbing onto an external support. This has been observed in forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C96">Putz 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C118">Stansbury <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>), open habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C46">Gianoli 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C93">Price and Wilcut 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C56">González-Teuber and Gianoli 2008</xref>) and controlled environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C94">Puntieri and Pyšek 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C115">Schweitzer and Larson 1999</xref>). Support finding not only involves enhanced fitness but also triggers changes in growth form, biomass allocation, morphology and physiology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C102">Raciborski 1900</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C63">Jaffe and Galston 1968<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C121">Strong and Ray 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C103">Ray 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C94">Puntieri and Pyšek 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C27">den Dubbelden and Oosterbeek 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C45">Gianoli 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C47">2003</xref>). Therefore, the location (and colonization) of a suitable support is a key process in the life history of climbing plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C58">Hegarty 1991</xref>).Darwin's observations on the oscillatory movements of exploring stems and tendrils (circumnutation) somehow founded the field of climbing plant behaviour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin 1875</xref>). Since then, a plethora of studies on climbing plant behaviour with regard to support searching and attachment have elucidated mechanistic details at the anatomical, biomechanical, physiological and cellular levels (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C124">Tronchet 1945</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C125">1946</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C6">Baillaud 1962</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C63">Jaffe and Galston 1968<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C83">Millet <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C117">Silk and Hubbard 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C12">Brown 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C130">Weiler <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C111">Scher <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C70">Kitazawa <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C116">Silk and Holbrook 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C57">Goriely and Neukirch 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C11">Bowling and Vaughn 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C120">Stolarz 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C119">Steinbrecher <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C8">Bauer <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C43">Gerbode <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). However, far fewer studies have addressed the ecological significance of support-finding behaviour in climbing plants and the factors that affect it (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C90">Peñalosa 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C73">Larson 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C51">Gianoli and Molina-Montenegro 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C56">González-Teuber and Gianoli 2008</xref>). Without this knowledge, limited progress can be made in the understanding of the evolution of support-finding behaviour in climbers. Here, I review studies that have addressed ecological causes and consequences of support location and use by climbing plants. I also propose the use of behavioural ecology theoretical frameworks to study climbing plant behaviour. The article focusses mainly on twining plants, but also considers cases from plants having the other two ‘active’ modes of attachment: tendrils and adhesive roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin 1875</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C62">Isnard and Silk 2009</xref>).Several host tree attributes may determine the probability of colonization by climbers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C58">Hegarty 1991</xref>). The size (diameter) of supports influences their suitability for twining plants. Specifically, both theoretical and empirical approaches show that when support diameter increases beyond some point twining plants are unable to maintain tensional forces and therefore lose attachment to the trellis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C96">Putz 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C57">Goriely and Neukirch 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C18">Carrasco-Urra and Gianoli 2009</xref>). That these plants have problems to twine round a thick support was already pointed out by Darwin, citing Hugo von Mohl's observations and reporting his own experiments with shoots of the twining vine <italic>Wisteria sinensis</italic> (Sims) Sweet, which could not climb onto a support nearly 15 cm wide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin 1875</xref>). Field studies in tropical, subtropical and temperate rainforests confirm that the relative abundance of stem twiners decreases with increasing tree diameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C96">Putz 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C97">Putz and Chai 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C19">Carsten <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C18">Carrasco-Urra and Gianoli 2009</xref>). In a tropical rainforest, 90 % of stem twiners individuals with a diameter at breast height (dbh) of ≤1 cm grew on trees with a dbh of ≤8 cm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C86">Nabe-Nielsen 2001</xref>). The support-size biomechanical constraints for twining plants are intermediate compared with tendril climbers, whose upper limit of usable trunk diameter is even lower, and root climbers, which are not constrained at all by large support diameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C96">Putz 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C97">Putz and Chai 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C21">Chalmers and Turner 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C28">DeWalt <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C86">Nabe-Nielsen 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C18">Carrasco-Urra and Gianoli 2009</xref>). There is also a significant variation in the range of suitable support diameters within a given climbing mode. Thus, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C90">Peñalosa (1982)</xref> studied two twining lianas that differed in their degree of morphological specialization (shoot architecture) and found differential success rate of attachment across the population of support diameters in a tropical rainforest. As expected, vines may modify their climbing behaviour when twining around supports of different diameters. Thus, the ascent angle decreased with increasing support diameter in <italic>Humulus lupulus</italic> L. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C9">Bell 1958</xref>) and <italic>Dioscorea bulbifera</italic> L. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C111">Scher <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>), but the radius of curvature of the twining vine helix was unaffected. It has been suggested that the climber's coils lose stability when the radius of curvature of the helix is no longer greater than the support radius (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>).Circumnutation behaviour and phenotypic responses to support availability, which may determine the suitable range of support sizes, should show—at least to some extent—environmental and genetic control. It has been shown that the shrub vs. vine growth forms in <italic>Toxicodendron diversilobum</italic> (Torr. &amp; A.Gray) Greene are determined environmentally, mainly by support availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C41">Gartner 1991</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin (1875)</xref> noted that the twining vine <italic>Phaseolus coccineus</italic> L. failed to twine round sticks 8–10 cm in diameter when tested in a room with lateral light but the vines succeeded when placed outdoors. He further remarked that twiners from the tropics, or from warmer temperate regions, seemingly are able to ascend thicker trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin 1875</xref>). Whether twining plants from warmer habitats are better endowed to exploit thick supports is yet to be demonstrated, and should be addressed with a phylogeny-wise analysis since environment and species may be confounded factors. Interestingly, a recent study comparing climbing plants from temperate and subtropical South America found that a greater proportion of twiners occur in the subtropical, warmer area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C33">Durigon <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). With regard to genetic variation, there is some evidence of differences in circumnutation behaviour and morphological plasticity in response to support availability between congeneric twining vines tested in a common environment (<italic>Convolvulus</italic> spp. and <italic>Ipomoea</italic> spp., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C1">Atala and Gianoli 2008</xref>; <italic>Lonicera</italic> spp., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C115">Schweitzer and Larson 1999</xref>). However, at the within-species level, the maternal family did not influence phenotypic responses to support availability in <italic>I. purpurea</italic> (L.) Roth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C50">Gianoli and González-Teuber 2005</xref>). The quantitative trait loci controlling climbing ability have been identified in a recombinant inbred line of common bean, and most of these loci were found on the lower half of a given linkage group, suggesting the existence of a major pleiotropic locus controlling the climbing habit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C23">Checa and Blair 2008</xref>). Experiments with mutants of <italic>I. nil</italic> (L.) Roth have demonstrated a link between circumnutation and gravisensing cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C70">Kitazawa <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>).Tree features such as bark roughness and flakiness may also influence support use by climbers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C95">Putz 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C96">1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C97">Putz and Chai 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C17">Campbell and Newbery 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C122">Talley <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C19">Carsten <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C16">Campanello <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C128">van der Heijden <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Bark flakiness has been considered an adaptation of trees against liana infestation, assuming that lianas may be unable to climb trees with rapidly shed bark because it implies loosing points of anchorage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C122">Talley <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C19">Carsten <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). However, field evidence suggests that liana infestation is not particularly deterred in tree species that shed bark frequently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C19">Carsten <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C18">Carrasco-Urra and Gianoli 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C66">Jiménez-Castillo and Lusk 2009</xref>): climbers somehow manage to use as supports trees with peeling bark. On the other hand, the frequency of stem twiners in a rainforest did increase with bark roughness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C19">Carsten <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). Interestingly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin (1875)</xref> observed in kidney beans that the stem's axial twisting increased with support roughness, thus suggesting that twisted stems might be more rigid and that it could be advantageous to deal with rugged supports. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C116">Silk and Holbrook (2005)</xref> showed that the torsion of the twining stem was determined by helical parameters that vary with support diameter.Successful climbing by twining vines not only may help avoid shading by co-occurring taller plants, but also may place climbers beyond ground herbivores. There is field evidence that prostrate, unsupported vines suffer more herbivore damage than plants climbing onto neighbouring vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C51">Gianoli and Molina-Montenegro 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C56">González-Teuber and Gianoli 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C49">Gianoli and Carrasco-Urra 2014</xref>). Moreover, within a forest community, the identity of the supporting tree to which the climber is associated influences herbivore damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C110">Sasal and Suárez 2011</xref>; E. Gianoli and F. Carrasco-Urra, unpubl. data). In agreement with a hypothesis of adaptive climbing behaviour, it has been shown that circumnutation behaviour, measured as the twining rate on experimental supports, was enhanced in several Convolvulaceae vines receiving leaf damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C51">Gianoli and Molina-Montenegro 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C1">Atala and Gianoli 2008</xref>). This induced twining—compared with undamaged plants—did not result from increased stem growth rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C51">Gianoli and Molina-Montenegro 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C1">Atala and Gianoli 2008</xref>), which somewhat challenges the notion that circumnutation is intrinsically a growth movement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C84">Mugnai <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). In <italic>C. arvensis</italic> L. the induced twining occurred similarly in both sun and shade conditions, and it was paralleled by an increase in photosynthetic rate, but only under shade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C51">Gianoli and Molina-Montenegro 2005</xref>). This suggests that enhanced twining under low light entails an extra demand for resources by these vines. When stems of the twiner <italic>C. chilensis</italic> Pers. were clipped mimicking rabbit grazing in a semiarid shrubland, there was an increased production of tendril-like lateral stems that facilitated climbing in shade conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C56">González-Teuber and Gianoli 2008</xref>). This phenomenon granted protection against herbivores by promoting the association with nurse plants (cacti and thorny shrubs); interestingly, such induction of tendril-like stems following damage only occurred in the shade, which is a cue of the presence of the nurse plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C56">González-Teuber and Gianoli 2008</xref>). Induced twining was also observed in <italic>I. purpurea</italic> after subjecting plants to folivory by snails as well as to exposure to conspecific volatiles (released from ground leaves) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C5">Atala <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). In summary, the described phenomena of climbing plant behaviour in response to herbivory and abiotic conditions are likely to occur in natural ecological communities.The exogenous application of jasmonic acid, a ubiquitous mediator of defensive responses in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C129">Wasternack and Parthier 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C37">Farmer <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>), caused induced twining in <italic>I. purpurea</italic> as did leaf damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C1">Atala and Gianoli 2008</xref>). This could be a rather general response, as the application of jasmonate on the climbing plant <italic>Bryonia dioica</italic> caused tendril coiling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C36">Falkenstein <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C130">Weiler <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>). With regard to abiotic regulation of the phenomenon, water stress had contrasting effects on induced twining (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C4">Atala <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). On the one hand, moderate drought, which increases trichome density on stems of <italic>I. purpurea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C2">Atala and Gianoli 2009<italic>a</italic></xref>), enhanced the twining response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C4">Atala <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). This result is consistent with the finding that trichomes facilitate climbing in this species as they function like ratchets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C116">Silk and Holbrook 2005</xref>), which are analogous to hooks used by some climbing plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C8">Bauer <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). On the other hand, severe water stress limited the induced twining in <italic>I. purpurea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C3">Atala and Gianoli 2009<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C4">Atala <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), probably because extreme drought elicits plant responses that counteract phenotypic responses to herbivory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C101">Quezada and Gianoli 2010</xref>).Going back to the issue of the helical geometry of twining vines, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin (1875)</xref> noted that the terminal internodes made first a close spire, securing plant attachment during windy conditions, but the following spires were more open. This agrees with observations that a loosely coiled, old vine segment can be sustained by one or two tight younger coils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>). It is also consistent with biomechanical experiments showing that forces pulling down a twining vine will tend to stabilize the plant–support interaction (i.e. the normal load exerted by the vine towards the support increases linearly with axial downward tension), unless the forces are applied close to the vine tip, because the twining vine is weak in compression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C116">Silk and Holbrook 2005</xref>). Thus, grazing herbivores pulling down the climbing plant would not succeed: they would tear the vine before getting it to slip down. Interestingly, when documenting induced twining in <italic>Ipomoea</italic> vines, it was observed that leaf damage mimicking insect herbivory caused a reduction in the angle of ascent within the first three gyres in all tested species (<italic>I. purpurea</italic>, <italic>I. tricolor</italic> Cav., <italic>I. nil</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C1">Atala and Gianoli 2008</xref>). Thus, vines respond to leaf damage as if they were twining around a thicker support (see above). Whether reduced angles of ascent in twiners translate into enhanced appression of the support remains to be tested, but related evidence suggests the opposite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C117">Silk and Hubbard 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C111">Scher <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>).From an adaptive standpoint, an expected feature of climbing plant behaviour is that vines should be able to locate their supports and grow towards them. After conducting several simple experiments indoors, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin (1875)</xref> concluded that tendrils of <italic>Bignonia capreolata</italic> L. actively grow towards the dark, a phenomenon he later termed ‘apheliotropism’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C26">Darwin 1880</xref>). He remarked that circumnutation in these tendrils was extremely irregular, often staying static, that the apheliotropic movement was a modified circumnutation, and that this vine depended on apheliotropism to find tree trunks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C26">Darwin 1880</xref>). One century later, experiments by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C121">Strong and Ray (1975)</xref> in a tropical forest showed that seedlings of the root climber <italic>Monstera tenuis</italic> K.Koch are attracted to the darkness, which is associated with the trees in the forest, and coined the term ‘skototropism’. Importantly, once the tree is found, the vine switches back and starts growing towards light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C121">Strong and Ray 1975</xref>). Most documented cases of skototropism correspond to root climbers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C103">Ray 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C58">Hegarty 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C82">Metcalfe 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C69">Kato <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>), but tendril-bearers can also exhibit this support-finding behaviour. Thus, apart from <italic>B. capreolata</italic> and its skototropic tendrils described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin (1875)</xref>, it has been reported that <italic>Dolichandra unguis-cati</italic> (L.) L.G.Lohmann (another Bignoniaceae) shows intra-plant variation in light response: the claw-like tendrils are skototropic and the shoot tips are positively phototropic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C74">Lee and Richards 1991</xref>).The above-described cases somewhat lend support to earlier claims that some climbing plants, including tendril-bearers (<italic>Cyclanthera pedata</italic> (L.) Schrad.) and stem twiners (<italic>Cuscuta gronovii</italic> Willd. ex Roem. &amp; Schult.), were able to change their circumnutation patterns in order to reach support targets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C125">Tronchet 1946</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C126">1977</xref>); these reports were received with a degree of scepticism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C105">Roussel 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>). In the case of <italic>Cuscuta</italic> there is now solid evidence that these parasitic vines locate their host plants via oriented growth. Thus, experiments have proved that <italic>Cuscuta</italic> <italic>pentagona</italic> Engelm. seedlings grow towards regions of lowered red : far-red radiation ratio (a signal of the presence of chlorophyll-bearing organisms, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C7">Ballaré <italic>et al</italic>. 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C88">Orr <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>), and that they can locate host plants in the dark following volatile chemical cues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C108">Runyon <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). The evolution of this highly specialized host location behaviour presumably results from strong selective pressures related to the parasitic lifestyle because, in order to survive, <italic>Cuscuta</italic> seedlings must attach to a host plant shortly after emergence; otherwise their energy reserves are exhausted. Thus, in a greenhouse experiment with autotrophic <italic>Ipomoea</italic> species there was no correlation between the red : far-red ratio in coloured stakes or corn plants and the frequency of vines twining around them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C93">Price and Wilcut 2007</xref>).Do community-level studies support the notion that climbers do not find support/hosts merely by chance? A number of field studies, conducted in almost all forest types, have shown associations between climbing plant species and tree species that are statistically different from what would be expected by chance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C58">Hegarty 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C17">Campbell and Newbery 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C21">Chalmers and Turner 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C122">Talley <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C24">Chittibabu and Parthasarathy 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C19">Carsten <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C85">Muñoz <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C87">Nesheim and Økland 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C75">Leicht-Young <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C10">Blick and Burns 2011</xref>). Consequently, host selection or host specificity has often been invoked to explain these patterns. An alternative explanation could consider the occurrence of convergence in microsite preference between vines and trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C10">Blick and Burns 2011</xref>). Apart from the tree traits possibly explaining differential susceptibility to vine infestation, the underlying mechanisms or the adaptive value of these patterns are rarely reported or discussed. This information is needed in order to determine the reliability and ecological significance of field patterns.A central question that could be asked is whether vines actually make ‘decisions’ when it comes to support searching and selection. Apart from the evidence of oriented growth towards trees or experimental stakes discussed above, it could be added that climbing plants may reject a particular support. This was first described by Darwin for tendrils in <italic>B. capreolata</italic> initially seizing but then loosing sticks that were inappropriate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin 1875</xref>). A similar phenomenon is observed when herbaceous twining vines get in contact with a very thick trunk and wind up on themselves instead of attempting to twine around it (a hopeless try, in view of the diameter constraints discussed above). In the case of annual vines, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin (1875)</xref> remarked that, even without support diameter constraints, it would be maladaptive to twine around thick—and hence large—trees, as these vines would hardly reach high-light layers by the end of the growing season.The ‘self-twining’ (i.e. vine stems twining around each other) often occurs when vines grow beyond the height of a short support and then go up and down it, or when they fail to encounter a suitable support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin 1875</xref>). What is the adaptive value of self-twining? To keep on circumnutating seems to be meaningless as new available supports would rarely appear, it would be energy-consuming, and—for a given species—circumnutation's range cannot be extended beyond some point because of biomechanical constraints: the diameters of circumnutation by shoot tips range from a few centimetres to over 1 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>). Ideally, twining vines should have a dual system, with trailing, skototropic stems searching for supports in addition to (or giving rise to) circumnutating stems. However, the closest known case did not prove efficient in this regard. Thus, the twining liana <italic>I. phillomega</italic> (Vell.) House produces creeping shoots (stolons) with high elongation rates under shade conditions, while twining shoots are produced in high-light conditions; but stolons did not switch to twining stems once support was found (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C91">Peñalosa 1983</xref>). A more efficient strategy is deployed by <italic>Syngonium</italic> root climbers, where a slender, skototropic prostrate stem searches for supports across the forest floor, but if a tree is not found after ∼2 m of extension (∼30 internodes), the plant reverts to the original, ‘sessile’ rosette form; the shoot alternates indefinitely between both forms until a tree is located (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C103">Ray 1987</xref>). Overall, climbers rarely show such functional division of labour among orthotropic (vertical) and plagiotropic (horizontal) shoots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C73">Larson 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C45">Gianoli 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C127">Valladares <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Some climbing plants seem to have a ‘give-up’ time concerning support finding. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin (1875)</xref> found that the twining hop (<italic>H. lupulus</italic>) stopped circumnutation after 5 days (37 revolutions) failing to find a support. Likewise, when the tip of a prostrate shoot of the climber <italic>Lonicera sempervirens</italic> touches the ground, circumnutation stops; it may resume after continued growth, but often in a different compass direction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C73">Larson 2000</xref>). Long-lived species may have further chances: if searcher shoots of some lianas in a tropical rainforest fail to find a support, they fall over and are replaced by another shoot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C96">Putz 1984</xref>).Plant behaviour involves rapid morphological or physiological responses to events or environmental changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C67">Karban 2008</xref>). Theoretical frameworks from behavioural ecology, traditionally applied to animals, have been successfully used to study plant behaviour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C81">Marshall and Folsom 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C30">Dudley and File 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C15">Cahill and McNickle 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C65">Jensen <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C68">Karst <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C39">Gagliano <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). Climbing plants have shown patterns of herbivory-induced chemical defences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C53">Gianoli <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>) that conform to optimal defence theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C131">Zangerl and Rutledge 1996</xref>). However, theoretical approaches from behavioural ecology have not been applied to the study of climbing plant behaviour. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C104">Ray (1992)</xref> described what he termed foraging behaviour in tropical Araceae climbers, characterizing shoot developmental patterns (length and diameter of internodes) in both trailing and climbing stems through the forest. In general terms, foraging behaviour in plants refers to their capacity of placing resource-acquiring structures (leaves and root tips) selectively within their habitat, where essential resources are usually heterogeneously distributed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C60">Hutchings and De Kroon 1994</xref>). In the case of climbing plants, support finding brings about enhanced access to light resources (see above), but only then vines should fully display resource-acquiring structures. Accordingly, leaf expansion is delayed relative to stem extension in erect leader shoots of twiners and tendril climbers, thereby reducing stem load and facilitating support searching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C102">Raciborski 1900</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C6">Baillaud 1962</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C38">French 1977</xref>). Field observations indicate that the maximum length these leafless leader shoots can attain before falling over (‘searcher shoot length’, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C96">Putz 1984</xref>) is species specific and largely determines the distance a climber can traverse between supports in the forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C96">Putz 1984</xref>). The capacity to span between supports is very important for the ecology of vines; however, to my knowledge, no study has specifically addressed phenotypic plasticity or evolutionary responses in searcher shoot length. In the following discussion of theoretical approaches to climbing plant behaviour, I will focus on foraging behaviour, specifically with regard to support searching.Anti-predator behaviour, measured as leaf alkaloid concentration (= density of points), and foraging behaviour, measured as internode length, in <italic>C. arvensis</italic> vines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C53">Gianoli <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). Experimental plants were subjected to a factorial array of light availability (sun vs. shade) and support availability (climbing vs. prostrate vines). Field data indicate that predation (herbivory) risk is much higher on prostrate vines. Results verified the hypothesis that vines should show reduced anti-predator behaviour and increased foraging in the shade (fewer resources available). This agrees with animal-derived theory that posits that individuals are more willing to take predation risks during foraging when energetically stressed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C76">Lima 1998</xref>).Optimality models based on economic decisions have long been used to study animal foraging behaviour (Optimal Foraging theory; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C35">Emlen 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C80">MacArthur and Pianka 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C22">Charnov 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C100">Pyke 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C71">Krebs and Davies 1993</xref>) and may well be used to better understand climbing plant behaviour. In fact, Darwin, after concluding that—unlike tendrils—twining stems are not irritable, pointed out that it was not expected ‘as nature always economizes her means, and irritability would have been superfluous’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin 1875</xref>); this alludes to an optimality approach. The value of Darwin's analogies between plant strategies and economic concepts has been highlighted earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C29">Drouin and Deroin 2010</xref>).The hypothetical optimal tree size for vines (tree size includes both tree diameter and height) should vary with the climbing mechanism: tendril-bearers, stem twiners and root climbers. Benefits (∼ energy values) are assumed to increase with tree height because light harvest by climbing plants increases with height; the curve is further assumed to flatten out because most vines are not able to climb up to the top of canopy trees. Costs (∼ handling times) increase with tree diameter particularly for tendril-bearers and stem twiners because of biomechanical constraints: they fail to attach to thick trunks (see text); root climbers are free from this constraint but costs are assumed to increase slightly in very thick trunks—and hence old trees—because of the expected greater competition with other vines or epiphytes. Therefore, the optimal tree size, determined at the maximum distance between the cost and benefit curves, should be largest for root climbers and smallest for tendril-bearers.Components of support value (∼ prey profitability) for climbing plants may show a trade-off because of the intrinsic association between tree diameter and tree height (dashed line). Thin trees are easy to climb (low handling time) but result in short heights (low energy value), while the opposite occurs for thick trees. Highest and lowest support values are shown in blue and red, respectively.All support's components taken together (energy value, handling time and search time) could lead to predictions of ‘favourite’ ecosystems for particular vine forms or species, and forest types and/or successional stages appear as good predictors of such differential suitability. There are some general patterns described in the literature, such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C33">Durigon <italic>et al</italic>. (2014</xref>), but functional explanations are wanting. For instance, root climbers are not constrained by thick tree trunks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C98">Putz and Holbrook 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C18">Carrasco-Urra and Gianoli 2009</xref>), often show an efficient searching strategy for shaded habitats: skototropism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C58">Hegarty 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C74">Lee and Richards 1991</xref>), but their attachment to trees should be challenged in open and dry habitats because adventitious roots may suffer desiccation at high irradiances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C20">Carter and Teramura 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C123">Teramura <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>). Therefore, it was no surprise to find that, globally, root climbers were more frequent in forests with greater precipitation and reduced seasonality, and that increasing temperature reduced root-climber occurrence in tropical sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C32">Durigon <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>).Climbing plants account for a significant component of plant evolution, diversity and abundance and play a major role in forest communities and ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C99">Putz and Mooney 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C112">Schnitzer and Bongers 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C48">Gianoli 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C31">Durán and Gianoli 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C114">Schnitzer <italic>et al</italic>. 2015</xref>). Moreover, the relative abundance of woody climbers is increasing in tropical forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C92">Phillips <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C113">Schnitzer and Bongers 2011</xref>) and several of the most aggressive invasive plants worldwide are vines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C59">Holm <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>). Therefore, from several different standpoints it is of paramount importance to understand the ecological factors and physiological mechanisms that determine the vines' successful use of neighbouring vegetation as support.In this overview I have identified main issues of climbing plant behaviour, most of them tracing back to Darwin's seminal observations, which deserve further ecological inquiry. Other aspects of climbing plant behaviour, such as patterns of twining handedness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C25">Darwin 1875</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C34">Edwards <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C14">Burnham and Revilla-Minaya 2011</xref>) or support-finding benefits in desert vines, which grow in environments where light availability is not limiting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C107">Rundel and Franklin 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C72">Krings 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C89">Parsons 2006</xref>), still wait for ecological explanations.I have shown that climbing plants are suitable study subjects for the application of behavioural–ecological theory. Optimality models are particularly useful because they often provide testable, quantitative predictions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C71">Krebs and Davies 1993</xref>). Further research under this theoretical framework should aim at characterizing the different stages of the support-finding process (search time, handling time) in terms of (i) their fit with the different climbing modes and environmental settings and (ii) their association with plant fitness. In particular, cost–benefit analysis of climbing plant behaviour should be helpful to infer the selective pressures that have operated to shape current climber ecological communities (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C106">Rowe <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). This should be followed by phenotypic selection analyses of field data and the determination of the genetic basis of the key plant traits (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C109">Saldaña <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV013C52">Gianoli and Saldaña 2013</xref>) in order to understand their potential for evolutionary responses.The study was supported by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">FONDECYT</grant-sponsor> (<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Fondo Nacional de Desarrollo Científico y Tecnológico—Chile</grant-sponsor>) grant <grant-num xlink:type="simple">1140070</grant-num>.None declared.I thank J. C. Cahill for the invitation to contribute to this special issue and F. E. Putz for thoughtful comments that significantly improved an earlier version of the manuscript.