Soil microbial community variation correlates most strongly with plant species identity, followed by soil chemistry, spatial location and plant genusPhylogenetic conservatism in plant-soil feedback and its implications for plant abundanceThe role of root exudates in rhizosphere interactions with plants and other organismsPlant species and nitrogen effects on soil biological properties of temperate upland grasslandsIdentifying spatial relationships at multiple scales: principal coordinates of neighbour matrices (PCNM) and geostatistical approachesPlant species and soil type cooperatively shape the structure and function of microbial communities in the rhizosphereRooting theories of plant community ecology in microbial interactionsPhylogeny and provenance affect plant–soil feedbacks in invaded California grasslandsCoevolution of roots and mycorrhizas of land plantsMolecular analysis of bacterial communities associated with the roots of Douglas fir (<italic>Pseudotsuga menziesii</italic>) colonized by different ectomycorrhizal fungiSoil fungi influence the distribution of microbial functional groups that mediate forest greenhouse gas emissionsMore closely related species are more ecologically similar in an experimental testPatterns in root trait variation among 25 co-existing North American forest speciesPlant growth-promoting bacteria in the rhizo- and endosphere of plants: their role, colonization, mechanisms involved and prospects for utilizationQuantifying phylogenetically structured environmental variationAn eigenvector method for estimating phylogenetic inertiaOn the selection of phylogenetic eigenvectors for ecological analysesMUSCLE: a multiple sequence alignment method with reduced time and space complexityMUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughputFeedback in the plant-soil systemSpatial soil ecologyCompositional dissimilarity as a robust measure of ecological distanceThe diversity and biogeography of soil bacterial communitiesPredicting microbial distributions in space and timeCross-biome metagenomic analyses of soil microbial communities and their functional attributesGeneralized collinearity diagnosticsDisentangling the phylogenetic and ecological components of spider phenotypic variationProperties of bacterial endophytes and their proposed role in plant growthThe impacts of individual plant species on rhizosphere microbial communities in soils of different fertilityAnalysis of network architecture reveals phylogenetic constraints on mycorrhizal specificity in the genus <italic>Orchis</italic> (Orchidaceae)Mycorrhizal response to experimental pH and P manipulation in acidic hardwood forestsPlant-soil feedbacks: a meta-analytical reviewPyrosequencing-based assessment of soil pH as a predictor of soil bacterial community structure at the continental scaleInteractions between ecto-mycorrhizal and saprotrophic fungiExperimental evidence for a phylogenetic Janzen-Connell effect in a subtropical forestGenes and signals in the Rhizobium-legume symbiosisPlant functional traits and phylogenetic relatedness explain variation in associations with root fungal endophytes in an extreme arid environmentRoot morphological-characteristics of host species having distinct mycorrhizal dependencyThe role of epiphytism in architecture and evolutionary constraint within mycorrhizal networks of tropical orchidsRelatedness is a poor predictor of negative plant-soil feedbacksA caution regarding rules of thumb for variance inflation factorsThe nineteenth century roots of ‘everything is everywhere’Variation partitioning of species data matrices: estimation and comparison of fractionsTesting the limits of 454 pyrotag sequencing: reproducibility, quantitative assessment and comparison to T-RFLP fingerprinting of aquifer microbesMore closely related plants have more distinct mycorrhizal communitiesPredicting plant responses to mycorrhizae: integrating evolutionary history and plant traitsphytools: an R package for phylogenetic comparative biology (and other things)Interactions between exotic invasive plants and soil microbes in the rhizosphere suggest that ‘everything is not everywhere’Root-secreted malic acid recruits beneficial soil bacteriar8s: inferring absolute rates of molecular evolution and divergence times in the absence of a molecular clockUnravelling rhizosphere–microbial interactions: opportunities and limitationsMEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methodsA first comprehensive census of fungi in soil reveals both hyperdiversity and fine-scale niche partitioningVariations in the soil microbial community composition of a tropical montane forest ecosystem: does tree species matter?Fine root morphology is phylogenetically structured, but nitrogen is related to the plant economics spectrum in temperate treesEvolution of the angiosperms: calibrating the family tree<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> James F. CahillThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Soil ecologists have debated the relative importance of dispersal limitation ("everything" is not "everywhere") and ecological factors in determining the structure of soil microbial communities. The relative explanatory power of spatial and ecological factors, including plant species identity and even plant relatedness, for different fractions of the soil microbial community (i.e. bacterial and fungal communities) are poorly understood. We sampled field soils in a northern California field site, and find that soil microbial community variation correlates most strongly with plant species identity, followed by soil chemistry, spatial location and plant genus.Soil ecologists have debated the relative importance of dispersal limitation and ecological factors in determining the structure of soil microbial communities. Recent evidence suggests that ‘everything is not everywhere’, and that microbial communities are influenced by both dispersal limitation and ecological factors. However, we still do not understand the relative explanatory power of spatial and ecological factors, including plant species identity and even plant relatedness, for different fractions of the soil microbial community (i.e. bacterial and fungal communities). To ask whether factors such as plant species, soil chemistry, spatial location and plant relatedness influence rhizosphere community composition, we examined field-collected rhizosphere soil of seven congener pairs that occur at Bodega Bay Marine Reserve, CA, USA. We characterized differences in bacterial and fungal communities using terminal-restriction fragment length polymorphism. Plant species identity was the single best statistical predictor of both bacterial and fungal community composition in the root zone. Soil microbial community structure was also correlated with soil chemistry. The third best predictor of bacterial and fungal communities was spatial location, confirming that everything is not everywhere. Variation in microbial community composition was also related to combinations of spatial location, soil chemistry and plant relatedness, suggesting that these factors do not act independently. Plant relatedness explained less of the variation than plant species, soil chemistry, or spatial location. Despite some congeners occupying different habitats and being spatially distant, rhizosphere fungal communities of plant congeners were more similar than expected by chance. Bacterial communities from the same samples were only weakly similar between plant congeners. Thus, plant relatedness might influence soil fungal, more than soil bacterial, community composition.The study of microbial community structure has long centred around the debate between the hypothesis that ‘everything is everywhere’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C4">Bass Becking 1934</xref>), and the alternative that dispersal limitation influences microbial community structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C44">O'Malley 2007</xref>). Because the soil microbial community is diverse, heterogeneous and difficult to characterize (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C54">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>), understanding the environmental correlates of soil microbial communities has lagged behind community ecology studies in other systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C24">Fierer and Ladau 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C25">Fierer <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Thus the relative explanatory powers of ecological factors (e.g. plant species identity, soil chemistry and plant relatedness) and dispersal limitation (i.e. spatial location) for determining soil microbial communities are not well characterized (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C6">Berg and Smalla 2009</xref>). By comparing bacterial and fungal community datasets, we explore whether ecological and spatial factors structure soil microbial communities, and, if so, how bacterial and fungal communities differ.Plant–microbial relationships are often plant species-specific (reviews in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C20">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C28">Hardoim <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C6">Berg and Smalla 2009</xref>). For example, legume species are often associated with particular strains or species of rhizobia bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C36">Long 2001</xref>). Plants exude chemicals from their roots that can foster beneficial microbes in the rhizosphere (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C20">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C2">Bais <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C14">Compant <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). For example, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> exudes malic acid in the presence of a pathogen, and malic acid attracts a beneficial bacterium, <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, protecting the roots from the pathogen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C52">Rudrappa <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). However, plant species-specific relationships are not universally found for soil microbial communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C20">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>), and data sets comparing bacterial and fungal communities for plant species-specificity are rare (but see, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C58">Ushio <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).Soil chemistry also influences soil microbial community composition, diversity and activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C20">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). For example, differences in pH explained 70 % of the variance in bacterial community diversity across soils sampled from North and South America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C23">Fierer and Jackson 2006</xref>). Greater soil fertility (NPK) increases bacterial biomass and activity in grassland mesocosms and these effects interact with plant species identity in some systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C29">Innes <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) and not in others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C3">Bardgett <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>), thus effects of soil chemistry are often system-dependent. Whether or how these soil chemistry effects may interact with plant species identity or plant relatedness is not generally known.Spatial location could also influence soil microbial composition, especially if microbial taxa are dispersal limited, resulting in spatial autocorrelation of microbial communities (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C21">Ettema and Wardle 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C24">Fierer and Ladau 2012</xref>). Early workers argued that microbes do not experience significant dispersal limitation, and thus ‘everything is everywhere: but the environment selects’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C4">Bass Becking 1934</xref>, reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C44">O'Malley 2007</xref>). However, more recent work has found strong spatial autocorrelation in many microbial communities, such that spatially close communities are more similar than expected by chance, and this similarity decays with distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C21">Ettema and Wardle 2002</xref>). Such a pattern of spatial autocorrelation suggests that dispersal limitation does influence patterns of distribution for microbes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C44">O'Malley 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C51">Rout and Callaway 2012</xref>). The relative importance of dispersal limitation and ecological factors is still an area of ongoing research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C6">Berg and Smalla 2009</xref>).If closely related plants are similar in root morphology (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C13">Comas and Eissenstat 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C59">Valverde-Barrantes <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), root exudates, or other drivers of microbial associations, plant relatedness might also be expected to correlate with soil microbial community structure. Consistent with this hypothesis, plant clades, in some cases, have similar responses to soil biota (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C8">Brandt <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C35">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C49">Reinhart <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C1">Anacker <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Closely related plants also often share characteristics of root morphology, such as the absence of many fine roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C59">Valverde-Barrantes <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), a trait which is correlated with higher mycorrhizal colonization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C38">Manjunath and Habte 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C9">Brundrett 2002</xref>). In addition, there is evidence, especially in Orchidaceae, of closely related plants sharing similar soil fungal associates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C30">Jacquemyn <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C39">Martos <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and close relatives sometimes respond similarly to arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C49">Reinhart <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C37">Lugo <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). However, such relationships are by no means universal, and there are cases were plant relatedness does not correlate with effects of soil biota (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C48">Reinhart and Anacker 2014</xref>). Previous studies have often focused on whole-soil effects (i.e. plant-soil feedbacks, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C12">Burns and Strauss 2011</xref>) or have focused on a narrow fraction of the soil community (e.g. mycorrhizae, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C49">Reinhart <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C48">Reinhart and Anacker 2014</xref>); therefore, there is little comparative evidence about the relative influence of plant relatedness on different components of the soil microbiome (e.g. bacterial and fungal communities).We quantified the relative contributions of plant species, soil chemistry, spatial location and plant relatedness on soil microbial communities at Bodega Bay Marine Reserve, CA, USA. (i) We predicted that plant species identity may influence soil microbial community composition, if species differ in factors, such as root exudates, which influence microbial community composition. (ii) Soil chemistry (e.g. N, pH) may correlate with microbial communities, for example, if soil microbe species differ in their nutrient preferences or soil chemistry niche axes. (iii) Spatial separation may influence microbial community composition across samples, if microbes are dispersal limited. (iv) Finally, plant congeners may have similar soil microbial communities, if close relatives have similar traits or habitat preferences, which influence soil microbial community composition.To explore microbial community composition, we sampled field soils and used DNA fragment analysis to characterize differences among soil samples. For each of the 14 angiosperm species, we sampled soils from 6 unique collection locations in the field, at least 100 m apart, at Bodega Bay Marine Reserve, CA, USA [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>see Supporting Information</bold></ext-link>]. These species are <italic>Cirsium occidentale</italic>, <italic>C. quercetorum</italic>, <italic>Fragaria chiloensis</italic>, <italic>F. vesca</italic>, <italic>Gilia capitata</italic> ssp. <italic>chamissonis</italic>, <italic>G. millefoliata</italic>, <italic>Plantago erecta</italic>, <italic>P. subnuda</italic>, <italic>Rumex crassus</italic>, <italic>R. occidentalis</italic>, <italic>Sanicula arctopoides</italic>, <italic>S. crassicaulis</italic>, <italic>Trifolium fucatum</italic> and <italic>T. gracilentum</italic>. Soil samples were collected from the root zone of each focal plant species to 15 cm depth, roots were removed and soils were mixed within a core. Soils therefore represent rhizosphere and non-rhizosphere soil within the active root zone of the selected plants species, which we expect to be under the influence of the plant and therefore represent microbial communities cultivated by the influence of the representative plant species. Soil samples were stored on dry ice in the field and moved to −80 °C within &lt;12 h. To quantify the role of spatial proximity, we mapped collection locations using GPS coordinates.Terminal-restriction fragment length polymorphism (TRFLP) was used to characterize the soil bacterial and fungal communities following established methods (as in, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C10">Burke <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Terminal-restriction fragment length polymorphism is a DNA fragmentation technique that quantifies differences in the soil microbial community among samples but which cannot identify microbes to specific taxa. Terminal-restriction fragment length polymorphism estimates of microbial community structure have been found to be generally robust and concur with alternative approaches such as 454 pyrosequencing in documenting microbial community differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C46">Pilloni <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). See details of the TRFLP methodology in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information</bold></ext-link>. In brief, for each soil sample, DNA was extracted from two 500-mg subsamples of collected soil, amplified using PCR to target bacterial or fungal-specific target regions and restriction enzymes were used to digest the PCR product. We then averaged the subsample extractions within a soil sample for analysis. Terminal-restriction fragment length polymorphism results in size fragments that represent operational taxonomic units (OTUs) in our analyses.To characterize soil chemical properties, soil samples taken from each soil collection (<italic>n</italic> = 84) were analysed for NO<sub>3</sub> (ppm), Olsen P (ppm), K (ppm), K (meq/100 g), Na (ppm), Ca (meq/100 g), Mg (meq/100 g), cation-exchange capacity, organic matter and pH by the Division of Agriculture and Natural Resources Analytical Laboratory at the University of California, Davis.We sampled seven congeneric pairs and six soil replicates per species, and two subsamples per soil sample, to assess heterogeneity in soil microbial communities. We tested for effects of plant phylogeny, as well as tested just for effects of plant genus on microbial community composition (see below).To estimate the phylogeny among our sampled plant species, we downloaded all available DNA regions for <italic>mat</italic>K, ITS and <italic>trn</italic>L-<italic>trn</italic>F from genBank for the 14 sampled plant species <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold>. Each species was represented in the data set by at least 1 DNA region, <italic>mat</italic>K was present for 7 species, ITS for 13 and <italic>trn</italic>L-<italic>trn</italic>F for 11 [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>see Supporting Information</bold></ext-link>]. We aligned the sequences separately for each DNA region with MEGA version 5.2.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C56">Tamura <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) using MUSCLE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C18">Edgar 2004<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C19"><italic>b</italic></xref>) with the default gap open penalty of −400 and then concatenated the alignments. We conducted a maximum likelihood search using Garli version 0.951 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C61">Zwickl 2006</xref>) using a GTR + Γ + I model of evolution. To incorporate prior knowledge about angiosperm phylogeny, we enforced a constraint tree with the known relationships among genera within the Asterids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C55">Stevens 2009</xref>). Bootstrap analysis with 100 replicates was conducted without constraints. Thus bootstrap values reflect repeatability of clades, based on the raw DNA data. We calibrated the branch lengths using r8s with the NPRS method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C53">Sanderson 2003</xref>) and dates fixed at the Fabaceae, Rosaceae, Asteraceae, Apiaceae, Polygonaceae, Lamiales, Caryophyllales, coreeudicots, eurosid1 and easterid2 based on published fossil calibration dates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C60">Wikström <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>).We ordinated the community data using non-metric multidimensional scaling. We used the ‘metaMDS’ function in the ‘vegan’ package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C43">Oksanen <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), using 20 random starts and a Bray–Curtis distance matrix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C22">Faith <italic>et al.</italic> 1987</xref>). We conducted ordinations with and without data transformation, and with and without removing rare taxa (taxa present in ≤7 % of subsamples) prior to ordination. These strategies did not reduce ordination stress, and we therefore present ordinations on untransformed whole community data. In addition, we conducted visual inspection of a graph of stress versus the number of dimensions in the ordination, and chose the number of axes that reduced stress below 0.20, where the graph appeared to asymptote (<italic>k</italic> = 4). NMDS ordination resulted in a reduced number of dimensions that describe differences in soil communities, and with which we could conduct further analyses.To describe the amount of community variance potentially represented by the ordination, we conducted a post hoc partial Mantel correlation between a Euclidean distance matrix from the ordination and the total community data matrix using Bray–Curtis distances following recommendations in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C40">McCune and Grace (2002)</xref>. We used <italic>multi.mantel</italic> in the phytools package with 1000 permutations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C50">Revell 2012</xref>) to conduct this analysis and present <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> values converted to percentages.We used two statistical tools to explore the correlations in this data set: phylogenetic eigenvector regression (PVR) and a variance partitioning analysis. The PVR approach allows us to test for statistical significance of effects of our predictors on soil microbial community structure. Because many predictors may covary in this observational data set, the variance partitioning approach allows us to ask about the relative explanatory power of combinations of predictors and is purely descriptive.First, we fit four PVR models, each with one of the ordination axes as the response variable; predictors in each model included the eigenvectors that represented plant species, soil chemistry, spatial location and plant phylogeny, as described below. To acquire phylogenetic eigenvectors, we first decomposed the phylogeny with 14 plant taxa using <italic>PVRdecomp</italic> in the PVR library (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C16">Diniz-Filho <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C17">2012</xref>). We examined a graph of the eigenvalues against the vector number for the decomposition and used a visual break in the data to determine which eigenvectors to consider for the model selection, which included the first seven. Next, we decomposed spatial distance into a set of two eigenvectors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C5">Bellier <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). To select a minimal model for each ordination axis, we fit a full linear model with the first seven phylogenetic eigenvectors and two spatial eigenvectors using the <italic>lm</italic> function. We then choose the subset of phylogenetic eigenvectors that were statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for the reduced model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C17">Diniz-Filho <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). This approach never resulted in more than three phylogenetic predictors. Because identical values for eigenvectors were associated with each species, species identity could not simultaneously be included in this model. We compared this full model (e.g. fungal community axis 1 ∼ plant phylogeny + spatial location) to models dropping effects from the model using a likelihood ratio test to determine the statistical significance of each predictor. Because ‘phylogeny’ and ‘spatial location’ consisted of multiple vectors, this approach tested the overall significance of these predictors of microbial community structure. To select minimal soil chemical models, we used stepAIC on a model with all soil chemical vectors and included only statistically significant predictors in the final model. This reduced variance inflation factors to below 2.5 for all predictors. Because phylogeny co-varied with soil chemistry (Spearman rank correlation range: −0.44 to 0.59) and models with both phylogeny and soil chemistry resulted in high multicollinearity (VIF &gt; 100), phylogeny and soil chemistry effects were tested separately. Finally, we report the adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for models with each of four classes of predictors (i.e. plant species, soil chemistry, spatial location and plant phylogeny) individually, to estimate the maximum relative explanatory power of each, adjusted for the number of predictors in the model. Because our sampling was concentrated on congeners, we also conducted a PVR analysis with plant genus as a predictor, rather than plant phylogeny, to ask whether plant genus alone could predict differences in microbial community composition.Standard diagnostic plots were examined and residuals were normally distributed for all PVR models. We used adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value comparisons among models to ensure that models were not over-fit. Variance inflation factors were &lt;2.5 for all predictors in all final models (median VIF = 1.03), which is generally considered very low multicollinearity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C26">Fox and Monette 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C42">O'Brien 2007</xref>).Finally, some of these predictors may covary, such as if closely related species prefer the same habitats and are thus spatially close together, and multiple predictors combined could influence microbial community composition. To describe the combined effects of plant phylogeny, soil chemistry and spatial location on soil community structure, we used variance partitioning methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C15">Desdevises <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C45">Peres-Neto <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C27">Gonçalves-Souza <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). See the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information</bold></ext-link> for more details about this analysis. All analyses were conducted in the R statistical package (version 3.0.2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C47">R Development Core Team 2008</xref>). Data are available from the Dryad Digital Repository: <uri xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.9bf7f" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.9bf7f</uri>.Soils from the Bodega Bay site were primarily loamy sand with a somewhat acidic average pH of 6.07 ± 0.05 SE (range = 5.01–8.03). Organic matter was generally low with a mean 4.2 % ± 0.2 SE (range = 0.6–15.5 %). Salinity was highly variable and ranged from 12 to 390 ppm with a mean of 91.8 ± 6.7 SE at this coastal site.Linear PVR models were used to test the effects of plant species, soil chemistry, spatial location and plant relatedness on soil microbial community composition. Model selection was conducted by retaining statistically significant phylogenetic eigenvectors (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for the combined data set (see text for details). Significant results (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) are highlighted in bold.NMDS ordination with species means ± 1 SE for soil samples collected in the field at Bodega Bay, CA from the rhizospheres of 14 plant species. (A and B) The bacterial community ordination with a stress of 0.12. (C and D) The fungal community ordination with a stress of 0.15.Soil bacterial communities were significantly, but weakly, correlated with plant phylogeny on ordination axis 3 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Plant phylogeny explained 29 % of the variance in soil fungal communities on ordination axis 2 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>).The NMDS ordination for the fungal data set had a stress of 0.15 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV030F1">1</xref>C and D), and the total ordination (axes 1–4 combined) explained ∼71 % of the fungal community composition in a partial Mantel test. Plant species identity explained 56, 31 and 20 % of the variation on ordination axes 1, 2 and 3, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Phosphorus, Ca and Mg explained 45 % of the variance on fungal axis 1 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Variation among soil samples in pH explained 27 % of the variation in fungal community composition on axis 2 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Spatial location also explained a significant amount of the variance in fungal community composition, explaining 43, 9 and 10 % of the variance on ordination axes 1, 3 and 4 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Plant phylogeny explained 29 % of the variance on ordination axis 2 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). The alternative analysis with plant genus, rather than plant phylogeny, suggested that plant genus explained 16 and 30 % of the variance on ordination axes 1 and 2, respectively <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information—Table S2</ext-link>]</bold>. For example, <italic>Rumex</italic> species fungal rhizosphere communities were very close in ordination space (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV030F1">1</xref>C, blue points) as were <italic>Gillia</italic> congeners (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV030F1">1</xref>C, grey points), and <italic>Sanicula</italic> congeners (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV030F1">1</xref>C, pink points). This signal of plant genus was especially strong on ordination axis 2 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV030F2">2</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information—Table S2</bold></ext-link>). Combinations of the predictors explained larger percentages of the fungal community composition than individual predictors alone <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information—Fig. S2</ext-link>]</bold>.Consistent with a large body of literature (reviews in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C9">Brundrett 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C20">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C6">Berg and Smalla 2009</xref>), we found a signal of plant species identity on the soil bacterial and fungal communities, and plant species was the single best statistical predictor of soil microbial community variation (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Variance in bacterial community composition was higher than for fungal communities, and no combination of predictors could explain a large amount of this variance <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information—Fig. S2</ext-link>]</bold>. This large variance could reflect a high degree of fine-scale heterogeneity within the root zone to which bacterial communities respond. For example, the presence of fungal biomass was found to influence the community structure of important bacterial functional groups (e.g. denitrifying bacterial) at fine spatial scales within a forest system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C11">Burke <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). This high heterogeneity of microsites for bacterial within the root zone, coupled with the high degree of species diversity within the bacterial domain, could be responsible for the weaker predictors of bacterial communities in our study. In addition, our examination of bacterial community structure using general 16S rDNA primers could miss the potential relationship between plant species and specific bacterial functional groups. Analysis of the nitrogen-fixing functional group, for example, could reveal plant effects on that functional group, because we expect some plants to have co-evolved relationships with these nitrogen-fixing bacteria (e.g. rhizobia-plant relationships; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C36">Long 2001</xref>). The weaker signal of plant species identity on bacteria could therefore be due to our focus on overall bacterial community structure and not functional group distribution, which could yield different results.Plant species explained a significant amount of the variance in fungal community composition (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Effects of plant species identity on soil microbial communities might be the result of ‘active’ selection by plants for soil microbes (e.g. via root exudates), a ‘passive’ by-product of nutrient uptake, root structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C54">Singh <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) or shared habitat preferences by plants and microbes. It is increasingly accepted that soil fungi, and especially mutualistic organisms such as mycorrhizal fungi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C9">Brundrett 2002</xref>), may form plant species-specific relationships that can affect plant growth and community composition. Plant species-specific associations with soil microbes likely contribute to the strong plant-soil feedbacks observed in many systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C32">Kulmatiski <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), which have important implications for coexistence and community assembly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C7">Bever <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).Soil chemistry had the second strongest correlation with differences in microbial communities (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Previous studies have found strong correlations between soil chemistry and soil microbial communities at large spatial scales (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C33">Lauber <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), consistent with our results at smaller spatial scales. Variation in pH is often correlated with bacterial communities at the continent scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C33">Lauber <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), and we found pH to correlate with bacterial community composition. Fungal communities, including AMF and EMF communities, also frequently differ across soils with differences in pH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C31">Kluber <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), also consistent with the correlation between fungal ordination axis 2 and pH. Further, many fungi can affect C and N availability and cycling through their saprotrophic capabilities (e.g. production of extracellular enzymes for liberation of organic nutrients) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C34">Leake <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>), though we found no strong evidence for correlations between the fungal community and N.We found significant associations between soil microbial communities and spatial location (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Thus ‘everything’ is not ‘everywhere’ in this data set, as many other workers have also found for soil microbial communities (reviews in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C21">Ettema and Wardle 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C51">Rout and Callaway 2012</xref>). This is consistent with the hypothesis that dispersal limitation influences microbial distributions even at fairly restricted spatial scales <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information—Fig. S1</ext-link>]</bold>. The correlations we observed between soil chemistry, plant relatedness and spatial locations on fungal community composition suggest that these factors co-varied in the field, making disentangling the relative importance of these predictors difficult <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information—Fig. S2</ext-link>]</bold>.Plant relatedness explained less of the variation in soil microbial communities than plant species, soil chemistry or spatial location (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV030TB1">1</xref>). Plant congeners had similar soil fungal (but not bacterial) communities, even when they occurred in divergent habitats. For example, congeners in <italic>Sanicula</italic> and <italic>Rumex</italic> had similar fungal communities (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV030F2">2</xref>) but they are found in different habitats and are spatially distant (&gt;1 km) from one another <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv030/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information—Fig. S1</ext-link>]</bold>. Thus, spatial location and similarity in habitat preferences between close relatives are not the sole drivers of the correlation between plant relatedness and soil fungal communities. Similar root exudates or root morphology between close relatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C13">Comas and Eissenstat 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C59">Valverde-Barrantes <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) may be other explanations for shared fungal community composition.DNA fragmentation tools, like TRFLP, do not identify taxa without additional work. Because our soil sampling procedure may have broken some plant roots, endophytic fungi could be contributing to the pattern we observed. Our general ITS fungal primers preferentially amplify non-arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (D. J. Burke, pers. obs.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C57">Taylor <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), suggesting that arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi are not driving the correlation that we observed between plant phylogeny and fungal rhizosphere community. Given the species-specific nature of some mycorrhizal associations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C9">Brundrett 2002</xref>), we may be underestimating the importance of host plant relatedness in influencing fungal rhizosphere communities.Meta-analyses suggest that plant relatedness does not explain much of the overall variance in plant-soil feedbacks, where plant performance is compared between conspecific soils and heterospecific soils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C41">Mehrabi and Tuck 2015</xref>); however, phylogenetic relatedness in plant-soil feedbacks did improve predictions of plant abundance for 57 species within an old field community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C1">Anacker <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Some fractions of the soil community may be similar between closely related plants. For example, arbuscular mycorrhizal effects are similar between closely related plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C49">Reinhart <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C37">Lugo <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>) and some mycorrhizal associates are specialized to particular plant clades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C9">Brundrett 2002</xref>). Our results suggest that plant relatedness correlates with the fungal fraction of the soil community, but only weakly with the bacterial community. Thus the relative importance of fungal and bacterial components of the soil microbiota to plant performance may influence whether close relatives have similar plant–soil feedback effects on one another (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV030C12">Burns and Strauss 2011</xref>).Plant species identity was the best predictor of bacterial and fungal community composition in the soil, followed by soil chemistry, spatial location and plant relatedness. Because ‘everything’ is not ‘everywhere’ in microbial communities, spatial location can confound our attempts to predict microbial community structure. Future work should use experimental manipulations to disentangle covarying predictors, such as soil chemistry, spatial location and plant relatedness in the field. Understanding the feedbacks between soil microbial community structure and plant communities may benefit from considering the evolutionary relationships among plants.Our work was funded by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">National Science Foundation (United States)</grant-sponsor> DEB (<grant-num xlink:type="simple">11-20387</grant-num>) and by the Holden Arboretum Trust and the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Corning Institution for Education and Research</grant-sponsor>.J.H.B. contributed to data collection and analysis and wrote the manuscript. B.L.A. collected soil samples in the field, sent soil samples for nutrient analysis and contributed to data analysis. S.Y.S. co-conceived the project and data collection design, discussed data analysis and commented on drafts. D.J.B. trained J.H.B. and undergraduate researchers in TRFLP techniques in the laboratory, mentored undergraduates in the laboratory and contributed to data analysis and manuscript writing. All authors contributed to manuscript revision.None declared.The following additional information is available in the online version of this article –<bold>Table S1.</bold> Plant species sampled to examine rhizosphere soil microbial communities at Bodega Bay, CA, USA.<bold>Figure S1.</bold> Map of the spatial sampling locations for the 14 species and 6 replicate soil collections per species at Bodega Bay, CA, USA.<bold>Figure S2.</bold> Variance partitioning analysis on the bacterial and fungal data sets.<bold>Table S2.</bold> Linear PVR models were used to test the effects of plant species, spatial location and plant genus on soil microbial community composition.Special thanks to J. Sones and P. Conners for assistance with sampling locations. Thanks also to A. Flanigan, M. MacBeth and X. Zhao for assistance in the laboratory and P. Peres-Neto for analysis advice. We thank K. Abbott, M. Benard, C. Cope, K. Dananay, S. Diamond, R. Martin, J. Murphy, B. Nolting, A. Osvaldsson, H. Rollins and R. Snyder, for constructive feedback on the manuscript.