  In situ  morphometric characterization of  Aframomum melegueta  accessions in Ghana  World reference base for soil resources  Characterization and grouping of plantain clones on the basis of their genomic constitution and morphological traits of economic importance  Notes on  Aframomum  (Zingiberaceae) in West Africa, with a new key to the species  The cultivation of melegueta pepper ( Aframomum melegueta ) in Ghana  A preliminary study of the genus  Hornstedtia conica  (Zingiberaceae) in Thailand  Phytochemicals, vitamins and mineral contents of two Nigerian medicinal plants  An ethnobotanical survey of herbal markets and medicinal plants in Lagos State of Nigeria  Xenic culturing of plant-parasitic nematodes: artificial substrates better than soil-based culture systems  Ecosystem consequences of bird declines  Issues in new crops and new uses  Piperaceae  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Misidentification of  Aframomum melegueta , an important medicinal plant has huge adverse health implications. Thus, the scientific description and characterization of the accessions in Ghana was imperative. The study found the plant to bear creepy stolons which bear terminal bud for production of tillers instead of rhizomes which had earlier been reported by other investigators. All the accessions had a distinctive non storage bulbous structure at the base of the pseudostem. The UPGMA dendrogram clustered the accession into Ashanti and Eastern accessions based on ecological location. The Eastern accessions were sub-clustered in two groups based on fruit colour.  In spite of the huge economic importance of  Aframomum melegueta  in the herbal and pharmaceutical industries, its production is limited by lack of planting materials (propagules). The plant also lacks scientific descriptors, which has often led to misidentification with adverse health implications. We therefore aimed at developing a descriptor list to facilitate the identification of  A. melegueta  using 34 morphometric traits comprising 18 quantitative and 16 qualitative characters. The morphological traits showed that  A. melegueta  has a characteristic stolon that produces tillers instead of rhizomes. The unweighted pair group method with arithmetic mean using both the nearest-neighbour and complete-linkage methods based on the 34 morphometric traits clustered the eight accessions into two main groups based on ecological location. The accessions from the Eastern and Ashanti regions were separated at similarity coefficients of 0.822 and 0.644, respectively, with a highly significant discriminant function. The Eastern accessions were further clustered into red or yellow fruits at similarity indexes of 0.936 and 0.865 using the nearest-neighbour and complete-linkage methods, respectively. The present study has shown that morphometric traits of  A. melegueta  are greatly influenced by its ecological habitat. It is envisaged that the descriptor list developed coupled with a morphometric description would enhance its identification and utilization.   Aframomum melegueta , commonly referred to as grains of paradise, alligator pepper or melegueta pepper, is a very important member of the family Zingiberaceae. It is endemic in the tropical rainforest of West Africa, where it occurs in the coastal forest zone from Senegal to Cameroon ( Lock  et al . 1977 ;  Weiss 2002 ). Although in Ghana the plant is endemic in the Atewa range in the Eastern region, it is also cultivated in the Ashanti, Brong Ahafo, Central and Eastern regions ( Lock  et al . 1977 ;  Lock 1980 ). Variations in morphometric traits of  A. melegueta  have been acquired over the years due to co-evolution with its ecological habitat. The fruit colour may be red or yellow with a smooth surface that wrinkles when dried while the number of seeds per fruit also varies. For example, while  Weiss (2002)  reported that a fruit of  A. melegueta  contains 60–100 seeds,  Simon  et al.  (2007)  counted 1200–2000 seeds per fruit. All these variations are indicative of genotypic differences in a phenotypically heterogeneous species. Thus, characterization will lead to the estimation of true genetic diversity within the species and will also provide a complete description of the morphometric traits of the plant.  Besides its rich aroma, the seeds of  A. melegueta  are nutritionally rich, containing high concentrations of calcium, potassium, iron as well as vitamins (thiamine, riboflavin, niacin and ascorbic acid) that confer medicinal properties to the plant ( Okwu and Okpara 2005 ). Consequently, the plant is used to cure dysentery, fever, measles, leprosy, excessive lactation, post-partum haemorrhage and male erectile dysfunction ( Allas  et al . 1995 ;  Olowokudejo  et al . 2005 ).  However, in spite of its huge economic potential in the food, herbal medicine and pharmaceutical industries, the species is still conserved  in situ  in the wild and on farmers' fields. While  in situ  conservation allows the maintenance and co-evolution of viable species in natural environments, it also exposes the species germplasm to both biotic and abiotic stresses. With rapid depletion of the tropical rainforest coupled with emerging climate change,  in situ  conservation poses a serious threat to the continuous survival of this economically important plant in the wild.  Furthermore, the lack of a standard descriptor list for  A. melegueta  has resulted in poor ethno-nomenclature and misidentification of the plant. Consequently,  A. melegueta  is often confused with  Amomum granum  [ paradisi ], also a member of the family Zingiberaceae ( Anonymous 2010 a  ), with disastrous health consequences in traditional herbal medicine. Consequently, we developed a morphometric-based descriptor list using that of  Elletaria cardamomum  (International Plant Genetic Resource Institute ( IPGRI) 1994 ) as a guide for  in situ  characterization of  A. melegueta  accessions grown in Ghana. We also identified phenotypic traits that differentiate the accessions using discriminant analysis.  Geographical map of southern Ghana showing ecological areas where samples of  A. melegueta  were characterized  in situ . A GPS was used to map out the sampling points and the points were fitted on a standardized map of southern Ghana.  Descriptor states of quantitative and qualitative traits used in the characterization of  A. melegueta .  Quantitative traits used for the characterization were the number of tillers per cluster of plants, the number of pedicels per cluster of tillers and the number of flower buds per pedicel. The number of sepals as well as seed weight and number of seeds per fruit were recorded. Additionally, the total number of leaves per plant, the average number of leaves in a longitudinal sequence before alternation (phyllotaxy), was recorded. The diameter of the tallest pseudostem as well as the height (from the base to the leaf axil of the fully opened distal leaf), leaf length and width at the broadest part of the fifth and sixth leaves were measured. The lengths of the pedicels were also measured and recorded as either &lt;1 cm or &gt;1 cm.  Qualitative data recorded were the basal colour of young tillers (3–8 months old) as well as fruit (capsule), stolon, corolla and calyx colours. These colours were described using the HyperText Markup Language colour chart ( Anonymous 2010 b  ). The presence or absence of panicle, petiole and midrib pigmentation as well as panicle habit and branching pattern were recorded. Furthermore, the shapes of leaf, capsule and capsule cross-section as well as flower type and fusion status were recorded. All qualitative data were standardized on a numerical scale using the  IPGRI (1994)  system of coding of qualitative data to allow for statistical analysis.  The data on colour traits and leaf shape were standardized on a scale of 1–5 (Table  1 ). The colours crimson, dark red, burlywood and any other, as well as the shapes linear, lanceolate, oblong-lanceolate, ovate and any other were coded as 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5, respectively (Appendix 1). One (1) or zero (0) was used to designate the presence or absence, respectively, of petiole, panicle and midrib pigmentation, while 1 and 2 designated basal and terminal inflorescence origin, respectively, as well as chasmogamous and cleistogamous flower types respectively. The various panicle habits (namely prostrate, semi-erect and erect) and panicle branching patterns were standardized using a scale of 1–3. The colour of the stolon, calyx, corolla and fruit (capsule) as well as fruit shape and cross- section, and leaf shape were also standardized accordingly.  All data were taken on 15 plants per accession for all traits except the yield, where only five plants per accession were used for the study. The data for each accession were averaged per number of tillers in the plants, and the averages were used to design a similarity data matrix for pairwise comparison between the accessions using unweighted pair group method with arithmetic mean (UPGMA) statistical methods.  UPGMA cluster analysis was performed using GenStat version 9.2 ( Lawes Agriculture Trust 2007 ) to generate a dendrogram. Euclidean similarity coefficient or Euclidean distance was computed from the averaged morphological data for all the accessions. The nearest-neighbour linkage method based on the nearest-neighbour rule or the maximum similarity between two samples and the complete-linkage method based on the minimum similarity between two samples were used to cluster the accessions into groups. A two-group discriminant analysis was performed using SPSS version 16.0 ( SPSS Inc. 2007 ) to determine the validity of the clusters as well as the discriminant traits. To determine how widely the accessions were separated from each other, group predictor variable means and standard errors were computed using the 34 morphometric traits.  Variations in morphological traits of  A. melegueta  accessions from the Ashanti and Eastern regions and Subgroups A and B. Pseu., Pseudostem; Caps, capsules or fruits; s, significant differences at  P  ≤ 0.05; ns, non-significant differences at  P  ≤ 0.05.   Aframomum melegueta  plant showing (A) a bulbous pseudostem with brown leaf sheaths, (B) a pseudostem with two inflorescences at the base, (C) ellipsoid-shaped red fruits from the Ashanti region and (D) globose-shaped yellow fruits from the Eastern region (scale bars: A = 2 cm, B = 4 cm, C and D = 15 mm).  Each pseudostem bears 2–4 brown leaf sheaths at the bulbous end, and numerous green leaves at the middle to the distal end. The number of leaves per pseudostem from Eastern accessions (28.60) was also significantly ( P  ≤ 0.05) higher than that for accessions from Ashanti (23.27). The older leaves close to the base of the pseudostem have a vestigial lamina that withers at maturity while those at the middle and distal ends have a distinct broad lamina and are either linear or lanceolate in shape with an alternate branching pattern.   Aframomum melegueta  plant showing (A) a creeping stolon (arrow) and (B) a basal pseudostem of crimson and burlywood in green tint colours (scale bars: A = 10 cm, B = 15 cm).  The inflorescence arises from the base of the pseudostem (Fig.  2 B) and develops into fruit as the plant matures. The accessions from the Ashanti region produced comparatively more fruit per shoot (1.73) than those from the Eastern region (1.64). The fruits varied in width, length, shape and colour (Fig.  2 C and D), with fruits of accessions from the Eastern region having significantly ( P  ≤ 0.05) greater diameter and length than the Ashanti region accessions. Consequently, fruits of the Eastern region accessions had more seeds (442.36) per fruit than accessions from the Ashanti region (348.00).  The average seed weight of the Eastern region accessions (23.8 mg) was also significantly ( P  ≤ 0.05) higher than that of those from Ashanti (17.5 mg). The fruits of accessions from Ashanti were all red in colour and ellipsoid to elongate in shape, while those from the Eastern region had both red and yellow fruits that were either globose or ellipsoid in shape (Fig.  2 C and D).  Nearest-neighbour (A) and complete-linkage (B) dendrograms of  A. melegueta  constructed from 34 morphometric traits.  The morphometric traits of the subgroups also varied. For example, the width of leaves (broadest part of the leaf) of Subgroup A accessions (5.59 cm) was significantly greater than that of Subgroup B accessions (3.55 cm). Contrarily, the fruits of Subgroup B accessions on average had a significantly ( P  ≤ 0.05) wider diameter (5.66 cm) than Subgroup A accessions (5.42 cm), and consequently produced significantly ( P  ≤ 0.05) more seeds per fruit (452.89) than Subgroup A accessions (436.44). However, the fruits of Subgroup A accessions were marginally heavier (45.11 g) than those of Subgroup B (44.58 g).  Of the 34 morphometric traits, only four, namely pseudostem basal colour, capsule colour, capsule diameter and capsule weight, were used by the standardized canonical discriminant function coefficient (DF1) to distinguish between Groups I and II. The Wilk's lambda of discriminant analysis performed to determine the significance and validity of the clusters as well as the morphometric traits used to predict group membership was highly significant ( P  ≤ 0.05), confirming that all eight accessions belong to two distinct subgroups of the same species. Similarly, the discriminant function (DF2) used to predict Subgroups A and B was also highly significant ( P  ≤ 0.05).  Standardized canonical discriminant function (DF) coefficient of  A. melegueta  traits with predictive values.  Although morphometric traits are highly influenced by environmental factors, they have provided the basis for characterizing several plant species of economic importance. Thus, in this study we used morphometric traits to define variations in  A. melegueta  accessions. All the accessions had a swollen bulbous structure at the basal portion of the pseudostem whose size and shape differed significantly with ecological habitat. Accessions from the Eastern region had significantly ( P  ≤ 0.05) wider bulbous structures with a globose shape compared with those from the Ashanti region which had a smaller diameter and an ellipsoid shape. The swollen bulbous structure can be attributed to osmotic movement of water from the soil into cells as a result of the water potential gradient and therefore cannot be classified as a functional storage organ. Similar swellings with non-functional storage features have been reported in  Hornstedtia conica  ( Maknoi 2009 ).  All the pseudostems studied had one or two creeping stolons. This observation is contrary to the report of  Lock  et al.  (1977)  and  Weiss (2002)  who independently claimed that  A. melegueta  has a rhizome. Arguably, rhizomes are underground modified stems that serve as sinks for storage of photosynthates and for vegetative propagation due to the presence of axillary buds. The stolons observed in  A. melegueta  had no lateral buds but a distal terminal bud that develops into a new shoot. Thus, the stolon bears neither a functional storage organ nor buds, and therefore cannot be classified as a rhizome as suggested by  Lock  et al . (1977)  and  Weiss (2002) .  The basal colour of young tillers or pseudostems varied from crimson to burlywood, becoming green at maturity, and this may be attributed to the presence of anthocyanins. In banana and plantain, the pseudostem pigmentation varies from red to green and is an important morphometric trait for characterization ( Irizarry  et al . 2001 ;  Queneherve  et al . 2010 ). Thus, the pseudostem colour of  A. melegueta  could be a useful trait for characterization and identification of the plant by taxonomists.  There were also significant variations in fruit colour, length and number of fruits as well as the number of seeds per fruit. The number of fruits per plant in accessions from the Ashanti region (1.73) was comparatively higher than those from the Eastern region (1.64), although the Eastern region accessions had significantly larger fruit (5.5 cm) than the Ashanti region accessions (3.08 cm). Although we could not elucidate the exact reason for this observation, the low fruit set in the Eastern accessions could be attributed to noise from illegal mining activities that scared away potential insect pollinators (bumblebees).  Sekercioglu  et al . (2004)  similarly reported that the low fruit set in  Rhynchantus beesianus  (of the family Zingiberaceae) in the Yunnan province of China was caused by the extinction of pollinators through habitat fragmentation. It is also possible that stiffer competition for assimilates among the fruits of the Ashanti accessions led to smaller fruit size and weight.  In determining the phenetic clusters or intraspecific relationships among the accessions, both the nearest-neighbour and complete-linkage methods separated all the accessions into two groups (Groups I and II) at similarity indexes of 0.822 and 0.644, respectively, based on ecological location of the crops. All Eastern accessions were clustered into Group I while the Ashanti accessions were in Group II. Subjecting the two phenetic clusters to discriminant analysis to authenticate the uniqueness of each group or cluster yielded a highly significant test statistic, a Wilk's lambda of 0.008 associated with the discriminant function (DF1), thereby confirming that Groups I and II are morphometrically distinct. Of the several morphometric traits, only pseudostem basal colour, capsule colour, capsule diameter and capsule weight had a highly significant standardized canonical discriminant function coefficient to separate the accessions into two major groups. The agro-ecological differences between the two regions may have had an influence on vegetative growth, seed production (yield), capsule and pseudostem base colour as well as fruit size.  Furthermore, the Eastern accessions were subdivided into two phenetic clusters at similarity coefficients of 0.936 and 0.865 using the nearest-neighbour and complete-linkage methods, respectively. Discriminant analysis of the clusters resulted in a discriminant function (DF2) with a highly significant Wilk's lambda (0.156), confirming that the two subgroups were unique. Although Subgroups A and B varied in a number of morphometric traits, the standardized canonical discriminant function coefficient revealed capsule (or fruit) colour as the only trait that subdivided the Eastern accessions into two clusters of distinct races.  Our study has shown that there are two races of  A. melegueta  growing in the forest zones of Ghana that are distinct from each other in the colour of the fruits. Using the 34-morphological-descriptor list, a dendrogram separated accessions with red colour from those with yellow colour at similarity indexes of 0.936 and 0.865 using the nearest-neighbour and complete-linkage methods, respectively. We also observed that the plant has a stolon that bears a terminal bud and thus gives rise to tillers instead of rhizomes, as has been reported by other authors ( Lock  et al . 1977 ;  Weiss 2002 ). The pseudostem of the shoot has a bulbous structure that has no functional storage properties. Although the morphological traits observed on the plant could be used for identification of the accessions, there is a need for molecular characterization of the plant to make its identification more authentic.  The Government of Ghana provided the funding for this study.  The main idea and topic of the study were formulated and proposed by K.E.D. and N.A. J.A. planned and conducted the research, which formed part of his M.Phil. thesis. W.E. also assisted in conducting the research and analysis of the data.  None declared.  We acknowledge financial support from the Government of Ghana as well as logistical support from the Director of the Biotechnology and Nuclear Agriculture Institute (BNARI). We also appreciate Irene Kafui Amponsah (Statistic Department, University of Cape Coast) for helping with the statistical analysis. We are appreciative of all the help given by  A. melegueta  farmers in the study area.  1.1  PSEUDOSTEM HEIGHT   Measured on the tallest tiller (up to the distal fully opened leaf axil). Average of five plants, 2–5 years old.  Average height in metres (cm) □  1.1.1  Number of tillers (pseudostems) per plant   Average of five plants, 2–5 years old □  1.1.2  Tiller colour   Observed at the base of the pseudostem  1 Crimson □  2 Dark red □  3 Burlywood □  4 Green □  5 Other (specify in the NOTES descriptor)  1.1.3  Pseudostem diameter (cm)   Average of five tallest pseudostems recorded 10 cm from the base □  1.1.4  Stolon colour   1 Crimson □  2 Dark red □  3 Burlywood □  4 Other (specify in the NOTES descriptor)  1.1.5  Number of leaves   Average of five plants, 2–5 years old □  1.1.6  Leaf shape   1 Linear □  2 Lanceolate □  3 Oblong-lanceolate □  4 Ovate □  5 Other (specify in the NOTES descriptor)  1.1.7  Primary leaf length (cm)   Average leaf lengths of the fifth and sixth leaves from a plant base of five plants, 2–5 years □  1.1.8  Primary leaf width   Average maximum width of the fifth and sixth leaves from the base of five plants, 2–5 years □  1.1.8.1  Phyllotaxy   Average number of leaves in longitudinal sequence before alternation  1.1.9  Pigmentation of midrib   Basal half  0 Not pigmented □  1 Pigmented □  1.1.10  Presence of petiole   0 Absent □  1 Present □  1.1.11  Petiole length   1 (&lt;1 cm) □  2 (&gt;1 cm) □  1.2 INFLORESCENCE AND FRUIT  1.2.1  Presence of panicle   0 Absent □  1 Present □  1.2.2  Inflorescence origin   1 Basal □  2 Terminal □  1.2.3  Number of panicles per plant   Average of five plants, 2–5 years □  1.2.4  Number of panicles per tiller   Average number of panicles per tiller of five 2- to 5-year-old plants □  1.2.5  Number of flower buds per panicle   Average of five plants □  1.2.6  Panicle habit   1 Prostrate □  2 Semi-erect (i.e. intermediate) □  3 Erect □  1.2.7  Panicle branching   1 Non-branching □  2 Branching □  1.2.7.1  Panicle branching pattern   1 Distal □  2 Entire □  3 Proximal □  1.2.8  Flower type   1 Chasmogamous □  2 Cleistogamous □  1.2.9  Pedicel length   1 &lt;1 cm □  2 &gt;1 cm □  1.2.10  Colour of calyx   1 Light green □  2 Deep green □  3 Other (specify in the NOTES descriptors)  1.2.10.1  Number of sepals   Average of five plants □  1.2.11  Colour of corolla   1 Yellow □  2 Purple □  3 Red □  4 Other (specify in the NOTES descriptors)  1.2.11.1  Number of petals   Average of flowers from five plants □  1.2.12  Androecium: number of stamens   1.2.12.1  Fusion of stamen   1 Free □  2 Synandrous □  1.2.12.2  Fused stamen   1 Filaments fused □  2 Anthers fused □  1.2.13  Number of capsules per plant   Average of five plants, 2–5 years old □  1.2.14  Capsule colour   1 Red □  2 Yellow □  3 State other  1.2.15  Capsule shape   1 Globose □  2 Ovoid □  3 Narrowly ellipsoid to elongate □  1.2.16  Cross-section of capsule   1 Round □  2 Angular □  3 Ovate □  1.2.17  Number of seeds per capsule   Average of 10 randomly selected capsules counted at third harvest □  1.2.18 Seed weight  Specify seed weight □ 