Effect of light on the growth and photosynthesis of an invasive shrub in its native rangeA preliminary assessment of the establishment and persistence of <italic>Berberis darwinii</italic> Hook., a naturalised shrub in secondary vegetation near Dunedin, New ZealandFruit and seed production in <italic>Berberis darwinii</italic> Hook., a shrub recently naturalised in New ZealandPlant architecture: a dynamic, multilevel and comprehensive approach to plant form, structure and ontogeny<italic>.</italic>Temperature and CO<sub>2</sub> responses of leaf and canopy photosynthesis: a clarification using non-rectangular hyperbola model of photosynthesisA handbook of protocols for standardized and easy measurement of plant functional traits worldwideWhat makes a community invasible?Comparison of native and invasive <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> populations: growth, reproduction and morphology under field conditionsInvasive and native <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> populations: is there evidence for genotypic differences in germination and growth?Seed germination in temperate rain forest species of southern Chile: chilling and gap-dependency germinationCommunity-wide germination strategies in a temperate rainforest of southern Chile: ecological and evolutionary correlatesGermination requirements and seedling shade tolerance are not correlated in a Chilean temperate rain forestAdaptation to sun and shade: a whole-plant perspectiveNative and introduced populations of <italic>Solidago gigantean</italic> differ in shoot production but not in leaf traits or litter decompositionBiotic and abiotic consequences of differences in leaf structureA biogeographical approach to plant invasions: the importance of studying exotics in their introduced and native rangeInvasion success of exotic plants in natural ecosystems: the role of disturbance, plant attributes and freedom from herbivoresTree invasions: a comparative test of the dominant hypotheses and functional traitsRevision of <italic>Berberis</italic> (Berberidaceae) in Chile and adjacent southern ArgentinaGlobal meta-analysis shows that relationships of leaf mass per area with species shade tolerance depend on leaf habit and ontogenyWhy are evergreen leaves so contrary about shade?A model for C3 leaves describing the dependence of net photosynthesis on irradiance. I. DerivationSeedling recruitment of the invasive species Berberis darwinii (Darwin's Barberry): what contributes to invasion success?Biomass allocation, shade tolerance and seedling survival of the invasive species <italic>Berberis darwinii</italic> (Darwin's barberry)Photosynthesis and water-use efficiency: a comparison between invasive (exotic) and non-invasive (native) speciesPhotosynthetic characteristics of invasive and noninvasive species of <italic>Rubus</italic> (Rosaceae)Abundance and dispersion of the invasive Mediterranean annual, <italic>Centaurea melitensis</italic> in its native and non-native rangesLack of belowground mutualisms hinders Pinaceae invasionsBerberidaceaeGrowth response of 15 rain-forest tree species to light gradient: the relative importance of morphological and physiological traitsAre species adapted to their regeneration niche, adult niche, or both?Natural selection on ecophysiological traits of a fern species in a temperate rainforestResponse of leaf anatomy and photosynthetic capacity in <italic>Alocasia macrorrhiza</italic> (Araceae to a transfer from low to high lightInvasibilidad de los bosques, protección de especies nativas en el matorral de exóticas y su aprovechamiento para la restauración de áreas degradadasLight heterogeneity and plants: from ecophysiology to species coexistence and biodiversityShade tolerance, a key plant feature of complex nature and consequencesThe functional ecology of shoot architecture in sun and shade plants of <italic>Heteromeles arbutifolia</italic> M. Roem., a Californian chaparral shrubLow leaf-level response to light and nutrients in Mediterranean evergreen oaks: a conservative resource-use strategy?Is there evidence for the post-invasion evolution of increased size among invasive plant species?The worldwide leaf economics spectrumAssociate Editor: James F. CahillThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We studied the growth and photosynthetic capacity of <italic>Berberis darwinii</italic> shrub growing under different light conditions in their native area of Argentina to test if plant physiology differs from invaded area (using studies carried out in New Zealand). In its native range <italic>B. darwinii</italic> grows under different light conditions by adjusting shoot and leaf morphology and physiology. Plants of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> growing under the same light environments show similar physiology in native and invasive ranges. Therefore, intra-specific variations of the functional traits in native area do not condition successful invasiveness.Invasive species' success may depend on ecophysiological attributes present in their native area or those derived from changes that took place in the invaded environment. We studied the growth and photosynthetic capacity of <italic>Berberis darwinii</italic> shrubs growing under different light conditions (gap, forest edge and below the canopy) in their native area of Patagonia, Argentina. Leaf photosynthesis results determined in the native area were discussed in relation to information provided by studies carried out under the same light conditions in an invaded area in New Zealand. Shoot elongation, leaf production, stem and leaf biomass per shoot, and specific leaf area (SLA, cm<sup>2</sup> g<sup>−1</sup>) were determined in five adult plants, randomly selected in each of the three light conditions at two forest sites. Net photosynthesis as a function of PPFD (photosynthetic photon flux density), stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>), maximum light-saturated photosynthesis rate (<italic>P</italic><sub>max</sub>), <italic>P</italic><sub>mass</sub> (on mass bases) and water-use efficiency (WUE<sub>i</sub>) were determined in plants of one site. We predicted that functional traits would differ between populations of native and invasive ranges. In their native area, plants growing under the canopy produced the longest shoots and had the lowest values for shoot emergence and foliar biomass per shoot, while their SLA was higher than gap and forest edge plants. Leaf number and stem biomass per shoot were independent of light differences. Leaves of gap plants showed higher <italic>P</italic><sub>max</sub>, <italic>P</italic><sub>mass</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> but lower WUE<sub>i</sub> than plants growing at the forest edge. In its native range <italic>B. darwinii</italic> grows under different light conditions by adjusting shoot and leaf morphology and physiology. Plants of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> growing under the same light conditions show similar physiology in native and invasive ranges. This means that for <italic>B. darwinii</italic>, intra-specific variation of the functional traits studied here does not condition successful spread in new areas.Studies of the successfulness of invading exotic species commonly focus on plant attributes and environmental factors that control their persistence in the invaded area, but less information is available on populations of the same species growing in its native area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C11">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C12">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C19">Hierro <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). One main objective is to establish whether the properties that determine the survival and spread of an exotic species in their invasion range are inherent to the species (i.e. are already present in native area populations) or represent changes in plant traits in the new, invaded ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C17">Güsewell <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Comparative studies have determined that populations of species growing in invaded areas exhibit higher plant density and dominance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C32">Moroney and Rundel 2012</xref>), size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C9">Crawley 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C46">Willis <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>) and growth rates, as well as the presence of shorter-lived leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C11">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2004</xref>) than in their native areas. Exotic invasive <italic>Rubus</italic> species showed higher photosynthetic capacity, maximum photosynthesis, water and nitrogen use efficiency than native <italic>Rubus</italic> growing in the same areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C31">McDowell 2002</xref>).Light availability, which varies both spatially and temporally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C20">Horn 1971</xref>) and exhibits qualitative and quantitative heterogeneity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C42">Valladares 2003</xref>), limits the establishment of forest species, determining differences in plant growth and in physiological and morphological plant responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C39">Sims and Pearcy 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C36">Poorter 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C43">Valladares and Niinemets 2008</xref>).<italic>Berberis darwinii</italic> Hook. (Berberidaceae) is a spiny evergreen shrub native to southern Argentina and the Chilean Andean forests, and is an introduced invasive species in New Zealand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C1">Allen 1991</xref>), Great Britain, Australia and the USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C41">USDA 2006</xref>). In its native area of Chiloé (Chile), a wetter region than its distribution range in Argentina, high seed germination and seedling growth occurs both under the forest canopy and in gaps with canopy openness greater than 20 % (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C14">Figueroa and Armesto 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C15">Figueroa and Lusk 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C13">Figueroa 2003</xref>). In New Zealand <italic>B. darwinii</italic> can become established and persist below the forest canopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C1">Allen 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C2">Allen and Wilson 1992</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C29">McAlpine and Jesson (2007)</xref>, seedlings of this species are shade intolerant, while adult plants growing under the canopy come from surviving seedlings with increased shade tolerance. However, although this shrub can grow in both low and high light levels, it achieves higher performance (seedling establishment, total biomass, maximum photosynthesis) in the latter conditions, outperforming even coexisting native species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C28">McAlpine 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C30">McAlpine <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).The photosynthetic responses of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> leaves to different light levels and other ecophysiological characteristics have been studied extensively in invaded areas of New Zealand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C1">Allen 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C2">Allen and Wilson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C28">McAlpine 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C29">McAlpine and Jesson 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C30">McAlpine <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).In the present work we studied growth and biomass allocation to stems and leaves in current-year shoots and variation in photosynthesis, instantaneous water-use efficiency (WUE<sub>i</sub>) and leaf morphology in adult plants of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> growing under different light conditions in the evergreen temperate forests of the Andean region of Patagonia, Argentina. We hypothesized that adult plants of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> populations in Argentina would exhibit differences in some characteristics in response to different forest light levels. We predicted that plants growing in gaps would have, for example, greater shoot growth, biomass and leaf photosynthetic activity than plants growing at the forest edge and in the understorey. Photosynthetic parameters (estimated from photosynthesis models; see below) and specific leaf area (SLA, cm<sup>2</sup> g<sup>−1</sup>) values obtained in the native area studied were compared with those of the invaded area (bibliographic data) for the same light environments. We predicted that although the <italic>B. darwinii</italic> populations in the native and invaded areas (New Zealand) might show a similar pattern of variation in relation to different light environments in the forest, the physiology of the introduced populations would differ from that of plants growing in their native range.The study was conducted at two sites located on Victoria Island in Nahuel Huapi lake, within the Nahuel Huapi National Park in Neuquen province, Argentina. Mean annual precipitation in the area is 1700 mm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C3">Barros <italic>et al.</italic> 1983</xref>). The soils are derived from volcanic ash; they are sandy, acidic and rich in organic matter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C21">Koutche 1942</xref>).At both study sites (Site 1: 40°57.94′S, 70°31.34′W, 791 m.a.s.l.; Site 2: 40°59,02′S, 71°31.33′W, 790 m.a.s.l.) the forest is dominated by the native evergreen species <italic>Nothofagus dombeyi</italic> (Mirb.) Oerst (Fagaceae).Canopy openness (mean ± SE) in the gap, at the forest edge and under the canopy of the <italic>N. dombeyi</italic> forest at the two sampling sites. Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences between the three light environments compared at Site 1; for the same comparison at Site 2, different uppercase letters are used. Two-way ANOVA.Mean percentage (±SE) of soil moisture, air temperature and relative humidity in the gap, at the edge and under the canopy of the <italic>N. dombeyi</italic> forest at two sites on Victoria Island, Argentina, corresponding to the native area. NS indicates no significant differences. Different lowercase letters indicate significant differences between light environments in each season.Seasonal soil moisture values did not differ between the three light environments at each site (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU033F2">2</xref>), possibly due to the existence of a 10-cm layer of volcanic ash on the ground during sampling, a result of the Puyehue volcano eruption in June 2011, which prevented soil water evaporation.Soil nutrient availability did not differ between disturbed forest areas located near plantations and the native undisturbed forests on Victoria Island (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C34">Nuñez <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).<italic>Berberis darwinii</italic> is a shrub that grows up to 2 m in height and produces yellow-orange flowers in racemose inflorescences and blue-black berries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C6">Brion <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Fasciculate leaves are four in number. In Argentina this species is widely distributed in forests of the Andean region of Neuquen, Rio Negro and Chubut provinces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C35">Orsi 1984</xref>). It grows in forests of <italic>Nothofagus pumilio</italic> (Poepp. and Endl.) Krasser (Fagaceae), <italic>N. dombeyi</italic> and <italic>Austrocedrus chilensis</italic> (D. Don) Pic. Serm. and Bizzarri (Cupressaceae), in shrublands of <italic>Nothofagus antarctica</italic> (G. Forst.) Oerts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C10">Damascos 2005</xref>) and in the Valdivian rainforest of Puerto Blest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C6">Brion <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Albeit with low coverage, it grows in disturbed areas in shrublands of the exotic species <italic>Rosa rubiginosa</italic>, Rosaceae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C40">Svriz 2008</xref>). In Chile it grows from 33°25′ to 46°40′S, between 150 and 1300 m.a.s.l., at similar latitudes to Argentina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C24">Landrum 1999</xref>). On Chiloe Island, Chile, <italic>B. darwinii</italic> grows at the edges of the Valdivian forest and at open sites together with secondary vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C14">Figueroa and Armesto 2001</xref>). According to germination requirements, <italic>B. darwinii</italic> would appear to be a generalist species with regard to light, but when seedling survival is considered this species seems to prefer intermediate–high light conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C15">Figueroa and Lusk 2001</xref>).Gap, edge and area under the canopy were delimited at each site using a global positioning system. Edge area corresponded to the projection of the tree canopy surrounding the gap, from the outer limit of the latter and to a distance of 5m into the forest. Canopy area was defined as being from the internal edge limit into the forest.Current-year shoot production, leaf and stem shoot biomass and growth as well as leaf traits were measured on plants from the two sampling sites, while photosynthesis (see below) was evaluated only at Site 1.During spring (mid-October 2011), at each site and for each light environment (gap, edge and under the forest canopy), five <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants between 0.5 and 1.50 m height were randomly selected. Since apex abscission occurs in long shoots at the end of the growing season (M.S., unpubl. res.), three lateral buds located immediately below the apex were labelled on two previous-year shoots per plant. Every 15 days the number of buds producing shoots was quantified, stem elongation was measured using a caliper, and the number of leaves on each shoot emerging from the labelled buds was counted.In February 2012 (summer) following the cessation of current-year shoot extension, the net leaf photosynthesis (<italic>P</italic><sub>n</sub>; µmol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>) curves as a function of PPFD (photosynthetic photon flux density) were obtained for the same five individuals considered for growth measurements at Site 1. Measurements were performed during mid-morning using a gas exchange infrared Li-cor 6400 (Lincoln, NE, USA) with PPFD values of 10, 50, 100, 200, 500, 1000 and 1500 µmol photons m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>. Each measurement was made using a minimum waiting time of 180 s at each light intensity, under controlled conditions of air temperature (19 °C) and relative humidity (35 %). Leaf-to-air vapour pressure deficit was held between 1.0 and 1.5 kPa, and sample CO<sub>2</sub> concentration was 400 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup>. Photosynthesis was measured on healthy, expanded leaves present on the upper third of a shoot selected on each individual growing in the gap, at the edge and below the forest canopy.For SLA (cm<sup>2</sup> g<sup>−1</sup>) determination, we used samples of 50 healthy leaves taken from each of the five <italic>B. darwinii</italic> individuals per site and light environment. One leaf disc (of known area) per blade was cut away from the midrib (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C8">Cornelissen <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Leaf circles were dried in an oven at 70 °C for 3 days until constant dry weight. Leaf mass per area (LMA, g m<sup>−2</sup>) was calculated from the same data.During the same period, current-year shoots (the shoots that emerged from labelled buds, and of which stem elongation had been measured and leaf production counted) were cut. The stem and leaves of each one were separated and dried using the method mentioned above for determination of dry biomass.Since sites did not differ significantly in the canopy openness of each light environment (gap, edge and area below the forest canopy) the data obtained from the plant variables studied at each site were pooled, so that 10 measurements of each variable per light environment were obtained.Leaf and node numbers, internode length, and stem and leaf biomass per shoot were compared between gap, edge and below canopy growing plants using the Kruskal–Wallis test. Mean values of SLA were compared between plants of the three forest environments studied using the same procedure, while LMA was compared with a one-way ANOVA.Relative frequency of marked buds with or without shoot production in <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants present in the gap, at the edge and under the canopy of the <italic>N. dombeyi</italic> forest. Chi square test.Mean (±SE) values for shoot growth (cumulative length, in cm) in the <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants present in the gap, at the edge and under the canopy of the <italic>N. dombeyi</italic> forest as a function of time. Distinct letters indicate significant differences between light environments analysed using the global-fitting technique.Mean values (±SE) for leaf number, node, internodes length and stem biomass, leaves of current year leaf mass per area (LMA), in plants of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> growing in the gap, at the edge and under the canopy of the <italic>N. dombeyi</italic> forest. Distinct letters indicate statistically significant differences between light environments. Kruskal–Wallis one way analysis of variance on ranks. <italic>P</italic>, associated probability.Maximum light-saturated photosynthesis rate (<italic>P</italic><sub>max</sub>), quantum yield (<italic>α</italic>), curvature angle (<italic>θ</italic>), water-use efficiency (WUE<sub>i</sub>), stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) and photosynthetic rate on a per-unit mass basis (<italic>P</italic><sub>mass</sub>) for leaves of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants present in the gap, at the edge and under the forest canopy of the <italic>N. dombeyi</italic> forest. Distinct letters indicate significant differences and similar letters indicate no significant differences between gaps, forest edge and under canopy plants. The first three variables (<italic>P</italic><sub>max</sub>, <italic>α</italic> and <italic>θ</italic>) were compared with the global adjustment technique and the evidence ratio (ER) in favour of the better model (i.e. global vs. separate fitting to the data) while WUE<sub>i</sub>, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub>mass</sub> were analysed using a one-way ANOVA.Adjusted curves of net photosynthesis as a function of PFFD (photosynthetically active radiation) of leaves in <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants growing in the gap and at the <italic>N. dombeyi</italic> forest edge. Distinct letters indicate significant differences between models of the light environments considered, analysed using the global-fitting procedure.The WUE<sub>i</sub> was significantly higher in the leaves of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants growing at forest edges and below the canopy than in leaves of gap plants (<italic>P</italic> = 0.003; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU033TB2">2</xref>), while stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) was higher (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) in leaves of gap plants than in the other two light environments (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU033TB2">2</xref>).Specific leaf area differed significantly for plants from the gap (51.33 ± 1.73 cm<sup>2</sup> g<sup>−1</sup>), the forest edge (77.48 ± 3.33 cm<sup>2</sup> g<sup>−1</sup>) and growing under the canopy (122.27 ± 10.12 cm<sup>2</sup> g<sup>−1</sup>), as did LMA (<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.001; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU033TB1">1</xref>). Stem biomass of current-year shoots did not differ between plants growing in the three light environments studied (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU033TB1">1</xref>). The lowest leaf biomass value was found in shoots of plants growing below the canopy (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU033TB1">1</xref>).The variation in physiological and morphological traits of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants growing under different light conditions at the study sites provides information on their degree of acclimatization to contrasting environments. Plant architecture depends on endogenous growth processes but is affected by the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C4">Barthélémy and Caraglio 2007</xref>). At sites with similar soil moisture content, light availability differences influence <italic>B. darwinii</italic> branching abundance. Since plants growing in sunny environments produce more shoots than those in intermediate and low light, leaf exposure is reduced. Shoot morphology also shows differences, since <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants growing in the gap evade full sunlight by producing shorter shoots with smaller internode length than in the other environments studied. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C44">Valladares and Pearcy (1998)</xref>, great differences can be found in overall plant architecture depending on whether they should maximize capture or avoid excess of light. Light capture also depends on leaf display angles, leaf anatomy and other morphological and physiological traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C16">Givnish 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C18">Gutschick 1999</xref>) not considered in the present work. Although <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants growing under the canopy are less branched, longer shoots allow spatial exploration, producing the same leaf number but with lower biomass investment. Low leaf biomass and LMA could be achieved by low mesophyll density or the presence of thin cell walls, although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C26">Lusk <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> found different patterns in seedlings. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C37">Poorter (2007)</xref> indicates that these variables are dependent on variations in plant ontogeny from seedlings to adult plants. With regard to the increase in SLA values from gaps to under the canopy, <italic>B. darwiini</italic> plants follow the typical intra-specific variation due to declining light availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C36">Poorter 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C45">Valladares <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>).The higher variability in shoot production, growth and morphology of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants present at the forest edge could be caused by the lower homogeneity of light availability in this transitional environment.Comparing the morphological and functional traits of several invading species, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C23">Lamarque <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> found that growth rate was more linked to tree species invasiveness than other traits, such as seedling survival, density, biomass and seed germination. The information on the growth of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> adult plants in their native area will be a valuable contribution to future studies in invasive areas.In the gap environment <italic>B. darwinii</italic> leaves lost more water but <italic>P</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub>mass</sub> were higher than in shade plants. Consequently, lower water-use efficiency does not affect assimilation rates in gap plants. In contrast, in species with other life forms in the southern temperate forests in Chile, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C38">Saldaña <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> found higher WUE<sub>i</sub> in plants growing in gaps than under the canopy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C47">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> showed that leaf mass per area (LMA) is strongly correlated with photosynthetic capacity on mass bases. Differences in both LMA and SLA between <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants growing in gaps and at the forest edge are not in concordance with similar and high leaf photosynthesis on mass bases. This result shows that leaves of gap and forest edge plants have similar resources allocated to symplastic components, but gap plant leaves would have a higher proportion of structural components. Both components contribute to leaf construction, allowing adaptation to different light environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C25">Lusk and Warton 2007</xref>). Plants living under the canopy have higher SLA but lower photosynthesis (<italic>P</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub>mass</sub>), approximately half the value of gap and forest edge plants, but they tolerate low light. Nevertheless, as observed at different sites and during successive years, only <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants growing below the canopy produce no flowers (M.S., unpubl. res.), so that the fixed carbon is dedicated to vegetative growth alone.Our results allow us to establish that in its native range <italic>B. darwinii</italic> is a species with the ability to grow under different light conditions by adjusting leaf morphology and physiological attributes, but its under canopy performance is lower.Contrary to our hypothesis, which proposed that the values for the studied variables would differ in <italic>B. darwinii</italic> populations of native and invasive areas, leaf photosynthetic activity determined in the present work shows similar values to those reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C30">McAlpine <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> in the New Zealand invasion area under similar conditions of canopy openness. These authors determined <italic>P</italic><sub>max</sub> values of around 18 µmol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> in plants growing in full sun and 5 µmol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> in shade plants, while <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> was 0.22 mol H<sub>2</sub>O m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> and 0.05 mol H<sub>2</sub>O m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> respectively for sun and shade plants. Furthermore, both in New Zealand and in the native area studied, <italic>B. darwinii</italic> plants showed lower WUE<sub>i</sub> under full light as a result of higher stomatal conductance. It is important to note that in the invasion area the maximum photosynthetic rate of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> is almost double that of native species in sun, but is similar to all the other species in shade, and stomatal conductance is higher than coexisting native species in the latter environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C28">McAlpine 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C30">McAlpine <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Inter-species differences could be the main factor affecting exotic species' success.The only difference observed when the information obtained in native areas is compared with invaded areas is that in the latter the SLA of shade plants (200 cm<sup>2</sup> g<sup>−1</sup>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C30">McAlpine <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) is higher than in plants of the native area. This would explain why, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C1">Allen (1991)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C2">Allen and Wilson (1992)</xref>, <italic>B. darwinii</italic> is one of the few naturalized shrubs in New Zealand that can become established and persist under the canopy. This fact supports the idea that an increase in SLA promotes the invasiveness of exotic plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU033C22">Lake and Leishman 2004</xref>).Plants of <italic>B. darwinii</italic> growing in different light environments show similar physiology in their native and invasive ranges. This means that for <italic>B. darwinii</italic>, intra-specific variation of the functional traits studied is not an indicator of successful invasion in new areas.This work was supported by Universidad Nacional del Comahue. M.S. received a doctoral fellowship from Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Tecnológicas (CONICET).M.S. was involved in planning and performing the experiments, the data analyses and manuscript writing. M.A.D. contributed to manuscript writing. K.D.L. and S.A.V. participated in performing the experiments and data analysis. D.B. was involved in relevant research discussions with other authors.None declared.We thank Ana Raselli and Juan Karlanian for their field assistance. We also thank Administración de Parques Nacionales for allowing access to the study sites, particularly Susana Seijas and Juliana Nielsen.