Body condition and habitat use by Hermann's tortoises in burnt and intact habitatsThermal utility of desert vegetation for the Egyptian tortoise and its conservation implicationsFibrocement slabs as useful tools to monitor juvenile reptiles: a study in a tortoise speciesShrewd shrikes and spiny shrubs: a calamity for hatchling Moorish tortoise<italic>Testudo hermanni</italic> (Gmelin 1789) Hermann's TortoiseWhat is the appropriate timescale for measuring costs of reproduction in a capital breeder such as the aspic viper?Sexual dimorphism in steppe tortoises (<italic>Testudo horsfieldii</italic>): influence of the environment and sexual selection on body shape and mobilityShelter availability, stress level, and digestive performance in the aspic viperMovement patterns and homing behavior of <italic>Testudo hermanni</italic> Gmelin (Reptilia Testudinidae)Biologie et écologie de la Tortue d'Hermann <italic>Testudo hermanni</italic> (Gmelin, 1789)<italic>Testudo hermanni</italic> Gmelin, 1789 – Griechische LandschildkrötePlan national d'actions en faveur de la Tortue d'Hermann <italic>Testudo hermanni hermanni</italic>Impacts of a wildfire on mortality and short-term movements of a Hermann's tortoise <italic>Testudo hermanni hermanni</italic> population in south-eastern FranceEstimating abundance and population trends when detection is low and highly variable: a comparison of three methods for the Hermann's tortoiseMediterranean landscape changes: evidence from old postcardsLong-term demographic fluctuations of the spur-thighed tortoise <italic>Testudo graeca</italic> in SW SpainSexual body size and body shape dimorphism of <italic>Testudo hermanni</italic> in central and eastern SerbiaDoes translocation influence physiological stress in the desert tortoise?Effects of desert wildfires on desert tortoise (<italic>Gopherus agassizii</italic>) and other small vertebratesEstructura de una poblacion de tortuga mediterranea (<italic>Testudo hermanni robertmertensi</italic>, Wermuth), antes y despues de un incendio forestalReturn to the wild: translocation as a tool in conservation of the Desert Tortoise (<italic>Gopherus agassizii</italic>)Pressions anthropiques subies par les chéloniens dans le VarMoving in the real world: tortoises take the plunge to cross steep stepsEffect of high-intensity wildfire and silvicultural treatments on reptile communities in sand-pine scrubThe effects of fire and mechanical habitat destruction on survival of the tortoise <italic>Testudo hermanni</italic> in northern GreeceAssessing body mass condition in the tortoise <italic>Testudo hermanni</italic>Measuring the lipid content of live animals using cyclopropane gasSeasonal and annual energy budgets of female desert tortoises (<italic>Gopherus agassizii</italic>)Reproductive effort and reproductive nutrition of female desert tortoises: essential field methodsSampling on private property to evaluate population status and effects of land use practices on the gopher tortoise, <italic>Gopherus polyphemus</italic>Rythme d'activité de la Tortue d'Hermann (<italic>Testudo hermanni hermanni</italic>) en semi-liberté dans le massif des Maures (Var)Sexual size dimorphism in steppe tortoises (<italic>Testudo horsfieldi</italic>): growth, maturity, and individual variationA short spring before a long jump: the ecological challenge to the steppe tortoise (<italic>Testudo horsfieldi</italic>)Foraging behaviour and diet of an ectothermic herbivore: <italic>Testudo horsfieldi</italic>Slowness and acceleration: a new method to quantify the activity budget of cheloniansBushes protect tortoises from lethal overheating in arid areas of MoroccoAnalysis of Variance in Complex Experimental DesignsRecensement de la Tortue d'Hermann <italic>Eurotestudo hermanni</italic> dans le VarDistribution of the endangered Hermann's tortoise <italic>Testudo hermanni hermanni</italic> in Var, France, and recommendations for its conservationLong-term post-fire effects on spatial ecology and reproductive output of female Agassiz's desert tortoises (<italic>Gopherus agassizii</italic>) at a wind energy facility near Palm Springs, California, USAHow far can a tortoise walk in open habitat before overheating? Implications for conservationPhysiological ecology of desert tortoises in southern NevadaBody condition threshold for breeding in a viviparous snakeAre wildfires a disaster in the Mediterranean basin? – A reviewNon-commercial collection of spur-thighed tortoises: a cultural problem in southeast SpainAssessing translocation outcome: comparing behavioral and physiological aspects of translocated and resident African elephants (<italic>Loxodonta africana</italic>)The effects of a large-scale fire on the demographic structure of a population of Hermann's (<italic>Testudo hermanni boettgeri</italic> Mojsisovics,1889) and Spur-thighed (<italic>Testudo graeca ibera</italic> Pallas, 1814) tortoises in Eastern Rhodopes Mountains, BulgariaLa banque de données sur les incendies de forêts en région méditerranéenne en FranceR: A Language and Environment for Statistical ComputingCoexisting with fire: the case of the terrestrial tortoise <italic>Testudo graeca</italic> in mediterranean shrublandsImpact du changement climatique sur la sècheresse et l'eau du sol en France: les résultats du projet CLIMSECBody Composition Analysis of Animals: A Handbook of Non-destructive MethodsConservation threats due to human-caused increases in fire frequency in Mediterranean-climate ecosystemsRoad mortality of amphibians and reptiles in the Anatolian part of TurkeyBody mass condition in Greek tortoises: regional and interspecific variationSexual dimorphism of body size and shell shape in European tortoisesGopher tortoise response to habitat management by prescribed burning<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Herman tortoises can maintain their mean body condition in similar range of inter-annual variations in severely burnt versus intact habitats. Therefore, burnt areas provide sufficient food, shelter, and thermally buffered habitats to meet the eco-physiological requirements of the tortoises. Burnt habitats are thus suitable for population reinforcement programs.In Mediterranean regions, fires threaten terrestrial tortoises. Nevertheless, varying proportions of adults survive fire; these surviving individuals can play a central role for population recovery. The regions devastated by fire often include important habitat of Hermann's tortoises (<italic>Testudo hermanni hermanni</italic>), so assessing the ability of survivors to persist is essential for conserving the species. Body-condition indices provide an integrative estimate of how well individuals cope with environmental variations and impacts, including fires. Between 2002 and 2009, we monitored Hermann's tortoises in intact and burnt habitats in southeastern France. In summer 2003, a strong fire ravaged half of the surveyed zone, providing an opportunity to compare body condition of tortoises between intact and burnt areas over time. Six years later, the impact of fire on vegetation was still marked; large trees were abundant in the intact area, whereas open shrub vegetation prevailed in the burnt area. In both areas, the mean body condition of tortoises fluctuated over time; however, there were no differences between the two areas. A radio-tracking experiment demonstrated that individuals from each area were residents, and not vagrants commuting between areas. We also assessed changes in body condition and microhabitat use in radio-tracked individuals. We found no significant differences between the tortoises living in the burnt and intact areas, despite subtle differences in habitat use. In conclusion: (i) surviving tortoises in an area ravaged by fire can maintain their body condition like individuals living in an intact area, and thus, individuals from burnt areas should not be translocated to supposedly better areas; and (ii) depopulated burnt areas are likely to be appropriate for population-augmentation programmes.In combination with other threats (e.g. illegal collection), the drastic loss and fragmentation of habitat threaten populations of the Hermann's tortoise (<italic>Testudo hermanni hermanni</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C11">Cheylan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). As the most favourable areas for <italic>T. hermanni hermanni</italic> are under strong anthropogenic pressures from rapid urbanization, including construction of highways and railways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C14">Debussche <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C38">Livoreil, 2009</xref>), the less-urbanized habitat areas are necessary for species conservation. In 2003, 380 fires devastated 18 813 hectares of hilly and mountainous areas of south-eastern France, destroying 20% of the native forests and almost 10% of the <italic>T. hermanni</italic> habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C47">Prométhée, 2010</xref>). Therefore, it is critical that we assess these areas for their suitability in providing key resources, notably food and shelter, to Hermann's tortoises.In Mediterranean regions, immediate mortality due to fire affects tortoise populations with variable intensity depending upon topography, forest density and season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C24">Hailey, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C49">Sanz-Aguilar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Previous studies showed that the mortality rate ranged between 30% in open landscapes of Spain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C19">Felix <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>) to 88% in wooded habitats of France (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C10">Cheylan, 2001</xref>). The survivors are essential for population recovery, and fire intensity and frequency are major determinants of whether populations can persist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C49">Sanz-Aguilar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). In the present study, we focused on a complementary issue, identifying the suitability of burnt habitat for tortoises by using body condition as an index of the physiological and health status of individuals surviving fires (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C45">Pinter-Wollman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).Body condition, i.e. body mass scaled by body size, provides information regarding nutritional and physiological status [body reserves + ovarian follicles + stomach (gut) content + stored water] in vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C51">Speakman, 2001</xref>), including tortoises (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C41">Nagy and Medica, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C26">Henen, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C27">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C32">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). In reptiles, when nutrient resources are abundant, females build up important body reserves and are more likely to undertake vitellogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C42">Naulleau and Bonnet, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C28">Henen, 2002</xref>), and they exhibit higher survival rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C5">Bonnet <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Tortoise body condition may decline after fires, because most fires are ignited in summer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C47">Prométhée, 2010</xref>), during part of the tortoise active season, and burnt habitats may limit food availability. Also, the massive destruction of vegetation probably reduces the availability of shelter, increases predation risk, perturbs thermoregulation and may generate deleterious chronic stress, causing excessive energy expenditure, thereby reducing body condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C18">Esque <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C7">Bonnet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Overall, burnt habitats may directly and indirectly expose tortoises to a strong degradation of their body condition, with negative consequences on reproductive rate and, ultimately, on populations.Conversely, tortoises may adjust well to burnt habitats, finding enough food and suitable refuges. Tortoises are low-energy specialists, displaying marked tolerance to fasting and bet-hedging reproductive strategies in unpredictable environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C27">Henen, 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C28">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C33">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Thus, we assessed the possible impact of the modification of habitats caused by fire on tortoises. For this, we surveyed tortoise populations in burnt and intact areas 1 year before a strong fire (2002), immediately before (2003) and for the ensuing 5 years (2004–2009). We compared the mean body condition of the tortoises sampled in the two areas. Although straightforward, this comparison was limited by an important potential methodological bias. Individuals captured in one area (intact or burnt) may originate from neighbouring intact or burnt areas. Tortoises can travel over long distances, and the limit created by fire does not necessarily correspond to the natural boundaries of their home ranges. Including vagrant tortoises that commute between areas in the analyses may mix individuals using various habitats and thus generate spurious results. It is therefore important to consider this potential problem. Long-term mark–recapture and radio-tracking surveys are appropriate tools for such assessment. Alternatively, homing behaviour can provide key information; displaced tortoises should rapidly attempt to return home (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C8">Chelazzi and Francisci, 1979</xref>). In our study, we used this philopatric behaviour to enable better interpretation of the results regarding body condition. In addition, we radio-tracked tortoises in order to provide a more detailed assessment of the impact of fire on habitat use and changes in body condition during the main active period in spring.Hermann's tortoise exhibits the typical life-history traits of terrestrial chelonians, including delayed maturity, low fecundity and, thus, low renewal rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C9">Cheylan, 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C10">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C4">Bertolero <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Hermann's tortoises do not burrow, rather they tend to shelter beneath thick (and inflammable) shrubs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C9">Cheylan, 1981</xref>). The study site (80 ha) is situated in the Massif des Maures in France (Var 83-district, 43°25′N, 6°28′E), a hilly region characterized by dense scrubland ‘maquis’ with cork oak (<italic>Quercus suber</italic>) and pine (<italic>Pinus pinea</italic>) forests. This sclerophyllic vegetation and the extremely powerful wind regimens (e.g. Mistral) make this habitat highly prone to fire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C43">Pausas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C52">Syphard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).The geological substrates are homogeneous across the 80 ha area, which is characterized by a natural, thick maquis and forests, where tortoises have been monitored since 2002. More than 30 years ago (1969), a fire moderately impacted the area (&lt;15% of the surface was burnt), and in 2002, the 80 ha study site was considered as a typical mature maquis (B. Livoreil, unpublished observations). Indeed, in southeast France, the regrowth of mature maquis following a strong fire requires ∼20–30 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C47">Prométhée, 2010</xref>). In July 2003, a very strong fire destroyed half of the area (&gt;90% of the vegetation was burnt, and three fire fighters died; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C47">Prométhée, 2010</xref>). However, half of the study site was spared, with a road delimiting the two halves into two adjacent areas of ∼40 ha each and named intact vs. burnt areas. In each area, we monitored tortoise body condition over 8 years (2002–2009), assessed vegetation cover and performed a homing-behaviour experiment in 2009. Although the two areas are separated by a road, they are connected to surrounding areas, and tortoises can move from one area to another. Hermann's tortoises will cross roads, as indicated by reports of road mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C53">Tok <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C21">Gagno <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).In 2009, after 5 years of vegetation regrowth, we assessed the vegetation cover of each area using satellite images (Google Earth, 2009). We randomly selected three 2500 m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C2">2</xref></sup> squares in each area, then we divided each square into smaller 25 m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C2">2</xref></sup> squares (<italic>n</italic> = 100). In each small square, we estimated by eye the surface covered by trees (i.e. canopy), shrubs and lower layers. The crowns of large trees (crown diameter &gt;8 m) were clearly visible; smaller trees (crown diameter &lt;8 m) were also easily visible. The surface covered by the trees provided an index of the ground surface covered by the canopy. We also estimated the proportion of the surface represented by bare/herbaceous substrate and by shrubs.During thermoregulation, tortoises (<italic>Testudo</italic> spp.) navigate between open habitats and thick bushes or trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C35">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C1">Attum <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Therefore, to assess the thermal suitability of each area, we placed four physical models per area (i.e. operant temperature models constructed from empty tortoise shells filled with a hydro-gel and placed on the ground; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C35">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C40">Moulherat <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref> for details) fitted with a temperature logger (Maxim's iButton<sup>®</sup> device, Thermochron<sup>®</sup>; Maxim Integrated Products, Dallas, TX, USA; accuracy ±0.5°C, glued on the back and recording one measurement every 30 min) in the following two microhabitats: (i) open herbaceous layer exposed to sunlight (two models in each area); and (ii) supposedly thermally buffered thick shrubs or large trees (two models in each area; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C35">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). These physical models were deployed between 10 April and 20 May 2009 and were used to examine the range of temperatures available to tortoises in each area.We assessed the mean body condition of free-ranging tortoises before and after the fire, in both the intact and the burnt areas. Each individual encountered was captured, sexed using plastron and tail shape, permanently marked (using small metallic tags; B. Livoreil, unpublished observations) and released immediately at the place of capture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C38">Livoreil 2009</xref>). For most individuals, the body mass (±1 g, using electronic scales, KL-9505 Kologn) and body size [straight carapace length, SCL ±1 mm, using callipers, Horex 200] were measured. Several individuals were not sexed, notably juveniles, and/or were not fully measured (e.g. SCL lacking) due to human error.Field population surveys were performed annually. Searches were conducted during the tortoises' main active season of the year (mid-April to mid-June) following a standard protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C37">Livoreil 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C38">2009</xref>). In each intact or burnt area, several (between one and four) randomly localized quadrats of 50 m × 50 m were surveyed by one person. Surveys were performed by experienced researchers (e.g. B.L.) and/or by volunteers. In each quadrat of 50 m × 50 m, one person randomly searched for tortoises by sight for 30 min. Tortoises were processed (e.g. measured) in the field immediately after capture. The time required to measure tortoises in the field was not counted in order to maintain a net searching time of 30 min per quadrat-session. Volunteers were trained during 1 week prior to their participation in the surveys [e.g. tortoise handling, sex identification, Global Positioning System (GPS) positioning]. Participants were distributed alternately across the quadrats and areas, so that possible observer biases were equally distributed. At least 2 weeks elapsed between consecutive surveys in a given area.Between 10 April and 20 May 2009, 24 adult males were measured and fitted with telemetric and temperature devices. Twelve tortoises were monitored in each area (intact and burnt). In each group of 12 tortoises, we randomly assigned six individuals to the control group (released at the place of capture) and displaced six others to trigger homing behaviour. Displacements were performed within each area (intact or burnt), but not between areas in order to minimize the likelihood of tortoises being killed if they crossed the road to home. More specifically, in each study area (intact or burnt) we selected three disparate subareas and released two displaced tortoises in each of them (6.3 ± 0.3 ha on average). These subareas were ∼500–600 m straight line distance apart; therefore, this distance represented the distance used to test homing behaviour for the 12 tortoises released away from their capture sites.Each individual was fitted with an AVM-K16 transmitter and a temperature data logger glued to the carapace to infer body temperature. This equipment represented &lt;10% of the body mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C34">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The tortoises were located three times per day [morning (09.00–12.00 h), around mid-day (12.00–14.00 h) and afternoon (14.00–17.00 h)], randomly changing individual order every day. We used a Garmin GPS to record each location at a resolution of 5 m. The homing experiment was performed between the 10 April and 20 May 2009. The devices were removed at the end of the experiment; the tortoises were weighed again and released at the place of initial capture. We used only adult males so as not to perturb female reproduction.In order to characterize the microhabitats used by the radio-tracked tortoises, we viewed a circle 1 m in diameter around each fix, in which we visually estimated the ground surface respectively covered by litter (i.e. leaves), bare soil and herbaceous layer (grass). Then, we evaluated the surface covered by different vegetation types, namely shrubs, small trees (&lt;4 m tall) and large trees (&gt;4 m tall). The same procedure (1 m circle) was applied 25 m away from the tortoise fix, in a random direction (using a table of random numbers), to describe a reference microhabitat that we called ‘randomly sampled habitat’.Body condition was estimated using residual values from a general linear regression (all individuals pooled), with the natural logarithm (ln) of body mass as the dependent variable and ln SCL as the independent variable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C31">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C51">Speakman, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C25">Hailey, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C54">Willemsen and Hailey, 2002</xref>). Individual body-condition values were therefore expressed as negative or positive values (without units), with the mean value set to zero by definition. The distribution of residual values did not deviate from normality (Shapiro–Wilk test, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05); therefore, we used parametric analyses of variance (general linear model ANOVA) to assess differences in mean body condition between years, areas and groups of radio-tracked tortoises (i.e. factors). We excluded recaptures to avoid pseudo-replication. Body size, body condition, habitat use and, possibly, energy budget differ between the sexes in <italic>Testudo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C6">Bonnet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C55">Willemsen and Hailey, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C16">Djordjević <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>); thus, we used sex as an additional factor to detect possible sex-specific differences in tortoises from burnt and intact areas. In two years, 2006 and 2008, there was little survey effort and few tortoises were observed; corresponding sample sizes were low, especially when categorical variables were considered simultaneously (e.g. <italic>n</italic> = 3 per cell), and associated analyses of variance were not robust (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C36">Lindman, 1974</xref>); therefore, we discarded these years from body-condition analyses (although retaining them did not change the outcomes). We reperformed separate analyses disregarding sex to increase the statistical power of several analyses; this did not change the results.We did not aim specifically to assess thermoregulation or movement patterns. Instead, to examine changes in mean body condition over time (2002–2009), we focused on the impact of vegetation status (intact vs. burnt) on control vs. displaced radio-tracked tortoises. For instance, we examined whether the degraded vegetation of the burnt area imposed thermal or movement constraints that may influence body condition. For each individual, therefore, we averaged the body-temperature values recorded every day between 10.00 and 16.00 h. This time window was selected to represent a period when individuals could have reached their preferred body temperature, within the range of optimal body temperatures (25–30°C) during activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C30">Huot-Daubremont and Grenot, 1997</xref>). We calculated the mean daily distance travelled during the experiment, using daily starting and ending GPS co-ordinates. During periods of cold weather (when body temperature was below 13°C) and at night, the tortoises remained sheltered; these periods were discarded from temperature and movement analyses. Three temperature data loggers malfunctioned and the data were not used. The 24 tortoises were not fitted with electronic devices simultaneously, and several individuals managed to return home in a few days while others did not. These factors (e.g. malfunctioning device, individual homing speed) generated variations in the sample size (e.g. number of fixes per individual) across analyses.For the comparisons of the vegetation between intact and burnt areas (2009), we calculated the mean value in each area using the three 2500 m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C2">2</xref></sup> replicates per area (instead of the 100 25 m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C2">2</xref></sup> squares per area to avoid an inflation in replicate number); proportions were expressed as values ranging between zero and one (using arcsine transformation did not change the results). Temperatures and canopy cover from selected and randomly sampled microhabitats were compared using Wilcoxon tests. Means were expressed ±1 SD unless stated otherwise (e.g. in figures for presentation clarity). Statistics were performed using R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C48">R Development Core Team, 2012</xref>).Mean and 1 SE (error bars) percentage cover of the main vegetation types (large trees with a crown wider than 8 m, smaller trees and shrubs) and open ground (herbaceous material, no vegetation) for intact (grey bars) and burnt habitats (black bars) in 2009, 6 years after the 2003 fire. Note that statistics were not performed on percentages, but on values ranging between zero and one (see main text).Mean ±1 SD temperatures recorded every 30 min, using physical models, in open microhabitat (herbaceous layer, <italic>n</italic> = 4) and in closed microhabitat (ground beneath large trees, thick shrubs, <italic>n</italic> = 4). Data presented were recorded between April and May 2009, when tortoises are active. The grey shaded area indicates the range of preferred body temperatures during activity in tortoises belonging to the <italic>Testudo</italic> genus; temperatures above 40°C (grey dashed line) can be lethal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C35">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).Summary of the Scheffé <italic>post hoc</italic> tests used to examine differences in mean body condition of tortoises among years (tortoises from intact and burnt areas combined)Two years, 2003 and 2005, were significantly different from the others.*Significant probabilities.Comparison of mean annual body condition (mass scaled by size; residuals, see main text) of tortoises monitored in two areas, intact and burnt. A major fire occurred in summer 2003 (note that most tortoises, 80%, were assessed before the fire in 2003). Means are expressed ±1 SE; numbers indicate sample size. Due to small sample sizes (<italic>n</italic> &lt; 10 tortoises observed per year), means could not be calculated reliably in 2006 and 2008.At the beginning of the homing experiment, the control and displaced tortoises did not differ in body size (area, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,21</sub> = 2.89, <italic>P</italic> = 0.10; displacement status, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,21</sub> = 1.56, <italic>P</italic> = 0.23; interaction, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,21</sub> = 0.11, <italic>P</italic> = 0.74). The control and displaced tortoises also did not differ in body condition (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,20</sub> = 0.00, <italic>P</italic> = 0.95; displacement status, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,20</sub> = 0.67, <italic>P</italic> = 0.42; interaction, <italic>F</italic><sub>1,20</sub> = 1.65, <italic>P</italic> = 0.43).Changes in mean body condition (±1 SE) in control and displaced radio-tracked tortoises in intact and burnt areas, from 10 April to 20 May 2009. Sample size was six for each group.Mean (±1 SE) daily distance travelled by control (<italic>n</italic> = 12; open bars) and displaced radio-tracked tortoises (<italic>n</italic> = 12; hatched bars). Intact and burnt areas are indicated in white and grey, respectively (sample size was six for each group).Mean (±1 SE, <italic>n</italic> = 6 per group) microhabitat use (expressed as a percentage) by control (black bars) and displaced (dark grey bars) radio-tracked tortoises in intact (<bold>A</bold>; top graph) and burnt areas (<bold>B</bold>; bottom graph). Significant selection was evaluated as high (preference) or low (aversion) compared with randomly sampled microhabitats (Random; light grey bars). *Statistically significant differences (Wilcoxon test <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; see main text).Summarized mean temperatures (±1 SD) of the four experimental groups of tortoises radio-tracked in spring 2009, between 10 April and 20 May (three loggers did not function well, reducing the initial sample size in two groups)The 2003 fire, classified as one of the strongest ever recorded in southeastern France, carbonized almost all of the vegetation in its path, and its effects on vegetation were still marked 6 years later (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU019F1">1</xref>). This is consistent with fire-recovery timing in Mediterranean regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C47">Prométhée, 2010</xref>). The tortoises that survived the highly destructive fire could have experienced the following consequences: (i) permanent physiological and morphological trauma; (ii) a burnt habitat, with very sparse herbaceous or shrub vegetation, causing possible food and shelter shortages; and (iii) a drastically modified landscape during several years, posing possible complications to the individuals (e.g. different vegetation, odours) during their day-to-day life. Therefore, we expected strong negative impacts on tortoises.The main outcome of this study is that fire-surviving tortoises that remained in habitats ravaged by fire had body condition similar to those tortoises in unburnt habitat. This counter-intuitive result was supported by several lines of evidence and results, which showed that migration and dispersal processes were not mixing tortoises from different areas, at least 6 years after the fire. First, the homing experiment revealed that the tortoises sampled in 2009 in each area were resident and not vagrant individuals, in accordance with the home fidelity exhibited by tortoises (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C8">Chelazzi and Francisci, 1979</xref>), and thus were representative of the intact and burnt habitat, respectively. Radio-tracked control tortoises remained in their subarea, whereas most displaced tortoises travelled large distances in straight lines to return home. Second, individually marked tortoises were systematically recaptured in the same area over time (B. Livoreil, unpublished observations). Third, we did not find individuals (e.g. road-kill, radio-tagged) crossing the road that separates the intact and burnt areas. Other results from the homing experiment suggest that tortoises coped equally well in intact and fire-impacted habitats.The results for body condition and temperature indicate that the tortoises from the burnt area did not face specific difficulties in finding food and thermal resources compared with individuals living in the intact area (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU019F3">3</xref>). Indeed, marked inter-annual variations in mean body condition were observed, but with no significant difference between the two areas. It is likely that in both areas, annual climatic conditions (e.g. ambient temperatures, rainfall) influenced food and water availability, energy budgets and, thus, individual body condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C41">Nagy and Medica, 1986</xref>). Notably, 2003 and 2005 were two very hot years in France, characterized by marked spring and summer droughts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C50">Soubeyroux <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), and the mean body condition of the tortoises was particularly low during these two years (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COU019F3">3</xref>). Results from the homing experiment provided further support that habitat differences between intact and burnt areas were not the main drivers of the fluctuations in body condition. Indeed, we did not find any significant differences in mean body condition or in mean body temperatures between the four experimental groups of tortoises. This suggests that the wide range of microhabitats (e.g. herbaceous layer, shrubs and trees) available in each habitat, although different in the intact and burnt area, enabled tortoises to find adequate shelter and, probably, to thermoregulate reasonably well (i.e. there were no indications of heat-stressed or frozen tortoises). Taken together, these results suggest that tortoises adjusted well to the burnt habitat. Following fire, in late August, the rapid growth of herbaceous vegetation after rain in late summer may well have provided sufficient food to surviving tortoises.A lack of impact of fire on body condition and fecundity has also been reported for Agassiz's desert tortoise (<italic>Gopherus agassizii</italic>), a species that can retreat into deep burrows to avoid fire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C39">Lovich <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). In addition, prescribed fires where the main combustible vegetation is the herbaceous cover are not necessarily destructive, especially for burrowing chelonians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C23">Greenberg <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C29">Hermann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C56">Yager <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C39">Lovich <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). In contrast, strong Mediterranean forest fires are often highly destructive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C52">Syphard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), notably for tortoises belonging to the <italic>Testudo</italic> genus, because they do not burrow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C24">Hailey, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C10">Cheylan, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C46">Popgeorgiev, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C12">Couturier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C49">Sanz-Aguilar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Slow-moving and non-burrowing animals cannot easily escape heat waves and heavy smoke. In the present study, many individuals were found burnt or asphyxiated in the burnt area; 30 recently dead burnt tortoises with a complete shell and seven dead individuals without burn scars (B. Livoreil, unpublished observations). Overall, although fires can have a strong immediate negative impact on tortoise populations in Mediterranean regions, this does not mean that surviving individuals face specific (or unsurmountable) difficulties after fire.Our study focused on adults. However, neonates and juveniles are extremely elusive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C2">Ballouard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C13">Couturier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) and they are more vulnerable to environmental perturbations than adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C24">Hailey, 2000</xref>). Due to their small body size, young tortoises are particularly sensitive to overheating, dehydration and predation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C3">Barje <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). Maturity requires ∼8–12  years in <italic>Testudo</italic> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C9">Cheylan, 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C10">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C31">Lagarde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C15">Díaz-Paniagua <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Overall, possible short- (direct fire mortality and predation) and long-term impacts (low recruitment) of fire on populations through the effect on juveniles was not examined, and this issue should be evaluated in the future.Despite this important limitation, our results have important management implications. For example, tortoises walking in burnt landscapes provide the deceptive impression that they may not survive without help, possibly triggering inappropriate action, such as translocations to unburnt areas, at least by the general public (B. Livoreil, unpublished observations). We suggest promoting (e.g. via technical notes, media campaigns) a different option, i.e. tortoises surviving fire should be left in their home range, even if the habitat is severely burnt. Indeed, inappropriate translocations may elicit homing behaviours, increase mortality risks due to hazardous displacements (e.g. crossing road or obstacles; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C44">Pérez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C22">Golubović <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) and hamper population recovery. Population augmentation programmes (e.g. using captive breeding) should be tested to compensate for mortality caused by fire. Although this option has not been evaluated, successful translocations of adults have been performed in tortoises (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C20">Field <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C17">Drake <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Given that fire destroys thick bushes and, thus, may expose juveniles to specific mortality, a possible efficient practical action would be to increase refuge availability in order to promote juvenile survival. Refuge availability can be reduced by strong and/or subsequent fires or by the rarefaction of shrubs caused by closing of the habitat. Promoting the growth of thick bushes (e.g. forest clearing, plantation) or setting up artificial refuges suitable for small tortoises should be tested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU019C2">Ballouard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).We thank the volunteers and students who contributed to population surveys conducted under the supervision of the Station d'Observation et de Protection des Tortues et de leurs Milieux (SOPTOM). B.L. directed field surveys between 1998 and 2009. We warmly thank the landowners, Office National des Forêts (ONF), for allowing field investigations, and R. Cambag for companionship. We also thank three anonymous referees for extremely valuable comments. The SOPTOM provided logistical and financial support. The foundations Noë Conservation and Nicolas Hulot, the companies Autoroutes du Sud de la France (ASF), Autoroutes Estérel Côte d'Azur (ESCOTA), and the Région Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur (PACA) provided financial support to perform long-term population surveys. In 2009, the Fonds européen de développement économique et régional (FEDER) program provided financial support to the translocation experiment.