Seed germination and seedling development ecology in world-wide populations of a circumboreal Tertiary relictTrait stasis versus adaptation in disjunct relict species: evolutionary changes in seed dormancy-breaking and germination requirements in a subclade of <italic>Aristolochia</italic> subgenus <italic>Siphisia</italic> (Piperales)Radiosensitivity of onion seeds with different moisture contentsBiogeography of oaks in the Arcto-Tertiary provinceA classification system for seed dormancyOverview of seed dormancy in <italic>Viburnum</italic> (Caprifoliaceae)Inference by eye: confidence intervals and how to read pictures of dataA paleoclimatic interpretation of the Eocene floras of southeastern North AmericaThe selection of native and invasive plants by frugivorous birds in MaineFruit removal in <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic>: copious seed predation and sporadic massive seed dispersal in a temperate shrubInvasive and native <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> populations: is there evidence for genotypic differences in germination and growth?Afterripening and germination of seed of American highbush cranberry (<italic>Viburnum trilobum</italic>)Germination and seedling production of species of <italic>Viburnum</italic>Refugial areas and postglacial colonizations in the Western PalearcticBirds and guelder rose <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic>: selective consumption and dispersal via regurgitation of small-sized fruits and seedsMorphophysiological dormancy in seeds of two North American and one Eurasian species of <italic>Sambucus</italic> (Caprifoliaceae) with underdeveloped spatulate embryosEpicotyl dormancy in <italic>Viburnum acerifolium</italic> (Caprifoliaceae)Seed germination ecophysiology of two western North American species of <italic>Sambucus</italic> (Caprifoliaceae <italic>sensu lato</italic>), and comparisons with eastern North American and European congenersEvolution and phylogenetic importance of endocarp and seed characters in <italic>Viburnum</italic> (Adoxaceae)Seasonal changes in the fruits of <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic>, a fleshy-fruited temperate-zone shrubA comparative study of germination ecology of four <italic>Papaver</italic> taxaComparing after-ripening response and germination requirements of <italic>Conyza canadensis</italic> and <italic>C. bonariensis</italic> (Asteraceae) through logistic functionsVariation within species and inter-species comparison of seed dormancy and germination of four annual <italic>Lamium</italic> speciesComplex combination of seed dormancy and seedling development determine emergence of <italic>Viburnum tinus</italic> (Caprifoliaceae)Effects of temperature treatment and of a native inhibitor on seed dormancy and of cotyledon removal on epicotyl growth in <italic>Viburnum trilobum</italic> MarshBiological flora of the British Isles No. 226: <italic>Viburnum lantana</italic> L. and <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> L. (<italic>V. lobatum</italic> Lam., <italic>Opulus vulgaris</italic> Borkh.)Seed dormancy in <italic>Trillium camschatcense</italic> and the possible roles of light and temperature requirements for seed germination in forestsCorresponding taxa and their ecological background in the forests of temperate Eurasia and North AmericaDoes invasion involve alternation of germination requirements? A comparative study between native and introduced strains of an annual Brassicaceae, <italic>Cardamine hirsuta</italic>Patterns of resource allocation in fleshy fruits of nine European tall-shrub speciesEvolution of certain floristic associations in western North AmericaEcological genetics of seed germination regulation in <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> L. I. Phenotypic variance among and within populationsThe origin and evolution of Tertiary relict florasCorrelates of diversification in the plant clade Dipsacales: geographic movement and evolutionary innovationsEffect size, confidence interval and statistical significance: a practical guide for biologistsPatterns of seed dormancy and germination as related to plant phylogeny and ecological and geographical conditions of their habitatsTerrestrial ecoregions of the world: a new map of life on EarthGeographical distribution and ecological conservatism of disjunct genera of vascular plants in eastern Asia and eastern North AmericaPlant molecular phylogeography in China and adjacent regions: tracing the genetic imprints of Quaternary climate and environmental change in the world's most diverse temperate floraIntercontinental correlation of geographical ranges suggests stasis in ecological traits of relict genera of temperate perennial herbsSeed dormancy in <italic>Carex canescens</italic>: regional differences and ecological consequencesDeterministic Plio-Pleistocene extinctions in the European cool-temperate tree floraThe use of geological and paleontological evidence in evaluating plant phylogeographic hypotheses in the Northern HemisphereDeep complex morphophysiological dormancy in <italic>Sanicula europaea</italic> (Apiaceae) fits a recurring pattern of dormancy types in genera with an Arcto-Tertiary distributionSeed dormancy and germination of the European <italic>Chaerophyllum temulum</italic> (Apiaceae), a member of a trans-Atlantic genusDivergence among arctic and alpine populations of the annual, <italic>Koenigia islandica</italic>: morphology, life-history, and phenologyDivergence in germination traits among arctic and alpine populations of <italic>Koenigia islandica</italic>: light requirementsDivergent norms of reaction to temperature in germination characteristics among populations of the arctic-alpine annual, <italic>Koenigia islandica</italic>Ombrohydrochory and its relationship to seed dispersal and germination strategies in two temperate North American <italic>Oenothera</italic> species (Onagraceae)Seed germination ecophysiology of the Asian species <italic>Osmorhiza aristata</italic> (Apiaceae): comparison with its North American congeners and implications for the evolution of types of dormancyDefining transient and persistent seed banks in species with pronounced seasonal dormancy and germination patternsEvolution of eastern Asian and eastern North American disjunct distributions in flowering plants<italic>Viburnum</italic> phylogeny based on combined molecular data: implications for taxonomy and biogeographyNutritional interactions and fruit removal: cedar waxwing consumption of <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> fruits in springNeogene floristic and vegetational history of the Pacific NorthwestGenetic differentiation in temperature-enforced seed dormancy among golf course populations of <italic>Poa annua</italic> LDispersal-vicariance analyses of intercontinental disjuncts: historical biogeography implications for angiosperms in the Northern HemisphereSeed germination patterns in green dragon (<italic>Arisaema dracontium</italic>, Araceae)Some results on the effect of temperatures on the seeds and plumules of <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> L. during stratification in order to hasten seedling emergenceThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Ecological traits of the circumboreal plant <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> were examined to improve understanding of the variation of populations occurring in the same biome but on different continents. Seedling development/emergence is shown to be highly similar but some degree of variation was present in other traits, among populations.Temperate forests are disjunct in the Northern Hemisphere, having become fragmented from the earlier widespread (Tertiary) boreotropical forest. We asked ‘What are the contemporary patterns of population variation in ecological traits of a Tertiary relict in a macroecological context?’. This issue underpins our understanding of variation in populations occurring in the same biome but on different continents.We examined characters associated with root and shoot emergences among populations of <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> in temperate forests of Asia, North America and Europe. This species has complex seedling emergence extending over several years and requiring various temperature cues.Populations varied in germination responses and clustered into groups that were only partly related to varietal status. Whereas roots (at warm temperatures) and shoots (following a cold period) simultaneously emerged from seeds of all populations when simulated dispersal occurred in winter, they were delayed in some populations when dispersal occurred in summer.<italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> populations, some separated by 10 300 km, showed high similarity in seedling development and in germination phenology, and we suggest that stabilizing selection has played a key role in maintaining similar dormancy mechanisms. Nevertheless, there was some degree of variation in other germination characters, suggesting local adaptation.The boreotropical forest was a belt of vegetation consisting of tropical and temperate elements concentrated around the Northern Hemisphere during the Eocene epoch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C59">Wen 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C64">Xiang and Soltis 2001</xref>). Floristic exchanges between North America,  Europe and Asia occurred via the North Atlantic Land Bridge and via the Bering Land Bridge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C35">Milne and Abbott 2002</xref>). With climatic cooling during the Tertiary (late Miocene and Pliocene) and Quaternary, this forest became fragmented. Today, disjunct populations of these boreotropical elements, commonly called Tertiary relict floras, remain in two or more of the following areas: southeastern Europe, eastern Asia, western Asia, eastern North America and western North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C64">Xiang and Soltis 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C35">Milne and Abbott 2002</xref>).Stasis of morphological traits has presumably occurred among populations of Tertiary relicts given their high degree of morphological similarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C59">Wen 1999</xref>). On the other hand, two schools of thought have emerged regarding ecological traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C1">Adams <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). The first school believes that ecological tolerances and physiological requirements have remained relatively unchanged over time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C30">Kornas 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C3">Axelrod 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C43">Ricklefs and Latham 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C48">Tiffney and Manchester 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C45">Svenning 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C41">Qian and Ricklefs 2004</xref>). In this view, the main reason for continued survival of taxa was ‘climate tracking’, i.e. shifts in species' distributions to fit those in climate, while adaptation to a new climate played only a minor role. Researchers in the second school have argued that ecophysiological attributes have changed through time with plant lineages adapting to new environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C33">Mason 1947</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C62">Wolfe 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C7">Dilcher 1973</xref>). Ecological studies examining these two viewpoints have resulted in conflicting results. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C43">Ricklefs and Latham (1992)</xref> found a significant correlation in the geographic ranges of herbaceous species between eastern Asia and eastern North America indicating ecological stasis, but no correlation for woody species. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C45">Svenning (2003)</xref> found strong evolutionary conservatism in climatic requirements among the tree floras of Europe, Asia and North America.Over the last few years, seed biologists have entered the realm of addressing the stasis/divergence of ecological traits among Tertiary relicts by examining their seed dormancy (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C18">Hidayati <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C57">Walck <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C1">Adams <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C51">Vandelook <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C50">Vandelook and Van Assche 2008</xref>). These studies—some finding stasis and others divergence (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C20">Hidayati <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>)—have largely focused on species of herbaceous plants usually representing one population on each of two continents. All cases listed above involved seeds that are morphophysiologically dormant (MPD) at maturity, i.e. the embryo is tiny in comparison with the copious endosperm and must grow for the radicle to emerge from the seed, but a physiological block must also be overcome before, during and/or after elongation of the embryo. Thus, levels of MPD, distinguished on the basis of requirements for embryo growth and dormancy break (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C4">Baskin and Baskin 2004</xref>), have been compared between intercontinental taxa. Yet, differentiation of seed traits is documented best at the population level where fine-scaled adaptations to specific habitat conditions may occur.Seed traits among populations have been examined from relatively small (e.g. 10<sup>1</sup>–10<sup>4</sup> m: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C63">Wu <italic>et al</italic>. 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C23">Karlsson and Milberg 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C25">2008</xref>) to large (e.g. &gt; 10<sup>5</sup> m: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C44">Schütz and Milberg 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C34">Meyer and Allen 1999</xref>) geographic scales. Uncommonly, comparisons have been carried out over a continent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C65">Yang <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>) and rarely at an intercontinental level. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C24">Karlsson and Milberg (2007<italic>b</italic>)</xref> reported that germination attributes were relatively similar among populations of the weedy <italic>Conyza bonnariensis</italic> from Mexico, Ethiopia and Morocco. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C53">Wagner and Simons (2009<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C54"><italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C55"><italic>c</italic></xref>) found divergence in seed, morphology, life-history and phenology traits among North American and European populations of the circumpolar annual <italic>Koenigia islandica</italic> growing in arctic, high-latitude alpine and alpine habitats.While all these studies have shown population-level variation in seed traits, they may have little bearing on Tertiary relicts that are broadly distributed over several continents and that occur in the same biome. Considering that Tertiary relicts constitute an important floristic component in the Northern Hemisphere, we wanted to better understand the contemporary pattern of population-level variation for seed and seedling traits in a macroecological context. We selected the woody plant <italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> L., which has a circumboreal distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C28">Kollmann and Grubb 2002</xref>), for the investigation. Seeds of this species have a special kind of MPD, called epicotyl dormancy, in which temperature requirements differ for root emergence (and prior embryo growth) versus shoot emergence as well as temporally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C12">Giersbach 1937</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C27">Knowles and Zalik 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C66">Zolobova 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C11">Fedec and Knowles 1973</xref>).The 12 populations of <italic>V. opulus</italic> in our study occur in temperate broadleaf and mixed forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C40">Olson <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>) in four countries on three continents, with a gradient of intra- and intercontinental distances (1–10 300 km). We compared embryo and seed sizes, as well as germination (i.e. both root and shoot emergence) responses to a range of temperatures, among <italic>V. opulus</italic> populations from different parts of the world. We were also interested in the developmental timing from seed to seedling and the relationship between the timing of dispersal and that of emergence since seeds of this species have a long dispersal period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C61">Witmer 2001</xref>). Overall, we predicted that the seed and seedling traits of <italic>V. opulus</italic> would not differ among populations since they occur in the same (albeit disjunct) biome. Our study is the first to investigate the degree of ecophysiological differentiation in populations of a species over three continents.To understand differences in germination responses among circumboreal populations of <italic>V. opulus</italic>, we conducted a series of experiments in a controlled (laboratory) environment as well as in a common garden. We examined (i) embryo size and seed size and (ii) specific temperature requirements for root and shoot emergences among a subset of 12 populations from Asia, North America and Europe. For all 12 populations, we determined the timing of root and shoot emergences, and of embryo growth, in relation to a sequence of simulated seasonal temperatures. Lastly, emergence phenology of roots and shoots was observed in a common garden in Sweden for 11 of the 12 populations.<italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> occurs from Europe through the Caucasus to Central Asia as var. <italic>opulus</italic>, in East Asia as var. <italic>sargentii</italic> (Koehne) Takeda, and in North America as var. <italic>americanum</italic> Ait. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C15">Hara 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C49">United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service 2008</xref>). In addition, plants of var. <italic>opulus</italic> are naturalized in North America, though they are not always easily distinguishable from var. <italic>americana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C38">Nellessen 2006</xref>). These three taxa are members of the strongly supported <italic>Opulus</italic> clade, which also includes <italic>V. koreanum</italic> and <italic>V. edule</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C36">Moore and Donoghue 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C21">Jacobs <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The circumboreal distribution of this clade is thought to have ‘arose quite recently’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C60">Winkworth and Donoghue 2005</xref>).The study species is a deciduous shrub up to 4 m tall, frequently forming adventitious roots and new vertical shoots on branches close to the ground (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C28">Kollmann and Grubb 2002</xref>). It occurs in a variety of moist to wet habitats: carr, upland deciduous and mixed pine forests, hedgerows, floodplains, alder swamps, and montane and subalpine forests. Fruits mature and are produced in autumn with seeds being consumed and regurgitated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C16">Hernández 2009</xref>) mainly during late autumn or winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C22">Jones and Wheelwright 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C9">Englund 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C28">Kollmann and Grubb 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C8">Drummond 2005</xref>) into spring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C61">Witmer 2001</xref>).<bold>Collection locations and dates for seeds from three varieties of</bold> V. opulus.<sup>a</sup>Collection sites are named by the nearest town or by place names occurring on detailed maps.Laboratory work on Asian and North American seeds was performed at Middle Tennessee State University in Tennessee, USA (MTSU), and that on European seeds at Linköping University in Sweden (LiU). A preliminary study showed that the timing of emergence and the percentages of emergence for roots and shoots from seeds collected in Tokarp (Sweden) and in Sapporo (Japan) did not differ between laboratories.Incubators (MTSU: I-36LL, Percival Scientific, Perry, IA, USA; LiU: Rumed Cooled 3122, Rubarth Apparatebau, Laatzen, Germany) were set at alternating 12/12 h (day/night) temperatures of 15/5, 20/10, 25/15 and 30/15 (or 30/20) °C. A constant temperature of 5 °C was achieved in another incubator (MTSU) or in a cold room (LiU; room: Ki-PANEL, Huurre Sweden AB, Sweden; temperature control: ADU 200, Styrprojektering AB, Sweden). We used the same set of temperature regimes among all populations to simulate seasons: 5 °C, winter; 15/5 °C, early spring and late autumn; 20/10 °C, late spring and early autumn; and 25/15 and 30/15 (or 30/20) °C, summer. With the exception of photoperiod, light conditions were similar in incubators and the cold room [described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C56">Walck and Hidayati (2007)</xref> for MTSU and by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C26">Karlsson <italic>et al</italic>. (2005)</xref> for LiU]. The photoperiod was 14 h (MTSU) or 12 h (LiU), which apparently had no effect given that root and shoot emergences were similar between laboratories in the preliminary study (see above).Since germination in <italic>V. opulus</italic> has two distinct phases, temporally separated, we use the term ‘rootling’ for seedlings in the first phase of germination (i.e. a seed with only an emerged radicle and no shoot) to distinguish it from seedlings in the second phase (i.e. a seed with a root and shoot). To examine root emergence, seeds were placed on two filter papers moistened with distilled water in 10-cm-diameter Petri dishes and incubated in light. Dishes were wrapped with plastic film and placed in polyethylene plastic bags to reduce water loss during the experiment, and additional water was added if needed. Roots were determined to have emerged when the radicle protruded ∼1 mm beyond the seed. To study shoot emergence, a rootling was removed from the dish and planted in a 7-cm-deep plastic container, filled with 2–3 cm of moist sand, and covered with plastic film; only the root and lower portion of the seed were covered with sand. Shoots were judged to have emerged when at least one cotyledon was completely exposed from the seed coat. Seeds/rootlings were either placed in one dish/container or divided equally among two to three dishes/containers.Lengths of 20–25 embryos were obtained each time by excising them from seeds using a razor blade and measuring them with a micrometer under a dissecting microscope. At the start of the study, seed and embryo lengths were determined for fresh seeds 24 h after they were placed on moist filter paper at room temperature (∼22 °C). Measurements for fresh seeds and embryos were obtained for Mombetsu, Sapporo, Sendai (Japan), Moncton (Canada), Ithaca (USA) and Tokarp (Sweden) populations; the embryo : seed (E : S) ratios were calculated from these measurements.Root and shoot emergences were evaluated fortnightly. Percentages of root emergence are based on number of viable seeds, and those of shoot emergence on the number of seeds in which a radicle had emerged. Seeds from which radicles did not protrude were checked to determine whether the embryos were white and firm, indicating that they were viable, or if the embryos were brown and soft, indicating that they were nonviable. Throughout all laboratory studies, 70–97 % of seeds maintained their viability. Survivorship of rootlings until the end of all experiments varied from 62 to 93 % among populations, except for 22 and 39 % in the Kaminokuni and Sendai (Japan) populations, respectively.Twenty-six Mombetsu (Japan), 150 Moncton (Canada) and 50 Tokarp (Sweden) seeds were used for each treatment. Dishes were placed at 5, 15/5, 20/10, 25/15 °C and either 30/15 (MTSU) or 30/20 °C (LiU) for 12 weeks of stratification and were then transferred to (or remained at) each of these temperature regimes for 12 weeks of incubation, e.g. seeds stratified at 5 °C were incubated at 5, 15/5, 20/10, 25/15 °C and either 30/15 or 30/20 °C. Seeds were checked for an emerged radicle fortnightly, and if present, counted and removed from the dish. At the end of the experiment, seeds from which radicles did not protrude were checked for viability.Several hundred seeds from the Moncton (Canada), E Stocklycke and Tokarp (Sweden) populations were placed at 25/15 °C to allow radicle emergence. After many seeds had radicles, the experiment was set up using 15, 33 or 40 seeds, respectively, per treatment. They were cold stratified at 5 °C for 0, 12 and 24 weeks (Canadian population) or 0, 6, 12 and 24 weeks (Swedish populations). After each cold period, seeds were incubated at 15/5, 20/10 and 25/15 °C for 12 weeks. Seeds in which the shoot emerged during stratification were removed from the containers before incubation and subtracted from the total tested. Control seeds were kept at 5 °C for 36 weeks. Rootlings were checked for an emerged shoot fortnightly and, if present, were counted and removed from the dish.Seeds from all populations were exposed to two conditions. (i) In continuous temperature regimes, seeds were incubated at 5, 15/5, 20/10 and 25/15 °C for 80 weeks. (ii) In annual temperature cycles, which simulated a natural sequence of seasonal temperatures, seeds were given a winter (5 °C) regime progressing to a summer (25/15 °C) regime (cold (C) temperatures → warm (W) temperatures) or a summer regime progressing to a winter regime (W → C) for two annual cycles equalling 80 weeks. The number of seeds used in this study was: 45 for Sapporo (Japan); 132 for Kaminokuni (Japan); 100 for Sweden (except for Tokarp); 150 for North America, Mombetsu and Sendai (Japan), and Tokarp (Sweden). Rootlings were removed from dishes, planted in containers, and the cycle continued.Embryo growth was examined for Mombetsu, Sapporo (Japan), Moncton (Canada) and Tokarp (Sweden) populations. In each of the continuous temperature regimes, embryos were measured following 12 and 36 weeks of incubation at 5, 15/5, 20/10 and 25/15 °C for Japanese populations, and following 6, 12, 24 and 36 weeks of incubation for the Canadian and Swedish populations. In the annual temperature cycles, embryos from these four populations were measured each time dishes or containers were moved to a new temperature regime (for up to 60 weeks). Embryo length was measured only in ungerminated seeds.With the exception of Mombetsu (Japan), all populations were used in this study. Japanese and North American seeds were sent to LiU 1–2 days after arriving at MTSU. Fifty seeds were sown on top of soil on 13 November 2004 (except for Sendai, sown on 1 January 2005) in each of 2–5 (2 L) pots per population. The soil used was found locally (Ledberg) and sterilized for 20 min at 120 °C before being placed in pots containing a non-woven glass-fibre sheet in the bottom. The pots were placed at Ledberg, Sweden (58°26′N, 15°28′E), close to the Tokarp population. A 0.15-m-deep hole was dug in the ground and filled with 2- to 6-mm-diameter ceramic clay pellets (AB Svenska, Leca, Sweden) before pots were added. The pots were buried to a depth such that the surface of the soil was at the same level as the surface of the surroundings. They were protected from direct wind, but otherwise subjected to natural weather conditions. Animals were excluded by a 20-mm-mesh net. Temperature (without protection from sunshine) was measured every hour (TinytagPlus, Intab, Sweden) at the soil surface in an additional pot and precipitation was measured daily, ∼15 m away from the pots. On 7 October 2005, 1–2 pots from each population were examined for rootlings, and after recording their number they were replanted. Shoot emergence was examined fortnightly throughout the study, except when the pots were covered with snow. At the end of the study (31 August 2007), the number of remaining seeds (with and without a radicle) that had not produced a shoot during the study were counted. Percentages of root and shoot emergences were calculated based on the number of seeds sown at the start of the study.Characters, and their acronyms, used in the Mantel test and PCA.<sup>a</sup>Emergence speed, measured as the number of days to reach 50 % of final emergence (T50), was calculated using a formula taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C2">Amjad and Anjum (2002)</xref>.<bold>Mean lengths for fresh embryos (E) and seeds (S), and their ratio, of <italic>V. opulus</italic> from five native populations in Asia (A), North America (NA) and Europe (E), and from a non-native population in North America of the European variety (E/NA).</bold> Confidence intervals ± 95 % are shown.<bold>Root emergence for seeds of <italic>V. opulus</italic> from three populations representing Asia (A), North America (NA) and Europe (E).</bold> Seeds were incubated for 12 weeks at 5, 15/5, 20/10, 25/15 and 30/15 (or 30/20) °C following 12 weeks of stratification at each of these temperatures. The dotted line represents emergence that occurred during stratification. Confidence intervals (95 %), based on statistics for binomial distribution, are shown.<bold>Effects of cold stratification on shoot emergence from rootlings of <italic>V. opulus</italic> populations representing North America (NA) and Europe (E).</bold> Control seeds were maintained at 5 °C for 36 weeks. Treated European seeds were cold stratified at 5 °C for 0, 6, 12 and 24 weeks, and North American seeds for 0, 12 and 24 weeks, before incubation at 15/5, 20/10 and 25/15 °C for 12 weeks. Confidence intervals (95 %), based on statistics for binomial distribution, are shown.<bold>Root emergence from seeds (A) and shoot emergence from rootlings (B) of <italic>V. opulus</italic> from 11 native populations in Asia (A), North America (NA) and Europe (E), and from one non-native population in North America of the European variety (E/NA).</bold> Seeds were incubated continuously for 80 weeks at four temperature regimes (shown in (B)). An X in (B) indicates that no rootlings were available to follow shoot emergence. Confidence intervals (95 %), based on statistics for binomial distribution, are shown.<bold>Cumulative root emergence from seeds and shoot emergence from rootlings of <italic>V. opulus</italic> from 12 populations (as explained in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS007F4">4</xref>).</bold> Population symbols for root emergence are shown in the corresponding panel for shoot emergence. Seeds were subjected to an annual temperature cycle (thick grey lines) starting at a winter (W) regime and progressing to a summer (S) regime. Confidence intervals (95 %), based on statistics for binomial distribution, are shown only for the last data point.<bold>Cumulative root emergence from seeds and shoot emergence from rootlings of <italic>V. opulus</italic> from 12 populations (as explained in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS007F4">4</xref>).</bold> Population symbols for root emergence are shown in the corresponding panel for shoot emergence. Seeds were subjected to an annual temperature cycle (thick grey lines) starting at a summer (S) regime and progressing to a winter (W) regime. Confidence intervals (95 %), based on statistics for binomial distribution, are shown only for the last data point.<bold>Principal components analysis results displaying the 12 populations (A) and 26 characters (B).</bold> See Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS007F4">4</xref> for population information and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS007TB2">2</xref> for acronyms.<bold>Temperature, precipitation, root emergence and cumulative shoot emergence for <italic>V. opulus</italic> seeds from 11 populations.</bold> Populations were as explained in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS007F4">4</xref> without Mombetsu (Japan) and were sown on 13 November 2004 (or 1 January 2005 for Sendai) in a common garden in Ledberg, Sweden. Root emergence (single data points) was examined only on 7 October 2005, and shoot emergence throughout the study until 31 August 2007. Confidence intervals (95 %), based on statistics for binomial distribution, are shown only for the last data point of shoot emergence if both upper and lower intervals are ≥ 6 % (i.e. West Stocklycke, Örnslid and Rimforsa populations).<bold>Percentages of <italic>V. opulus</italic> seeds among categories at the end of the emergence phenology study.</bold> The number of seeds used in the study from each population is indicated above each bar. See Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS007F8">8</xref> for additional explanation.Seed size, but not embryo size, varied among the <italic>V. opulus</italic> populations. In contrast to our work, other studies have reported trends in embryo size. For <italic>Osmorhiza aristata</italic>, embryos in a southern population were longer than those in a northern population in Japan, but seed length did not differ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C57">Walck <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C39">Nikolaeva (1999)</xref> reported decreased embryo lengths in <italic>Fraxinus excelsior</italic> with increasing latitude in Europe.Root emergence (and also prior embryo growth) for nearly all seeds from each of the <italic>V. opulus</italic> populations occurred at 25/15 °C. In addition, roots from seeds in the Ithaca (USA) and Tokarp (Sweden) populations also emerged at 20/10 and 30/20 °C. Very low shoot emergence occurred at any temperature unless seeds received cold stratification: either ≥ 12 weeks for the Canadian population or 24 weeks for the Swedish populations. Thus, embryo growth and root emergence occurred in warm temperatures without a requirement for pre-treatment at any other temperature; in contrast, a cold period was required before shoot emergence took place. Seeds in the 12 populations would be classified as having ‘deep simple epicotyl morphophysiological dormancy’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C5">Baskin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>).In nature, root emergence from seeds of 11 populations from Asia, North America and Europe sown in a common garden in Sweden occurred in the first autumn following the autumn–winter sowing. Although none to a few shoots emerged from these populations during the second spring following sowing, larger percentages did so in the third spring. In contrast, germination (presumably root emergence) of <italic>V. opulus</italic> seeds sown outdoors in England was observed during the first spring after fruiting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C32">Lee <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C28">Kollmann and Grubb (2002)</xref> suggested that the first spring would be the normal germination season of the species and that studies reporting delayed germination until years 2 or 3 may have been influenced by storage conditions of the seeds. However, our results for <italic>V. opulus</italic>, along with those for other temperate species of <italic>Viburnum</italic> with epicotyl dormancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C12">Giersbach 1937</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C19">Hidayati <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>), show that delayed germination is normal. Thus, germination of <italic>V. opulus</italic> in the spring (after the previous autumn dispersal) is highly unlikely.At the end of our common garden experiment (∼3 years following sowing), lowtomoderate percentages of remaining seeds were viable and had only roots (and no shoots yet) or had not yet produced roots (or shoots). These results show that <italic>V. opulus</italic> has the capability of forming a persistent soil seed bank (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C58">Walck <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>) and a rootling bank. In contrast, transient soil seed banks (i.e. seeds persist in soil for &lt;1 year) have been mostly reported for <italic>V. opulus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C47">Thompson <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>). Animal exclusion in our study might have affected the likelihood of seeds remaining in the soil. This idea is supported by the observation that 66 % of 150 <italic>V. opulus</italic> fruits placed on the ground disappeared after 16 days, primarily due to rodents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C22">Jones and Wheelwright 1987</xref>).The 12 populations in our study clustered into three distinct groups based on the germination characters. The groups did not correspond to the (morphological) varietal status assigned to the species. Instead, populations from Asia were clustered with those from North America or from Europe; one Asian population did not group with any other population. The similarity of European populations is not too surprising as they are in close proximity. The Asian populations were geographically widely separated from each other, and as such, the amount of variation in germination was relatively broad given their wide dispersion in the PCA. The clustering of populations was mainly driven by the W <italic>→</italic> C treatment. Whereas roots and shoots from all populations in the C <italic>→</italic> W treatment emerged simultaneously, they were delayed in some populations in the W <italic>→</italic> C treatment. The different germination responses between these treatments suggest that the timing of dispersal for <italic>V. opulus</italic> seeds in relation to ambient temperatures may have important ecological consequences of spreading germination over time.<italic>Viburnum opulus</italic> collected in Ithaca (USA) was determined to be a naturalized population of the European var. <italic>opulus</italic> based on morphology. In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C61">Witmer's (2001)</xref> study, only one of more than 50 shrubs surveyed in the Ithaca area was morphologically identified as var. <italic>americanum</italic>. Likewise, the germination characters of the Ithaca population clustered within a group comprising all the European populations and its E : S ratio more closely matched that recorded for the Tokarp (Sweden) var. <italic>opulus</italic> population. Thus, not only have the naturalized plants in North America retained their morphological resemblance to their counterparts in Europe, but their seed ecophysiology also closely resembles them. Our results are in contrast to other studies on shrubs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C10">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2005</xref>) and herbs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C31">Kudoh <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>) that documented differences in germination between native and non-native ranges of species.The degree of population divergence in our study varied among the seed and seedling traits that we examined. First, seedling development for winter (peak)-dispersed seeds (C <italic>→</italic> W treatment) and the phenology of germination were remarkably similar among populations of <italic>V. opulus</italic>. Comparable to morphological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C35">Milne and Abbott 2002</xref>) or ecological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C43">Ricklefs and Latham 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C45">Svenning 2003</xref>) stasis in other Tertiary relicts, we suggest that stabilizing selection has maintained similar dormancy mechanisms, allowing the near simultaneous seedling emergence among <italic>V. opulus</italic> populations. There are selective advantages for root emergence in summer, allowing root system development in autumn without exposing the shoot to winter conditions, and then for shoot emergence at the beginning of a growing season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C29">Kondo <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). These traits apparently have been maintained in these populations since their separation. Apart from being a long time period, a substantial part of the current geographic distribution of <italic>V. opulus</italic> has been glaciated or under periglacial conditions during the Pleistocene. Hence, there have been substantial range shifts, likely fluctuations in population size and possible small refugia during glacial maxima (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C14">Habel <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS007C42">Qiu <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and, thus, ample opportunity for differentiation.Second, at a finer scale, populations varied in seed lengths and in the level and duration of temperatures required for root and shoot emergences. In addition, seedling development for late-dispersed seeds (W <italic>→</italic> C treatment) was delayed in some populations. Seed and seedling traits may adapt to environmental conditions and differentiate populations, if the variation is genetically based. To what extent variation in <italic>V. opulus</italic> is genetically controlled remains to be determined. However, an interesting trend can be observed. The northern-most populations (Sweden) in our study had the broadest temperature range for root emergence and the longest cold stratification requirement for shoot emergence. In a climate where summer temperatures average 21/13 °C, it is advantageous to have root emergence occur at slightly lower temperatures as compared with southern populations. Moreover, the cold stratification period coincides with the relatively long winter, possibly preventing precocious seedling emergence during unusual winter thaws. Altogether, these responses suggest that adaptation to the local environment has occurred.None declared.The order of authorship corresponds to decreasing levels of contribution in conceiving the idea, leading the research, collecting and analysing the data, and writing the manuscript.None declared.The authors thank M. Ajima, J. Bellemare, K. Suzuki and Nova Tree Company for supplying some of the seeds used in the study. Assistance from M. Cofer, M. Imboden, P. Reneby and M. Rolig is greatly appreciated.