Genetic diversity and floral width variation in introduced and native populations of a long-lived woody perennialSwitch from specialized to generalized pollinationMechanisms of hummingbird-mediated selection for flower width in <italic>Ipomopsis aggregata</italic>Silica gel: an ideal material for field preservation of leaf samplesPhenotypic plasticity of introduced versus native purple loosestrife: univariate and multivariate reaction norm approaches<italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> in native and exotic environments, with particular reference to Turkey and the British IslesEffects of flower size and number on pollinator visitation to wild radish, <italic>Raphanus raphanistrum</italic>Biological flora of the British Isles <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic>The establishment of <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> in the Killarney oakwoods, S.W. Ireland<italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> in Britain and Ireland: social, economic and ecological factors in its successful invasionA rapid DNA isolation procedure for small quantities of fresh leaf materialDo hermaphrodites of gynodioecious <italic>Phacelia linearis</italic> (Hydrophyllaceae) trade off seed-production to attract pollinators?Population genetic consequences of small population-size—implications for plant conservationComparisons of native and invasive <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> populations: growth, reproduction and morphology under field conditionsInvasive and native <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> populations: is there evidence for genotypic differences in germination and growth?Invasibility or invasiveness? Effects of habitat, genotype, and their interaction on invasive <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> populationsMaintenance of high genetic diversity during invasion of <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic>Genetic and phenotypic differentiation between invasive and native <italic>Rhododendron</italic> (Ericaeae) taxa and the role of hybridizationAnalysis of molecular variance inferred from metric distances among DNA haplotypes—application to human mitochondrial DNA restriction dataMultispecies comparison reveals that invasive and native plants differ in their traits but not in their plasticityEffects of life history traits on genetic diversity in plant speciesHistorical effects and sorting processes as explanations for contemporary ecological patterns: character syndromes in Mediterranean woody plantsDNA banking for plant breeding, biotechnology and biodiversity evaluationEvidence for massive clonal growth in the invasive weed <italic>Fallopia japonica</italic> (Japanese Knotweed)Evolutionary genetics of invasive speciesThe role of propagule pressure in explaining species invasionsAnalysis of population genetic structure with RAPD markersComparative analysis of genetic diversity in the mangrove species <italic>Avicennia marina</italic> (Forsk.) Vierh. (Avicenniaceae) detected by AFLPs and SSRsReproductive ecology of <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> (Ericaceae) in relict Mediterranean populationsEcology and biogeography of plant communities associated with the post Plio-Pleistocene relict <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> subsp. <italic>baeticum</italic> in southern SpainAlmost forgotten or latest practice? AFLP applications, analyses and advancesOrigin and evolution of invasive naturalized material of <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> L. in the British IslesIsolation and characterization of microsatellites of <italic>Rhododendron metternichii</italic> Sieb et Zucc. var. <italic>hondoense</italic> NakaiGenetic distance between populationsPropagule pressure hypothesis not supported by an 80-year experiment on woody species invasionEffects of life history traits and sampling strategies on genetic diversity estimates obtained with RAPD markers in plantsEffects of population size and isolation on heterosis, mean fitness, and inbreeding depression in a perennial plantGenAlEx 6: genetic analysis in excel. Population genetic software for teaching and researchEvolutionary implications of allozyme and RAPD variation in diploid populations of dioecious Buffalograss, <italic>Buchloe dactyloides</italic>Self-compatibility and plant invasiveness: comparing species in native and invasive rangesAdaptive evolution in invasive speciesRandom amplified polymorphic DNA markers reveal low genetic variation and a single dominant genotype in <italic>Eichhornia crassipes</italic> populations throughout China<italic>Rhododendron</italic> gone wild: conservation impications of <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> in BritainSize constraints and flower abundance determine the number of interactions in a plant−flower visitor webModelling establishment probabilities of an exotic plant, <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic>, invading a heterogeneous, woodland landscape using logistic regression with spatial autocorrelationTesting mechanistic models of seed dispersal for the invasive <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> (L.)Reproductive biology of the invasive exotic shrub, <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> L. (Ericaceae)Pollination of invasive <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> (Ericaceae) in IrelandPollination ecology and seed production of <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> in native and exotic habitatsPollinator restriction in the narrow-tube flower type of <italic>Mertensia ciliata</italic> (James) G Don (Boraginaceae)Data from amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) markers show indication of size homoplasy and of a relationship between degree of homoplasy and fragment sizeAFLP—a new technique for DNA fingerprintingThe population genetic consequences of habitat fragmentation for plantsEstimating population structure in diploids with multilocus dominant DNA markers<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Anna TravesetThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We demonstrate that invasive populations of <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> in Ireland are genetically distinct from ancestral populations in Spain and produce flowers which have wider floral tubes. Although Irish populations are spreading and Spanish ones are declining, we found low genetic diversity among individual plants within populations in both regions, and limited between-population gene flow. Wider floral tubes may have evolved in response to novel pollinators in Ireland. Few studies examine invasive species in both their introduced and native habitats, but this approach is needed to understand invasive species evolution and ecology.Populations of introduced species in their new environments are expected to differ from native populations, due to processes such as genetic drift, founder effects and local adaptation, which can often result in rapid phenotypic change. Such processes can also lead to changes in the genetic structure of these populations. This study investigated the populations of <italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> in its introduced range in Ireland, where it is severely invasive, to determine both genetic and flower width diversity and differentiation. We compared six introduced Irish populations with two populations from <italic>R. ponticum</italic>'s native range in Spain, using amplified fragment length polymorphism and simple sequence repeat genetic markers. We measured flower width, a trait that may affect pollinator visitation, from four Irish and four Spanish populations by measuring both the width at the corolla tip and tube base (nectar holder width). With both genetic markers, populations were differentiated between Ireland and Spain and from each other in both countries. However, populations displayed low genetic diversity (mean Nei's genetic diversity = 0.22), with the largest proportion (76–93 %) of genetic variation contained within, rather than between, populations. Although corolla width was highly variable between individuals within populations, tube width was significantly wider (&gt;0.5 mm) in introduced, compared with native, populations. Our results show that the same species can have genetically distinct populations in both invasive and native regions, and that differences in floral width may occur, possibly in response to ecological sorting processes or local adaptation to pollinator communities.When a species is introduced outside its native range as a result of human activity, genetic diversity and morphological variability within and between populations can vary. This may be a result of the phenotypic plasticity of the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C9">Chun 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C24">Godoy <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), propagule pressure (the number of individuals released and the number of release events; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C31">Lockwood <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>, but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C40">Nuñez <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) and post-introduction evolutionary processes like inbreeding, drift, hybridization and response to novel selection pressures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C30">Lee 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C46">Prentis <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Introduced populations may be expected to display low genetic diversity due to founder effects from a limited number of initially introduced individuals, with associated negative fitness consequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C17">Ellstrand and Elam 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C61">Young <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>), although this is not always the case. Populations of two highly successful introduced plants, <italic>Fallopia japonica</italic> (Japanese Knotweed) and <italic>Eichhornia crassipes</italic> (water hyacinth), have been shown to have very low genetic diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C28">Hollingsworth and Bailey 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C47">Ren <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>).Post-introduction changes in genetic and morphological variability in plant species may also be related to the life form and breeding system. For example, pollinator limitation, as a result of separation of an introduced plant from its native pollinators, may exert selection pressure on self-compatible populations to evolve from self-incompatible ancestors to ensure seed set (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C45">Petanidou <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). This is less likely in perennial species, which have more opportunities for sexual reproduction and the possibility of vegetative spread, and they may retain high genetic diversity post-introduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C25">Hamrick and Godt 1996</xref>). Another possibility is that rather than selection for self-compatibility, introduced plants may be more attractive to resident native pollinators. For example, this could be as a result of the production of larger flowers, which can be more attractive to foraging insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C16">Eckhart 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C11">Conner and Rush 1996</xref>). Furthermore, specialized floral characteristics that restrict access to floral rewards, such as narrow or long floral tubes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C55">Suzuki 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C49">Stang <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), may be selected against and plants that have more easily accessible rewards may receive more frequent pollinator visitation in their new environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C1">Armbruster and Baldwin 1998</xref>). In self-incompatible <italic>Ipomopsis aggregata</italic>, floral width is under strong selective pressure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C5">Campbell <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>) because wider flowers allow increased bill insertion by hummingbird pollinators and a greater proportion of pollen removal. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C49">Stang <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> found that in a Spanish floral community there were more visitors to flowers with wide nectar holders. Hence, floral width, particularly nectar holder width, may be an important floral trait determining attractiveness to floral visitors and potential pollinators.Here we investigate population genetic diversity and floral width variation of <italic>Rhododenron ponticum</italic> (Ericaceae) in expanding introduced populations and compare these with declining native populations. This long-lived woody species was once widely distributed throughout Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C12">Cross 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C7">Chamberlain <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C37">Milne and Abbott 2000</xref>), but now is primarily found in northern Turkey, the Caucasian states, Lebanon, southern Bulgaria and the Iberian Peninsula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C12">Cross 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C13">1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C10">Colak <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C48">Rotherham 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C34">Mejías <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). Iberian populations are small and confined to three isolated areas, the largest of which is in the Aljibe Mountains in southern Spain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C6">Castroviejo <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C34">Mejías <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>), where it is classified as endangered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C2">Blanca <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>) under IUCN red list criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C29">IUCN 1994</xref>). In this region it is known from ∼20 populations, which, although not undergoing rapid decline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C35">Mejías <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), suffer from very low recruitment, and thus it is considered a vulnerable species in the area (VU: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C4">Cabezudo <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). <italic>Rhododenron ponticum</italic> was introduced as an ornamental plant into Britain and Ireland in the late 18th century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C37">Milne and Abbott 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C14">Dehnen-Schmutz and Williamson 2006</xref>) and now forms large invasive populations, which are spreading into, and having negative impacts on, native ecosystems on both islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C12">Cross 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C13">1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C10">Colak <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Repeated introductions into many locations over time have created intense propagule pressure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C50">Stephenson <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Molecular analysis of chloroplast and nuclear ribosomal DNA indicated that British and Irish populations are predominantly derived from Spanish populations, and that hybridisation with North American species (<italic>Rhododendron catawbiense</italic> and <italic>R. maximum</italic>) occurred after <italic>R. ponticum</italic> was introduced in Britain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C37">Milne and Abbott 2000</xref>). This was thought to have contributed to the competitive success of populations of <italic>R. ponticum</italic> in Ireland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C19">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C20">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2010</xref>), where it is particularly successful in the Atlantic climate of the west coast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C13">Cross 1981</xref>). However, analyses using amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) markers showed that hybridization is unlikely to have contributed to invasiveness in Irish populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C22">Erfmeier <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Relatively low genetic diversity was found in both Irish and Spanish populations, compared with Georgian ones, with weak genetic differentiation among populations within the three countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C21">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2011</xref>). Studies of growth traits and life history have found that Irish populations had higher rates of annual growth and seedling recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C18">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2004</xref>), and suggest a genetic basis for these traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C19">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2005</xref>). A previous study comparing the pollination ecology of Irish and Spanish populations has shown that a range of generalist pollinator species visit <italic>R. ponticum</italic> flowers in both ranges, although visitor communities are dominated by different species in Ireland versus Spain, and that a greater volume of nectar is produced in plants from introduced populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C54">Stout <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). This may indicate that these populations contain individuals with wider flowers that hold greater quantities of nectar. However, no previous studies have investigated floral traits (e.g. nectar holder width) in introduced populations of <italic>R. ponticum</italic>, which may be important given that this species has a mixed mating system, primarily relying on animal-mediated outcrossing to produce seeds for invasion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C34">Mejías <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C52">Stout 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>). Selective pressures or ecological sorting in the introduced range could have resulted in larger, more open flowers to enhance attractiveness to resident generalist pollinators.We examined genetic and floral morphological diversity within and between populations of <italic>R. ponticum</italic> in Ireland, and compared them with native populations in the ancestral range in the Aljibe Mountains in Spain. The objectives were to: (i) quantify genetic diversity both within and among introduced and native populations; (ii) determine genetic differentiation among introduced and ancestral populations; and (iii) quantify floral width (corolla width and tube width) in the introduced and native range. Specifically, we tested the hypothesis that there is genetic and floral width differentiation among populations in Ireland, and between Irish and Spanish populations.<italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> populations used for genetic analysis and genetic diversity estimates within populations using (i) AFLP markers and (ii) SSR markers. Size, approximate number of mature, flowering plants in a population; <italic>N</italic>, number of individuals analysed; Tb, total number of bands; Pb, number of private bands; <italic>P</italic>, percentage of polymorphic loci at the 5 % level; <italic>H</italic><sub>j</sub>, Nei's genetic diversity; <italic>N</italic><sub>a</sub>, observed allele number; <italic>N</italic><sub>e</sub>, effective allele number; <italic>H</italic><sub>O</sub>, observed heterozygosity; <italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>, expected heterozygosity; <italic>H</italic>, average heterozygosity.Leaf material was collected and stored in silica gel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C8">Chase and Hills 1991</xref>). DNA was extracted from ∼0.1 g of dried material using a modified 2× hexadecyltryltrimethyl-ammonium bromide procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C15">Doyle and Doyle 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C27">Hodkinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), and was purified with JetQuick columns (GENOMED Gmbh) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Two polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based methods were employed to assess genetic diversity: AFLPs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C58">Vos <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>) and nuclear microsatellites—simple-sequence repeats (SSRs).Sampled DNA was restricted with the endonucleases EcoRI and MseI and ligated to appropriate double-stranded adapters according to the manufacturer's protocols. Amplified fragment length polymorphism analysis was performed according to the AFLP plant mapping protocol of Applied Biosystems, Inc. Two steps of amplification followed: a pre-selective amplification using primer pairs with one selective base was followed by a selective amplification to further reduce the number of fragments. For the second amplification, the following three selective primer pairs were selected sequentially: EcoRI-ACA/MseI-CAG, EcoRI-AAG/MseI-CTC and EcoRI-AGC/MseI-CAG. The products were sized using an Applied Biosystems 310 Genetic Analyzer with GeneScan version 3.1 and Genotyper version 3.7 software. Amplified fragment length polymorphism profiles were manually scored with the presence of each peak recorded as ‘1’ and the absence of a peak as ‘0’. Only peaks ranging from 50 to 500 bp were scored. A peak was scored as present if it was separated by at least 1 bp and has a relatively high peak height threshold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C36">Meudt and Clarke 2007</xref>). In order to reduce genotyping error, AFLP profiles were scored at least twice by individuals with no knowledge of the origin of plant material.No SSR markers have been published for <italic>R. ponticum</italic>, and so nuclear SSR amplification of seven polymorphic loci isolated from <italic>R. metternichii</italic> var. <italic>hondoense</italic> was screened according to the methods described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C38">Naito <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref>, of which four were informative for <italic>R. ponticum</italic> (RM3D2, RM2D2, RM9D6 and RM2D5). Polymerase chain reaction amplification followed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C38">Naito <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>), and the amplicons were sized on an Applied Biosystems 310 Genetic Analyzer with GeneScan version 3.1 and Genotyper version 3.7 software.<italic>Rhododendron ponticum</italic> populations used for flower morphology measurements.For the AFLP data set, genetic diversity estimates were calculated with AFLPsurv V.1.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C57">Vekemans <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). To estimate allelic frequencies, the Bayesian method with a non-uniform prior distribution of allele frequencies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C62">Zhivotovsky 1999</xref>) was used. Due to the mixed mating system of the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C52">Stout 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>), we assumed some deviation (<italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub> = 0.1) from the Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium. Statistics of gene diversity were calculated according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C32">Lynch and Milligan (1994)</xref>. For each population, we calculated the proportion of polymorphic loci (<italic>P</italic>) and Nei's gene diversity (<italic>H</italic><sub>j</sub>). For the SSR data set, GenAlEx 6.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C43">Peakall and Smouse 2006</xref>) was used to test for departures from the Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium. Observed heterozygosity (<italic>H</italic><sub>O</sub>) and Nei's expected heterozygosity (<italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>) were calculated with GenAlEx 6.2, and the average heterozygosity was calculated with PopGene 1.32 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C60">Yeh <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>).Unweighted pair group method with arithmetic mean cluster analysis (UPGMA) was performed in PopGene 1.32 using Nei's genetic distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C39">Nei 1972</xref>) to analyse the patterns of population-level genetic distances across all populations for both the AFLP and SSR data sets. A Mantel test was used to compare pairwise genetic differences from the AFLP and SSR data.Corolla width and tube width were compared between regions (Ireland and Spain), among populations within regions and among plants within populations, using hierarchical (nested) ANOVA (with ‘region’, Ireland or Spain, as a fixed factor, ‘population’ nested within the region as a random factor and ‘plant’ nested within the population as a random factor; <italic>n</italic> = 5). Analyses were conducted using GMAV5 for Windows (University of Sydney, Australia). Data were tested for heterogeneity of variances using Cochran's test prior to analysis (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0976 and 0.0978 for corolla and tube width data, respectively) and were not transformed. <italic>Post-hoc</italic> Student–Newman–Keuls (SNK) tests were used to determine which means differed from each other (using the standard threshold of significance <italic>α</italic> = 0.05).Analysis of molecular variance based on: (a) 402 AFLP loci and (b) four nuclear SSR loci. <italic>φ</italic><sub>RT</sub> is the correlation of individuals from the same region (Spain or Ireland) relative to that of the total; <italic>φ</italic><sub>PR</sub> is the correlation between individuals within a population relative to that of individuals within the same region; <italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> is the correlation between individuals within a population relative to that of individuals of the total (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C44">Peakall <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>).Genetic distances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C39">Nei 1972</xref>) based on the (a) AFLP data set and (b) SSR data set. Values and levels of significance are given in the lower left and upper right of triangle, respectively. Significances are based on random permutations (9999). *<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05 , **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 ,***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.Rooted UPGMA tree depicting relationships between the populations investigated based on: (A) the AFLP data set and (B) the SSR data set using Nei's genetic distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C39">Nei 1972</xref>). Asterisks indicate native Spanish populations and scale bars represent genetic distance.A total of 29 alleles were detected within the 83 <italic>R. ponticum</italic> individuals and across the four nuclear SSR loci examined (RM3D2 = 6, RM2D2 = 9, RM9D6 = 8, RM2D5 = 6). There were no significant departures from the Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium for any of the markers across populations. All populations had similar percentages of heterozygosity and the effective allele number ranged from 2.00 to 2.92 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU087TB1">1</xref>). Analysis of molecular variance revealed that 76 % of the variance was partitioned among individuals within populations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU087TB3">3</xref>b). There was, however, significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and relatively high genetic differentiation among all populations (<italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> = 0.243), among populations within regions (<italic>φ</italic><sub>PR</sub> = 0.133, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and between regions (<italic>φ</italic><sub>RT</sub> = 0.127, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU087TB3">3</xref>b). Pairwise <italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> values between populations were variable, ranging from &lt;0.001 to 0.427 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU087TB4">4</xref>b). Non-hierarchical AMOVAs (not shown) revealed significant differentiation between Irish populations (<italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> = 0.126; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and no differentiation between Spanish populations (<italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> = 0.104; <italic>P</italic> = 0.065). In contrast to the AFLP results, the UPGMA grouped the two Spanish populations with the Irish Glencullen population. Within this group, the Glencullen population grouped most closely with the El Palancar population (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU087F1">1</xref>B). No relationship was found between linear AFLP and SSR individual pairwise genetic distance matrices (<italic>r</italic><sub>xy</sub> = 0.360, <italic>P</italic> = 0.076).Nested ANOVA results comparing corolla widths and tube widths of flowers between regions (Ireland and Spain), among populations (four per country, nested within regions) and within population (among five sampled plants nested within populations) (<italic>n</italic> = 5).Mean (±SE) (A) corolla width in millimetre and (B) tube width in millimetre of flowers from each population within each region (Ireland and Spain). Means were calculated from five flowers from each of five plants within each population, and then for the population. Letters above scale bars correspond to the results of multiple comparison tests (SNK, <italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05).This study shows that both genetic diversity and floral width vary between populations of <italic>R. ponticum</italic>, but that native, rare populations are genetically and morphologically distinct from invasive populations. We found similar levels of genetic diversity in both declining native (Spanish) and invasive introduced (Irish) populations of <italic>R. ponticum</italic>. However, populations and regions were also genetically differentiated, a trend detected with both AFLP and SSR markers. Such genetic differentiation is expected when genetic drift and inbreeding occur in geographically isolated populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C42">Oakley and Winn 2012</xref>). Our findings of low genetic diversity and genetic similarity between Spanish and Irish populations support the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C21">Erfmeier and Bruelheide (2011)</xref> using AFLP markers on native and invasive populations of <italic>R. ponticum</italic>. Although the level of diversity detected with AFLP and SSR markers was low, it was within the range for a species with a mixed mating system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C41">Nybom and Bartish 2000</xref>). <italic>Rhododenron ponticum</italic> primarily relies on insect-mediated pollination for sexual reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C34">Mejías <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C52">Stout 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>); however, clones may be prominent within populations resulting from vegetative spread (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C34">Mejías <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). We found 28 SSR genotypes in the Irish samples, of which 12 occurred more than once, and so may be clonal, with one to eight unique genotypes per population <bold>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu087/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">see Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold>. Therefore, pollen transfer between neighbouring plants may result in bi-parental inbreeding (where both parents are closely related), rather than outcrossing. In fact, observations of the behaviour of pollinators suggest that the levels of geitonogamy (pollen transfer among flowers of the same plant) may be high, since the main pollinators of <italic>R. ponticum</italic> in Ireland (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) tend to move between flowers on the same plant far more frequently than between flowers on different plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C53">Stout 2007<italic>b</italic></xref>).The native Spanish <italic>R. ponticum</italic> populations had more private AFLP bands (each population had 14 private bands) than invasive Irish ones (which had a mean of six private bands). Spanish populations contained fewer than 30 individual plants possibly due to range contraction and lack of sexual regeneration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C34">Mejías <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). The introduced Irish populations were generally larger than the Spanish ones and were expanding as a result of both sexual and vegetative reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C54">Stout <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), but they may have derived from a small number of founding individuals. Thus Irish populations contained lower genetic variation and a lower number of private bands. Examination of polymorphic chloroplast DNA would be useful to explore founder effects further, as if there were a small number of founding individuals, we might expect low plastid diversity.Our data show that native Spanish populations have probably experienced a recent genetic bottleneck as they have both low overall expected heterozygosity (<italic>H</italic><sub>j</sub>), as estimated by AFLPs, and low allelic diversity, as estimated by SSRs. In addition, Irish Glencullen population groups with Spanish populations in both the AFLP and SSR analyses (and Irish Howth, Glencullen and Recess are not significantly differentiated from the Spanish Las Corzas population in AFLP pairwise <italic>φ</italic><sub>PT</sub> comparisons), which reveals the similarity of Irish and Spanish populations. However, the grouping of one of the Irish populations (Glencullen) with the Spanish populations could be due to homoplasy (a similar genetic structure due to convergence): this population also has more private alleles (alleles that are unique to a particular population from many populations sampled), and other Irish populations may have grouped together as they have fewer private alleles.The population differentiation found, even between pairs of populations in each geographical location in Ireland (counties Galway, Kerry and Dublin), suggests that the gene flow is limited. This supports findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C51">Stephenson <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> who examined seed dispersal in this species and concluded that a very small proportion (0.02 %) of seeds moved &gt;50 m, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C53">Stout (2007<italic>b</italic>)</xref> who found that pollen dispersal was also likely to be limited (with 98 % of bee moves between flowers &lt;1 m apart). Thus, with limited gene flow via both pollen and seeds, spread is likely to be the result of populations spreading in the form of an ‘invasion front’ and/or repeated introductions. Hence, management should focus on containing existing populations and preventing new introductions.Corolla width varied much more within populations than between them, particularly in Spain. This suggests that this trait is not under strong selection pressure or is naturally highly variable, and our measurements are consistent with other descriptions of corolla width (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C34">Mejías <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> describe flowers as having a corolla of up to 6 cm in diameter). Tube width is clearly a highly variable trait in <italic>R. ponticum</italic>, varying between individuals within populations, among populations and between regions, similar to the patterns found for genetic diversity. No previous published studies have described tube width in <italic>R. ponticum</italic>. However, corolla tubes were, on average, &gt;0.5 mm wider in Irish populations than in Spanish ones. Wider corolla tubes may be associated with increased pollinator visitation rates, because a greater range of pollinating insects can access the nectar from more open flowers with wider tubes. Wider corolla tubes in the introduced range may be an advantage, given that introduced species have to rely on native generalist insects for pollination. Indeed, a range of generalist visitor species were recorded visiting <italic>R. ponticum</italic> in Ireland, including solitary bees, bumblebees and hoverflies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C54">Stout <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). The most common pollinators in Ireland are bumblebees, which have relatively long tongues (compared with hoverflies and solitary bees) and the ability to rob nectar if corolla tubes are too narrow for them to probe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C54">Stout <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). However, the most effective pollinators are large queen bumblebees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C53">Stout 2007<italic>b</italic></xref>), which may be able to visit and collect nectar more efficiently if corolla tubes are wider (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C55">Suzuki 1994</xref>). Further comparisons of pollinator behaviour in the invasive and native range would be needed to test this hypothesis. Given that populations have diverged at a genetic level, we can also expect divergence at a morphological level (although the same populations were not compared for molecular and morphological analyses in this study). It may be non-adaptive processes, such as ecological sorting, different introduction times of <italic>R. ponticum</italic> to Ireland historically and phenotypic plasticity (i.e. changed phenotype in response to environmental conditions, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C26">Herrera 1992</xref>), that have a strong effect on the results observed. Indeed genetic drift and founder effects may explain the relatively low, though significant, levels of genetic differentiation observed. More work is needed to clarify whether such non-adaptive processes alone, or in combination with adaptive evolution in novel habitats, drive population differentiation in non-native populations. Although <italic>R. ponticum</italic> is very long-lived, it was introduced 200–250 years ago, and there has been time for post-introduction evolutionary change. Indeed, studies have found evidence for post-introduction selection affecting vegetative growth in <italic>R. ponticum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C19">Erfmeier and Bruelheide 2005</xref>). Alternatively, initial introductions into Ireland may have been of wider tubed individuals; historical herbarium flower specimens could be used to investigate this, as long as the corolla tube is visible and intact. However, this is relatively unlikely given that there have been repeated introductions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C50">Stephenson <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). In addition, there is little evidence for this floral difference to be a result of post-introduction hybridization with other <italic>Rhododendron</italic> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU087C22">Erfmeier <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).Using both the AFLP and SSR markers, we have shown that invasive <italic>R. ponticum</italic> in Ireland has low genetic diversity and populations are closely related to ancestral Spanish ones, but are also differentiated from one another, with limited between-population gene flow. Introduced individuals produce flowers with wider corolla tubes, which may attract more floral visitors due to increased nectar availability. The results of this study show that native Spanish populations are distinct and should be the focus of continuing conservation attention due to their restricted distribution and small size.This work was funded by an <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">Enterprise Ireland Postdoctoral Fellowship</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">PD/2001/050</grant-num>), a Trinity Trust Award, a <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">British Ecological Society Small Ecological Project Grant</grant-sponsor>, a grant from the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Percy Sladen Memorial Fund (Linnean Society)</grant-sponsor> and a <grant-sponsor id="cs2" rid="cn2" xlink:type="simple">Science Foundation Ireland Research Frontiers Programme</grant-sponsor> grant (<grant-num id="cn2" rid="cs2" xlink:type="simple">10/RFP/EOB2842</grant-num>). K.J.D. is funded by the University of KwaZulu-Natal Postdoctoral fellowship.The lead author designed the study, obtained the funding, carried out fieldwork, laboratory work, data analysis and writing; all other authors contributed to study design, fieldwork, laboratory work, data analysis and writing.None declared.The following <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu087/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link> is available in the online version of this article –<bold>File S1.</bold> 28 unique genotypes from 61 <italic>R. ponticum</italic> individuals in Irish populations identified by 4 SSR markers.The authors thank Dr Naomi Kingston for assistance and advice in the laboratory and Dr Juan Arroyo for showing them the location of populations in Spain and to Parque Natural ‘Los Alcornocales’ for permission to sample there. They are grateful to three anonymous reviewers for comments that greatly improved this paper.