 Genome size variation and evolution in allotetraploid  Arabidopsis kamchatica  and its parents,  Arabidopsis lyrata  and  Arabidopsis halleri   Polyploidy and genome evolution in plants  Nuclear DNA content in some species of  Lessingianthus  (Vernonieae, Asteraceae) by flow cytometry  Fitting linear mixed models in R  Nuclear DNA content and minimum generation time in herbaceous plants  Anthocyanin inhibits propidium iodide DNA fluorescence in  Euphorbia pulcherrima : implications for genome size variation and flow cytometry  Karyological analysis and genome size in  Milium  (Gramineae) with special reference to polyploidy and chromosomal evolution  Rapid, repeated, and clustered loss of duplicate genes in allopolyploid plant populations of independent origin  Genetic and epigenetic mechanisms for gene expression and phenotypic variation in plant polyploids  Characterizing polyploidy in  Arabidopsis lyrata  using chromosome counts and flow cytometry  Large-scale polymorphism of heterochromatic repeats in the DNA of  Arabidopsis thaliana   In IOPB chromosome number reports LXIII  Redundancy and rewiring of genetic networks following genome-wide duplication events  Nuclear genome size: are we getting closer?  Flow cytometric estimation of nuclear DNA amount in diploid bananas ( Musa acuminata  and  M. balbisiana )  Nuclear DNA content and genome size of trout and human  Estimation of nuclear DNA content in plants using flow cytometry  Role of adaptive and non-adaptive mechanisms forming complex patterns of genome size variation in six cytotypes of polyploid  Allium oleraceum  (Amaryllidaceae) on a continental scale  Systemic endopolyploidy in  Arabidopsis thaliana   Impact of mating systems on patterns of sequence polymorphism in flowering plants  Intraspecific variation in genome size in angiosperms: identifying its existence  Aneuploidy and genetic variation in the  Arabidopsis thaliana  triploid response  Dosage and parent-of-origin effects shaping aneuploid swarms in  A. thaliana   Population fragmentation causes randomly fixed genotypes in populations of  Arabidopsis kamchatica  in the Japanese Archipelago  Simultaneous inference in general parametric models  The role of triploid hybrids in the evolutionary dynamics of mixed-ploidy populations  A metapopulation perspective on genetic diversity and differentiation in partially self-fertilizing plants  A unique recent origin of the allotetraploid species  Arabidopsis suecica : evidence from nuclear DNA markers  Ancestral polyploidy in seed plants and angiosperms  Interspecific and interploidal gene flow in central european  Arabidopsis  (Brassicaceae)  Gene loss, silencing and activation in a newly synthesized wheat allotetraploid  Wheat: reconstitution of the tetraploid component (AABB) of hexaploids  Applications of flow cytometry to evolutionary and population biology  A case of genome partition in polyploid oats  Genome downsizing in polyploid plants   S -gene polymorphism in  Phlox drummondii   Massive genomic variation and strong selection in  Arabidopsis thaliana  lines from Sweden  Flow cytometric and microscopic analysis of the effect of tannic acid on plant nuclei and estimation of DNA content  Ecological determinants of genetic structure in plant populations  A preliminary note on the chromosomes of  Oenothera lamarckiana  and one of its mutants,  O. gigas   Polyploidy and its effect on evolutionary success: old questions revisited with new tools  Natural variation and persistent developmental instabilities in geographically diverse accessions of the allopolyploid  Arabidopsis suecica   Cytotype diversity and genome size variation in eastern Asian polyploid  Cardamine  (Brassicaceae) species  Allopolyploidization lays the foundation for evolution of distinct populations: evidence from analysis of synthetic  Arabidopsis  allohexaploids  Relationship between endopolyploidy and cell cize in epidermal tissue of  Arabidopsis   Synopsis of the genus  Arabis  (Brassicaceae) in Canada, Alaska and Greenland  DAPI staining of fixed cells for high-resolution flow cytometry of nuclear DNA  Polyploid incidence and evolution  Allopolyploidy-induced rapid genome evolution in the wheat ( Aegilops–Triticum ) group  Associated chromosomal DNA changes in polyploids  Chloroplast DNA indicates a single origin of the allotetraploid  Arabidopsis suecica   Arabidopsis hybrid speciation processes  The evolutionary history of the  Arabidopsis lyrata  complex: a hybrid in the amphi-Beringian area closes a large distribution gap and builds up a genetic barrier  Genome size variation among accessions of  Arabidopsis thaliana   Attempts to relate cytological and molecular chromosome data of  Arabidopsis thaliana  to its genetic linkage map   Arabidopsis kamchatica  (fisch. Ex dc.) K. Shimizu &amp; Kudoh and  A. kamchatica  subsp.  kawasakiana  (Makino) K. Shimizu &amp; Kudoh, new combinations  The allopolyploid  Arabidopsis kamchatica  originated from multiple individuals of  Arabidopsis lyrata  and  Arabidopsis halleri   Understanding intraspecific variation in genome size in plants  Polyploidy: recurrent formation and genome evolution  The evolutionary dynamics of polyploid plants: origins, establishment and persistence  The origins of genomic duplications in  Arabidopsis   Multilocus analysis of genetic divergence between outcrossing  Arabidopsis  species: evidence of genome-wide admixture  Yesterday's polyploids and the mystery of diploidization  The frequency of polyploid speciation in vascular plants   Associate Editor:  W. Scott Armbruster  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Genome doubling and changes in genome size are fundamental evolutionary processes.  Arabidopsis kamchatica  has been reported to contain both diploid and tetraploid individuals (2 or 4 copies of every chromosome). We did find genome size differences among populations, and among populations genome size varied 7%. However, all sampled  A. kamchatica  plants from a wide geographic range were tetraploids. This level of intraspecific genome size variation in  A. kamchatica  is lower than in other  Arabidopsis  taxa. Due to its close relationship to  A. thaliana ,  A. kamchatica  has the potential to be very useful in the study of polyploidy and genome evolution.  Polyploidization and subsequent changes in genome size are fundamental processes in evolution and diversification. Little is currently known about the extent of genome size variation within taxa and the evolutionary forces acting on this variation.  Arabidopsis kamchatica  has been reported to contain both diploid and tetraploid individuals. The aim of this study was to determine the genome size of  A. kamchatica , whether there is variation in ploidy and/or genome size in  A. kamchatica  and to study how genome size has evolved .  We used propidium iodide flow cytometry to measure 2C DNA content of 73 plants from 25 geographically diverse populations of the putative allotetraploid  A. kamchatica  and its parents,  Arabidopsis lyrata  and  Arabidopsis halleri . All  A. kamchatica  plants appear to be tetraploids. The mean 2C DNA content of  A. kamchatica  was 1.034 pg (1011 Mbp), which is slightly smaller than the sum of its diploid parents ( A. lyrata : 0.502 pg;  A. halleri : 0.571 pg).  Arabidopsis kamchatica  appears to have lost ∼37.594 Mbp (3.6 %) of DNA from its 2C genome. Tetraploid  A. lyrata  from Germany and Austria appears to have lost ∼70.366 Mbp (7.2 %) of DNA from the 2C genome, possibly due to hybridization with  A. arenosa , which has a smaller genome than  A. lyrata . We did find genome size differences among  A. kamchatica  populations, which varied up to 7 %.  Arabidopsis kamchatica  ssp.  kawasakiana  from Japan appears to have a slightly larger genome than  A. kamchatica  ssp.  kamchatica  from North America, perhaps due to multiple allopolyploid origins or hybridization with  A. halleri . However, the among-population coefficient of variation in 2C DNA content is lower in  A. kamchatica  than in other  Arabidopsis  taxa. Due to its close relationship to  A. thaliana ,  A. kamchatica  has the potential to be very useful in the study of polyploidy and genome evolution.  Polyploidy is one of the most important forces influencing plant diversification. Polyploidy was likely involved in 15 % of all recent angiosperm speciation events ( Wood  et al.  2009 ) and ancient polyploidy is apparent in all plant genomes sequenced to date ( Jiao  et al.  2011 ). Similarly, the majority of cultivated crops have undergone polyploidization during domestication ( Otto and Whitton 2000 ). Polyploidy influences the ecology and physiology of plants by generating novel phenotypes that may influence mating system, habitat and geographical distribution ( Levin 2002 ). It can have major genetic and genomic effects, such as altering chromosome segregation, masking deleterious mutations, influencing levels of genetic diversity, changing gene expression, causing rearrangements, gene loss and epigenetic changes, rewiring genetic networks, and altering rates of adaptation ( Levin 2002 ;  Adams and Wendel 2005 ;  Chen 2007 ;  De Smet and Van de Peer 2012 ;  Madlung 2013 ). Ploidy variation has the potential to promote the origin of new species, but ploidy variation within species (or species complexes) may also be an important source of genetic and phenotypic variation ( Thompson and Lumaret 1992 ). Thus, plant biodiversity cannot be understood without understanding the processes of polyploid evolution ( Lutz 1907 ;  Stebbins 1950 ;  Grant 1981 ;  Madlung 2013 ).  Polyploids are thought to experience high levels of genomic instability and undergo massive genetic and epigenetic changes within the first few generations after formation ( Chen 2007 ). It is likely that a great deal of genomic and phenotypic diversity is generated and the majority of early generation polyploids are unable to survive in nature. However, if one or a few stable genotypes arise that happen to reconcile genomic incompatibilities, are vigorous and are well suited to survival in the prevailing habitat, polyploids can persist ( Chen 2007 ;  Madlung  et al.  2012 ). After this rapid ‘genomic revolution’, it is likely that a slow process of diploidization begins, where gene duplicates may be silenced, lost or evolve new functions ( Wolfe 2001 ). It is thought that nearly all angiosperms have experienced at least one polyploidy event in their evolutionary history ( Wolfe 2001 ). However, due to extensive mutation, gene loss and rearrangements, these diploidized paleopolyploids, such as  Arabidopsis thaliana , have only recently been recognized as whole-genome sequences became available for detailed analysis ( Vision  et al.  2000 ). Both the rapid genomic revolution and gradual process of diploidization are likely to result in variation and evolution in genome size as DNA is deleted, duplicated and rearranged, and variants are subject to genetic drift and selection.  Polyploidy can arise from the duplication of genomes within a single species (autopolyploidy) or through hybridization between two species, accompanied by chromosome doubling (allopolyploidy) ( Levin 2002 ). Either allopolyploidy or autopolyploidy may arise via a single polyploidization event, like in  Arabidopsis suecica  ( Säll  et al.  2003 ;  Jakobsson  et al.  2006 ), or may have multiple origins ( Soltis and Soltis 1999 ), as has been suggested for  A. kamchatica  ( Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  2009 ). Further, variation in ploidy level is frequently found within species both within and among populations ( Schmuths  et al.  2004 ;  Marhold  et al.  2010 ), and gene flow between ploidy levels is known to occur, either via a triploid bridge or through recurrent formation of unreduced gametes by diploids ( Levin 2002 ;  Husband 2004 ;  Henry  et al.  2005 ,  2009 ;  Jørgensen  et al.  2011 ). This gene flow from diploids to polyploids is likely an important source of genetic variation in polyploids ( Jørgensen  et al.  2011 ).   Arabidopsis kamchatica  is an allotetraploid plant produced through hybridization through two closely related diploid taxa,  Arabidopsis lyrata  ssp.  petraea  and  Arabidopsis halleri  ssp.  gemmifera  ( Shimizu  et al.  2005 ;  Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  2009 ).  Arabidopsis kamchatica  has an amphi-Beringian distribution, and the pattern of genetic diversity suggests that it migrated northward out of Japan (or near Japan) to eastern Russia, across the Bering land bridge into Alaska, and down the west coast of Canada ( Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  2009 ). It has been suggested that  A. kamchatica  may have multiple origins through independent hybridization and polyploidization events ( Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  2009 ), and/or that it may hybridize with its diploid parental taxa ( Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  2009 ;  Wang  et al.  2010 ). Both of these processes have the potential to give rise to genome size variation. Further,  A. kamchatica  has been suggested to contain both diploid and tetraploid individuals ( Dawe and Murray 1981 ;  Wang  et al.  2010 ). Because  A. kamchatica  is a close relative of the model plant,  A. thaliana , a treasure trove of molecular research is easily applied to this organism, and development of  A. kamchatica  into a model system for the evolution of polyploidy has the potential to yield a great deal of insight into the evolution of polyploid genomes.  The goal of this study was to investigate genome size variation in  A. kamchatica  using flow cytometry. We characterized the nuclear DNA content of  A. kamchatica  and its putative parental species,  A. lyrata  and  A. halleri , in a total of 25 populations from North America, Europe and Japan. We used the results to determine whether there is variation in ploidy and/or genome size in  A. kamchatica  and its parents, and to determine how genome size has evolved in polyploids relative to their diploid parents.  Collection locations, collectors and mean (±1 SE) genome size of each population.  1 Assumes  Glycine max  ‘Polanka’ 2C DNA content of 2.5 pg ( Doležel  et al.  1994 ;  Doležel and Greilhuber 2010 ).  2 Populations with different letters have significantly different means ( P  &lt; 0.05) in post hoc comparisons among  A. kamchatica  populations with &gt;2 individuals.  3 Conversion from pg to Mbp assuming Mbp = pg × 978 ( Doležel  et al.  2003 ).  Map of collection localities of plants used for flow cytometry.  Chromosome counting is the traditional method for determining ploidy level of an organism; however, it is labour intensive and may be inaccurate in  Arabidopsis  species due to their very small chromosomes (ranging from 1.5 m to 2.8 µm in  A. thaliana ;  Schweizer  et al.  1987 ) and the high frequency of endopolyploidy ( Galbraith  et al.  1991 ;  Melarango  et al.  1993 ). Flow cytometry allows rapid analysis of thousands of nuclei per sample and high throughput of many samples ( Kron  et al.  2007 ). Therefore, we used flow cytometry to estimate genome size and infer DNA ploidy. Because flow cytometry reveals genome size rather than a count of chromosomes, ploidy must be verified by chromosome counts in at least a few samples. In our study, we included both diploid and tetraploid references from  Arabidopsis  locations where both flow cytometry and chromosome counts have previously been carried out ( A. kamchatica  from Japan, and  A. l. petraea  from Iceland and Austria; Table  1 ;  Dart  et al.  2004 ).  Each  Arabidopsis  sample was co-chopped and run with soybean leaf,  Glycine max  ‘Polanka’, as an internal reference standard. The standard was grown from the same seed stock previously quantified ( Doležel  et al.  1994 ). Young leaves were collected from each  Arabidopsis  plant and kept on ice until processing, which occurred within 3 h of leaf collection. For each plant, three fresh leaves were placed in a plastic Petri dish with approximately half as much fresh leaf tissue from  G. max . Leaf tissue was chopped in the presence of 0.5 mL of cold chopping buffer using a fresh stainless-steel razor blade. The chopping buffer was modified from  Otto (1990)  Buffer I by adding 0.5 % v/v of Triton X-100 rather than Tween 20. When the leaves were well chopped, we added an additional 0.5 mL of cold chopping buffer. The sample was then filtered through a 30-µm Partec CellTrics ®  filter and centrifuged for 20 s at 3500 rpm. The supernatant was drawn off and 2 µL of RNase A was added to the pellet. The pellet was resuspended in 0.2 mL of propidium iodine staining buffer. The propidium iodine staining buffer (28.65 g of dibasic sodium phosphate, 190 mL of deionized water and 10 mL of propidium iodine stock, which consists of 5 mg of propidium iodine and 10 mL of deionized water) was modified from  Otto (1990) . Samples were stained in the dark for 40 min prior to performing flow cytometry.  Fluorescence intensity histograms (PE-A) for (A) tetraploid  A. kamchatica  (2C = 4 x  = 32), (B) diploid  A. h. gemmifera  (2C = 2 x  = 16) and (C) diploid  A. lyrata  (2C = 2 x  = 16).  Arabidopsis  leaves show extensive endopolyploidy ( Galbraith  et al.  1991 ), and the 2C, 4C and 8C peaks are indicated, along with the soybean standard (std). The mean fluorescence of the smallest peak (2C) relative to the soybean peak was used to estimate 2C DNA content.  To determine whether the taxa differed in genome size, we used a linear mixed-effects model with species as the fixed effect, populations as the random effect and 2C DNA content (pg) as the dependent variable with the  lme4  package ( Bates 2005 ), implemented in R. The hypothesis test of the species effect was conducted with 5000 iterations of the parametric bootstrap approach based on the likelihood ratio statistics,  D  = −2 × (log-likelihood ratio), of  Faraway (2006) . To determine which species differed from one another in 2C DNA content, we performed Tukey's multiple comparison tests with an R package,  multcomp  ( Hothorn  et al.  2008 ). To determine whether populations of  A. kamchatica  differed in 2C DNA content, a second one-way ANOVA was performed with population as the fixed effect and 2C DNA content (pg) as the dependent variable. For this analysis we restricted our dataset to include only the nine  A. kamchatica  populations for which we had at least three samples. The mean number of samples per population was 5.3. Tukey's multiple comparison tests were performed to determine which  A. kamchatica  populations significantly differed from one another in genome size. In order to test the additivity of the tetraploid genome size, we examined a contrast null hypothesis, where the 1Cx genome size (i.e. the haploid genome size,  sensu   Greilhuber 2005 ) of  A. kamchatica  is the average of the two parental species, in the subset of data including  A. kamchatica ,  A. h. gemifera  and  A. lyrata  (two subspecies were combined). A linear mixed-effects model was fitted with 1Cx values as the dependent variable, population as a random effect and species as a fixed effect, and the linear contrast, (1Cx of  A. kamchatica ) = [(1Cx of  A. h. gemifera ) + (1Cx of  A. lyrata )]/2, was tested with an R package,  multcomp . For estimates of genome size diversity in each taxon, we used the CV among populations in 2C DNA content with the bias correction ( Sokal and Rohlf 1995 ). To estimate genome size diversity in diploid  A. thaliana , we used data from  Schmuths  et al.  (2004)  collected from 18 worldwide accessions using the same flow cytometry methods that we used.  Estimates of 2C DNA content (pg) of each taxon and the 95 % confidence intervals of the estimates. Letters indicate significant differences ( P &lt; 0.05) based on Tukey's post hoc comparisons.  There was significant variation in genome size among  A. kamchatica  populations ( F  8,39  = 15.7,  P  &lt; 10 −9 ). Post hoc tests indicate that the genome size of the Japanese  A. kamchatica  population (Shinbo) was significantly larger than the North American populations. The Canadian  A. kamchatica  population did not differ in genome size from the Alaskan populations. However, two of the six Alaskan populations differed in genome size; the nuclear DNA content of the Goodnews Bay population was 3 % smaller than that of the Grant Lagoon population. Despite the minor amounts of variation among populations, none of the  A. kamchatica  plants sampled appear to be diploid.  The 2C DNA content of  A. l. lyrata  (0.503 pg/2C, 95 % CI [0.484, 0.522]) and diploid  A. l. petraea  (0.502 pg/2C, 95 % CI [0.484, 0.521]) did not significantly differ from one another (Fig.  3 ). The  A. h. gemmifera  genome (0.571 pg/2C, 95 % CI [0.539, 0.604]) was 14 % larger than  A. l. petraea  and  A. l. lyrata  (Fig.  3 ). We did not have enough samples/population of these taxa to analyse differences among populations.  Estimates of 1Cx (haploid) genome size (pg) of each taxon. The error bars are 95 % confidence intervals of the estimates. Letters indicate significant differences ( P  &lt; 0.05) based on Tukey's post hoc comparisons.  Genome size diversity in  Arabidopsis  taxa, measured as CV in 2C DNA content. Only diploid  A. thaliana  and  A. l. petraea  are included because there were too few tetraploids to estimate CV (two from each taxon).  Our genome size estimates are very similar to those of  Dart  et al.  (2004)  for diploid and tetraploid collections in common (Table  1 ), suggesting that our results are reliable. Using both chromosome counting and flow cytometry,  Dart  et al.  (2004)  found that plants from Japan (Shinbo) and Austria are tetraploid (2 n  = 4 x  = 32) with genome sizes of 1.1 pg/2C (Japan) and 0.9 pg/2C (Austria), while plants from Iceland are diploid (2 n  = 2 x  = 16) with a genome size of 0.52 pg/2C. The small differences between our data and those of  Dart  et al.  (2004)  are likely due to the fact that  Dart  et al.  (2004)  used fluorescent beads as an internal size standard, whereas we used leaf tissue from  G. max . While beads are sufficient for ploidy determination, leaf tissue is the preferred internal size standard for absolute genome size estimation because staining variation can be taken into account ( Doležel  et al.  2007 ).  Several previous reports have suggested that  A. kamchatica  contains both diploid and tetraploid individuals ( Dawe and Murray 1981 ;  Wang  et al.  2010 ). While many species show a mix of ploidy levels, even within a population, these are likely autopolyploids ( Schmuths  et al.  2004 ;  Jørgensen  et al.  2011 ). Given that  A. kamchatica  is an allopolyploid, diploids spontaneously produced from tetraploids would likely have low vigour and fertility ( Kerber 1964 ;  Ladizinsky and Fainstein 1978 ), as allopolyploidization appears to rapidly result in gene silencing and gene loss for numerous loci ( Kashkush  et al.  2002 ;  Adams and Wendel 2005 ). Our data from 52  A. kamchatica  specimens representing most of the species' range found no evidence of diploid  A. kamchatica , and we suggest that the species is likely to be entirely tetraploid. If diploids are present, they are likely to be in very low frequencies, and not maintained by selection.  Deeper investigation into previous reports also suggests that there is no good evidence for the presence of diploid  A. kamchatica .  Dawe and Murray (1981)  report chromosome counts from three diploid (2 n  = 2 x  = 16) and two tetraploid  A. kamchatica  samples (2 n  = 4 x  = 32).  Arabidopsis kamchatica  is very difficult to morphologically distinguish from mostly diploid  A. lyrata ; however, molecular data suggest that the two species have distinct geographical ranges ( Schmickl  et al.  2010 ). The tetraploid counts reported by  Dawe and Murray (1981)  are within the species range of  A. kamchatica  suggested by  Schmickl  et al.  (2010) , whereas two of the three diploid counts are from plants growing north of the Brooks Range in Alaska and are probably  A. l. petraea  ( Schmickl  et al.  2010 ) or  A. media  ( Mulligan 1995 ). One of the diploid counts (originally reported in  Dawe and Murray 1979 ) comes from well within  A. kamchatica 's range in interior Alaska, near several of our collections (63°02′N, 145°29′W), and was likely taken from  A. kamchatica . However,  Mulligan (1995)  claims that the diploid report is an error, and that the voucher in ALA indicates that 2 n  = 32 (tetraploid), not 2 n  = 16 (diploid). Other chromosome counts reported for  A. kamchatica  by  Mulligan (1995)  are all tetraploid, and he suggests that the species is entirely tetraploid.   Wang  et al.  (2010)  claim to have detected both diploid and tetraploid  A. kamchatica  in Taiwan using flow cytometry and sequencing of nuclear DNA from 98 genes. They suggest that diploids have a ‘mosaic genome’ of the two parental species. Although this would be very interesting if confirmed, more complete evidence is desirable. First, their flow cytometry runs seem to lack an internal standard. The absolute value of nucleus fluorescence cannot reliably be used to estimate genome size as this value shifts due to variation in sample preparation, staining and analysis ( Doležel  et al.  2007 ). This shift can be seen by comparing Fig. S1A and S1B in  Wang  et al  (2010 ), which were presented as evidence of diploid and tetraploid  A. kamchatica . Further, their DNA sequence data do not provide any evidence of ploidy since only a single clone per PCR reaction was sequenced, ensuring that only a single homeologue (randomly chosen from one of the two parental genomes of tetraploids) could be obtained from each individual ( Wang  et al.  2010 ). Although we have not sampled  A. kamchatica  from Taiwan for our study, the ‘mosaic genome’ of purported diploid  A. kamchatica  can possibly be explained by misinterpretation of flow cytometry data and randomly sequencing only one of the two homeologues from each gene.  We appear to have identified variation in the 2C DNA content among  A. kamchatica  populations.  Greilhuber (2005)  suggested that a great deal of apparent within-species, within-ploidy variation in genome DNA content estimated by flow cytometry is due to methodological artefacts. For instance, different levels of anthocyanins, tannic acid and other secondary metabolites in leaves can influence fluorescence and apparent DNA content ( Loureiro  et al.  2006 ;  Bennett  et al.  2008 ). Following best-practice recommended protocols ( Doležel  et al.  2007 ), we used an internal size standard co-chopped with each sample, we used Otto's buffer, which reduces the effects of tannic acid ( Loureiro  et al.  2006 ), and leaves were not pigmented. Further, repeated measurements of the same plant on different days produced very similar DNA content estimates (&lt;1.1 % variation). Thus the variation we observed should be biologically real ( Schmuths  et al.  2004 ). However, co-chopping two putatively different samples from different populations would further increase certainty that differences among populations are not artefactual ( Greilhuber 2005 ).  The 2C DNA content of Japanese  A. kamchatica  appears to be slightly larger than North American  A. kamchatica . This observed genome size difference may differentiate the two  A. kamchatica  subspecies:  A. kamchatica  ssp.  kamchatica  and  A. kamchatica  ssp.  kawasakiana . Our Japanese  A. kamchatica  samples are from subspecies  A. k. kawasakiana , whereas the rest of our samples represent subspecies  A. k. kamchatica  from North America. These two subspecies differ in habitat, morphology and nucleotide allele frequencies ( Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  2009 ;  Higashi  et al.  2012 ), and  Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  (2009)  suggested that  A. k. kawasakiana  may represent a distinct origin of  A. kamchatica . The difference in genome size between the Japanese  A. k. kawasakiana  and North American  A. k. kamchatica  potentially supports that hypothesis. Alternatively, ongoing hybridization between  A. kamchatica  and its diploid parent,  A. h. gemmifera , in Asia ( Wang  et al.  2010 ) could increase the genome size in Asia by reintroducing homeologues that may have been deleted in the allotetraploid.  Other possible explanations for the genome size differences between Japan and North America include biogeographic history and selection. It has been suggested that time-limited environments may select for a smaller genome with more rapid cell division (reviewed in  Šmarda and Bureš 2010 ). As  A. kamchatica  expanded north out of Japan and across the cold Bering land bridge into North America ( Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  2009 ), a smaller genome may have been favoured due to the short growing season. Interestingly, despite the difference in genome size, Japanese and North American samples appear to have lost similar numbers of genes (P. L. Chang, unpubl. res.). Our sampling from Japan was very limited. A thorough investigation of genome size variation from throughout Japan, accompanied by an investigation of introgression and deletions, is needed for a thorough understanding of genome size evolution in this species.  Within-species variation in nuclear genome size may be an important source of genetic diversity, especially if it is associated with phenotypic and ecological variation ( Levin 2002 ;  Matsushita  et al.  2012 ). Although we did find significant levels of genome size diversity in the allotetraploid  A. kamchatica , levels of genome size diversity were much lower than in the diploid  Arabidopsis  taxa studied (Fig.  5 ). This is consistent with the low levels of nucleotide diversity in  A. kamchatica  relative to the other taxa studied ( Shimizu-Inatsugi  et al.  2009 ). Although nucleotide diversity is generated by point mutations, while genome size variation is generated by indels, changes in repetitive DNA and transposon activity ( Šmarda and Bureš 2010 ;  Long  et al.  2013 ), the two forms of genetic diversity are likely to be governed by many of the same population genetic processes such as mating system, biogeography and demographic history ( Loveless and Hamrick 1984 ;  Ingvarsson 2002 ;  Glémin  et al.  2006 ;  Duchoslav  et al.  2013 ).  The DNA content of tetraploid  A. kamchatica  was slightly less than expected based on the sum of the two parental taxa. It is possible that this apparent loss in DNA content could be artefactual, due to differences between species in plant secondary compounds ( Greilhuber 2005 ). However, rapid loss of DNA after polyploidization appears to be common in polyploids, as the 1Cx genome size has been shown to decrease as the ploidy level increases ( Bennett and Thomas 1991 ;  Raina  et al.  1994 ;  Ozkan  et al.  2001 ;  Leitch and Bennett 2004 ;  Angulo and Dematteis 2013 ;  Duchoslav  et al.  2013 ).  Bennett and Thomas (1991)  suggest that these changes in DNA content may have adaptive significance, perhaps because the rate of cell division is slowed considerably as genome size increases ( Bennett 1972 ) and it may be beneficial to remove unnecessary DNA when ploidy level is high.  The majority of genome size variation within plant species at a single ploidy level is due to variation in amounts of repetitive DNA such as transposable elements, ribosomal genes and centromeric repeats ( Levin 1993 ;  Davison  et al.  2007 ;  Šmarda and Bureš 2010 ;  Long  et al.  2013 ). However, polyploids may also lose considerable amounts of functional DNA either because it is not necessary to have two copies or because it may allow the two parental genomes to resolve incompatibilities ( Kashkush  et al.  2002 ;  Adams and Wendel 2005 ;  Buggs  et al.  2012 ). Whole-genome sequencing of  A. kamchatica , and comparison to its parental taxa, suggests that each of three accessions from different geographic regions lost ∼463 of more than 60 000 total genes (∼2 % of assembled genes; P. L. Chang, unpubl. res.). Considering that our flow cytometry estimate of the  A. kamchatica  genome size was 3.6 % smaller than expected based on the sum of the parental genomes, the total amount of DNA lost is comparable to the percent of genes lost. This suggests that DNA was lost from both genic regions and non-functional regions in  A. kamchatica .   Arabidopsis l. petraea  tetraploids appear to have lost considerably more DNA than  A. kamchatica . Although these plants are thought to be  A. l. petraea  autotetraploids, they may have experienced hybridization and introgression of DNA from  A. arenosa  ( Jørgensen  et al.  2011 ;  Schmickl and Koch 2011 ), which has a genome size that is 13 % smaller than  A. l. petraea  ( Jørgensen  et al.  2011 ). Using DNA content numbers from  Jørgensen  et al.  (2011) ,  A. l. petraea  tetraploid genomes are just slightly smaller than expected from the sum of diploid  A. l. petraea  and diploid  A. arenosa  genomes: observed tetraploid  A. l. petraea  relative genome size 0.44; vs expected diploid  A. l. petraea  0.23 + diploid  A. arenosa  0.20 = 0.43 (data are presented as a ratio of the sample peak over the internal standard peak, and cannot be converted to picograms since the 2C DNA content of the standard,  Ilex crenata , is unknown;  Jørgensen  et al.  2011 ). The apparent loss of DNA in tetraploid  A. l. petraea  may thus be largely due to hybridization rather than gradual DNA loss through diploidization.  Contrary to some prior reports, all  A. kamchatica  plants in our samples appear to be tetraploid. We found that the allotetraploid,  A. kamchatica , has a genome size that is just slightly less than the sum of its diploid parental taxa,  A. l. petraea  and  A. h. gemmifera . Genome size diversity was lower in  A. kamchatica  than in other  Arabidopsis  taxa. However, there was some variation in genome size, where North American populations of  A. k. kamchatica  seem to have lost slightly more DNA than the Japanese population of subspecies  A. k. kawasakiana . The development of  A. kamchatica  into a model system for the study of polyploidy has the potential to yield a great deal of insight, as its parental taxa have been well studied at both the ecological and genetic levels, and myriad molecular tools from  A. thaliana  are available.  This research was supported by the  National Center for Research Resources (NCRR) at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) (Alaska INBRE)  [ RR016466 and 5P20RR016466 ] and the  National Science Foundation (NSF) Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (Alaska EPSCoR)  [ 0346770 ].  Plants were collected by J.A.S., D.E.W. and N.T. Methods were developed and debugged by J.A.S., G.J.H. and N.T. J.A.S. collected the data. J.A.S. and N.T. analysed the data and produced figures. D.E.W. conceived and wrote the manuscript, which was edited by J.A.S., G.J.H. and N.T.  None declared.  We thank Beth Dunkel for helping with collection of the flow cytometry data. We thank J. Doležel for generously providing seeds of the genome size standard,  Glycine max  ‘Polanka’. We thank Mark Wright at the UAF IAB Greenhouse for growing and maintaining plants. 