Metabolic and transcriptional regulatory mechanisms underlying the anoxic adaptation of rice coleoptileEffects of O<sub>2</sub> concentration on rice seedlingsThe bZIP transcription factor <italic>OsABF1</italic> is an ABA responsive element binding factor that enhances abiotic stress signaling in riceContext-specific metabolic networks are consistent with experimentsA comparison of normalization methods for high density oligonucleotide array data based on variance and biasSampling the solution space in genome-scale metabolic networks reveals transcriptional regulation in key enzymesInterpreting expression data with metabolic flux models: predicting <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> mycolic acid productionEnhancing the anaerobic responseMYB transcription factors in Arabidopsis<italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> phenotypes can be predicted by using constraint-based analysis of a genome-scale reconstructed metabolic networkEffect of anoxia on carbohydrate metabolism in rice seedlingsPlant cis-acting regulatory DNA elements (PLACE) database: 1999Arabidopsis RAP2.2: an ethylene response transcription factor that is important for hypoxia survivalEvidence for a role for <italic>AtMYB2</italic> in the induction of the Arabidopsis alcohol dehydrogenase gene (<italic>ADH1</italic>) by low oxygenAn algorithm for <italic>ab-initio</italic> DNA motif detectionAdaptation to flooding during emergence and seedling growth in rice and weeds, and implications for crop establishmentGenome-wide classification and expression analysis of MYB transcription factor families in rice and ArabidopsisExpression profile analysis of the low-oxygen response in Arabidopsis root culturesElucidating rice cell metabolism under flooding and drought stresses using flux-based modeling and analysisTranscript profiling of the anoxic rice coleoptileConstraining the metabolic genotype–phenotype relationship using a phylogeny of <italic>in silico</italic> methodsHRE1 and HRE2, two hypoxia-inducible ethylene response factors, affect anaerobic responses in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Oxygen sensing in plants is mediated by an N-end rule pathway for protein destabilizationAlpha-amylase expression under anoxia in rice seedlings: an updateGibberellins are not required for rice germination under anoxiaA genome-wide analysis of the effects of sucrose on gene expression in Arabidopsis seedlings under anoxiaRice germination and seedling growth in the absence of oxygenTRANSFAC: transcriptional regulation, from patterns to profilesThe promoter signatures in rice LEA genes can be used to build a co-expressing LEA gene networkRole of aldehyde dehydrogenase in submergence tolerance during anaerobic germination in rice. <italic>11th ISPA Conference 2013</italic>Connecting extracellular metabolomic measurements to intracellular flux states in yeastEffect of anoxia on energy charge and protein synthesis in rice embryoEffects of anoxia on growth and carbohydrate-metabolism in suspension-cultures of soybean and riceDetection and preliminary analysis of motifs in promoters of anaerobically induced genes of different plant speciesPatterns of cis-element enrichment reveal potential regulatory modules involved in the transcriptional regulation of anoxia response of japonica riceOsiris: an integrated promoter database for <italic>Oryza sativa L</italic>Expression of a gene encoding mitochondrial aldehyde dehydrogenase in rice increases under submerged conditionsMapping condition-dependent regulation of metabolism in yeast through genome-scale modelingIdentification and expression analysis of hypoxia stress inducible CCCH-type zinc finger protein genes in riceThe organization and regulation of plant glycolysisQuantitative prediction of cellular metabolism with constraint-based models: the COBRA Toolbox v2.0Combined <italic>in silico</italic> modeling and metabolomics analysis to characterize fed-batch CHO cell cultureGene networks involved in drought stress response and toleranceNetwork-based prediction of human tissue-specific metabolismInsights into the molecular mechanism of RGL2-mediated inhibition of seed germination in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Candidate metabolic network states in human mitochondria. Impact of diabetes, ischemia, and dietlimmaGUI: a graphical user interface for linear modeling of microarray dataSub1A is an ethylene-response-factor-like gene that confers submergence tolerance to riceAGRIS: the Arabidopsis gene regulatory information server, an updateTranscriptional regulatory network triggered by oxidative signals configures the early response mechanisms of japonica rice to chilling stressIdentification of gene modules associated with drought response in rice by network-based analysisThese authors contributed equally.<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Michael B. JacksonThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Rice is a unique crop plant since it can survive under anoxia condition by flooding and also germinate and grow up to coleoptile through its distinctive adaptations. Despite several decades of research on this topic, the current knowledge on the molecular machinery of rice under anoxia is very limited. Therefore, we unraveled the possible regulatory mechanisms by resorting to systems biology approach which combines the metabolic modeling and transcriptome analysis. Such integrative analysis highlight the critical role of MYB, bZIP, ERF and ZnF transcription factors in up-regulating the fermentation and sucrose metabolism genes to generate sufficient energy for cellular growth.The ability of rice to germinate under anoxia by extending the coleoptile is a highly unusual characteristic and a key feature underpinning the ability of rice seeds to establish in such a stressful environment. The process has been a focal point for research for many years. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying the anoxic growth of the coleoptile still remain largely unknown. To unravel the key regulatory mechanisms of rice germination under anoxic stress, we combined <italic>in silico</italic> modelling with gene expression data analysis. Our initial modelling analysis via random flux sampling revealed numerous changes in rice primary metabolism in the absence of oxygen. In particular, several reactions associated with sucrose metabolism and fermentation showed a significant increase in flux levels, whereas reaction fluxes across oxidative phosphorylation, the tricarboxylic acid cycle and the pentose phosphate pathway were down-regulated. The subsequent comparative analysis of the differences in calculated fluxes with previously published gene expression data under air and anoxia identified at least 37 reactions from rice central metabolism that are transcriptionally regulated. Additionally, <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory content analyses of these transcriptionally controlled enzymes indicate a regulatory role for transcription factors such as MYB, bZIP, ERF and ZnF in transcriptional control of genes that are up-regulated during rice germination and coleoptile elongation under anoxia.Rice is one of the few plant species that can survive submerged conditions. In particular, it can successfully germinate by extending a coleoptile underwater in the complete absence of oxygen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C26">Magneschi and Perata 2009</xref>). Most of the early biochemical studies reported that even under anoxia, rice is able to metabolize reserve carbohydrates via glycolysis and fermentation to generate sufficient cellular energy, i.e. ATP needed for plant growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C31">Mocquot <italic>et al.</italic> 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C1">Alpi and Beevers 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C32">Mohanty <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C10">Guglielminetti <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>). Microarray data show that this is associated with a strong up-regulation of sucrose and starch metabolism, glycolysis and fermentation genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C19">Lasanthi-Kudahettige <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). This work also showed many other significantly up- and down-regulated genes associated with various metabolic and signalling pathways. These findings highlight that rice globally reconfigures its molecular machinery under anoxic stress by selectively synthesizing the necessary transcripts coding for enzymes that produce and conserve energy.Despite past efforts to characterize the biochemical adaptations of rice under anoxia, current knowledge on how oxygen deficiency is sensed and on the regulatory cascade that fine-tunes the transcriptional and translational changes is still very limited. To date, only the induction of GA-response-free RAmy3D under anoxic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C23">Loreti <italic>et al.</italic> 2003<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C24"><italic>b</italic></xref>) is the notable trait unravelled at the molecular level. Even with the availability of abundant high-throughput data, such limitations still exist mainly due to the lack of appropriate systematic frameworks to analyse and derive a valid hypothesis from them. In this regard, constraint-based <italic>in silico</italic> metabolic modelling and analysis can be helpful. Not only do they allow predictions concerning the physiological behaviour and metabolic states of an organism exposed to various environmental or genetic changes but they also serve as a scaffold to contextualize multiple ‘-omics’ data, thereby enabling biologically meaningful correlations to be identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C20">Lewis <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). As a result, several frameworks are now available to integrate metabolic models and high-throughput data such as transcriptomics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C3">Becker and Palsson 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C6">Colijn <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C5">Bordel <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), metabolomics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C30">Mo <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C41">Selvarasu <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and proteomics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C43">Shlomi <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) within the context of systems biology. One such approach compares the flux levels simulated by the metabolic model with corresponding gene expression data resulting from environmental or genetic changes. This has, for example, highlighted key transcriptional mechanisms in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C9">Famili <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C5">Bordel <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C37">Osterlund <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Therefore, following a similar method, here, we identified the transcriptionally regulated reactions in rice during its anoxic germination. Our approach used initial random flux sampling using the recently published rice central metabolic network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C18">Lakshmanan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), and subsequently compared the differences in flux levels with previously published gene expression data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C19">Lasanthi-Kudahettige <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) between air and anoxia. Furthermore, to gain a deeper insight into the key regulatory mechanisms during anoxic adaptation, we also found the possible transcription factors (TFs) of transcriptionally regulated enzymes by analysing the distribution of putative <italic>cis</italic>-elements in their promoter regions.We used the recently published rice central metabolic model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C18">Lakshmanan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) to characterize the metabolic states of germinating rice seeds under air and anoxia. The gene–protein reaction (GPR) mappings were updated for all reactions since the original model did not include the unique genes associated with enzymes having multiple isozymes across different cellular compartments. The updated model is provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu026/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information</bold></ext-link>.The raw transcriptome data generated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C19">Lasanthi-Kudahettige <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> were first downloaded from the Gene Expression Omnibus (accession no. GSE6908) and normalized using the quantile method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C4">Bolstad <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Differentially expressed genes were then identified by a linear model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C46">Wettenhall and Smyth 2004</xref>). The resulting <italic>P</italic> values were also corrected for multiple testing using Benjamini–Hochberg correction.The artificial centring hit-and-run (ACHR) Monte Carlo sampling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C45">Thiele <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C30">Mo <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) was utilized to sample uniformly the metabolic flux solution space under aerobic and anaerobic conditions with appropriate flux constraints. Under both conditions, we constrained sucrose uptake rate, oxygen uptake rate and cell growth rate with experimentally measured values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C18">Lakshmanan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). To make a fair comparison between both conditions, oxygen uptake and growth rates were normalized with respect to sucrose uptake rate. The solution space was sampled with 100 000 randomly distributed points for 10 000 iterations in each simulation. In this study, the COBRA toolbox (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C40">Schellenberger <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) was utilized to implement the random flux sampling.Finally, the absolute <italic>Z</italic>-scores were translated to <italic>P</italic> values using the normal cumulative distribution function and the reactions with <italic>P</italic> values &lt;0.05 were deemed as statistically different between aerobic and anaerobic conditions.Using the <italic>P</italic> values of transcriptome data and flux sampling, we identified the reactions that are transcriptionally regulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C5">Bordel <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Briefly, if the flux and gene expression (for both up- and down-regulated) significantly changes in the same direction, the corresponding enzyme is classified as ‘transcriptionally regulated’. On the other hand, if the values significantly change in the opposite direction, the enzyme is classified as ‘metabolically regulated’. In the case of reactions with multiple isozymes, the gene expression was considered to be up- or down-regulated based on the expression values of the majority of the transcripts. For example, if a gene has more up-regulated transcripts than down-regulated ones, then it is considered as up-regulated.Promoter sequences [−1000, +200 nt relative to the transcription start site (TSS)] for transcriptionally up- and down-regulated genes related to anaerobic central metabolism were extracted from our in-house rice promoter sequence database. Known and novel promoter motifs were detected using the Dragon Motif Builder program with EM2 option (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C14">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Thirty motifs were detected each time having a length of 8–10 nucleotides per detection at a threshold value of 0.875. Motif occurrences in over 50 % of the sequences at a threshold e value of ≤10<sup>−3</sup> were considered as statistically overrepresented. Motif classes were identified by their matches in different plant Transcription Factor Binding databases such as TRANSFAC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C27">Matys <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <uri xlink:href="http://www.gene-regulation.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.gene-regulation.com</uri>), PLACE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C11">Higo <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <uri xlink:href="http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/htdocs/PLACE" xlink:type="simple">http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/htdocs/PLACE</uri>), AGRIS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C48">Yilmaz <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <uri xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.med.ohio-state.edu/" xlink:type="simple">http://arabidopsis.med.ohio-state.edu/</uri>) and Osiris (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C35">Morris <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <uri xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics2.wsu.edu/cgi-bin/Osiris/cgi/home.pl" xlink:type="simple">http://www.bioinformatics2.wsu.edu/cgi-bin/Osiris/cgi/home.pl</uri>). A similar method was used for the extraction and detection of motifs in the negative sets.We sampled the plausible metabolic states of rice coleoptile in air and under anoxia using ACHR Monte Carlo sampling to estimate the range of possible steady-state flux values through each of the reactions in the rice model (see Methods). The resulting probability distributions of individual reaction fluxes revealed significant differences in central metabolic pathways such as glycolysis, the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle, the pentose phosphate pathway and oxidative phosphorylation between aerobic and anaerobic conditions <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu026/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold>.Under anoxia, the TCA cycle, the pentose phosphate pathway and oxidative phosphorylation had only a small range of fluxes, with some even having zero flux due to the imposed capacity constraints, i.e. the absence of oxygen exchange <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu026/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold>. As a result, the fluxes across various amino acid and lipid synthetic pathways were also severely restricted under anoxic conditions (data not shown). On the other hand, random sampling allowed us to observe the possibility of high fluxes through cytosolic glycolysis and fermentation, mainly to produce all the ATP required for anaerobic cell growth. Other energy-producing pathways such as oxidative phosphorylation and the TCA cycle are grossly impaired under such conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C32">Mohanty <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C18">Lakshmanan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).We compared the differences in flux samples and gene expression data between air and anoxia, thereby identifying the reactions that are likely to be transcriptionally regulated (see Methods). Overall, among the 63 reactions in rice central metabolism, 37 and 5 exhibit transcriptional and metabolic regulation, respectively. The remaining 38 reactions could not be classified in any of these categories as they exhibited an insignificant change in either flux or gene expression. The complete lists of transcriptionally and metabolically regulated reactions are provided in <bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu026/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link></bold>.Central metabolic reactions of rice showing transcriptional and metabolic regulation under anoxia. Green, red and blue colours indicate the transcriptionally down-, up- and metabolically regulated enzymes, respectively. Reactions with black arrows represent enzymes whose regulation mechanism has not been investigated or identified in this study. Metabolite abbreviations are as follows: α-KG, α-ketoglutarate; 1,3-PGA, 1,3-diphosphoglycerate; 2-PGA, 2-phosphoglycerate; 3-PGA, 3-phosphoglycerate; AA, amino acids; Acald, acetaldehyde; Ac-CoA, acetyl-coenzyme A; ADP-G, ADP-glucose; Ala, alanine; Asn, asparagine; Asp, aspartate; DHAP, dihydroxyacetone phosphate; E-4-P, erythrose-4-phosphate; F-6-P, fructose-6-phosphate; F-1,6-bP, fructose-1,6-bisphosphate; G-1-P, glucose-1-phosphate; G3P, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate; G-6-P, glucose-6-phosphate; Gln, glutamine; Glu, glutamate; OAA, oxaloacetate; PEP, phosphoenolpyruvate; PRPP, phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate; Q, ubiquinone; QH2, ubiquinol; R-5-P, ribose-5-phosphate; Ru-5-P, ribulose-5-phosphate; UDP-G, UDP-glucose; X-5-P, <sc>d</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate. Enzyme abbreviations are as follows: ACO, aconitase; ADH, alcohol dehydrogenase; ALAAT, alanine aminotransferase; ALD, aldolase; APS, glucose-1-phosphate adenylyltransferase; ASP1, aspartate aminotransferase; ASPG, asparaginase; COX, cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase; CSY, citrate synthase; FK, fructokinase; FUM, fumarase; GAPDH, glyceraldehyde phosphate dehydrogenase; IDP, isocitrate dehydrogenase (NADP-dependent); INV, invertase; MDH, malate dehydrogenase; NAD9, NADH dehydrogenase; PDC, pyruvate decarboxylase; PDH, pyruvate dehydrogenase; PEPE, phosphoenolpyruvate enolase; PFK, 6-phosphofructokinase; PFP, PPi-dependent phosphofructokinase; PGI, phosphoglucoisomerase; PGK, phosphoglycerate kinase; PGLYCM, phosphoglucomutase; PGM, phosphoglucomutase; PPC, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase; PPDK, pyruvate orthophosphate dikinase; PRS, ribose-phosphate diphosphokinase; PYK, pyruvate kinase; RPE, ribose-5-phosphate epimerase; TKT, transketolase; TPI, triose phosphate isomerase; SDH, succinate dehydrogenase; SSI, starch synthase; SUCLG, succinyl-CoA ligase; SUS, sucrose synthase; UGPP, UDP-glucose pyrophosphorylase.All the reactions in the fermentation pathway including pyruvate decarboxylase (PDC), alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) and aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH) were up-regulated (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU026F1">1</xref>). In rice, both alcohol and aldehyde dehydrogenases have multiple isozymes and a few of them such as <italic>ADH1</italic>, <italic>ADH2</italic> and <italic>ALDH2a</italic> showed a drastic increase in gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C19">Lasanthi-Kudahettige <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Interestingly, the up-regulation of ALDH at both flux and transcriptional level is in very good agreement with earlier experimental reports on both tolerant and intolerant lines of rice under hypoxic conditions during submergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C36">Nakazono <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C29">Miro <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), indicating that ALDH is likely to play a key role in detoxifying the excess acetaldehyde from PDC that cannot be metabolized via ADH. In this regard, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C19">Lasanthi-Kudahettige <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> hypothesized that the acetate resulting from ALDH can enter the TCA cycle to further fuel amino acid synthesis pathways. However, our flux analysis revealed that the acetate from ALDH primarily fuels lipid biosynthesis in plastids, as fatty acid synthesis needs sufficient carbon flux to synthesize the required saturated fatty acids under anoxia.Unlike other central metabolic pathways, the glycolytic reactions did not show an overall up- or down-regulation in gene transcription and fluxes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU026F1">1</xref>). Out of a total of 25 reactions, only 11 showed transcriptional regulation. Among the remaining 14, 5 were oppositely correlated between flux and gene expression, indicating that these enzymes are most likely to be metabolically regulated. Plastidic pyruvate kinase, UDP-glucose pyrophosphorylase, PPi-dependent phosphofructokinase (PFP), and cytosolic and plastidic pyruvate phosphate dikinase (PPDK) are the five enzymes with metabolic regulation. Such observations are in good agreement with the earlier hypothesis by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C39">Plaxton (1996)</xref>, who suggested that PK, PPDK, PFK and PFP are involved in the fine control of plant glycolysis and are most likely to be regulated based on the variation in substrate(s) and cofactor concentrations, pH and other metabolite effectors.Potential <italic>cis</italic>-elements identified in the promoters of transcriptionally controlled up-regulated genes of rice seeds germinated under anoxia.Potential <italic>cis</italic>-elements identified in the promoters of transcriptionally controlled down-regulated genes of rice seeds germinated under anoxia.To ensure that our <italic>cis</italic>-element analysis did not identify an excessive number of false positives, we sought motifs from the promoters of a similar number of genes that are not anoxia specific using the same protocol (see Methods). For this purpose, we used two negative datasets: (i) randomly selected genes from the non-differentially expressed gene list under anoxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C19">Lasanthi-Kudahettige <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) (negative Set 1) and (ii) up-regulated genes associated with drought response in rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C50">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) (negative Set 2). The list of genes from the negative sets and the results of this analysis are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu026/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supplementary Information</bold></ext-link>. Using the negative control Set 1, we identified a few common motifs such as MYB, bZIP and DOF, and their total enrichment was much lower compared with the motifs detected in transcriptionally up- or down-regulated genes of anoxia (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU026TB1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU026TB2">2</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu026/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supplementary Information</bold></ext-link>). Similarly, the motif analysis of negative Set 2 also revealed a significantly different <italic>cis</italic>-element enrichment pattern where most of the identified TFs such as MYB, bZIP, ERF, NAC and MYC have been experimentally confirmed to play a regulatory role in drought stress response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C42">Shinozaki and Yamaguchi-Shinozaki 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C50">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Collectively, these results clearly demonstrate that our <italic>cis</italic>-element method identifies reasonably precise motifs that are specific to anoxic stress.Our study analysed the plausible metabolic states of rice under aerobic and anaerobic conditions using random sampling and compared their differences. We also compared the changes in flux levels of individual enzymes in the central metabolism of rice grown in the two conditions with that of gene expression and identified the transcriptionally controlled reactions. Accordingly, the major contribution of the current work is the demonstration of the utility of random flux sampling and gene expression data for elucidating metabolic differences and the identification of corresponding putative TFs responsible for such changes under the stress conditions.Monte Carlo flux sampling has been shown to be an effective tool to analyse and compare the plausible solution space of a metabolic network across different environmental/genetic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C9">Famili <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C5">Bordel <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C37">Osterlund <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). When compared with the commonly used constraint-based analysis methods such as flux balance analysis (FBA) and minimization of metabolic adjustment, which predict just a single flux distribution based on a particular objective function, random sampling allows us to account for uncertainty in the flux distributions as it uniformly samples the possible solution space in an unbiased manner and, thus, potentially minimizes the possibility of overestimating the actual flux differences between the two conditions. This can be clearly exemplified by comparing the results of previous work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C18">Lakshmanan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), which utilized FBA for simulating flux differences between air and anoxia, with our current results. Although both studies show that most of the central metabolic reactions possess different flux levels in aerobic and anaerobic conditions, flux sampling can provide confidence scores to the reactions, thus allowing us to consider the reactions with the most plausible fluxes. Furthermore, by comparing the significant flux differences with gene expression data, we determined the reactions that are most probably regulated at the transcriptional level. Most importantly, we revealed that although the glycolytic reactions are not transcriptionally regulated, genes coding for reactions upstream and downstream of glycolysis, i.e. sucrose metabolism and fermentation, respectively, are regulated transcriptionally. It will be important now to compare and contrast such findings with anoxia-intolerant higher plants such as <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, wheat and maize to analyse whether the corresponding gene orthologues are commonly regulated at a similar level.List of anoxia-stressed up-regulated TFs with potential significance to the pattern of <italic>cis</italic>-element enrichment among the up-regulated genes.As mentioned above, our promoter analysis also highlighted significant overrepresentation of several other motifs associated with bZIP, ERF and ZnF TFs in the transcriptionally up-regulated genes. In this regard, an increase in transcript levels of bZIP TF (<italic>AtbZIP50</italic>) in anoxia-exposed root cultures of Arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C17">Klok <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>), the up-regulation of an ABRE-binding bZIP TF (<italic>OsABF1</italic>) in rice shoot and root under anoxic treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C2">Amir Hossain <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and the up-regulation of a number of bZIP TFs in rice anoxic coleoptile (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU026TB3">3</xref>) support the view that bZIP could orchestrate the transcription of up-regulated genes upon anoxic stress. The major role of ERF TF has been identified as a positive regulator of Sub1A expression in a flood-tolerant rice variety during hypoxic conditions caused by submergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C47">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). However, the anoxia-tolerant rice variety ‘<italic>Nipponbare</italic>’ that germinates and elongates under anoxia does not have this gene. Surprisingly, the presence of highly enriched putative GCC-box-like/ERE-like <italic>cis</italic>-elements in the promoters of all anoxia up-regulated genes in this variety of rice highlights the possiblity that these TFs might also control the transcription of relevant genes as it is in Arabidopsis under hypoxic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C12">Hinz <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C21">Licausi <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C22">2011</xref>). Unlike the ERF TFs, the role of ZnF TF in response to submergence/anoxia is not yet known. However, matching with our identification of ZnF binding site-like elements in transcriptionally up-regulated genes, the increase in expression of ZnF TF genes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU026TB3">3</xref>) in response to hypoxia/anoxia in both rice and Arabidopsis allows us to speculate on its potential regulatory role in transcriptional control under oxygen stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C25">Loreti <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C38">Pandey and Kim 2012</xref>).Presence of common putative <italic>cis</italic>-elements in the key transcriptionally regulated genes. The presence of potential putative <italic>cis</italic>-elements and their cognate known TFs are shown in different strands of the promoter region (−1000, +200 nt relative to TSS) of the key genes. Each putative <italic>cis</italic>-element/motif is represented by its consensus logo. TATA boxes are located between 25 and 30 nt upstream from the TSS.The current methods we used successfully identified several transcriptionally regulated reactions and their related TFs, some of which are experimentally confirmed. However, the overall results of this approach await experimental validation since the current prediction relies on several assumptions concerning model completeness, constraints used during simulation and the statistical cut-off values chosen for comparative analysis. In our work, we utilized the central model to simulate the differences in metabolic fluxes between air and anoxia. It should be noted that although this model predicts the overall cellular phenotype quite accurately (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU026C18">Lakshmanan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), it may not capture the global changes in cellular metabolism. This reservation is needed since the model does not take account of the secondary metabolic pathways. Moreover, we have utilized only a few external fluxes, i.e. sucrose uptake, O<sub>2</sub> uptake and growth yield, as the sole constraints to identify the internal flux distributions during flux sampling simulations. In such cases, the internal fluxes of some reactions are determined with statistically low confidence scores due to the possibility of multiple flux solutions. Such limitations can be overcome by the use of C<sub>13</sub> flux measurements as constraints to the internal reactions. Therefore, the list of transcriptionally regulated reactions and the TFs identified in this study need further confirmation by direct experiments.In this study, we presented a combined <italic>in silico</italic> modelling and gene expression data analysis framework to identify transcriptionally regulated reactions in rice central metabolism. Random flux sampling simulations highlighted significant changes in flux levels across oxidative phosphorylation, the TCA cycle, the pentose phosphate pathway, glycolysis, sucrose metabolism and fermentation. The subsequent comparative analysis of changes in flux levels and gene expression between aerobic conditions identified 37 reactions from these pathways that are regulated at the transcriptional level. The motif enrichment analysis of transcriptionally regulated enzymes highlighted the potential involvement of TFs MYB, bZIP, ERF and ZnF in controlling the transcription of sucrose metabolism and fermentation genes under anaerobic conditions. Thus, the current study successfully demonstrated how condition-specific gene expression data can be exploited to narrow down the metabolic changes in rice under anaerobic adaptations and <italic>in silico</italic> analysis to help us unravel the relevant transcriptional mechanisms.This work was supported by the <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">National University of Singapore, the Competitive Research Programme of the National Research Foundation of Singapore</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">NRF-CRP5-2009-03</grant-num>), the Biomedical Research Council of A*STAR (Agency for Science, Technology and Research), Singapore, and a grant from the <grant-sponsor id="cs2" rid="cn2" xlink:type="simple">Next-Generation BioGreen 21 Program</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num id="cn2" rid="cs2" xlink:type="simple">SSAC, No. PJ009520</grant-num>), Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea.M.L., B.M. and D.Y.L. conceived and designed the study. M.L. carried out flux sampling and gene expression data analysis. B.M. carried out the <italic>ab initio</italic> analysis of <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements. M.L., B.M. and D.Y.L. wrote the manuscript. S.H.L. and S.H.H. provided critical comments and helped in revising the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.None declared.The following <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu026/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link> is available in the online version of this article –<bold>File S1.</bold> Table. Rice central model with updated GPR associations.<bold>File S2.</bold> Diagram. Sampling histogram of glycolysis, pentose phosphate pathway, TCA cycle, oxidative phosphorylation and sucrose metabolism under aerobic and anaerobic conditions.<bold>File S3.</bold> Table. List of rice central metabolic reactions and their flux differences with <italic>P</italic> values. Expression patterns of corresponding gene louses and type of regulation, i.e. transcriptional or metabolic, are also listed.<bold>File S4.</bold> Table. List of genes used in negative sets.<bold>File S5.</bold> Table. Potential <italic>cis</italic>-elements identified in the promoters of negative sets.We thank Prof. Vladimir B. Bajic for the use of the Dragon Motif Builder Program. We also thank the associate editor Prof. Michael Jackson and anonymous referees for their useful comments.