Modelling leaf photosynthetic and transpiration temperature-dependent responses in <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Semillon grapevines growing in hot, irrigated vineyard conditionsScaling CO<sub>2</sub>–photosynthesis relationships from the leaf to the canopyPhotosynthetic temperature responses of <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> and <italic>Eucalyptus nitens</italic>Photosynthetic response and adaptation to temperature in higher-plantsOntogenetic effects on the stomatal apparatus of four Belgian sugar beet (<italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> subsp. <italic>vulgaris</italic> L.) cultivarsPartititioning concurrent influences of nitrogen and phosphorus supply on photosynthetic model parameters of <italic>Pinus radiata</italic>Does transpiration control stomatal responses to water vapour pressure deficit?Acclimation of photosynthesis to temperature in eight cool and warm climate herbaceous C3 species: temperature dependence of parameters of a biochemical photosynthesis modelModeling leaf maximum net photosynthetic rate of <italic>Festuca pallescens</italic>, the dominant perennial grass of Patagonian pine-based silvopastoral systemsTemperature and CO<sub>2</sub> responses of leaf and canopy photosynthesis: a clarification using the non-rectangular hyperbola model of photosynthesisPhysiological and environmental regulation of stomatal conductance, photosynthesis and transpiration: a model that includes a laminar boundary layerABA xylem concentrations determine maximum daily leaf conductance of field-grown <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. plantsStomatal function in relation to leaf metabolism and environmentA two-big-leaf model for canopy temperature, photosynthesis, and stomatal conductanceSimple scaling of photosynthesis from leaves to canopies without the errors of big-leaf modelsComparing model predictions and experimental data for the response of stomatal conductance and guard cell turgor to manipulations of cuticular conductance, leaf-to-air vapour pressure difference and temperature: feedback mechanisms are able to account for all observationsA biochemical model of photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation in leaves of C3 speciesModels of photosynthesisGrowth of <italic>Festuca pallescens</italic> in silvopastoral systems in Patagonia, Part 2: parameterization of models of stomatal conductance and leaf photosynthesisEffect of temperature on key physiological responses of grapevine LeafGrapevine response to soil temperature: xylem cytokinins and carbohydrate reserve mobilization from budbreak to anthesisWheat yield progress associated with higher stomatal conductance and photosynthetic rate, and cooler canopiesTemperature and humidity effects on branchlet gas-exchange in white spruce: an explanation for the increase in transpiration with branchlet temperatureA comparative analysis of four models of photosynthesis for 11 plant species in the Loess PlateauRelation of applied crop stress to inflorescence development, shoot growth, and cane starch reserves in ‘Concord’ grapevineDiurnal changes in leaf gas exchange and validation of a mathematical model for coffee (<italic>Coffea arabica</italic> L.) canopy photosynthesisPhotosynthesis of a temperate fallow C3 herbaceous ecosystem: measurements and model simulations at the leaf and canopy levelsPhotosynthetic and fluorescence light responses for kiwifruit (<italic>Actinidia deliciosa</italic>) leaves at different stages of development on vines grown at two different photon flux densitiesTemperature-dependence of carbon acquisition and demand in relation to shoot growth of kiwifruit (<italic>Actinidia deliciosa</italic>) vines grown in controlled environmentsModelling photosynthetic responses to temperature of grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Semillon) leaves on vines grown in a hot climateHeat stress affects flowering, berry growth, sugar accumulation and photosynthesis of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Semillon grapevines grown in a controlled environmentFrom controlled environments to field simulations: leaf area dynamics and photosynthesis of kiwifruit vines (<italic>Actinidia deliciosa</italic>)Shoot architecture, growth and development dynamics of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Semillon vines grown in an irrigated vineyard with and without shade coveringStomatal response to environment and a possible interrelation between stomatal effects on transpiration and CO<sub>2</sub> assimilationInteractive effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> and growth temperature on the tolerance of photosynthesis to acute heat stress in C3 and C4 speciesModelling optimal temperature acclimation of the photosynthetic apparatus in C3 plants with respect to nitrogen useSoil water stress and coupled photosynthesis-conductance models: bridging the gap between conflicting reports on the relative roles of stomatal, mesophyll conductance and biochemical limitations to photosynthesisA coupled model of photosynthesis, stomatal conductance and transpiration for a rose leaf (<italic>Rosa hybrida</italic> L.)Photosynthesis in vine leaves as a function of light intensity, temperature, and leaf ageLeaf photosynthetic light response: a mechanistic model for scaling photosynthesis to leaves and canopiesParameterization and testing of a biochemically based photosynthesis model for walnut (<italic>Juglans regia</italic>) trees and seedlingsA critical appraisal of a combined stomatal-photosynthesis model for C3 plantsA model for net photosynthesis of rose leaves as a function of photosynthetically active radiation, leaf temperature, and leaf ageHigh yields in advanced lines of pima cotton are associated with higher stomatal conductance, reduced leaf-area and lower leaf temperatureLimitations to leaf photosynthesis in field-grown grapevine under drought—metabolic and modelling approachesEffects of growth temperature on photosynthetic gas exchange characteristics and hydraulic anatomy in leaves of two cold-climate Poa speciesStomatal control of transpiration from a developing sugarcane canopyStomatal and environmental control of transpiration in a lowland tropical forest treeEnvironmental and physiological regulation of transpiration in tropical forest gap species: the influence of boundary layer and hydraulic propertiesA simple dynamic model of photosynthesis in oak leaves: coupling leaf conductance and photosynthetic carbon fixation by a variable intracellular CO<sub>2</sub> poolNeedle age-related and seasonal photosynthetic capacity variation is negligible for modelling yearly gas exchange of a sparse temperate Scots pine forestA comparison of photosynthesis-dependent stomatal models using twig cuvette field data for adult beech (<italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic> L.)An adequate model of photosynthesis—II. Dependence of parameters on environmental factorsA new, vapour-phase mechanism for stomatal responses to humidity and temperatureCanopy photosynthesis of sugar maple (<italic>Acer saccharum</italic>): comparing big-leaf and multilayer extrapolations of leaf-level measurementsModeling the effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> on plants: extrapolating leaf response to a canopyDoes night-time transpiration contribute to anisohydric behaviour in a <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cultivar?Ontogeny and leaf gas exchange mediate the carbon isotopic signature of herbaceous plantsModelling canopy production. II. From single-leaf photosynthetic parameters to daily canopy photosynthesisDifferences in hydraulic architecture account for near-isohydric and anisohydric behaviour of two field-grown <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. cultivars during droughtEffect of high temperature on grapevines (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.). II. Distribution of soluble sugarsIrrigated Shiraz vines (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>) upregulate gas exchange and maintain berry growth in response to short spells of high maximum temperature in the fieldEffects of leaf development and phosphorus supply on the photosynthetic characteristics of perennial legume species with pasture potential: modelling photosynthesis with leaf developmentDynamic model of leaf photosynthesis with acclimation to light and nitrogenLinked stomata and photosynthesis model for <italic>Corylus avellana</italic> (hazel)Effects of applied water amounts at various fractions of evapotranspiration (ETc) on leaf gas exchange of Thompson Seedless grapevinesEffects of crop load on fruiting and gas-exchange characteristics of ‘Braeburn’/M.26 apple trees at full canopyEffects of internal conductance on the temperature dependence of the photosynthetic rate in spinach leaves from contrasting growth temperaturesStomatal and non-stomatal limitations to photosynthesis in field-grown grapevine cultivarsModeling the water use efficiency of soybean and maize plants under environmental stresses: application of a synthetic model of photosynthesis–transpiration based on stomatal behaviorSeasonal fluctuations and temperature dependence in photosynthetic parameters and stomatal conductance at the leaf scale of <italic>Populus euphratica</italic> OlivUse of stomatal conductance and pre-dawn water potential to classify terroir for the grape variety KékfrankosThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly citedGrapevines growing in Australia suffer from high temperatures which have major effects on photosynthesis and transpiration. To learn more, gas exchange was measured over several seasons and then modelled across temperatures from 20 to 45°C and validated with independent data.Grapevines growing in Australia are often exposed to very high temperatures and the question of how the gas exchange processes adjust to these conditions is not well understood. The aim was to develop a model of photosynthesis and transpiration in relation to temperature to quantify the impact of the growing conditions on vine performance.Leaf gas exchange was measured along the grapevine shoots in accordance with their growth and development over several growing seasons. Using a general linear statistical modelling approach, photosynthesis and transpiration were modelled against leaf temperature separated into bands and the model parameters and coefficients applied to independent datasets to validate the model.Photosynthesis, transpiration and stomatal conductance varied along the shoot, with early emerging leaves having the highest rates, but these declined as later emerging leaves increased their gas exchange capacities in accordance with development. The general linear modelling approach applied to these data revealed that photosynthesis at each temperature was additively dependent on stomatal conductance, internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and photon flux density. The temperature-dependent coefficients for these parameters applied to other datasets gave a predicted rate of photosynthesis that was linearly related to the measured rates, with a 1 : 1 slope. Temperature-dependent transpiration was multiplicatively related to stomatal conductance and the leaf to air vapour pressure deficit and applying the coefficients also showed a highly linear relationship, with a 1 : 1 slope between measured and modelled rates, when applied to independent datasets.The models developed for the grapevines were relatively simple but accounted for much of the seasonal variation in photosynthesis and transpiration. The goodness of fit in each case demonstrated that explicitly selecting leaf temperature as a model parameter, rather than including temperature intrinsically as is usually done in more complex models, was warranted.Models of photosynthesis have been in vogue since <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C19">Farquhar <italic>et al</italic>. (1980)</xref> first published their biochemical model and much progress in the biochemical understanding of photosynthesis has followed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C68">von Caemmerer 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C20">Farquhar <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). Photosynthesis is recognized to be limited by the two processes of ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate (RuBP) carboxylation and RuBP regeneration, and many models of photosynthesis incorporate these limitations as an intrinsic part (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C2">Amthor 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C39">Hikosaka 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C44">Le Roux <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C7">Bown <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Other photosynthetic models are based on the photosynthetic light response curve for individual leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C4">Battaglia <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C56">Pachepsky and Acock 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C67">Thornley 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C29">Gómez <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>) while other models are extended to the whole canopy using the physics of light attenuation to extend the photosynthetic light responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C59">Reynolds <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C62">Sands 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C11">Cannell and Thornley 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C43">Kull and Kruijt 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C58">Raulier <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). Further still, the canopy has been partitioned into sun and shade leaves for some models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C17">De Pury and Farquhar 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C16">Dai <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C33">Greer <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Although the effect of temperature is usually inherent in these models, it is less common for the effect of leaf temperature over the wide range that plants can experience to be explicitly investigated in the models.The processes of photosynthesis are intrinsically related to temperatures, photon flux densities (PFD) and CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations (both ambient and internal) prevailing at the time and including stomatal conductance, these parameters have been incorporated into some dynamic models of photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C46">Lieth and Pasian 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C41">Kim and Lieth 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C53">Noe and Giersch 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C10">Caballé <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). These models often also couple photosynthesis with stomatal conductance and transpiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C13">Collatz <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C69">von Stamm 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C41">Kim and Lieth 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C40">Keenan <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). In turn, there are various ways to model stomatal conductance, notably that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C3">Ball <italic>et al</italic>. (1987)</xref> relating stomatal conductance to assimilation, relative humidity (RH) and the CO<sub>2</sub> mole fraction of the air, and the modification by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C45">Leuning (1995)</xref> involving replacing the RH term with a hyperbolic function of vapour pressure deficit (VPD). In addition, a multiplicative model relating stomatal conductance to RH, water status, PFD and air temperature has also been proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C21">Fernández <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C55">Op de Beeck <italic>et al.</italic> 2010<italic>b</italic></xref>) and to PFD and VPD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C53">Noe and Giersch 2004</xref>). In contrast, transpiration is simply modelled as a function of stomatal conductance and leaf-to-air VPD and the effect of leaf temperature is essentially encapsulated in determining the saturated vapour pressure of the leaf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C41">Kim and Lieth 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C73">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>).Semillon grapevines are grown in many parts of Australia and are an economically important crop for the different regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C1">Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) 2005</xref>). This cultivar is known to have high rates of transpiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C60">Rogiers <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and, therefore, irrigation is sometimes required for growth of the vines. The vines are also grown in climates where summer air temperatures readily exceed 35 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C27">Gladstones 1992</xref>). These high-temperature exposures, sometimes &gt;40 °C, are known to reduce photosynthesis of grapevine leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C42">Kriedemann 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C22">Ferrini <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C74">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C76">Zsófi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). In part, these reductions in photosynthesis are related to stomatal limitation and, generally, photosynthetic recovery occurs within a few days after a heat treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C64">Sepúlveda and Kliewer 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C22">Ferrini <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C65">Soar <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). A pot trial on Semillon vines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C35">Greer and Weston 2010</xref>) showed a reduction in photosynthesis after a heat event was caused by stomatal limitation but photosynthesis also recovered over a 10- to 12-day period. However, it is not known if stomata limit photosynthesis to the same extent in vineyard conditions, especially at the high temperatures to which the vines are exposed.Thus, the objective of the present study was to measure gas exchange of Semillon leaves throughout the growing season under the prevailing high-temperature conditions and then to model photosynthesis and transpiration in relation to stomatal conductance, internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, PFD, VPD and leaf temperature. The approach adopted was to use a statistical general linear model to assess which of these effects, as well as physical and biological effects such as time of day, day of season, leaf position, shoot position and vine, were significant. Temperature-dependent coefficients derived from the model for each parameter were then applied to independent datasets to assess the goodness of fit and validation of the model over a range of leaf temperatures.This project was undertaken in a commercial vineyard in the Riverina, NSW, Australia, over the growing season of 2008/09. Some additional measurements were collected in the 2007/08 and 2009/10 growing seasons. The vines (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. cv. Semillon) were not grown on a rootstock and were planted in north–south rows with 3.5 m spacing between rows and 1.8 m spacing between the vines. The vines were grown with a vertical shoot position trellis and catch wires were lifted from about canopy closure to constrain the shoots semi-vertically. Apart from a fungicide spray programme, the selected vines had no other management practices imposed. Drip irrigation was used, with drippers at 0.6-m spacing supplying water and nutrients at a rate of 2.4 L h<sup>−1</sup> for 12 h per week prior to ripening and 24 h per week after ripening started. Midday water potentials in midsummer averaged −1.6 ± 0.3 MPa and no indications of water stress were evident. Budbreak occurred at about 25 September and harvest of the grapes occurred on 12 February.Throughout the growing season, commencing on 9 October 2008 (14 days after budbreak, DAB) and finishing on 18 March 2009 (174 DAB), photosynthesis and associated gas exchange measurements (stomatal conductance, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>; transpiration, <italic>E</italic>; internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, <italic>c</italic><sub>i</sub>) were made at 7- to 14-day intervals with an open gas exchange system (LCA4, ADC BioScientific, Hoddesdon, UK). On each occasion, measurements were conducted on all leaves of each of two selected shoots of three vines in each of six whole panels (three vines per panel), totalling 36 shoots. In each case, all leaves present that were &gt;25 mm were measured on each occasion; thus, an increasing number of leaves were measured, starting with about five leaves and finishing with over 30 leaves at the end of the measurements. In all cases, gas exchange was measured between 0900 and 1600 h on the leaves in their natural orientation, and the PFD, leaf temperature and leaf-to-air vapour pressure deficit (VPD<sub>L</sub>) were measured concurrently. Leaf temperature was measured with a thermocouple appressed to the lower leaf surface within the gas exchange chamber.The models were fitted to all data across the growing season and coefficients for each parameter (<italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>c</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>p</sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub>v</sub>), including an intercept term (<italic>T</italic><sub>i</sub>), were derived from these analyses for each temperature band. These coefficients were then analysed as a function of leaf temperature, using the GLM procedure in SAS.A second dataset of photosynthetic and transpiration rates, stomatal conductances, internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations, PFDs, VPDs and leaf temperatures were measured over the 2009/10 growing season from 22 October 2009 until 2 February 2010. The same numbers of vines and shoots (although different plants) were used and the same methods of measuring gas exchange. These data were then used to independently evaluate the model in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="PLS009M3">equations (3) and (4)</xref> using the model parameters and encompassing their specific temperature coefficients derived from the comparable dataset in 2008/09.<bold>Changes in gas exchange after 48 days.</bold> Net photosynthesis (A), stomatal conductance (B) and transpiration (C) along the shoot (mean ± SE, <italic>N</italic> = 36) of Semillon vines growing in an irrigated vineyard at 48 DAB, which was about the time of flowering.<bold>Changes in gas exchange after 69 days.</bold> Net photosynthesis (A), stomatal conductance (B) and transpiration (C) along the shoot (mean ± SE, <italic>N</italic> = 36) of Semillon vines growing in an irrigated vineyard at 69 DAB, which was about the time when vegetative growth was terminating.<bold>Changes in gas exchange after 132 days.</bold> Net photosynthesis (A), stomatal conductance (B) and transpiration (C) along the shoot (mean ± SE, <italic>N</italic> = 36) of Semillon vines growing in an irrigated vineyard at 132 DAB, which was just after the grape harvest.<bold>The effect of leaf temperature on gas exchange</bold>. Net photosynthesis (A), transpiration (B), stomatal conductance (C) and internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (D) of Semillon leaves (mean ± SE, <italic>N</italic> &gt; 1000; see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS009TB1">1</xref>) measured over the whole growing season and averaged across all leaves, shoots and vines. These data were separated into the different leaf temperatures from 20 to 45 °C in ±2.5 °C bands and then analysed into least squares means using SAS 9.13.By contrast, mean transpiration rates increased exponentially with increasing leaf temperature (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS009F4">4</xref>B), particularly above 35 °C, and the increase in rates of transpiration between 20 and 45 °C was &gt;4-fold. Thus, transpiration was strongly temperature dependent. However, it was not related to mean stomatal conductance, which was not especially temperature dependent (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS009F4">4</xref>C) over the whole temperature range. Nevertheless, there were significant differences in stomatal conductance between the different leaf temperatures.Internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration did vary with temperature (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS009F4">4</xref>D) and highest at the low temperatures and lowest at 30–35 °C (by 30 %) with a slight (16 %) increase thereafter at the highest temperatures. Thus, the internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration was also strongly temperature dependent.Statistics of fitting the model to photosynthetic data. The percentage of the error mean square accounted for by each of the three terms of the model is included. In all cases, the model was highly significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). The number of measurements (<italic>n</italic>) used in parameterizing the model for each temperature band is also shown.<bold>Impact of temperature on intercepts and coefficients.</bold> The intercept (A) and coefficients for stomatal conductance (B), internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (C) and photon flux density (D) as a function of leaf temperature (mean ± SE, <italic>N</italic> = 9). These coefficients were derived from a general linear additive model fitted to the seasonal rates of photosynthesis for all Semillon leaves, shoots and vines growing in an irrigated vineyard during the 2008/09 growing season for each separate temperature band between 20 and 45 °C. The model used stomatal conductance, internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and the PFD that was measured concurrently with each photosynthetic rate as the parameters in the general linear model. The model was fitted separately to the data for each vine and replicate, and the coefficients were then averaged accordingly.<bold>Modelled rates of photosynthesis as a function of the measured rates.</bold> Rates were averaged over each vine and replicate (mean ± SE, <italic>N</italic> = 9) of Semillon vines growing in an irrigated vineyard during the 2009/10 growing season. The line is a linear regression fitted to the whole dataset (slope 1.104 ± 0.008 mol mol<sup>−1</sup>, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.82, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001).<bold>The intercept (A) and a combined stomatal conductance × VPD coefficient (B) as a function of leaf temperature</bold>. These coefficients (mean ± SE, <italic>N</italic> = 9) were derived from a general linear multiplicative model fitted to the seasonal rates of transpiration for all Semillon leaves, shoots and vines growing in an irrigated vineyard during the 2008/09 growing season for each separate temperature band between 20 and 45 °C. The model used stomatal conductance and the VPD that was measured concurrently with each transpiration rate as the parameters in the general linear model. The model was fitted separately to the data for each vine and replicate, and the coefficients were then averaged accordingly.<bold>Modelled rates of transpiration as a function of the measured rates, averaged over each vine and replicate</bold>. Semillon vines were growing in an irrigated vineyard during the 2009/10 growing season. The line is a linear regression fitted to the whole dataset (slope 1.08 ± 0.0002 mol mol<sup>−1</sup>, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.999, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) (mean ± SE, <italic>N</italic> = 9).The present study of gas exchange of Semillon leaves over the growing season revealed that both photosynthesis and transpiration varied along the shoots in accordance with their expansion and development. Earliest emerging leaves had the highest rates of photosynthesis and transpiration, and these were achieved early in the growing season. As the season progressed, rates of photosynthesis declined in the basal leaves and increased in leaves towards the apical meristem. It was notable, however, that the leaves appearing in the mid- and late season did not reach the highest rates of photosynthesis and transpiration that were observed in the early emerging leaves. This suggested that some ontogenetic factor might have been at play, where the early-forming leaves are photosynthetically most active because of vines being heterotrophic at this stage and dependent on carbon reserves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C28">Goffinet 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C23">Field <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). A similar conclusion was reached for the early-emerging leaves on <italic>Actinidia deliciosa</italic> vines and elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C12">Catský and Šesták 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C32">Greer and Jeffares 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C66">Suriyagoda <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Although transpiration followed a pattern similar to photosynthesis, it is much harder to suggest a reason for this except that high transpiration rates might support transport of carbon assimilates from the roots to the leaves and shoot apical meristem. However, it was also clear that all changes in photosynthesis and transpiration were highly correlated with stomatal conductance. Stomatal conductance is also known to change with leaf development, increasing initially but generally declining with leaf age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C6">Bogaert and Lemeur 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C66">Suriyagoda <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C61">Salmon <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) as shown here for the Semillon leaves.However, from the modelling of photosynthesis it was uncertain in statistical terms that there was a role of leaf development in photosynthetic capacity of the leaves. Leaf position, time of day and day of season were not significant terms in the model, which suggested that differences in photosynthesis along the shoot and during the season were almost entirely accounted for by leaf temperature, stomatal behaviour, internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and PFD. The model generally accounted for 80–90 % of the variance in photosynthesis across the various temperature bands, but it was noteworthy that stomatal conductance accounted for ∼55 % of the variance at lower temperatures but 80 % at very high temperatures. This conforms to the well-established linear dependence of photosynthesis on stomatal conductance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C71">Wunsche <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C10">Caballé <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), although at high <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> the response can be non-linear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C70">Williams 2012</xref>). In contrast, although photosynthesis was negatively correlated with internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C10">Caballé <italic>et al</italic>. 2011)</xref>, the percentage of the variance accounted for declined from ∼35–45 % at 20–25 °C to 15–20 % at 40–45 °C. Across all leaf temperatures, the PFD accounted for &lt;10 % of the variance in the model and suggesting that the leaves were generally exposed to saturating PFDs during measurements, even though basal leaves were exposed to PFDs of ∼200–400 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> from mid-season. This might also explain why a more complex model incorporating the non-linear relationship between photosynthesis and PFD did not improve the fit of the model. Nevertheless, the simple three-parameter model was successfully applied to the independent datasets of the 2007/08 and 2009/10 growing seasons, and the fit accounted for 80 % of the variance. Furthermore, the slope of the line fitted between the measured and modelled rates of photosynthesis gave a slope close to 1 : 1, which was another indication of the goodness of fit. This compares with the multiplicative PFD model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C21">Fernández <italic>et al.</italic> (2006</xref>) for <italic>Festuca pallescens</italic>, which accounted for 86.5 % of the variance, and the PFD-based model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C10">Caballé <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref> for the same species and which accounted for 82 % of the variance. Similarly, the more extensive biochemical model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C41">Kim and Lieth (2003)</xref> for rose leaves gave a similar slope and accounted for 96 % of the variance, while for a range of crops, shrubs and trees, both more extensive biochemical and leaf models gave variances from 50 to 85 % (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C26">Gao <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). The biochemical-leaf model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C30">Gouasmi <italic>et al</italic>. (2009)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C54">Op de Beeck <italic>et al</italic>. (2010<italic>a</italic>)</xref> also had a 1 : 1 slope between measured and predicted photosynthesis. Thus, the simple model presented here gave consistent results with the more complex models.Photosynthesis of Semillon grape leaves is sensitive to temperature with an optimum around25–30 °C and rates declining by 30 % with leaf temperatures around40–45 °C, consistent with that for other grapevine varieties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C42">Kriedemann 1968</xref>). The response is also well in keeping with the generally understood effect of temperature on photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C5">Berry and Björkman 1980</xref>). Underlying this temperature response are those of the stomata, internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and PFD and their response to temperature. Although there were effects of temperature on stomatal conductance, across the whole temperature range, there was only a small overall change. This is in contrast to stomatal conductance of <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> leaves, which were markedly affected by temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C4">Battaglia <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>), especially towards the higher temperatures where the VPD increases markedly and thus closed the stomata (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C59">Reynolds <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C4">Battaglia <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>). In contrast, for a range of warm- and cool-climate herbaceous species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C9">Bunce 2000</xref>), stomatal conductance increased with increasing temperatures, which may be the response when the increase in VPD is prevented from occurring. Similar results were observed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C24">Fischer <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C47">Lu <italic>et al</italic>. (1994)</xref>. In contrast, in a simulation, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C59">Reynolds <italic>et al</italic>. (1992)</xref> have suggested that stomatal conductance peaks at ∼12–15 °C and declines markedly at higher temperatures. A similar response was observed for spinach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C72">Yamori <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Stomatal conductance of two cool-temperature <italic>Poa</italic> species also declined with an increase in temperature from 7 to 12 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C49">Medek <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), while in <italic>Pisum sativum, g</italic><sub>s</sub> increased from 15 to 25 °C and in <italic>Chenopodium album</italic>, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> remained about constant between 20 and 30 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C38">Hamilton <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).Relative to other grapevine cultivars such as Campbell Early and Kyoho (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C74">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), Kékfrancos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C76">Zsófi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), Zinfandel and White Reisling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C63">Schultz 2003</xref>), Temperanillo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C48">Maroco <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>) and Thompson Seedless (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C70">Williams 2012</xref>), the average stomatal conductances for the Semillon vines in the present study were towards the lower end of the reported ranges. In addition, the values reported here are lower than those reported for this variety in a cultivar comparison (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C60">Rogiers <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). This reflects the fact that many leaves and days of measurements were used to determine the overall gas exchange response to temperature in the present study. It does appear, however, that the temperature response of stomatal opening in other grapevine cultivars has not been assessed.For the Semillon leaves, the internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>c</italic><sub>i</sub>) varied strongly with temperature, especially below 30 °C where the concentration increased markedly in a trend opposite to photosynthesis. In contrast, over a near similar range of temperatures, <italic>c</italic><sub>i</sub> of <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> leaves changed only slightly, rising at high and low temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C4">Battaglia <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>). Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C10">Caballé <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C72">Yamori <italic>et al</italic>. (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C18">Eamus <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref> found no effect of temperature on <italic>c</italic><sub>i</sub>, but <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C10">Caballé <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref> suggested that <italic>c</italic><sub>i</sub> should change in the same direction as photosynthesis when stomata are dominating photosynthesis. The coupled changes in photosynthesis and stomatal conductance accompanied by an increase in <italic>c</italic><sub>i</sub> that occurred in <italic>Coffea arabica</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C29">Gómez <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>) conforms with this hypothesis. For the present study, however, the temperature dependency of <italic>c</italic><sub>i</sub> was close to a mirror image of the temperature dependency of photosynthesis and, given that stomatal conductance was not strongly temperature dependent, suggests that non-stomatal limitations also played a part in regulating Semillon leaf photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C34">Greer and Weedon 2012</xref>).The model of photosynthesis of Semillon leaves was constructed with three parameters, namely stomatal conductance, internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and PFD, but determined separately for the different leaf temperatures. This model was similar to that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C41">Kim and Lieth (2003)</xref>, who used PFD, <italic>c</italic><sub>i</sub> and leaf temperature to determine photosynthesis, and to that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C10">Caballé <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>, who used leaf temperature, c<sub>i</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> in a multiplicative model. A multiplicative model was also used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C21">Fernández <italic>et al</italic>. (2006)</xref>, involving RH, air temperature and <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and PFD-dependent responses. Thus, it would appear that the model used in the present study was one of a few to focus on leaf temperature explicitly and to ascertain the specific effect of temperature on each parameter of the model. In fact, all the coefficients of the parameters were temperature dependent although all varied in different ways, but the differences in the coefficients at the different temperatures were significant and warranted the approach. When combined, and taking into account the coefficients at the different temperatures, the model applied to new datasets gave an excellent fit and this confirmed the approach of determining the temperature sensitivity of the parameters of the model and indeed validated the model.Transpiration of the Semillon leaves more than doubled when leaf temperatures increased from 20 to 45 °C, in keeping with the need for increased evaporative cooling at the higher temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C9">Bunce 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C40">Keenan <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). This cultivar is known to have high transpiration rates among common wine grape cultivars (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C60">Rogiers <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and this cooling capacity can maintain leaf temperatures several degrees cooler than air temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C36">Greer <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). In contrast, transpiration rates of the grape variety <italic>Trincadeira preta</italic> declined markedly above about35 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C14">Correia <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>) and similarly transpiration rates of <italic>Eucalyptus haemastoma</italic> leaves declined markedly above about 35 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C18">Eamus <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). For <italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic>, however, rates were maximal between 36 and 40 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C37">Hall and Schulze 1980</xref>). There are clearly differences in the temperature dependency of transpiration and the response may well depend on the growth conditions of each species.The modelling of transpiration over the growing season indicated that a multiplicative model of stomatal conductance and VPD<sub>L</sub> (leaf to air) gave the best fit, and accounted for almost 100 % of the variance in transpiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C15">Cowan and Farquhar 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C37">Hall and Schulze 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C52">Meinzer <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C75">Zhu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Using a similar relationship, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C54">Op de Beeck <italic>et al.</italic> (2010<italic>a</italic>)</xref> had comparable results between measured and modelled transpiration, with 93 % of the variance accounted for and a 1 : 1 slope. The same multiplicative model used here was also used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C52">Meinzer <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref>, but compared with whole tree transpiration. It is noteworthy that an additive model in the present study, where <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and VPD<sub>L</sub> were included separately in the model, accounted for 93–98 % of the variance in transpiration over all temperatures, but significantly, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> accounted for most of the variance even though the effect of VPD<sub>L</sub> was highly significant. Transpiration has been commonly reported to be linear function of stomatal conductance, as has been shown for <italic>V. vinifera</italic> x <italic>V. labrusca</italic> cv. Campbell's Early and Kyoho (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C74">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and sugarcane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C50">Meinzer and Grantz 1989</xref>). Likewise, from diurnal changes in transpiration and stomatal conductance, a linear function was evident for <italic>Anacardium excelsium</italic> leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C51">Meinzer <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>). In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C8">Bunce (1997</xref>) showed an inverse relationship between stomatal conductance and transpiration for <italic>Abutilon</italic> leaves.The role of temperature in transpiration is explicitly in the determination of VPD<sub>L</sub> and calculating the saturated vapour pressure of the leaf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C13">Collatz <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>), but also through the effect of temperature on <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C25">Fredeen and Sage (1999)</xref> have shown for white spruce seedlings that <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> increased with increasing leaf temperature but only if the VPD was 2–3 kPa. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C37">Hall and Schulze (1980)</xref> had observed a similar response, except that the temperature effect on conductance was greatest at low rather than at high VPDs. For well-watered grapevines, in contrast, <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> declined with increasing leaf temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C14">Correia <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C57">Peak and Mott (2011)</xref> concluded that a direct effect of temperature on <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> is relatively small when the VPD<sub>L</sub> is kept constant. With the approach adopted in the present study, it was not possible to exclude a direct temperature effect on <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> in relation to transpiration from that of the effect on VPD<sub>L</sub>. Nevertheless, the model including leaf temperature responses of the <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> × VPD<sub>L</sub> interaction was warranted, given the extremely high-quality fit of the model prediction of the independent datasets and, therefore, validated the approach.The modelling of photosynthesis and transpiration from measurements made over whole growing seasons using a statistical regression approach successfully accounted for much of the seasonal variation that occurred. The model was underpinned by the temperature response of the various parameters, including stomatal conductance, internal CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, leaf-to-air water vapour difference and PFD. In contrast to other more complex biochemically based models, the present model was relatively simple and accounted for a high percentage of the variance in independent datasets. It is common to include temperature in various photosynthetic models but more typically as an intrinsic property of various biochemical processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS009C19">Farquhar <italic>et al.</italic> 1980</xref>), whereas the temperature responses in the present study were explicitly encapsulated by the parameter coefficients and central to the model. This focus on temperature is related to the high-temperature climate in which the vines are grown and these models will contribute to more extensive models of vine growth and development in relation to the climate that are currently under development.This project was funded by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Winegrowing Futures, a Grape and Wine Research and Development Corporation</grant-sponsor>-funded initiative to the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">National Wine and Grape Industry Centre at Charles Sturt University</grant-sponsor>.None declared.I wish to thank Mr Mark Weedon, Research Associate, and Mr Chris Weston, Technical Officer, at the National Wine and Grape Industry Centre for assistance with collecting the data. I also thank the Vineyard Owner for allowing me to conduct this study on their property. I am also indebted to SAS Australia for providing further support.