Genome size variation and evolution in allotetraploid <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> and its parents, <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic>Polyploidy and genome evolution in plantsNuclear DNA content in some species of <italic>Lessingianthus</italic> (Vernonieae, Asteraceae) by flow cytometryFitting linear mixed models in RNuclear DNA content and minimum generation time in herbaceous plantsAnthocyanin inhibits propidium iodide DNA fluorescence in <italic>Euphorbia pulcherrima</italic>: implications for genome size variation and flow cytometryKaryological analysis and genome size in <italic>Milium</italic> (Gramineae) with special reference to polyploidy and chromosomal evolutionRapid, repeated, and clustered loss of duplicate genes in allopolyploid plant populations of independent originGenetic and epigenetic mechanisms for gene expression and phenotypic variation in plant polyploidsCharacterizing polyploidy in <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic> using chromosome counts and flow cytometryLarge-scale polymorphism of heterochromatic repeats in the DNA of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>In IOPB chromosome number reports LXIIIRedundancy and rewiring of genetic networks following genome-wide duplication eventsNuclear genome size: are we getting closer?Flow cytometric estimation of nuclear DNA amount in diploid bananas (<italic>Musa acuminata</italic> and <italic>M. balbisiana</italic>)Nuclear DNA content and genome size of trout and humanEstimation of nuclear DNA content in plants using flow cytometryRole of adaptive and non-adaptive mechanisms forming complex patterns of genome size variation in six cytotypes of polyploid <italic>Allium oleraceum</italic> (Amaryllidaceae) on a continental scaleSystemic endopolyploidy in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Impact of mating systems on patterns of sequence polymorphism in flowering plantsIntraspecific variation in genome size in angiosperms: identifying its existenceAneuploidy and genetic variation in the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> triploid responseDosage and parent-of-origin effects shaping aneuploid swarms in <italic>A. thaliana</italic>Population fragmentation causes randomly fixed genotypes in populations of <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> in the Japanese ArchipelagoSimultaneous inference in general parametric modelsThe role of triploid hybrids in the evolutionary dynamics of mixed-ploidy populationsA metapopulation perspective on genetic diversity and differentiation in partially self-fertilizing plantsA unique recent origin of the allotetraploid species <italic>Arabidopsis suecica</italic>: evidence from nuclear DNA markersAncestral polyploidy in seed plants and angiospermsInterspecific and interploidal gene flow in central european <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Brassicaceae)Gene loss, silencing and activation in a newly synthesized wheat allotetraploidWheat: reconstitution of the tetraploid component (AABB) of hexaploidsApplications of flow cytometry to evolutionary and population biologyA case of genome partition in polyploid oatsGenome downsizing in polyploid plants<italic>S</italic>-gene polymorphism in <italic>Phlox drummondii</italic>Massive genomic variation and strong selection in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> lines from SwedenFlow cytometric and microscopic analysis of the effect of tannic acid on plant nuclei and estimation of DNA contentEcological determinants of genetic structure in plant populationsA preliminary note on the chromosomes of <italic>Oenothera lamarckiana</italic> and one of its mutants, <italic>O. gigas</italic>Polyploidy and its effect on evolutionary success: old questions revisited with new toolsNatural variation and persistent developmental instabilities in geographically diverse accessions of the allopolyploid <italic>Arabidopsis suecica</italic>Cytotype diversity and genome size variation in eastern Asian polyploid <italic>Cardamine</italic> (Brassicaceae) speciesAllopolyploidization lays the foundation for evolution of distinct populations: evidence from analysis of synthetic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> allohexaploidsRelationship between endopolyploidy and cell cize in epidermal tissue of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Synopsis of the genus <italic>Arabis</italic> (Brassicaceae) in Canada, Alaska and GreenlandDAPI staining of fixed cells for high-resolution flow cytometry of nuclear DNAPolyploid incidence and evolutionAllopolyploidy-induced rapid genome evolution in the wheat (<italic>Aegilops–Triticum</italic>) groupAssociated chromosomal DNA changes in polyploidsChloroplast DNA indicates a single origin of the allotetraploid <italic>Arabidopsis suecica</italic>Arabidopsis hybrid speciation processesThe evolutionary history of the <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic> complex: a hybrid in the amphi-Beringian area closes a large distribution gap and builds up a genetic barrierGenome size variation among accessions of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Attempts to relate cytological and molecular chromosome data of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> to its genetic linkage map<italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> (fisch. Ex dc.) K. Shimizu &amp; Kudoh and <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> subsp. <italic>kawasakiana</italic> (Makino) K. Shimizu &amp; Kudoh, new combinationsThe allopolyploid <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> originated from multiple individuals of <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic>Understanding intraspecific variation in genome size in plantsPolyploidy: recurrent formation and genome evolutionThe evolutionary dynamics of polyploid plants: origins, establishment and persistenceThe origins of genomic duplications in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Multilocus analysis of genetic divergence between outcrossing <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> species: evidence of genome-wide admixtureYesterday's polyploids and the mystery of diploidizationThe frequency of polyploid speciation in vascular plants<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> W. Scott ArmbrusterThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Genome doubling and changes in genome size are fundamental evolutionary processes. <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> has been reported to contain both diploid and tetraploid individuals (2 or 4 copies of every chromosome). We did find genome size differences among populations, and among populations genome size varied 7%. However, all sampled <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> plants from a wide geographic range were tetraploids. This level of intraspecific genome size variation in <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> is lower than in other <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> taxa. Due to its close relationship to <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> has the potential to be very useful in the study of polyploidy and genome evolution.Polyploidization and subsequent changes in genome size are fundamental processes in evolution and diversification. Little is currently known about the extent of genome size variation within taxa and the evolutionary forces acting on this variation. <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> has been reported to contain both diploid and tetraploid individuals. The aim of this study was to determine the genome size of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>, whether there is variation in ploidy and/or genome size in <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> and to study how genome size has evolved<italic>.</italic> We used propidium iodide flow cytometry to measure 2C DNA content of 73 plants from 25 geographically diverse populations of the putative allotetraploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> and its parents, <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic>. All <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> plants appear to be tetraploids. The mean 2C DNA content of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> was 1.034 pg (1011 Mbp), which is slightly smaller than the sum of its diploid parents (<italic>A. lyrata</italic>: 0.502 pg; <italic>A. halleri</italic>: 0.571 pg). <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> appears to have lost ∼37.594 Mbp (3.6 %) of DNA from its 2C genome. Tetraploid <italic>A. lyrata</italic> from Germany and Austria appears to have lost ∼70.366 Mbp (7.2 %) of DNA from the 2C genome, possibly due to hybridization with <italic>A. arenosa</italic>, which has a smaller genome than <italic>A. lyrata</italic>. We did find genome size differences among <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> populations, which varied up to 7 %. <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> ssp. <italic>kawasakiana</italic> from Japan appears to have a slightly larger genome than <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> ssp. <italic>kamchatica</italic> from North America, perhaps due to multiple allopolyploid origins or hybridization with <italic>A. halleri</italic>. However, the among-population coefficient of variation in 2C DNA content is lower in <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> than in other <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> taxa. Due to its close relationship to <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> has the potential to be very useful in the study of polyploidy and genome evolution.Polyploidy is one of the most important forces influencing plant diversification. Polyploidy was likely involved in 15 % of all recent angiosperm speciation events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C69">Wood <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and ancient polyploidy is apparent in all plant genomes sequenced to date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C31">Jiao <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Similarly, the majority of cultivated crops have undergone polyploidization during domestication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C51">Otto and Whitton 2000</xref>). Polyploidy influences the ecology and physiology of plants by generating novel phenotypes that may influence mating system, habitat and geographical distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C39">Levin 2002</xref>). It can have major genetic and genomic effects, such as altering chromosome segregation, masking deleterious mutations, influencing levels of genetic diversity, changing gene expression, causing rearrangements, gene loss and epigenetic changes, rewiring genetic networks, and altering rates of adaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C39">Levin 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C1">Adams and Wendel 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C8">Chen 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C13">De Smet and Van de Peer 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C44">Madlung 2013</xref>). Ploidy variation has the potential to promote the origin of new species, but ploidy variation within species (or species complexes) may also be an important source of genetic and phenotypic variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C65">Thompson and Lumaret 1992</xref>). Thus, plant biodiversity cannot be understood without understanding the processes of polyploid evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C43">Lutz 1907</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C64">Stebbins 1950</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C22">Grant 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C44">Madlung 2013</xref>).Polyploids are thought to experience high levels of genomic instability and undergo massive genetic and epigenetic changes within the first few generations after formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C8">Chen 2007</xref>). It is likely that a great deal of genomic and phenotypic diversity is generated and the majority of early generation polyploids are unable to survive in nature. However, if one or a few stable genotypes arise that happen to reconcile genomic incompatibilities, are vigorous and are well suited to survival in the prevailing habitat, polyploids can persist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C8">Chen 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C45">Madlung <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). After this rapid ‘genomic revolution’, it is likely that a slow process of diploidization begins, where gene duplicates may be silenced, lost or evolve new functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C68">Wolfe 2001</xref>). It is thought that nearly all angiosperms have experienced at least one polyploidy event in their evolutionary history (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C68">Wolfe 2001</xref>). However, due to extensive mutation, gene loss and rearrangements, these diploidized paleopolyploids, such as <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, have only recently been recognized as whole-genome sequences became available for detailed analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C66">Vision <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). Both the rapid genomic revolution and gradual process of diploidization are likely to result in variation and evolution in genome size as DNA is deleted, duplicated and rearranged, and variants are subject to genetic drift and selection.Polyploidy can arise from the duplication of genomes within a single species (autopolyploidy) or through hybridization between two species, accompanied by chromosome doubling (allopolyploidy) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C39">Levin 2002</xref>). Either allopolyploidy or autopolyploidy may arise via a single polyploidization event, like in <italic>Arabidopsis suecica</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C54">Säll <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C30">Jakobsson <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), or may have multiple origins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C63">Soltis and Soltis 1999</xref>), as has been suggested for <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Further, variation in ploidy level is frequently found within species both within and among populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C57">Schmuths <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C46">Marhold <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), and gene flow between ploidy levels is known to occur, either via a triploid bridge or through recurrent formation of unreduced gametes by diploids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C39">Levin 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C28">Husband 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C24">Henry <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C25">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C32">Jørgensen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). This gene flow from diploids to polyploids is likely an important source of genetic variation in polyploids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C32">Jørgensen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).<italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> is an allotetraploid plant produced through hybridization through two closely related diploid taxa, <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic> ssp. <italic>petraea</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic> ssp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C59">Shimizu <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> has an amphi-Beringian distribution, and the pattern of genetic diversity suggests that it migrated northward out of Japan (or near Japan) to eastern Russia, across the Bering land bridge into Alaska, and down the west coast of Canada (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). It has been suggested that <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> may have multiple origins through independent hybridization and polyploidization events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), and/or that it may hybridize with its diploid parental taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C67">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Both of these processes have the potential to give rise to genome size variation. Further, <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> has been suggested to contain both diploid and tetraploid individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C12">Dawe and Murray 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C67">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Because <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> is a close relative of the model plant, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, a treasure trove of molecular research is easily applied to this organism, and development of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> into a model system for the evolution of polyploidy has the potential to yield a great deal of insight into the evolution of polyploid genomes.The goal of this study was to investigate genome size variation in <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> using flow cytometry. We characterized the nuclear DNA content of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> and its putative parental species, <italic>A. lyrata</italic> and <italic>A. halleri</italic>, in a total of 25 populations from North America, Europe and Japan. We used the results to determine whether there is variation in ploidy and/or genome size in <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> and its parents, and to determine how genome size has evolved in polyploids relative to their diploid parents.Collection locations, collectors and mean (±1 SE) genome size of each population. <sup>1</sup>Assumes <italic>Glycine max</italic> ‘Polanka’ 2C DNA content of 2.5 pg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C15">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C14">Doležel and Greilhuber 2010</xref>). <sup>2</sup>Populations with different letters have significantly different means (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in post hoc comparisons among <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> populations with &gt;2 individuals. <sup>3</sup>Conversion from pg to Mbp assuming Mbp = pg × 978 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C16">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>).Map of collection localities of plants used for flow cytometry.Chromosome counting is the traditional method for determining ploidy level of an organism; however, it is labour intensive and may be inaccurate in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> species due to their very small chromosomes (ranging from 1.5 m to 2.8 µm in <italic>A. thaliana</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C58">Schweizer <italic>et al.</italic> 1987</xref>) and the high frequency of endopolyploidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C20">Galbraith <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C48">Melarango <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>). Flow cytometry allows rapid analysis of thousands of nuclei per sample and high throughput of many samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C35">Kron <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Therefore, we used flow cytometry to estimate genome size and infer DNA ploidy. Because flow cytometry reveals genome size rather than a count of chromosomes, ploidy must be verified by chromosome counts in at least a few samples. In our study, we included both diploid and tetraploid references from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> locations where both flow cytometry and chromosome counts have previously been carried out (<italic>A. kamchatica</italic> from Japan, and <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> from Iceland and Austria; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU025TB1">1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C9">Dart <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>).Each <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> sample was co-chopped and run with soybean leaf, <italic>Glycine max</italic> ‘Polanka’, as an internal reference standard. The standard was grown from the same seed stock previously quantified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C15">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>). Young leaves were collected from each <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plant and kept on ice until processing, which occurred within 3 h of leaf collection. For each plant, three fresh leaves were placed in a plastic Petri dish with approximately half as much fresh leaf tissue from <italic>G. max</italic>. Leaf tissue was chopped in the presence of 0.5 mL of cold chopping buffer using a fresh stainless-steel razor blade. The chopping buffer was modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C50">Otto (1990)</xref> Buffer I by adding 0.5 % v/v of Triton X-100 rather than Tween 20. When the leaves were well chopped, we added an additional 0.5 mL of cold chopping buffer. The sample was then filtered through a 30-µm Partec CellTrics<sup>®</sup> filter and centrifuged for 20 s at 3500 rpm. The supernatant was drawn off and 2 µL of RNase A was added to the pellet. The pellet was resuspended in 0.2 mL of propidium iodine staining buffer. The propidium iodine staining buffer (28.65 g of dibasic sodium phosphate, 190 mL of deionized water and 10 mL of propidium iodine stock, which consists of 5 mg of propidium iodine and 10 mL of deionized water) was modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C50">Otto (1990)</xref>. Samples were stained in the dark for 40 min prior to performing flow cytometry.Fluorescence intensity histograms (PE-A) for (A) tetraploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> (2C = 4<italic>x</italic> = 32), (B) diploid <italic>A. h. gemmifera</italic> (2C = 2<italic>x</italic> = 16) and (C) diploid <italic>A. lyrata</italic> (2C = 2<italic>x</italic> = 16). <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaves show extensive endopolyploidy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C20">Galbraith <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>), and the 2C, 4C and 8C peaks are indicated, along with the soybean standard (std). The mean fluorescence of the smallest peak (2C) relative to the soybean peak was used to estimate 2C DNA content.To determine whether the taxa differed in genome size, we used a linear mixed-effects model with species as the fixed effect, populations as the random effect and 2C DNA content (pg) as the dependent variable with the <italic>lme4</italic> package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C3">Bates 2005</xref>), implemented in R. The hypothesis test of the species effect was conducted with 5000 iterations of the parametric bootstrap approach based on the likelihood ratio statistics, <italic>D</italic> = −2 × (log-likelihood ratio), of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C19">Faraway (2006)</xref>. To determine which species differed from one another in 2C DNA content, we performed Tukey's multiple comparison tests with an R package, <italic>multcomp</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C27">Hothorn <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). To determine whether populations of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> differed in 2C DNA content, a second one-way ANOVA was performed with population as the fixed effect and 2C DNA content (pg) as the dependent variable. For this analysis we restricted our dataset to include only the nine <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> populations for which we had at least three samples. The mean number of samples per population was 5.3. Tukey's multiple comparison tests were performed to determine which <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> populations significantly differed from one another in genome size. In order to test the additivity of the tetraploid genome size, we examined a contrast null hypothesis, where the 1Cx genome size (i.e. the haploid genome size, <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C23">Greilhuber 2005</xref>) of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> is the average of the two parental species, in the subset of data including <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>, <italic>A. h. gemifera</italic> and <italic>A. lyrata</italic> (two subspecies were combined). A linear mixed-effects model was fitted with 1Cx values as the dependent variable, population as a random effect and species as a fixed effect, and the linear contrast, (1Cx of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>) = [(1Cx of <italic>A. h. gemifera</italic>) + (1Cx of <italic>A. lyrata</italic>)]/2, was tested with an R package, <italic>multcomp</italic>. For estimates of genome size diversity in each taxon, we used the CV among populations in 2C DNA content with the bias correction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C62">Sokal and Rohlf 1995</xref>). To estimate genome size diversity in diploid <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, we used data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C57">Schmuths <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> collected from 18 worldwide accessions using the same flow cytometry methods that we used.Estimates of 2C DNA content (pg) of each taxon and the 95 % confidence intervals of the estimates. Letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05) based on Tukey's post hoc comparisons.There was significant variation in genome size among <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> populations (<italic>F</italic><sub>8,39</sub> = 15.7, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 10<sup>−9</sup>). Post hoc tests indicate that the genome size of the Japanese <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> population (Shinbo) was significantly larger than the North American populations. The Canadian <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> population did not differ in genome size from the Alaskan populations. However, two of the six Alaskan populations differed in genome size; the nuclear DNA content of the Goodnews Bay population was 3 % smaller than that of the Grant Lagoon population. Despite the minor amounts of variation among populations, none of the <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> plants sampled appear to be diploid.The 2C DNA content of <italic>A. l. lyrata</italic> (0.503 pg/2C, 95 % CI [0.484, 0.522]) and diploid <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> (0.502 pg/2C, 95 % CI [0.484, 0.521]) did not significantly differ from one another (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU025F3">3</xref>). The <italic>A. h. gemmifera</italic> genome (0.571 pg/2C, 95 % CI [0.539, 0.604]) was 14 % larger than <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> and <italic>A. l. lyrata</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU025F3">3</xref>). We did not have enough samples/population of these taxa to analyse differences among populations.Estimates of 1Cx (haploid) genome size (pg) of each taxon. The error bars are 95 % confidence intervals of the estimates. Letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) based on Tukey's post hoc comparisons.Genome size diversity in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> taxa, measured as CV in 2C DNA content. Only diploid <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> are included because there were too few tetraploids to estimate CV (two from each taxon).Our genome size estimates are very similar to those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C9">Dart <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> for diploid and tetraploid collections in common (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU025TB1">1</xref>), suggesting that our results are reliable. Using both chromosome counting and flow cytometry, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C9">Dart <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> found that plants from Japan (Shinbo) and Austria are tetraploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 32) with genome sizes of 1.1 pg/2C (Japan) and 0.9 pg/2C (Austria), while plants from Iceland are diploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 16) with a genome size of 0.52 pg/2C. The small differences between our data and those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C9">Dart <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> are likely due to the fact that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C9">Dart <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> used fluorescent beads as an internal size standard, whereas we used leaf tissue from <italic>G. max</italic>. While beads are sufficient for ploidy determination, leaf tissue is the preferred internal size standard for absolute genome size estimation because staining variation can be taken into account (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C17">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).Several previous reports have suggested that <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> contains both diploid and tetraploid individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C12">Dawe and Murray 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C67">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). While many species show a mix of ploidy levels, even within a population, these are likely autopolyploids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C57">Schmuths <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C32">Jørgensen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Given that <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> is an allopolyploid, diploids spontaneously produced from tetraploids would likely have low vigour and fertility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C34">Kerber 1964</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C36">Ladizinsky and Fainstein 1978</xref>), as allopolyploidization appears to rapidly result in gene silencing and gene loss for numerous loci (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C33">Kashkush <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C1">Adams and Wendel 2005</xref>). Our data from 52 <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> specimens representing most of the species' range found no evidence of diploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>, and we suggest that the species is likely to be entirely tetraploid. If diploids are present, they are likely to be in very low frequencies, and not maintained by selection.Deeper investigation into previous reports also suggests that there is no good evidence for the presence of diploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C12">Dawe and Murray (1981)</xref> report chromosome counts from three diploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 16) and two tetraploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> samples (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 32). <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic> is very difficult to morphologically distinguish from mostly diploid <italic>A. lyrata</italic>; however, molecular data suggest that the two species have distinct geographical ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C56">Schmickl <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The tetraploid counts reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C12">Dawe and Murray (1981)</xref> are within the species range of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C56">Schmickl <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>, whereas two of the three diploid counts are from plants growing north of the Brooks Range in Alaska and are probably <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C56">Schmickl <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) or <italic>A. media</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C49">Mulligan 1995</xref>). One of the diploid counts (originally reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C11">Dawe and Murray 1979</xref>) comes from well within <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>'s range in interior Alaska, near several of our collections (63°02′N, 145°29′W), and was likely taken from <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C49">Mulligan (1995)</xref> claims that the diploid report is an error, and that the voucher in ALA indicates that 2<italic>n</italic> = 32 (tetraploid), not 2<italic>n</italic> = 16 (diploid). Other chromosome counts reported for <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C49">Mulligan (1995)</xref> are all tetraploid, and he suggests that the species is entirely tetraploid.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C67">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> claim to have detected both diploid and tetraploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> in Taiwan using flow cytometry and sequencing of nuclear DNA from 98 genes. They suggest that diploids have a ‘mosaic genome’ of the two parental species. Although this would be very interesting if confirmed, more complete evidence is desirable. First, their flow cytometry runs seem to lack an internal standard. The absolute value of nucleus fluorescence cannot reliably be used to estimate genome size as this value shifts due to variation in sample preparation, staining and analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C17">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). This shift can be seen by comparing Fig. S1A and S1B in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C67">Wang <italic>et al</italic> (2010</xref>), which were presented as evidence of diploid and tetraploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>. Further, their DNA sequence data do not provide any evidence of ploidy since only a single clone per PCR reaction was sequenced, ensuring that only a single homeologue (randomly chosen from one of the two parental genomes of tetraploids) could be obtained from each individual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C67">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Although we have not sampled <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> from Taiwan for our study, the ‘mosaic genome’ of purported diploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> can possibly be explained by misinterpretation of flow cytometry data and randomly sequencing only one of the two homeologues from each gene.We appear to have identified variation in the 2C DNA content among <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> populations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C23">Greilhuber (2005)</xref> suggested that a great deal of apparent within-species, within-ploidy variation in genome DNA content estimated by flow cytometry is due to methodological artefacts. For instance, different levels of anthocyanins, tannic acid and other secondary metabolites in leaves can influence fluorescence and apparent DNA content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C41">Loureiro <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C5">Bennett <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Following best-practice recommended protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C17">Doležel <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), we used an internal size standard co-chopped with each sample, we used Otto's buffer, which reduces the effects of tannic acid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C41">Loureiro <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), and leaves were not pigmented. Further, repeated measurements of the same plant on different days produced very similar DNA content estimates (&lt;1.1 % variation). Thus the variation we observed should be biologically real (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C57">Schmuths <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). However, co-chopping two putatively different samples from different populations would further increase certainty that differences among populations are not artefactual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C23">Greilhuber 2005</xref>).The 2C DNA content of Japanese <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> appears to be slightly larger than North American <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>. This observed genome size difference may differentiate the two <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> subspecies: <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> ssp. <italic>kamchatica</italic> and <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> ssp. <italic>kawasakiana</italic>. Our Japanese <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> samples are from subspecies <italic>A. k. kawasakiana</italic>, whereas the rest of our samples represent subspecies <italic>A. k. kamchatica</italic> from North America. These two subspecies differ in habitat, morphology and nucleotide allele frequencies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C26">Higashi <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> suggested that <italic>A. k. kawasakiana</italic> may represent a distinct origin of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>. The difference in genome size between the Japanese <italic>A. k. kawasakiana</italic> and North American <italic>A. k. kamchatica</italic> potentially supports that hypothesis. Alternatively, ongoing hybridization between <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> and its diploid parent, <italic>A. h. gemmifera</italic>, in Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C67">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) could increase the genome size in Asia by reintroducing homeologues that may have been deleted in the allotetraploid.Other possible explanations for the genome size differences between Japan and North America include biogeographic history and selection. It has been suggested that time-limited environments may select for a smaller genome with more rapid cell division (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C61">Šmarda and Bureš 2010</xref>). As <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> expanded north out of Japan and across the cold Bering land bridge into North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), a smaller genome may have been favoured due to the short growing season. Interestingly, despite the difference in genome size, Japanese and North American samples appear to have lost similar numbers of genes (P. L. Chang, unpubl. res.). Our sampling from Japan was very limited. A thorough investigation of genome size variation from throughout Japan, accompanied by an investigation of introgression and deletions, is needed for a thorough understanding of genome size evolution in this species.Within-species variation in nuclear genome size may be an important source of genetic diversity, especially if it is associated with phenotypic and ecological variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C39">Levin 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C47">Matsushita <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Although we did find significant levels of genome size diversity in the allotetraploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>, levels of genome size diversity were much lower than in the diploid <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> taxa studied (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU025F5">5</xref>). This is consistent with the low levels of nucleotide diversity in <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> relative to the other taxa studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C60">Shimizu-Inatsugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Although nucleotide diversity is generated by point mutations, while genome size variation is generated by indels, changes in repetitive DNA and transposon activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C61">Šmarda and Bureš 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C40">Long <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), the two forms of genetic diversity are likely to be governed by many of the same population genetic processes such as mating system, biogeography and demographic history (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C42">Loveless and Hamrick 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C29">Ingvarsson 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C21">Glémin <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C18">Duchoslav <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).The DNA content of tetraploid <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> was slightly less than expected based on the sum of the two parental taxa. It is possible that this apparent loss in DNA content could be artefactual, due to differences between species in plant secondary compounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C23">Greilhuber 2005</xref>). However, rapid loss of DNA after polyploidization appears to be common in polyploids, as the 1Cx genome size has been shown to decrease as the ploidy level increases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C6">Bennett and Thomas 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C53">Raina <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C52">Ozkan <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C37">Leitch and Bennett 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C2">Angulo and Dematteis 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C18">Duchoslav <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C6">Bennett and Thomas (1991)</xref> suggest that these changes in DNA content may have adaptive significance, perhaps because the rate of cell division is slowed considerably as genome size increases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C4">Bennett 1972</xref>) and it may be beneficial to remove unnecessary DNA when ploidy level is high.The majority of genome size variation within plant species at a single ploidy level is due to variation in amounts of repetitive DNA such as transposable elements, ribosomal genes and centromeric repeats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C38">Levin 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C10">Davison <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C61">Šmarda and Bureš 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C40">Long <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). However, polyploids may also lose considerable amounts of functional DNA either because it is not necessary to have two copies or because it may allow the two parental genomes to resolve incompatibilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C33">Kashkush <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C1">Adams and Wendel 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C7">Buggs <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Whole-genome sequencing of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>, and comparison to its parental taxa, suggests that each of three accessions from different geographic regions lost ∼463 of more than 60 000 total genes (∼2 % of assembled genes; P. L. Chang, unpubl. res.). Considering that our flow cytometry estimate of the <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> genome size was 3.6 % smaller than expected based on the sum of the parental genomes, the total amount of DNA lost is comparable to the percent of genes lost. This suggests that DNA was lost from both genic regions and non-functional regions in <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>.<italic>Arabidopsis l. petraea</italic> tetraploids appear to have lost considerably more DNA than <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>. Although these plants are thought to be <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> autotetraploids, they may have experienced hybridization and introgression of DNA from <italic>A. arenosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C32">Jørgensen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C55">Schmickl and Koch 2011</xref>), which has a genome size that is 13 % smaller than <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C32">Jørgensen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Using DNA content numbers from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C32">Jørgensen <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref>, <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> tetraploid genomes are just slightly smaller than expected from the sum of diploid <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> and diploid <italic>A. arenosa</italic> genomes: observed tetraploid <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> relative genome size 0.44; vs expected diploid <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> 0.23 + diploid <italic>A. arenosa</italic> 0.20 = 0.43 (data are presented as a ratio of the sample peak over the internal standard peak, and cannot be converted to picograms since the 2C DNA content of the standard, <italic>Ilex crenata</italic>, is unknown; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU025C32">Jørgensen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The apparent loss of DNA in tetraploid <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> may thus be largely due to hybridization rather than gradual DNA loss through diploidization.Contrary to some prior reports, all <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> plants in our samples appear to be tetraploid. We found that the allotetraploid, <italic>A. kamchatica</italic>, has a genome size that is just slightly less than the sum of its diploid parental taxa, <italic>A. l. petraea</italic> and <italic>A. h. gemmifera</italic>. Genome size diversity was lower in <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> than in other <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> taxa. However, there was some variation in genome size, where North American populations of <italic>A. k. kamchatica</italic> seem to have lost slightly more DNA than the Japanese population of subspecies <italic>A. k. kawasakiana</italic>. The development of <italic>A. kamchatica</italic> into a model system for the study of polyploidy has the potential to yield a great deal of insight, as its parental taxa have been well studied at both the ecological and genetic levels, and myriad molecular tools from <italic>A. thaliana</italic> are available.This research was supported by the <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">National Center for Research Resources (NCRR) at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) (Alaska INBRE)</grant-sponsor> [<grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">RR016466 and 5P20RR016466</grant-num>] and the <grant-sponsor id="cs2" rid="cn2" xlink:type="simple">National Science Foundation (NSF) Experimental Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (Alaska EPSCoR)</grant-sponsor> [<grant-num id="cn2" rid="cs2" xlink:type="simple">0346770</grant-num>].Plants were collected by J.A.S., D.E.W. and N.T. Methods were developed and debugged by J.A.S., G.J.H. and N.T. J.A.S. collected the data. J.A.S. and N.T. analysed the data and produced figures. D.E.W. conceived and wrote the manuscript, which was edited by J.A.S., G.J.H. and N.T.None declared.We thank Beth Dunkel for helping with collection of the flow cytometry data. We thank J. Doležel for generously providing seeds of the genome size standard, <italic>Glycine max</italic> ‘Polanka’. We thank Mark Wright at the UAF IAB Greenhouse for growing and maintaining plants.