The fruit of <italic>Bursera</italic>: structure, maturation and parthenocarpyMorfología de plántulas de <italic>Bursera</italic> Jacq. ex L. (Burseraceae) y sus implicaciones filogenéticasComparative floral morphology and anatomy of Anacardiaceae and Burseraceae (Sapindales), with a special focus on gynoecium structure and evolutionEvolution of Mexican <italic>Bursera</italic> (Burseraceae) inferred from ITS, ETS, and 5S nuclear ribosomal DNA sequencesTiming the origin and expansion of the Mexican tropical dry forestSources and sinks of diversification and conservation priorities for the Mexican tropical dry forestGerminación de semillas de seis especies de <italic>Bursera</italic> del centro de MéxicoEnvironmental control of flowering periodicity in Costa Rican and Mexican tropical dry forestsPhenology of canopy trees of a tropical deciduous forest in MexicoSeed rain dynamics following disturbance exclusion in a secondary tropical dry forest in Morelos, MexicoSeed predation and survival in the infructescences of <italic>Protea repens</italic> (Proteaceae)BurseraceaeInsights into the historical construction of species-rich Mesoamerican seasonally dry tropical forests: the diversification of <italic>Bursera</italic> (Burseraceae, Sapindales)Seed and fruit structure: significance in seed conservation operationsPatch size and tree species influence the number and duration of birds visits in forest restoration plots in Southern Costa RicaLife expectancy and egg load affect oviposition decisions of a solitary parasitoidCalcium oxalate crystals in plantsBird rejection of unhealthy fruits reinforces the mutualism between juniper and its avian dispersersA study on the chalcidoid (Hymenoptera: Chalcidoidea) parasitoids of leafminers (Diptera: Agromyzidae) in Ankara ProvinceFruits: a developmental perspectiveAnatomy and fruit development in <italic>Schinopsis balansae</italic> (Anacardiaceae)Evaluation of restoration effectiveness: community response to the removal of alien plantsEarly seed fall and seedling emergence: precursors to tropical restorationGranivoryAvian fruit removal: effects of fruit variation, crop size, and insect damagePolinización y variabilidad de la producción de semillas en <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> L. (Anacardiaceae)Herbivory and concentrations affect calcium oxalate crystal formation in leaves of <italic>Sida</italic> (Malvaceae)Biodiversity hotspots for conservation prioritiesDispersión biótica de semillas y caracterización de los frutos de Bursera morelensis en el Valle de Tehuacan, PueblaParthenocarpy, attractiveness and seed predation by birds in <italic>Bursera morelensis</italic>Parthenocarpy and seed predation by insects in <italic>Bursera morelensis</italic>Parthenocarpy and seed production in BurseraceaeLas especies de <italic>Bursera</italic> (Burseraceae) en la cuenca superior del Río Papaloapan (México)Inventario del conocimiento taxonómico, así como de la diversidad y del endemismo regionales de las especies mexicanas de <italic>Bursera</italic> (Burseraceae)Relaciones fenológicas entre <italic>Pseudopachymerina spinipes</italic> (Bruchidae) y <italic>Acacia caven</italic> (Leguminosae)Extent and drivers of change of neotropical seasonally dry forestsMale and female gametophytes and development of the seeds in <italic>Bursera delpechiana</italic> PoissPatterns of fruit presentation and seed dispersal in bird-disseminated woody plants in the eastern deciduous forestPlant–insect interactions in terrestrial ecosystems<italic>Ambilobea</italic>, a new genus from Madagascar, the position of <italic>Aucoumea</italic>, and comments on the tribal classification of the frankincense and myrrh familyDeceptive fruits reduce insect seed predation in <italic>Pistacia terebinthus</italic> LConsecuencias de la ruptura de mutualismos planta-animal para la distribución de especies vegetales en las Islas BalearesThe fruit of <italic>Commiphora</italic>Less is better: new approaches for seedless fruit productionEcological causes, function, and evolution of abortion and parthenocarpy in <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> (Anacardiaceae)The effect of deceptive fruits on predispersal seed predation by birds in <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic>The nested assembly of plant facilitation networks prevents species extinctionsPericarp structure and generic affinities in the AnacardiaceaeCell-mediated crystallization of calcium oxalate in plantsParthenocarpic fruits in wild parsnip: decoy defence against a specialist herbivoreInfertile seeds of <italic>Yucca schottii</italic>: a beneficial role for the plant in the yucca–yucca moth mutualism?This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.This study provides new information on fruit ripening of Bursera, from a structural and phenological point of view, we show some development patterns that must be taken into account in future physiological, ecological and management studies.The deterioration of seasonally tropical dry forests will stop with the implementation of management plans for this ecosystem. To develop these plans, we require information regarding aspects such as germination and the presence of ‘empty seeds’ of representative species—like, for example, <italic>Bursera,</italic> a genus with a high number of endemic species of the Mesoamerican Hotspot—that would enable us to propagate its species. The main purpose of this study is to describe the phenological and structural characteristics of fruits of 12 <italic>Bursera</italic> species and provide useful data for future studies on germination and seed dispersal, and to acquire new and useful information to understand the phylogenetic relationships of the Burseraceae family.We described the phenology of fruit ripening in 12 species of <italic>Bursera.</italic> Fruits were collected from the study sites in three different stages of development. The histochemical and anatomical characteristics of fruits of all species were described with the use of inclusion techniques and scanning microscopy.There is a time gap between the development of the ovary and the development of the ovule in the 12 studied species. The exposed pseudoaril during the dispersion stage is an indicator of the seed's maturity and the fruit's viability. The <italic>Bursera</italic> fruit shows the same structural pattern as that of <italic>Commiphora,</italic> as well as many similarities with species of the Anacardiaceae family. All species develop parthenocarpic fruits that retain the structural characteristics of the immature fruits: soft tissues rich in nitrogen compounds and few chemical and physical defences. Insects were found mainly inside the parthenocarpic fruits in eight species of <italic>Bursera</italic>.The dispersion unit in <italic>Bursera</italic> consists of a seed, a lignified endocarp that protects the seed, and a pseudoaril that helps attract seed dispersers. The production of parthenocarpic fruits is energy saving; however, it is necessary to evaluate the potential benefits of this phenomenon.Owing to the rapid deterioration of seasonally dry tropical forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C47">Sánchez-Azofeifa and Portillo-Quintero 2011</xref>), we need to select native plant species that will help regenerate this habitat and stop its fragmentation. To do this, it is necessary to know the biology, the ecology, and the propagation and management systems of the new species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C58">Vázquez-Yanes <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>). The genus <italic>Bursera</italic> is a dominant element of the seasonally tropical dry forest, especially in the Mesoamerican Hotspot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C38">Myers <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>) and specifically in Mexico. There are 106 species of <italic>Bursera</italic>, 80 of which are endemic to Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C5">Becerra 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C45">Rzedowski <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C6">Becerra and Venable 2008</xref>). In spite of the richness, abundance and endemism of <italic>Bursera</italic>, the different processes that contribute to the reproductive success of the species, such as dispersion, pollination, competition, herbivory and the sexual system, and the dependence or contribution of each of these factors to their population dynamics, are practically unknown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C54">Traveset 2002</xref>). The first step to understanding such a network of processes, and which constitutes the main purpose of this study, is to acquire knowledge of the <italic>Bursera</italic> fruit as the structure containing the dispersion unit. It will then be possible to develop further studies about germination, seed dispersal and, subsequently, recruitment and seedling survival.According to descriptions by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C44">Rzedowski <italic>et al</italic>. (2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C45">2005</xref>), <italic>Bursera</italic> seeds disperse through the ‘endozoochory syndrome’, which means that the seeds are protected against physical and chemical damage by a hard layer, their pulp is rich in nutrients and their colour contrasts with the colour of the surrounding vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C55">Van der Pijl 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C30">Howe and Westley 1988</xref>). An obstacle for the propagation and management of <italic>Bursera</italic> has been the absence of information regarding its germination. The germination rate of the 12 studied species of <italic>Bursera</italic> was &lt;50 %, mainly due to the presence of ‘empty’ seeds. These results were attributed to the immaturity of the embryo and to genetic factors such as endogamy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C1">Andrés-Hernández and Espinosa-Organista 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C7">Bonfil-Sanders <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Two other species also showed the presence of ‘empty’ fruits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C59">Verdú and García-Fayos 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). These ‘empty’ fruits or seeds have been interpreted as parthenocarpy (the production of seedless fruits) but, excluding <italic>Bursera morelensis</italic>, the structural characteristics and the ecological role of seeded and seedless fruits remain unknown. Seed development in <italic>B. morelensis</italic> shows a time gap as regards the development of the ovary. The fertile ovule becomes latent for 7–11 months; the valves in these fruits are completely released, showing a brightly coloured pseudoaril (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). This same time gap was reported for <italic>Bursera delpechiana</italic> and <italic>B. medranoana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C48">Srivastava 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C13">Cortes 1998</xref>). Parthenocarpic fruits in <italic>B. morelensis</italic> are characterized by their development even in the absence of pollination, and abortion of the ovule is frequently caused by an abnormal growth of the ovary walls which ultimately crush the ovule. Regardless of the abortion of the ovule, the fruit continues its development, although as the stage of seed dispersal approaches, the fruit dries, the valves open partially, rarely falling off completely, and the fruit can remain on the tree even if the next flowering and fructification stages have started. During their development histologically, these fruits have fewer chemical and physical defences than those with seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). The same research with <italic>B. morelensis</italic> suggests that abortion of the ovule can also be caused by insects; these seeds can be recognized by the holes left by the insects when they deposit their eggs or when they abandon the fruit. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C7">Bonfil-Sanders <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref> also mention the presence of ‘empty’ seeds, deformed and with holes, although they do not refer to their possible origin. Considering that seeds develop from ovules and that, when mature, they have embryos, endosperm (in most cases) and testa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C17">Esau 1985</xref>), the use of the term ‘empty seed’ in the literature is contradictory. The anatomical description of the <italic>Bursera</italic> fruit, absent in the literature, can contribute to understanding the arrangement of different layers of the pericarp, and to define the composition of the dispersal unit. It can also help to better understand the phylogenetic relationships with other members of the Burseraceae family which, for a long time, have been based on the morphological characteristics of the fruit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C4">Becerra 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C14">Daly <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), and with members of the Anacardiaceae family, to which it is strongly related (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C62">Wannan and Quinn 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C2">Bachelier and Endress 2009</xref>).Accordingly, the particular objectives of this study were (i) to describe the phenological characteristics of 12 species of <italic>Bursera</italic> with regard to the production and maturation of the fruit; (ii) to determine whether the fruit of <italic>Bursera</italic> with seeds has the same structural pattern, by using 12 species that represent the six groups comprising the genus according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C4">Becerra (2003)</xref>; (iii) to establish whether the ‘empty’ fruits' are parthenocarpic, and to assess their physical and chemical defenses from a histochemical and anatomical perspective; (iv) to determine whether the time lag between the development of the ovule and the development of the ovary is a common phenomenon in the 12 species; and (v) to determine whether the fruits of the 12 species are inhabited by insects, linking their presence to the phenological and structural characteristics of the fruits.Morphological characteristics of the fruit in 12 <italic>Bursera</italic> species and sampling site; nine of them are endemic to Mexico (<sup>a</sup>). Fruit form; number of valves of the fruit; number of locules in the ovary. Gathered information from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C44">Rzedowski <italic>et al</italic>. (2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C45">2005</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C28">Guízar-Nolazco and Sánchez-Vélez (1991)</xref>.Characteristics of the study sites. Information obtained from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C18">Férnández (1999)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C36">Medina (2000)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C26">Gómez-Garzón (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C10">Ceccon and Hernández (2009)</xref>.The phenology of the species was described after six visits to the study sites (2010: February, May, mid-June, end of July and early December; 2011: May 2011). The production periods of leaves, flowers and fruits of female individuals per species (<italic>n</italic> = 324, minimum 10 trees, maximum 40 trees) were registered after qualitative observations. Species from the state of Puebla had been checked previously (May 2005 to May 2007) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). The flowering period of the species from the state of Morelos was determined after a literature search. The qualitative record of the reproductive period in which the trees were found was obtained during the first two visits. The approximate dates of the rainy season, the approximate amount of fruits produced by the trees and phenological periods were obtained through consultation with the inhabitants of the local community. The species were identified with the help of the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C28">Guízar-Nolazco and Sánchez-Vélez 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C44">Rzedowski <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>) and local guides. The individuals in places that were difficult to access, or those that were too high up, were viewed through binoculars. The species with fruits—<italic>B. aptera</italic>, <italic>B. arida</italic>, <italic>B. fagaroides</italic> and <italic>B. schlechtendalii</italic>—were identified and marked from the beginning (February) by the characteristics of the trunk and the presence of fruits. The rest of the species were identified and marked once the flowers and leaves had developed (June).Three fruit collecting stages were established during the fruiting season 2010–2011: the initial stage of development or when fruit set occurs, a middle stage that considered the latency period of the ovule and the final stage when seed dispersal occurs. The middle stage was defined as the period after the fruit set stage and before dispersal. The four species with fruits in February and May had a middle stage in December. According to the literature and people from the local community, fruit removal in other species began in October and ended in December, so the middle stage was established at late July.Collections were made in three trees of each species chosen at random in order to determine the structural characteristics of fruits with seeds and of ‘empty’ fruits, as well as the developmental stage of the ovule with regard to the stage of maturation in which the fruit was found. The same trees were used in every collection; we collected 50 fruits per tree, they were fixed with FAA (formol, acetic acid, 96 % ethanol and water 1 : 0.5 : 5 : 3.5) and taken to the laboratory. All fruits were dissected under a stereoscopic microscope and grouped in three different categories after registering the proportion of fruits with ovules or developing embryos, and fruits with an aborted ovule, occupied or not by insects. The occupied fruits were those with insects in any stage of development, or those that had oviposition marks or exit holes. Three samples per category were chosen randomly, embedded in paraffin and slices between 6 and 8 µm cut with a microtome. Approximately 700 glass slides were stained with safranin–fast green in order to describe their characteristics. Five hundred and forty glass slides and different staining methods were used to reveal the presence of starch (Lugol test), tannins (Vanillin test), cutin and suberin (oil red O), lignin (phloroglucinol-HCl) and insoluble polysaccharides and proteins (naphthol black blue-periodic acid-Schiff reagent). A second group of samples was chosen and dried to a critical point, coated with gold and observed under a scanning electron microscope (SEM). All techniques were carried out according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C35">López <italic>et al</italic>. (2005)</xref>.The stained glass slides were observed under a light microscope and a photographic record was created for all the results. Photographs were taken under an optical microscope (Olympus Provis AX70, Tokyo, Japan), a scanning microscope (JEOL Model JSM-5310LV, Tokyo, Japan; magnification 15× to 200 000×), and a stereoscopic microscope (Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany). Additionally, during the seed dispersal period, we collected from the trees (<italic>n</italic> = 30 fruits per species) fruits with an exposed pseudoaril as well as dry fruits, in order to describe their external characteristics.Phenological characteristics of 12 species of <italic>Bursera.</italic> Group A includes <italic>B. bicolor, B. biflora, B. bipinnata, B. copallifera, B. glabrifolia, B. grandifolia, B. lancifolia</italic> and <italic>B. submoniliformis.</italic> Group B includes <italic>B. aptera</italic>, <italic>B. arida</italic>, <italic>B. fagaroides</italic> and <italic>B. schlechtendalii.</italic> Species checked at the end of the 2009–2010 fruiting season and during the season 2010–2011. The leaf, flower and fruit production periods, and the number of individuals per species (<italic>n</italic> = 324, minimum 10, maximum 40 trees) were qualitatively recorded. Species were identified with the help of the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C28">Guízar-Nolazco and Sánchez-Vélez 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C44">Rzedowski <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) and local guides.<bold>Cross-sections of the bilocular ovary of <italic>B. submoniliformis</italic> (A), and a trilocular ovary of <italic>B. aptera</italic> (B), with a fertile ovule and the placental sept that divides the locule.</bold> Scale = 200 μm. fo, fertile ovule; lo, locule; se, septum; fu, funicule ovule. Fruits were collected during the initial stage of development (<italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per three trees per species) and fixed with FAA. Fruits were dissected and grouped into three categories (fruits with ovule or embryo in development; fruits with aborted ovules, occupied by insects; and fruits with aborted ovules, unoccupied). Photographs were taken with bright-field illumination.The characteristic of dry fruits is the absence of an embryo. The remains of an aborted ovule and/or endocarp malformations were found inside these dry fruits. At least one of the valves remains strongly attached to the rest of the fruit. Immature fruits with all the ovules aborted were seen during the three stages of development. These fruits were undetectable at first sight as they show the same morphological characteristics as immature fruits with a developing embryo.<bold>Cross-sections of the ovary of <italic>Bursera</italic> during the initial stage of development.</bold> (A) Wall of the pericarp of <italic>B. biflora</italic> with the general characteristics of 12 studied species; scale = 200 μm. (B) Exocarp of <italic>B. arida</italic>; scale = 25 μm. (C) Mesocarp of <italic>B. schlechtendalii</italic>; scale = 100 μm. (D) Endocarp and mesocarp of <italic>B. submoniliformis</italic>, the oval indicates the area where the internal mesocarp divides to give way to the pseudoaril; scale = 100 μm. Abbreviations: ex, exocarp; me, mesocarp; en, endocarp; rc, resiniferous canal; vb, vascular bundles; dz, dehiscence zone; tr, trichome; cu, cuticle; ep, epidermis; sep, subepidermis; pc, parenchymatic cells; ps, pseudoaril; cc, crystalliferous cells. Fruits were collected during the initial stage of development (<italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per three trees per species), and fixed with FAA. Photographs were taken with bright-field illumination in (A), (B) and (D), and phase-contrast illumination in (C).Distribution and amount of calcium oxalate crystals in fruits with seeds (S) and parthenocarpic fruits (P), in the intermediate stage of maturation. They are represented by the presence and proportion of crystals in each structure: (+) solitary or in pairs, (++) in groups of four to six, (+++) in groups of more than seven crystals. Fruits were collected during the intermediate development stage (<italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per three trees per species) and fixed in FAA. Slices were viewed with cross-polarized light illumination and phase-contrast illumination. At least three repetitions were made for each type of fruit for each species.<bold>Cross-section of the ovary of <italic>Bursera</italic> during the intermediate stage.</bold> (A) Pericarp of <italic>B. grandifolia</italic> showing cells with secondary walls; scale = 400 μm. (B) Pericarp of <italic>B. copallifera</italic> showing the disposition of the calcium oxalate crystals (arrows) found in 12 studied species; scale = 400 μm. (C) Crystals in the dehiscence area of <italic>B. glabrifolia</italic>; scale = 100 μm. (D) Abortive ovules of <italic>B. schlechtendalii</italic>; scale = 100 μm. ex, exocarp; me, mesocarp; en, endocarp; rc, resiniferous canal; dz, dehiscence zone; cc, crystalliferous cells. Fruits were collected during the intermediate stage of development (<italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per three trees per species) and fixed with FAA. Photographs were taken with bright-field illumination in (A), cross-polarized light illumination in (B) and phase-contrast illumination in (C) and (D).<bold>(A) Group of calcium oxalate crystals (druses), accompanied by tannins on the exocarp and external mesocarp of <italic>B. arida</italic> during the dispersal stage; scale = 50 μm</bold>. (B) Sclerenchymatic cells associated with vascular bundles on the mesocarp of <italic>B. bipinnata</italic>; scale = 200 μm. (C) Cell of multilaminated wall of the lignified endocarp of <italic>B. aptera</italic>; scale = 1 μm. Abbreviations: me, mesocarp; sep, subepidermis; en, endocarp; d, druses; tc, tanniniferous cells; ps, pseudoaril; sc, sclerenchymatic cells; dz, dehiscence zone; rc, resiniferous canal; is, intracellular space; mw, multilamellar wall. Fruits were collected during the final development stage (<italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per three trees per species). In (A) and (B), the fruits were fixed with FAA and imbibed in paraffin; photographs were taken with bright-field illumination. In (C), fruits were dried to a critical point and covered in gold, SEM micrograph.<bold>(A) Fruit of <italic>B. arida</italic> with a developing embryo; scale = 100 μm.</bold> (B) Higher magnification of the box marked in (A), showing the detail of the seed's cover; scale = 10 μm. Abbreviations: em, embryo; sco, seed coat; en, endocarp. Fruits were collected during the final development stage (<italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per three trees). Fruits were dried to a critical point and covered in gold, SEM micrographs.<bold>(A) Proliferation of the endocarp filling the locule in the parthenocarpic fruit of <italic>B. arida</italic>; scale = 400 μm; safranin–fast green staining.</bold> (B) Viable fruit of <italic>B. schlechtendalii</italic> with a developing ovule and normal pericarp; scale = 1 mm. (C) Parthenocarpic fruit of <italic>B. lancifolia</italic> with a collapsed endocarp and infertile ovules; scale = 200 μm. (D) Viable fruit of <italic>B. bicolor</italic> in early development stages. (E and F) Result of the lignin test on the parthenocarpic fruit (E) and viable fruit (F) of <italic>B. arida</italic>, the positive result in (F) is characterized by the strongly black-tinted cell walls. Abbreviations: enp, proliferation of endocarp; lo, locule; fo, fertile ovule; io infertile ovule; me, mesocarp; ps, pseudoaril; en, endocarp; l-en, lignified endocarp. Fruits were collected during the initial and intermediate stages of development (<italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per three trees per species), and fixed with FAA. Fruits were dissected and grouped into three categories (fruits with ovule or embryo in development, and fruits with aborted ovule, occupied, or not, by insects). For the lignin test in (C) and (D), we used phloroglucinol-HCl previously deparaffinated with gradual ethanols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C35">López <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). Photographs were taken with bright-field illumination in (A), (C), (E) and (F); photographs of scanning microscopy (15× to 200 000×) in (B) and (D).Tannins were found in all of the species, their distribution and amount varied in relation to the species and the age of the fruit. These are produced during the latency stage of the fruit, mainly in the subepidermis, the external mesocarp and the ovule, and persist during the dispersal stage. Species in Group B had more tannins than those in Group A. This difference was also seen among the types of fruits produced, as the parthenocarpic fruits had much less tannins than those with seeds. In fact, no tannins were found in parthenocarpic fruits of <italic>B. aptera</italic>. The apparent latency of the ovule is interrupted and it is possible to see embryos in the first stages of development; this was seen mainly during the dispersal stage in fruits that were still indehiscent but whose colouration indicated they were near maturation, i.e. when the green exocarp started acquiring a reddish (in most species), purple (in <italic>B. fagaroides</italic>) or orange–yellow (in <italic>B. aptera</italic>) colouration. During the same stage, fruits in Group B had an abnormally developed endocarp and an ovule with not enough space to develop after its activity had re-initiated. These results indicate that fruits of all species develop while the ovule remains in an apparent state of latency.Average percentage of parthenocarpic fruits with/without insects recorded during the initial, intermediate and final development stages. Species were arranged by group, and the percentage of parthenocarpic fruits without insects during the initial stage. Fruits were collected and fixed in FAA (<italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per tree per species per stage). Collection took place during the 2010–2011 fructification season.<bold>Fruits of <italic>Bursera</italic> occupied by insects (arrowheads).</bold> (A) Fruit of <italic>B. aptera</italic> with two pairs of aborted ovules (arrows), indicating an abortion during the very early stages of development. (B) Fruit of <italic>B. aptera</italic> with the locule full of tissue and an adult wasp in its interior. (C) Fruit of <italic>B. bipinnata</italic> with a pupa of a beetle; the line indicates the width of the cocoon. Scale = 1 mm. Fruits were collected during the initial stage (<italic>B. bipinnata</italic>) and final stage of development (<italic>B. aptera</italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 50 fruits per three trees). Fruits were dried to a critical point and covered with gold, SEM photographs.The average number of occupied fruits was below or the same as the proportion of unoccupied fruits in the three stages (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS027TB5">5</xref>). In species of Group A (except <italic>B. glabrifolia</italic>), occupation was higher during the initial stage, while species in Group B had more insects towards the dispersion stage. In <italic>B. schlechtendalii</italic>, a wasp larva was found during the intermediate stage. This larva was in a state of decomposition in the mesocarp; the ovule and the lignified endocarp looked undamaged. This phenomenon was also seen in <italic>B. bipinnata</italic> during the dispersal stage, a fact which suggests that the lignified endocarp is one of the strongest defenses against insects.The phenology of the studied species was very similar to that of <italic>B. morelensis</italic> and other species of trees typical of dry seasonal tropical forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C9">Bullock and Solís-Magallanes 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C8">Borchert <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). The development of the fruit showed the same pattern described for <italic>B. morelensis</italic> and <italic>Canarium oleosum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C62">Wannan and Quinn 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), in which only the locule that will contain the seed develops. The results suggest that the lack of synchronicity between the development of the ovary and the development of the seed is another characteristic of the genus <italic>Bursera</italic>, as this takes place in the 12 studied species, besides <italic>B. delpechiana, B. medranoana</italic> and <italic>B. morelensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C48">Srivastava 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C13">Cortes 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>).The structure and differentiation of the pericarp of <italic>Bursera</italic> show an immense similarity to those of the genus <italic>Commiphora</italic> published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C56">Van der Walt (1975)</xref>, suggesting a morphologic sinapomorphy. Nevertheless, ontogenetic studies are necessary to demonstrate this (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C51">Thulin <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C14">Daly <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). The resiniferous canals associated with the vascular bundles in the external mesocarp are a characteristic shared by the 12 species and by <italic>Canarium oleosum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C62">Wannan and Quinn 1990</xref>). The endocarp with sclereids is also a characteristic of <italic>C. oleosum</italic>, Spondiadoideae and Anacardioideae (Anacardiaceae), supporting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C62">Wannan and Quinn (1990)</xref>, who suggested that it is a plesiomorphic characteristic in the Anacardiaceae family.From a structural point of view, the viable and parthenocarpic fruits of <italic>Bursera</italic> are similar, as is the case with <italic>Schinopsis balansae</italic> (Anacardiaceae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C27">González and Vesprini 2010</xref>). Nevertheless, the difference with our study lies in the observation that the parthenocarpic fruits keep the characteristics of the immature fruits, such as the soft tissue with a high availability of nitrogen compounds, and a limited production of secondary metabolites.According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C16">Dickie and Stuppy (2003)</xref>, besides its mechanical purpose, the seed cover, or a part of it, can develop structures that will help dispersion, such as a brightly coloured pulp (aril) that will attract dispersers. Results indicate that the protective role of the testa has been transferred to the endocarp, like in Anacardiaceae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C12">Corner 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C62">Wannan and Quinn 1990</xref>), and the attractive tissue is the pseudoaril, thus named because it is part of the fruit and not of the seed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C21">Font-Quer 1953</xref>). As a consequence, the unit of dispersion of the species studied consists of the seed, the endocarp and the pseudoaril or internal mesocarp. No external differences between the immature viable fruits and the immature perthenocarpic fruits were found. Nevertheless, the data indicate that the exposed pseudoaril is a sign of maturity of the seed, as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C1">Andrés-Hernández and Espinosa-Organista (2002)</xref>, apart from being a characteristic of the viability of the fruit, like in <italic>B. morelensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C40">Ramos-Ordoñez and Arizmendi 2011</xref>).<italic>Bursera glabrifolia</italic> provided an interesting piece of information: two-thirds of its pseudoaril, sometimes all of it, covering the pyrene, the same as in the Copallifera group in which <italic>B. submoniliformis</italic>, <italic>B. bipinnata</italic>, <italic>B. bicolor</italic> and <italic>B. copallifera</italic> are found (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C4">Becerra 2003</xref>). Molecular phylogeny assembles <italic>B. glabrifolia</italic> with <italic>B. biflora</italic>, and other species, in the Glabrifolia group, in which less than two-thirds of the pyrene is covered by the pseudoaril (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C4">Becerra 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C52">Toledo (1982)</xref> included the pseudoaril as a taxonomic character in a study of the species in the state of Guerrero, México; thus, in this context, it would be useful to do a revision of the morphological characteristics that fit the most recent results on the phylogeny of the genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C15">De-Nova <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>).Results show that parthenocarpy might be a common phenomenon in <italic>Bursera</italic> and can take place during any stage of development, as has been suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C48">Srivastava (1968)</xref>. It is also possible that parthenocarpy is a plesiomorphic character present in a common ancestor of both the Burseraceae and the Anacardiaceae families, selected for an unknown reason, and that has remained thus to this day (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C59">Verdú and García-Fayos 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). The abortion of the ovule and the absence of tissue in the locule seen in species with short ripening or maturation periods are very similar to those of <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic>, another parthenocarpic species of the Anacardiaceae family in which fruits with remains of the funicule or of aborted embryo have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C34">Jordano 1988</xref>). The abnormal development of the pericarp, common in species with longer periods of maturation or ripening, coincides with what has been described for <italic>B. morelensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). This phenomenon is well known in artificially manipulated crops such as citrus plants. Parthenocarpy could therefore be related to a hormonal imbalance, as is the case with such crops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C25">Gillaspy <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C57">Varoquaux <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>).The presence of insects in the fruits seems to be related to diminished physical and chemical defenses as well as to nutrient availability; both of these factors are also influenced by the period of time the fruits take before they mature. The tannins, lignin and calcium oxalate crystals are known to reduce the palatability of the tissues, inhibit the digestion of carbohydrates, reduce the growth rate of many insects and harden plant tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C22">Franceschi and Horner 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C43">Rosenthal and Berenbaum 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C63">Weeb 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C37">Molano-Flores 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C50">Strauss and Zangerl 2002</xref>). For many plant species, therefore, predation of fruits and/or seeds by insects is related to scarce chemical and physical defenses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C64">Zangerl <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C32">Hulme and Benkman 2002</xref>). In addition, species that retain their fruits for long periods of time have more defences than those species with short maturation periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C49">Stiles 1980</xref>). All this would explain why more insects were found during the first stages of development and in parthenocarpic fruits. It also explains the variation found in the production of secondary metabolites between the initial stage and the intermediate stage, and why the species of Group A had less tannins those in Group B.Those insects that did not trespass into the lignified endocarp have already been described in another study on <italic>B. morelensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C3">Barranco-Salazar 2011</xref>). In that study, the endocarp moved inwards, reducing the locule, which had the embryo with no indications of abortion. The space left by the movement was occupied by a larva that fed on the mesocarp. This suggests that the lignified endocarp of <italic>Bursera</italic> is the best, and maybe the last, defence against insect predation during the development of the embryo.Because of the scarce information on Neo Tropical phytofagous entomofauna (V. Hernández-Ortiz, Instituto de Ecología A.C. México, pers. commun.), as well as the small number of specimens obtained, we can only speculate on the possible interactions of the insects found. The superfamily Chalcidoidea is characterized for grouping a large number of parasitoid insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C24">Gencer 2004</xref>). Nevertheless, in this and other studies on <italic>Bursera</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C3">Barranco-Salazar 2011</xref>), no evidence has been found on wasps as parasites of another insect inside the fruit. There is the possibility that, when they do not find their primary food, the parasitoid eats other resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C20">Fletcher <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>) such as the embryo and/or pericarp of <italic>Bursera</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C3">Barranco-Salazar 2011</xref>). The availability of nitrogenated compounds in immature and parthenocarpic fruits of <italic>Bursera</italic> could mean they are a food resource for the larvae until they become adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C46">Saiz <italic>et al</italic>. 1987</xref>). This result could also explain why granivorous birds eat parthenocarpic fruits of <italic>B. morelensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C40">Ramos-Ordoñez and Arizmendi 2011</xref>), as the removal of these fruits coincides with the reproductive stage of the birds, just when the protein demand is high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C39">Ramos-Ordoñez 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C3">Barranco-Salazar 2011</xref>).The results do not enable us to determine whether seed predation by insects is reduced by the production of parthenocarpic fruits, as is the case with other plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C11">Coetzee and Giliomee 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C64">Zangerl <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C53">Traveset 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C65">Ziv and Bronstein 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C60">Verdú and García-Fayos 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C41">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). We suggest a detailed monitoring to determine the time intervals in the development, as well as enlarging the fruit sample, as our sample (50 fruits per three trees per species) is small if one considers that individual trees can produce harvests that range from a few hundred to several thousand fruits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C42">Ramos-Ordoñez <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>), and that populations can be very abundant. In species of Group A, in particular, it is necessary to carry out experiments that exclude the insects, in order to determine the real proportion of parthenocarpic fruits produced and occupied.Birds feeding on fruits were seen in both study sites, suggesting there is a plant–bird interaction. It is important to examine whether this interaction plays an important role in the reproduction of the different species, as has previously been seen in <italic>B. morelensis</italic>, as well as the effect of endozoochory in germination, and of parthenocarpy in the removal of fruits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C39">Ramos-Ordoñez 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C3">Barranco-Salazar 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C40">Ramos-Ordoñez and Arizmendi 2011</xref>). It is also important to determine whether the presence of insects in the fruits has negative effects in dispersion by frugivorous animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C33">Jordano 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C23">Garcia <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>). In spite of being adapted for dispersion by birds, many seeds fall to the ground (barochory), increasing the possibility of secondary dispersion as another important mechanism by which the seeds are taken to favourable sites for their germination. It is necessary to determine which animal species participate in this process, and what their contribution is in the establishment of the seedlings, a key process in dry tropical seasonal forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C61">Verdú and Valiente-Banuet 2008</xref>). This information will help us to understand the intricate web of processes that are needed to sustain a plant community, and will contribute to ecological restoration plans, as is the case with other species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C19">Fink <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C29">Heleno <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS027C31">Howe <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>).The anatomical description of the fruit helps one to better understand the phylogenetic relationship between the Burseraceae and the Anacardiaceae families, while the phenological characteristics of the maturation process constitute a useful tool in future studies of ecological aspects such as germination and seed dispersal. The presence of insects in fruits of eight of the 12 species seems to be related to the structural characteristics of immature and parthenocarpic fruits. Nevertheless, a more detailed analysis of this interaction is necessary. Parthenocarpy is represented in the two sections into which the genus <italic>Bursera</italic> is divided; production of seedless fruits is energy saving for the plant because, on the one hand, it takes place during the early stages of development and, on the other, the production of defence structures and compounds stops. In this context, we need further studies that will determine the ecological role of these fruits and their impact on the reproductive success of the species.Financial support was provided by the internal budget of the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Laboratorio de Desarrollo de Plantas to J. Márquez-Guzmán, Facultad de Ciencias, PAPIIT IN217511-3 project to M. C. Arizmendi, FES Iztacala, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</grant-sponsor> and <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Dirección General de Asuntos del Personal Académico (DGAPA, UNAM)</grant-sponsor> postdoctoral fellowship to M. F. Ramos-Ordoñez.All the authors contributed to a similar extent overall.None declared.We thank Dra. Silvia Espinosa and Master in Photography. Ana Isabel Bieler from the Laboratory of Microscopía Electronica de Barrido and Microcine, Facultad de Ciencias, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México for microscopy technical assistance. We thank Master in Sciences. R. Wong, M. en C. M. Pérez-Pacheco, Biologist M. Espinosa-Sanchez and Biol. S. Gómez-Sanchez for their technical assistance. We thank Biol. C. Machuca and M. López-Carrera for assistance in the field. We thank two anonymous reviewers for the revision of an earlier draft of the manuscript. We thank J. Bain for text translation.