Strong positive growth responses to salinity by <italic>Ceriops tagal</italic>, a commonly occurring mangrove of the Gujarat coast of IndiaGrowth and physiology of <italic>Salicornia bigelovii</italic> Torr. at suboptimal salinityExperimental assessment of salinity tolerance of <italic>Ceriops tagal</italic> seedlings and saplings from the Indus delta, PakistanEcophysiology of mangrovesPhotosynthetic and stomatal responses of two mangrove species, <italic>Aegiceras corniculatum</italic> and <italic>Avicennia marina</italic> to long term salinity and humidity conditionsGrowth responses to salinity in relation to distribution of two mangrove species, <italic>Sonneratia alba</italic> and <italic>S. lanceolata</italic>Rapid determination of free proline from water stress studiesGrowth and respiration in two mangrove species at a range of salinitiesGrowth and salt balance of the mangroves <italic>Avicennia marina</italic> (Forssk.) Vierh. and <italic>Rhizophora stylosa</italic> Griff. in relation to salinityUptake and role of ions in salt toleranceDisplacement of Ca<sup>2+</sup> by Na<sup>+</sup> from the plasmalemma of root cells. A primary response to salt stress?Growth and osmotic relations of the mangrove <italic>Avicennia marina</italic>, as influenced by salinityFertilization management of crops irrigated with saline waterThe mechanism of salt tolerance in halophytesSaltEffect of salinity on germination and growth of <italic>Pennisetum macrourum</italic> in southern TasmaniaCation nutrition of barley as influenced by soil solution composition in a saline soilPhysiological studies in germination of mangrovesEffect of salinity on the growth of some mangrove plants in BangladeshEffect of salinity on germination and seedlings growth of two <italic>Atriplex species</italic> (Chenopodiaceae)Salinity tolerance in some mangrove species from PakistanThe effect of salinity and temperature on the germination of polymorphic seeds and growth of <italic>Atriplex triangularis</italic> WilldThe effect of salinity on the growth, water status, and ion content of a leaf succulent perennial halophyte, <italic>Suaeda fruiticosa</italic> (L.). ForsskEffects of salinity on growth, water relations and ion accumulation of the subtropical perennial halophyte, <italic>Atriplex griffithii</italic> Moq. var. <italic>stocksii</italic> BoissSalinity effects and differential germination of several half-sib families of baldcypress from different seed sourcesThe inhibition of salinity on the germination of halophyte seedsEffect of NaCl on photosynthesis, salt accumulation and ion compartmentation in two mangrove species, <italic>Kandelia candel</italic> and <italic>Bruguiera gymnorhiza</italic>Effects of growth form, salinity, nutrient and sulfide on photosynthesis, carbon isotope discrimination and growth of red mangrove (<italic>Rhizophora mangle</italic> L.)Variation in propagule mass and its effect on carbon assimilation and seedling growth of red mangrove (<italic>Rhizophora mangle</italic> L.). in Florida, USASalinity reduces membrane-associated calcium in corn root protoplastsHigh light intensity enhances chlorosis and necrosis in leaves of zinc, potassium and magnesium deficient bean <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> plantsComparative physiology of salt and water stressEffects of salinity and nitrogen on growth and plant water relations in the mangrove <italic>Avicennia marina</italic> (Forsk.) VierhSalt tolerance in the succulent halophyte, <italic>Sarcocornia natalensis</italic>Effect of salt stress and manganese supply on growth of barley seedlingsSalt tolerance mechanisms in mangroves: a reviewEffect of soil salinity on growth, water status and nutrient accumulation in seedlings of <italic>Cassia montana</italic> (Fabaceae)Effect of salinisation of soil on growth, water status and nutrient accumulation in seedlings of <italic>Acacia auriculiformis</italic> (Fabaceae)Salinity tolerance of <italic>Aegiceras corniculatum</italic> (L.) Blanco from Gujarat coasts of IndiaSalinity tolerance of <italic>Rhizophora mucronata</italic> Lam. from Gujarat coasts of IndiaChemical composition of Australian mangroves. I. Inorganic ions and organic acidsSalt resistance in herbaceous halophytes and mangrovesThe role of organic solutes in salinity adaptations of mangroves and herbaceous halophytesHurricane and mangrove vegetation: effects of Huricane Joan, October 1988, on the vegetation of Isla del Venado- Bluefields, NicaraguaHow mangroves desalinate seawaterEffect of calcium on root development and root ion fluxes in salinised barley seedlingsAdaptation to salinity in mangroves: implication on the evolution of salt toleranceThe role of proline accumulation in halophytesTaxonomic and ecological aspects of the distribution of glycinebetaine and related compounds in plantsSalinity effects on the leaf water relations components and ion accumulation patterns in <italic>Avicennia germinans</italic> L. seedlingsGrowth, gas exchange and ion content in <italic>Olea europeaea</italic> plants during salinity stress and subsequent reliefSalt tolerance of Mexican wheat. I. Effect of NO<sub>3</sub> and NaCl on mineral nutrition, growth and grain production of four wheatsEffect of salinity on seed germination, growth and ion accumulation of <italic>Atriplex patula</italic> (Chenopodiaceae)Effects of free proline accumulation in petunias under drought stressSalinity resistance: physiologies and pricesQuantitative competition of calcium with sodium or magnesium for sorption sites on plasma membrane vesicles of melon (<italic>Cucumis melo</italic> L.) root cellsEffects of salinity on germination, seedling growth and physiology of three salt secreting mangrove speciesDynamics of element contents during the development of hypocotyls and leaves of certain mangrove speciesThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.<italic>Ceriops tagal</italic> commonly occurs along the Gujarat coast of India. It has evolved a high degree of salinity tolerance and optimal growth occurs at 12.6 ppt. This is related to an adaptive regulation of hydration and ionic content.Mangroves of Western Gujarat (India) are subject to die-back. Salinity intolerance is one possible cause, especially in young plants. We therefore quantified the extent to which young plants of one widely occurring mangrove species (<italic>Ceriops tagal</italic>) tolerate high salt in terms of establishment, growth, water status, proline content and mineral accumulation.In a greenhouse study, juvenile plants were established from mature propagules over 40 days in soil containing added NaCl, raising soil water salinity to 0.2, 2.5, 5.1, 7.7, 10.3, 12.6, 15.4, 17.9, 20.5 and 23.0 ppt (w/v). Growth and physiological characteristics were monitored over the subsequent 6 months.Despite a negative relationship between the percentage of young plant establishment and salt concentration (50 % loss at 22.3 ppt), the remaining plants proved highly tolerant. Growth, in dry weight, was significantly promoted by low salinity, which is optimal at 12.6 ppt. Water content, leaf expansion and dry matter accumulation in tissues followed a similar optimum curve with leaf area being doubled at 12.6 ppt NaCl. Salinity &gt;12.6 and &lt;23 ppt inhibited plant growth, but never to below control levels. Root:shoot dry weight ratios were slightly reduced by salinity (maximum 19 %), but the water potential of roots, leaves and stems became more negative as salinity increases while proline increases in all tissues. The concentration of Na increased, whereas concentrations of K, Ca, N and P decreased and that of Mg remained stable.<italic>Ceriops tagal</italic> has a remarkably high degree of salinity tolerance, and shows an optimal growth when soil water salinity is 12.6 ppt. Salinity tolerance is linked to an adaptive regulation of hydration and ionic content. The cause of localized die-back along the coastal region of Gujarat is thus unlikely to be a primary outcome of salinity stress although amendments with Ca and K, and perhaps proline, may help protect against extreme salinity.Mangroves are woody plants that inhabit intertidal zones with high salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C50">Shan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C37">Parida and Jha, 2010</xref>) and can tolerate a wide range of salinities under natural conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C53">Suarez <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). In nature, the growth and physiological tolerance mechanisms of mangroves vary due to a complex physical structure and differences in flooding regime, tidal inundation, rapid influx of extra nutrients and soil type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C10">Clough, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C34">Naidoo, 1987</xref>). Mangroves display a range of adaptive responses to their specific habitat, including salt exclusion by root ultrafiltration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C48">Scholander, 1968</xref>), salt secretion (elimination of substances not metabolically changed) via glands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C47">Roth, 1992</xref>), ion accumulation in leaf cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C45">Popp, 1994</xref>), leaf succulence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C47">Roth, 1992</xref>) and accumulation of organic acids as osmotica to counter toxic effects of salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C44">Popp, 1984</xref>). Like other halophytes, mangroves decrease their water and osmotic potentials to maintain leaf turgor at high salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C34">Naidoo, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C24">Khan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000<italic>a</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C25"><italic>b</italic></xref>). The level of salinity required for optimal growth varies from 10 to 50 % seawater (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C13">Downton, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C10">Clough, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C34">Naidoo, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C29">Lin and Sternberg, 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C30">1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C6">Ball and Pidsley, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C42">Patel NT <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), and a decline in growth occurs with a further increase in salinity. Lowered water potentials and an associated accumulation of inorganic ions are common patterns observed in mangrove plants in extreme saline habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C5">Ball and Farquhar, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C34">Naidoo, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C42">Patel NT <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>) and are seen as a mechanism for maintaining turgor.Mangroves are common along the coasts of Western Gujarat (India), but the stands are repeatedly decimated and fragmented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C38">Patel, 2009</xref>). Little information exists about the salt tolerance of mangroves of the coastal region of Gujarat, and this information is crucial for the success of mangrove restoration efforts in that region. <italic>Ceriops tagal</italic> is one of the most common species in the coastal region of Gujarat. Its range extends from the semi-arid (near-arid) region of Saurashtra to the saline desert of Kutch, adjacent to the border of Pakistan. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C4">Ball (1988)</xref> reported that <italic>C. tagal</italic> is a salt-tolerant mangrove with the competitive ability to grow in highly saline and poorly inundated locations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C2">Aziz and Khan (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C22">Khan and Aziz (2001)</xref> reported that <italic>C. tagal</italic> from Pakistan showed an optimal growth at 50 % seawater salinity. It is assumed that mangroves growing along the coasts of Western Gujarat have tolerance to arid conditions and high salinities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C38">Patel, 2009</xref>). Thus, the present study investigated the tolerance of <italic>C. tagal</italic> of Gujarat at increasing salinity levels, by measuring plant establishment from propagules, juvenile plant growth, and water and mineral status. Such studies have been lacking up to now for mangroves of arid regions.The study was performed in a greenhouse of the botanical garden of Saurashtra University at Rajkot (22°18′N latitude, 70°56′E longitude), Gujarat, India. For propagule establishment and growth of young plants, the top 15 cm of black-cotton soil (vertisol), which is predominant in the Saurashtra region of Gujarat, was collected from an agricultural field near Saurashtra University. This soil is a clayey loam, containing 19.6 % sand, 20.3 % silt and 60.1 % clay by weight of dry soil. The available soil water between wilting coefficient and field capacity ranged from 18.3 to 35.0 %. The total organic carbon content was 1.3 % and pH was 7.2. The salinity of the soil was 0.2 ppt (w/v of soil water). Nitrogen, phosphorus, potassium, calcium and sodium concentrations were 0.15, 0.05, 0.03, 0.05 and 0.002 % by weight of dry soil, respectively. This soil is fertile and used for intensive agriculture. Physical and chemical properties of the soil have been reported earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C36">Pandya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>).Surface soil was collected, air dried and passed through a 2-mm mesh. Twelve samples of soil, each of 100 kg, were separately spread, about 50 mm thick, over polyethylene sheets. Sodium chloride (NaCl) amounting to 0, 280, 690, 1410, 1900, 2400, 2900, 3300, 3800, 4200, 4700 and 5170 g was then allocated to each sample and thoroughly mixed to give interstitial soil water salinities of 0.2, 2.5, 5.1, 7.7, 10.3, 12.6, 15.4, 17.9, 20.5, 23.0, 25.6 and 28.2 ppt, measured by electrical conductivity in a soil suspension prepared in distilled water with a 1:2 soil:water ratio following Patel AD <italic>et al.</italic> (2010). The suspension was shaken and allowed to stand overnight. Thereafter, the electrical conductivity of the supernatant solution was determined with a conductivity meter (Systronics, Model No. 304, India). The salinity of untreated control soil was 0.2 ppt. Seawater salinity at Jamnagar coast in Saurashtra varies from 28.8 to 30.7 ppt during the rainy (monsoon) season, which favours the establishment of propagules. Thus, soil salinity in the present investigation was not imposed above 28.2 ppt.Propagules (turions) of <italic>C. tagal</italic> develop on branches of the plants. Mature propagules were collected on 14 December 2007 from the Jamnagar coast (22°27′N latitude, 70°07′E longitude) of the Saurashtra region of Western Gujarat with the help of Gujarat Forest Department. Mature propagules were yellowish green, approx. 6.5 g (fresh weight), 17–20 cm long and 0.8–1.0 cm wide. Young propagules are brighter green, and were avoided because of poor germination.Ten additional plants grown in the soil at each level of salinity were used for water potential and proline determinations 15 days before the termination of the growth experiment. Water potential of leaves, stems and roots was measured using a Dewpoint Potential Meter WP4 (Decagon Devices, Inc., USA) following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C41">Patel AD <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>. All the measurements were taken between 7.30 and 10.00 a.m. Proline concentrations were estimated following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C7">Bates <italic>et al.</italic> (1973)</xref>, using an extract of 0.5 g of fresh plant material in aqueous sulfosalicylic acid. The extracted proline was reacted with ninhydrin to form a chromophore read at 520 nm absorbance. Data were analysed by one-way ANOVA and linear regression.Mineral analyses were performed on leaves, stems and root tissues. Plant parts were pooled into one composite sample per salinity level separately. Plant samples were ground using a mortar and pestle, and three subsamples were analysed. Total nitrogen was determined by the Kjeldahl method and phosphorus content was estimated by the chlorostannous molybdophosphoric blue colour method in sulphuric acid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C43">Piper, 1944</xref>). Concentrations of Ca, Mg, Na and K were determined by Shimadzu double-beam atomic absorption spectrophotometer AA-6800 (Shimadzu Corporation, Kyoto, Japan) after tri-acid (HNO<sub>3</sub>:H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>:HClO<sub>4</sub> at a ratio of 10:1:4) digestion. Mineral data (mg g<sup>−1</sup> dry weight) were analysed by one-way ANOVA and linear regression.Under non-saline control conditions (0.2 ppt salinity), the first pair of leaves started to open 9 days after planting and 94.4 % of the propagules were established (i.e. showed signs of leaf opening) over 28 days (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F1">1</xref>). Under saline treatments, the appearance of the first pair of unfurled leaves on propagules did not occur until 1–6 days later, with higher salinities causing longer delays. Leaves continued to unfurl for up to 31 days at 5.1 and 7.7 ppt salinity, and for at least 25 days at 28.2 ppt. Total propagule establishment decreased from 94.0 % at 2.5 ppt to 27.6 % at 28.2 ppt. There was a significant reduction in the percentage of plant establishment with increasing soil salinity according to the following expression: <italic>Y</italic> = 107.270 − 2.561<italic>X</italic> (<italic>R</italic><sub>adj</sub><sup>2</sup> = 0.907, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), where <italic>Y</italic> is arcsine (degrees) of proportion of cumulative plant establishment and <italic>X</italic> is salt concentration.<bold>Cumulative establishment of propagules of <italic>C. tagal</italic> over 40 days after planting in response to increasing soil salinity.</bold> Error bars represent the SE, <italic>n</italic> = 200. Units of salinity are those measured in the soil water. The salinity of soil not receiving NaCl addition was 0.2 ppt. Percentage establishment indicates the percentage of 10 propagules (planted in each bag) that produced open leaves.The MANOVA showed a low value of Wilk's lambda (e.g. 0.08 with an associated d.f. of 90, 1237), while a high value for each of Pillai Trace (e.g. 1.47 with an associated d.f. of 90, 1701) and Hotelling–Lawley Trace (e.g. 6.24 with an associated d.f. of 90, 1613) demonstrated a statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) effect of salinity on the examined growth variables when considered simultaneously. Salinity significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) promoted the total dry weight (shoots + roots; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F2">2</xref>). Total dry weight increased up to 12.6 ppt salinity, but declined with further increases in salinity although dry weights did not fall below control values even at the highest salt concentration (23.0 ppt). The optimum dry weights were at moderate salinities (5.1–12.6 ppt). There was a quadratic relationship between the salt concentration in soil and the dry weight of the whole plant (<italic>Y</italic> = 2551.30 + 117.25<italic>X</italic> − 4.83<italic>X</italic><sup>2</sup>, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.291, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).<bold>Effect of increasing soil salinity on total dry weight of <italic>C. tagal</italic> plants after 6 months growth from propagules.</bold> A fitted quadratic polynomial curve (<italic>Y</italic> = 2243.60 + 354.02<italic>X</italic> − 30.89<italic>X</italic><sup>2</sup>, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.858, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) is shown. The data points show treatment means ± SE. <italic>n</italic> = 20. The large bar represents LSD at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Salinity significantly stimulated (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) stem and root elongation, although final lengths declined at concentrations over 12.6 ppt to levels similar to those of controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F3">3</xref>A and B). Actual stem heights were considerably greater than root lengths under all treatments. There was a quadratic relationship between shoot height (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.412, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) or root length (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.227, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and salt concentration. A positive relationship was obtained between stem height (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.176, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) or root length (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.107, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and total dry weight of plants. Leaf area was doubled by increasing salinity to 12.6 ppt (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) but was decreased by higher salinities, although never to below that of control plants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F3">3</xref>C). A quadratic relationship was obtained between leaf area and salt concentration in soil (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.537, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). There was a positive relationship between leaf area and total dry weight of plants (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.227, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).<bold>Effect of increasing soil salinity on size of <italic>C. tagal</italic> plants after 6 months growth from propagules.</bold> (A) Stem height, (B) length of longest root, (C) leaf area, (D) stem dry weight, (E) root dry weight and (F) leaf dry weight. The large bar represents LSD at <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05. Bars on symbols represent the SE, <italic>n</italic> = 20. Some error bars are smaller than the symbols.The dry weight of leaves, stems, shoots (leaves + stems) and roots was significantly promoted (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) by salinity up to 12.6 ppt, but, at higher salinity, declined to values similar to those of controls (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F3">3</xref>D–F and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F4">4</xref>A). There was a quadratic relationship between the salt concentration and dry weight (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.146, 0.229, 0.278, 0.141, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) for leaves, stems, shoots and roots, respectively. A positive relationship was obtained for dry weight of leaves (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.340, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), stems (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.921, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and roots (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.104, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) with total dry weight of plants. The root:shoot dry weight ratio was 0.06 for plants grown in control soil (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F4">4</xref>B) and did not change with increasing soil salinity.<bold>Effect of increasing soil salinity on (A) dry weight of shoot (leaf + stem) and (B) root:shoot dry weight ratios of <italic>C. tagal</italic> plants after 6 months growth from propagules.</bold> The large bar represents the LSD at <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05. Effect of salinity on root:shoot dry weight ratio was not statistically significant. Bars on symbols represent the SE, <italic>n</italic> = 20. Some error bars are smaller than the symbols.Water content (%) increased significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) in leaves, stems and roots up to 12.6 ppt salinity, but declined with further increases in salinity while always remaining above the control values (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F5">5</xref>A). A quadratic relationship was obtained between soil salinity and water content of leaves (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.219, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), stems (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.211, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and roots (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.128, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Tissues differed significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) in their water content. Moreover, the maximum water content was in leaves and the minimum in stems. Water potentials became more negative (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) as soil salinity increased (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F5">5</xref>B), but never dropped below ∼3.4 MPa. There was a negative relationship between soil salinity and the water potential of leaves (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.891, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), stems (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.869, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and roots (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.824, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Tissues differed (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) in their water potential, with leaves the most negative and roots the least.<bold>Effect of increasing soil salinity on (A) water content, (B) water potential and (C) proline content of <italic>C. tagal</italic> plants after 6 months growth from propagules.</bold> Water content was determined at final harvest. Water potential and proline concentrations were measured 15 days before harvest. Error bars represent the SE, <italic>n</italic> = 20 for water content and <italic>n</italic> = 5 for water potential and proline content.Proline concentrations (on a fresh weight basis) increased (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) in leaves, stems and root tissues linearly with soil salinity (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ011F5">5</xref>C). Stems contained slightly more proline than leaves, with roots containing about half the concentration of leaves. There was a positive relationship between salt and proline concentrations of leaves (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.871, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), stems (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.863, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) or roots (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.850, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). A significant inverse relationship was obtained between water potential (more negative values) and the proline content of leaves (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.865, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), stems (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.811, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and roots (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.748, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).The concentration of Na on a dry weight basis was greater than that of K, P, Ca and Mg in all tissues of plants under both control and saline conditions (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ011TB1">1</xref>). Sodium increased significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) in leaves, stems and roots with increased soil salinity, giving a statistically significant positive relationship (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). K in leaves, stems and roots decreased (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) with increasing salinity, giving a negative relationship between tissue K and salt in the soil (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The Na:K ratio increased (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) with salinity in all three tissues. There was a positive relationship between the Na:K ratio in tissues and salt concentration (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).Effect of soil salinity on nutrient concentration of tissues (leaf, stem and root) of <italic>C. tagal</italic> as indicated by mean ± SEM and estimated linear regression coefficientsRelationships are significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.NS, non-significant.<sup>a</sup><italic>F</italic>-values are significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.<sup>b</sup><italic>F</italic>-values are significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.Concentrations of N, P and Ca decreased significantly (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) in leaves, stems and roots in response to increasing salt concentration in soil. A negative relationship was obtained between N, P and Ca concentration in tissues and salt concentration (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The Ca:Na ratio in tissues decreased (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) with increasing salinity of soil. A negative relationship (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) was obtained between the Ca:Na ratio in tissues and salt concentration of soil. The concentration of Mg in tissues did not change with increasing salt concentration.It is well established that salinity can reduce and/or delay germination of halophyte seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C23">Khan and Ungar, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C57">Ungar, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C21">Katembe <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C27">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C42">Patel NT <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Similarly, with <italic>C. tagal</italic> propagules, salinity over the range 2.5–28.2 ppt delayed propagule establishment and reduced the final percentage of plant establishment to below the control value of 94.4 %. The establishment percentage of <italic>C. tagal</italic> was reduced to 50 % (SE<sub>50</sub>) at a salinity of 22.3 ppt, whereas a 50 % reduction in seed germination (SG<sub>50</sub>) for <italic>Cassia montana</italic>, a halophyte tree in the coastal region of Saurashtra, was already obtained at 6.0 dS m<sup>−1</sup> (3.8 ppt; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C39">Patel and Pandey, 2007</xref>). This confirms the high tolerance of the mangrove to salinity. <italic>Ceriops tagal</italic> is characterized by reduced but still considerable establishment of propagules under saline conditions. The capacity of <italic>C. tagal</italic> to invade upper estuarine habitats may thus be dependent on the tolerance shown to salt at this very early developmental stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C16">Harradine, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C26">Krauss <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). Adaptation of viviparous propagules to saline environments starts when they are still attached to the mother tree, by continuously absorbing salt from the tree or by a desalinating process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C19">Joshi <italic>et al.</italic>, 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C62">Zheng <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). The tolerance of <italic>C. tagal</italic> also extended to young plants. At all tested salinity levels (0.2–28.2 ppt), no mortality was recorded once the first leaves appeared. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C61">Ye <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> reported that for Hong Kong <italic>Avicennia marina</italic> seedlings, the establishment percentage was 100 % at salinities ranging from 0 to 35 ppt.Growth of young <italic>C. tagal</italic> plants was stimulated by low salinity and was optimal at 12.6 ppt. Similar results have also been reported for other halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C35">Naidoo and Raghunanan, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C1">Ayala and O'Leary, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C24">Khan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C39">Patel and Pandey, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C42">Patel NT <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Soil salinity at 12.6 ppt approximately equals 41 % rainy season seawater of the Jamnagar coast. Similarly, optimum growth of seedlings was obtained at 50 % seawater for <italic>A. marina</italic> from Sunderban (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C20">Karim and Karim, 1993</xref>), for <italic>A. marina, C. tagal</italic> and <italic>Rhizophora mucronata</italic> from Pakistan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C22">Khan and Aziz, 2001</xref>), and for <italic>Sonneratia alba</italic> from Australia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C6">Ball and Pidsley, 1995</xref>). Other studies have reported lower optimal ∼25 % seawater for <italic>A. marina</italic> and <italic>Rhizophora stylosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C13">Downton, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C10">Clough, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C34">Naidoo, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C8">Burchett <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>). This suggests that <italic>C. tagal</italic> growing along the semi-arid and arid coasts of Gujarat has considerable salinity tolerance. As a result, plants of <italic>C. tagal</italic> along the Gujarat coasts in India have approximately a similar salinity tolerance to those of the Karachi coast in Pakistan. Under natural conditions in Gujarat, propagules of <italic>C. tagal</italic> establish during the rainy season when the salinity level of seawater is somewhat diluted.High soil salinity affects plant growth due to low water potential, ion toxicities, nutrient deficiencies or a combination of these (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C24">Khan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000<italic>a</italic></xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C39">Patel and Pandey (2007)</xref> reported that seedlings of <italic>C. montana</italic> grow optimally at 7.9 dS m<sup>−1</sup> (5.1 ppt) salinity. Evidently, <italic>C. tagal</italic> can be grouped among such highly salt-tolerant plants. The water content of its tissues increased until 12.6 ppt and then declined with increasing salinity while never dehydrating to below control levels. A similar result was reported for <italic>Suaeda fruticosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C24">Khan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000a</xref>) and <italic>Aegiceras corniculatum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C40">Patel and Pandey, 2009</xref>). Halophytes are known to adjust their tissue water potentials to below those of the soil water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C56">Ungar, 1991</xref>). <italic>Ceriops tagal</italic> showed a progressive decrease in the water potential of leaves and stems with an increase in salinity, indicating that it adopts an osmoconforming strategy, as previously described for this species by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C22">Khan and Aziz (2001)</xref>.<italic>Ceriops tagal</italic> has the ability to exclude salts via root ultrafiltration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C17">Hagemeyer, 1997</xref>). In the present experiment, a high Na concentration was maintained in tissues with an increase in salinity. It was presumably achieved by compartmentalizing Na<sup>+</sup> into vacuoles, as has been found in mangroves and other halophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C15">Flowers <italic>et al.</italic>, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C28">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). High internal salt concentrations benefit mangrove plants by lowering the internal water potential, thereby driving water uptake from soil with high salinity and low soil water potential. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C59">Yeo (1983)</xref> has suggested that Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> accumulated in leaf tissue provide osmotic adjustment and turgor to maintain growth. This would explain the remarkable ability of <italic>C. tagal</italic> to expand its leaves more vigorously and improve its tissue hydration at modest salinity levels, and avoid dehydrating to below control levels when higher salinities were imposed.In the present study, the decrease of K<sup>+</sup> concentration with increasing soil salinity suggests that Na<sup>+</sup> inhibited the K<sup>+</sup> uptake. The Na:K ratio increased in leaves and stems with an increase in salinity, indicating an increase in transportation of Na<sup>+</sup> from root to shoot. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C54">Tattini <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref> reported that the Na:K ratio increases in salt-tolerant species with increasing salinity in the external medium, because mass transport of sodium takes place from root to shoot via the transpiration stream.Because of its zwitterionic, high-hydrophilic non-toxic character, proline can act as a ‘compatible solute’ and its accumulation is a common response to salinity and related stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C51">Stewart and Lee, 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C52">Storey <italic>et al.</italic>, 1977</xref>), allowing it to function at high concentrations to effect osmotic adjustment, stabilization of macromolecules and regulate cellular redox status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C52">Storey <italic>et al.</italic>, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C58">Yamada <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). The increase of proline concentrations in <italic>C. tagal</italic> with increasing Na concentration indicates that higher proline accumulation may help alleviate NaCl stress in <italic>C. tagal</italic>, although the increase may be too small to influence osmotic balance significantly. Proline accumulation was greater in shoots than in roots. This confirms the observation of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C33">Munns (2002)</xref> that organic solutes are often lower in roots than shoots. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C46">Popp and Albert (1995)</xref> reported that <italic>C. tagal</italic> accumulates cyclitols along with Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>−</sup> to maintain osmotic balance.In general, salinity reduces N accumulation in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C14">Feigin, 1985</xref>), and we observed a steady reduction in above- and below-ground tissues as salt application increases, with the greatest reduction (28 %) being in leaves. The effect may be ascribed to chloride toxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C55">Torres and Bingham, 1973</xref>). Similarly, decreases in P concentration were also seen, but both the decline in N and P occurred at low and medium salinities where growth was stimulated, indicating a strong regulation that avoided debilitatingly large declines at modest levels of salinity.Salinity also decreased Ca<sup>2+</sup>, suggesting that Na<sup>+</sup> reduced internal concentrations in roots and shoots that might have slowed the growth as optimal levels of salt were exceeded. Uptake of Ca<sup>2+</sup> may decrease because of ion interactions, precipitation and increase in ionic strength (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C18">Janzen and Chang, 1987</xref>). It is evidenced that in salt-stressed roots of cotton, Na<sup>+</sup> displaced membrane-associated Ca, which was believed to be primarily at the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C12">Cramer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1985</xref>). In addition, NaCl salinity displaced membrane-associated Ca on protoplasts of corn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C31">Lynch <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>) and plasma membrane vesicles of melon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C60">Yermiyahu <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>). One consequence of the displacement of membrane-associated Ca<sup>2+</sup> by Na<sup>+</sup> is the immediate increase in K<sup>+</sup> efflux across the plasma membrane of salt-stressed cotton roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C12">Cramer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1985</xref>). This effect may be related to the rapid depolarization of the membrane potential upon salinization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C11">Cramer, 1997</xref>). In the present study, the increased efflux of K<sup>+</sup> might be one of the reasons for the significant decrease in K concentration in tissues of <italic>C. tagal</italic> in response to NaCl salinity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C49">Shabala <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref> reported that in addition to significant Na<sup>+</sup> uptake into the root epidermis of barley, the onset of salt stress caused rapid and prolonged efflux of H<sup>+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup> and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>. But not all key nutrient ions were depressed by salinity. Magnesium concentrations stood out as being very stable and this may be a key feature supporting faster growth at low and moderate salinities, and protecting <italic>C. tagal</italic> from Mg<sup>2+</sup> decreasing to below control levels at high salinities. As is well known, Mg<sup>2+</sup> has central roles in chlorophyll structure, as an enzyme cofactor and in exporting photosynthate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ011C32">Marschner and Cakmak, 1989</xref>). The mechanism behind this magnesium homeostasis is unknown.High percentages of propagules established successfully under salinity stress, 50 % establishment being achieved at 22.3 ppt NaCl. Subsequent stem and root elongation, and especially leaf expansion, were increased substantially at low and moderate salinities (≤12.6 ppt) while greater salinity failed to slow growth to below control values. Dry matter accumulation in tissues of plants behaved similarly. These findings demonstrate that <italic>C. tagal</italic> is a highly salt-tolerant mangrove at this key early stage in its life cycle. The tolerance is linked to a proportionate regulation of tissue water potentials, which were seen to decrease with an increase in salinity, thereby helping to maintain normal tissue hydration (the osmoconforming strategy). An increased accumulation of proline may also have contributed to this stabilization. A significant increase in Na and a decrease in K, N, P and Ca in tissues may inhibit the growth of the plants in the more extreme saline habitats.Future work could usefully examine the ability of exogenous proline, and Ca and K to ameliorate the injurious effects of high concentrations of NaCl, although the high tolerance to low and moderate salinities that we demonstrated here strongly suggests that mangrove die-back on the Gujarat coast may have other causes which now merit further investigation.This study was supported with Departmental Special Assistance using funds provided by the Government of India University Grants Commission, New Delhi.N.T.P. and A.N.P. contributed to a similar extent to the experimental work and to writing the paper. A.G. performed the statistical analyses.None declared.