Mutualism-disrupting allelopathic invader drives carbon stress and vital rate decline in a forest perennial herbComparative water relations and photosynthesis of mycorrhizal and non-mycorrhizal <italic>Bouteloua gracilis</italic> H.B.K. Lag ex steudThe roles of hydraulic and carbon stress in a widespread climate-induced forest die-offMeasurement of bacterial and fungal contributions to respiration of selected agricultural and forest soilsAspects of the ecology of an invasive plant, garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>), in central IllinoisEffect of removal of garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>, Brassicaeae) on arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi inoculum potential in forest soilsUninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information CriterionInvasive species accelerate decomposition and litter nitrogen loss in a mixed deciduous forestArbuscular mycorrhizal symbiosis alters stomatal conductance of host plants more under drought than under amply watered conditions: a meta-analysisArbuscular mycorrhizal fungi protect a native plant from allelopathic effects of an invaderRole of mycorrhizal fungus origin in growth and nutrient uptake by <italic>Geranium robertianum</italic>Invasion by two plant species affects fungal root colonizersReduced competitive ability in an invasive plantMycorrhizal associations and other means of nutrition of vascular plants: understanding the global diversity of host plants by resolving conflicting information and developing reliable means of diagnosisThe mycorrhizal status, root anatomy, and phenology of plants in a sugar maple forestThe roots and mycorrhizas of herbaceous woodland plants. I. Quantitative aspects of morphologyA new method for observing the morphology of vesicular-arbuscular mycorrhizaeEffects of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (garlic mustard; Brassicaceae) on mycorrhizal colonization and community structure in three herbaceous plants in a mixed deciduous forestRelationship between soil enzyme activities, nutrient cycling and soil fungal communities in a northern hardwood forestGlobal biodiversity: indicators of recent declinesNovel weapons: invasive success and the evolution of increased competitive abilityNovel weapons: invasive plant suppresses fungal mutualists in America but not in its native EuropeLow allelochemical concentrations detected in garlic mustard-invaded forest soils inhibit fungal growth and AMF spore germinationEffects of herbicide on the invasive biennial <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Garlic Mustard) and initial responses of native plants in a southwestern Ohio forestCyanide in the chemical arsenal of garlic mustard, <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>Comparing allelopathic effects of root and leaf extracts of invasive <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>, <italic>Lonicera maackii</italic>, and <italic>Ranunculus ficaria</italic> on germination of three native woodland plantsSeparating above- and belowground effects of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> and <italic>Lonicera maackii</italic> on the performance of <italic>Impatiens capensis</italic>How do plants know when other plants are flowering? Resource depletion, pollen limitation and mast-seeding in a perennial wildflowerDemographic models inform selection of biocontrol agents for garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>)Arbuscular mycorrhizal development in three crucifersEffects of exotic plant invasions on soil nutrient cycling processesChanges in soil functions following invasions of exotic understory plants in deciduous forestsAssessing the relative importance of disturbance, herbivory, diversity, and propagule pressure in exotic plant invasionAcceleration of exotic plant invasion in a forested ecosystem by a generalist herbivoreA note on graphical presentation of estimated odds ratios from several clinical trialsDegradation kinetics of glucosinolates in soilIt is risky out there: the costs of emergence and the benefits of prolonged dormancyDisappearing plants: why they hide and how they returnDirect and indirect effects of allelopathy in the soil legacy of an exotic plant invasionAnalysis of repeated measures experimentsEstimating evolutionary parameters when viability selection is operatingPerspectives on allelopathic disruption of plant mutualisms: a framework for individual- and population-level fitness consequencesTesting the mutualism disruption hypothesis: physiological mechanisms for invasion of intact perennial plant communitiesBias and error in understanding plant invasion impactsDark septate endophytes: a review of facultative biotrophic root-colonizing fungiIn a long-term experimental demography study, excluding ungulates reversed invader's explosive population growth rate and restored nativesDemographic estimation methods for plants with unobservable life-statesMutualisms in a changing world: an evolutionary perspectiveThe importance of nitrogen and carbohydrate storage for plant growth of the alpine herb <italic>Veratrum album</italic>Feedback with soil biota contributes to plant rarity and invasiveness in communitiesDeer facilitate invasive plant success in a Pennsylvania forest understoryThe effects of arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungal and garlic mustard introductions on native AM fungal diversityMycorrhizal fungi and reproduction of field populations of <italic>Abutilon theophrasti</italic> Medic. (Malvaceae)Two co-occurring invasive woody shrubs alter soil properties and promote subdominant invasive species<italic>marked</italic>: an <italic>R</italic> package for maximum likelihood and Markov Chain Monte Carlo analysis of capture–recapture dataMorphology, growth, and vasculature of the sympodial rhizome of <italic>Smilacina racemosa</italic> (Liliaceae)Resistance and recovery of soil microbial communities in the face of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> invasionsInterpopulation variation in allelopathic traits informs restoration of invaded landscapesCoevolution between invasive and native plants driven by chemical competition and soil biotaEvolutionary limits ameliorate the negative impact of an invasive plantLong-term legacies and partial recovery of mycorrhizal communities after invasive plant removalFruit development in <italic>Trillium:</italic> dependence on stem carbohydrate reservesHost plant recognition in monophagous weevils: specialization of <italic>Ceutorhynchus inaffectatus</italic> to glucosinolates from its host plant <italic>Hesperis matronalis</italic>Competitive interactions of garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>) and damesrocket (<italic>Hesperis matronalis</italic>)Mechanisms underlying the impacts of exotic plant invasionsThe effects of mycorrhizal infection on components of plant growth and reproductionResponse of a forest understory community to experimental removal of an invasive nonindigenous plant (<italic>Alliaria petiolta</italic>, Brassicaceae)Mechanisms linking drought, hydraulics, carbon metabolism, and vegetation mortalityMechanisms of plant survival and mortality during drought: why do some plants survive while others succumb to drought?Competitive ability of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Garlic Mustard, Brassicaceae), an invasive, nonindigenous forest herbDisrupting mycorrhizal mutualisms: a potential mechanism by which exotic tamarisk outcompetes native cottonwoodsLongevity can buffer plant and animal populations against changing climatic variabilityMissing inaction: the dangers of ignoring missing dataA meta-analysis of plant responses to dark septate root endophytesCarbohydrate storage in five resprouting Florida scrub plants across a fire chronosequenceRelative allelopathic potential of invasive plant species in a young disturbed woodlandThe impact of the invasive shrub <italic>Lonicera maackii</italic> on the decomposition dynamics of a native plant communityApproximating variance of demographic parameters using the delta method: a reference for avian biologistsAllelopathic inhabitation of germination by <italic>Alliaria petiolate</italic> (Brassicaceae)Odds ratio: an ecologically sound tool to compare proportionsEffect of garlic mustard [<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Beib. Cavara &amp; Grande)] extracts on plants and arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungiReady or not, garlic mustard is moving in: <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> as a member of Eastern North American forestsThe invasive species <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (garlic mustard) increases soil nutrient availability in northern hardwood-conifer forestsInteractions between exotic invasive plants and soil microbes in the rhizosphere suggest that ‘everything is not everywhereInvasion of an annual exotic plant into deciduous forests suppresses arbuscular mycorrhiza symbiosis and reduces performance of sycamore maple saplingsNon-additive effects of invasive tree litter shift seasonal N release: a potential invasion feedbackHigh specificity in plant leaf metabolic responses to arbuscular mycorrhizaPlant-soil feedbacks between invasive shrubs and native forest understory species lead to shifts in the abundance of mycorrhizal fungiThe evolutionary ecology of vegetative dormancy in mature herbaceous perennial plantsPositive plant-soil feedback may drive dominance of a woodland invader, <italic>Euonymus fortunei</italic>Light, allelopathy, and post-mortem invasive impact on native forest understory speciesInvasive plant suppresses the growth of native tree seedlings by disrupting belowground mutualismsStudy of the role of antimicrobial glucosinolate-derived isothiocyanates in resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to microbial pathogensThe philosophy of multiple comparisonsGlobal change and species interactions in terrestrial ecosystemsThe unseen majority: soil microbes as drivers of plant diversity and productivity in terrestrial ecosystemsSimulated nitrogen deposition affects community structure of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi in northern hardwood forestsAllelochemicals isolated from tissues of the invasive weed garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>)Biological invasion by <italic>Myrica Faya</italic> in Hawai'i: plant demography, nitrogen fixation, ecosystem effectsMycorrhizal densities decline in association with nonnative plants and contribute to plant invasionDistinguishing allelopathy from resource competition: the role of densityBiochemical and physiological mechanisms mediated by allelochemicalsEcology of woodland herbs in temperate deciduous forestsCompetitive and allelopathic effects of garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>) on American ginseng (<italic>Panax quinquefolius</italic>)Breaking new ground: soil communities and exotic plant invasionThe invasive plant <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (garlic mustard) inhibits ectomycorrhizal fungi in its introduced rangeMycorrhizal sink strength influences whole plant carbon balance of <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> LCarbohydrate storage and use in an alpine population of the perennial herb, <italic>Oxytropis sericea</italic>Effects of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus on photosynthesis and water status of maize under high temperature stressInulin determination for food labeling<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> InderjitThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Most plants form mutually beneficial relationships with microorganisms in their roots, especially fungi. Invasive plants can release substances toxic to other species known as allelochemicals. Allelochemicals from the invasive species garlic mustard can inhibit beneficial soil fungi, thereby disrupting the plant-fungal mutualism. We demonstrate that treatment with garlic mustard leaves reduces the ability of a native plant, False Solomon's seal, to store carbohydrates. Additionally, we demonstrate that weeding garlic mustard from forest plots allows this native to grow larger, flower more frequently, and enter long-term dormancy less often relative to plots where garlic mustard occurs.Invasive plants can negatively affect belowground processes and alter soil microbial communities. For native plants that depend on soil resources from root fungal symbionts (RFS), invasion could compromise their resource status and subsequent ability to manufacture and store carbohydrates. Herbaceous perennials that depend on RFS-derived resources dominate eastern North American forest understories. Therefore, we predict that forest invasion by <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>, an allelopathic species that produces chemicals that are toxic to RFS, will diminish plant carbon storage and fitness. Over a single growing season, the loss of RFS could reduce a plant's photosynthetic physiology and carbon storage. If maintained over multiple growing seasons, this could create a condition of carbon stress and declines in plant vital rates. Here we characterize the signals of carbon stress over a short timeframe and explore the long-term consequence of <italic>Alliaria</italic> invasion using <italic>Maianthemum racemosum</italic>, an RFS-dependent forest understory perennial. First, in a greenhouse experiment, we treated the soil of potted <italic>Maianthemum</italic> with fresh leaf tissue from either <italic>Alliaria</italic> or <italic>Hesperis matronalis</italic> (control) for a single growing season. <italic>Alliaria</italic>-treated plants exhibit significant overall reductions in total non-structural carbohydrates and have 17 % less storage carbohydrates relative to controls. Second, we monitored <italic>Maianthemum</italic> vital rates in paired experimental plots where we either removed emerging <italic>Alliaria</italic> seedlings each spring or left <italic>Alliaria</italic> at ambient levels for 7 years. Where <italic>Alliaria</italic> is removed, <italic>Maianthemum</italic> size and vital rates improve significantly: flowering probability increases, while the probability of plants regressing to non-flowering stages or entering prolonged dormancy are reduced. Together, our results are consistent with the hypothesis that disruption of a ubiquitous mutualism following species invasion creates symptoms of carbon stress for species dependent on RFS. Disruption of plant–fungal mutualisms may generally contribute to the common, large-scale declines in forest biodiversity observed in the wake of allelopathic invaders.The majority of flowering plant species form mutualisms with root fungal symbionts (RFS) such as arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF; 74 % of angiosperms; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C21">Brundrett 2009</xref>) and dark septate endophytes (DSE; ≥600 species; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C54">Jumpponen and Trappe 1998</xref>). Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi and DSE live inside plant roots and deploy hyphae outside the root that increase water, nitrogen, phosphorus and other soil nutrients' availability to their plant partner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C110">Smith and Read 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C90">Newsham 2011</xref>). The RFS receive a substantial fraction of the plant partner's fixed carbon (for AMF up to 20 %; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C110">Smith and Read 2008</xref>).Recent work highlights how anthropogenic changes in the environment, such as invasion, can negatively affect mutualisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C114">Tylianakis <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C57">Kiers <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Invasive species can impact belowground processes and directly or indirectly alter soil microbial communities, including RFS. Mechanisms through which belowground impacts can occur (summarized in part by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C127">Wolfe and Klironomos 2005</xref>) include alterations in the quality, quantity and timing of litter inputs and subsequent changes in soil nutrient status (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C38">Ehrenfeld 2003</xref>), direct changes to soil nutrient status through novel nutrient fixation strategies by the invader (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C119">Vitousek and Walker 1989</xref>), mutualist degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C120">Vogelsang and Bever 2009</xref>) and allelopathy (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C29">Callaway <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C48">Grove <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Specifically, allelochemicals can act as novel weapons that are directly toxic to plants or act indirectly on their associated microbes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C28">Callaway and Ridenour 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C122">Weir <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>).The invasion of North American forests by <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Brassicaceae, garlic mustard) is an emerging model system for investigations of allelopathic effects on belowground processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C99">Rodgers <italic>et al.</italic> 2008<italic>a</italic></xref>). This species produces a suite of allelochemicals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C118">Vaughn and Berhow 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C32">Cipollini and Gruner 2007</xref>) that are toxic to RFS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C98">Roberts and Anderson 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C111">Stinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C61">Koch <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) even at low concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C29">Callaway <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C30">Cantor <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Field studies document that areas infested with <italic>Alliaria</italic> exhibit shifts in soil fungal community composition with frequent reductions in AMF species richness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C26">Burke <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C67">Lankau 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C72">Lankau <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), declines in total soil hyphal abundances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C30">Cantor <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C61">Koch <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and changes in the within-root community of AMF-dependent plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C25">Burke 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C17">Bongard <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Together, these studies suggest that within <italic>Alliaria-</italic>invaded ecosystems the function of the mutualistic fungal community can be compromised and that these changes contribute to <italic>Alliaria</italic>'s invasive success.Herbaceous perennials dominate the temperate forest understories that <italic>Alliaria</italic> invades and these species as a group are typically highly- to obligately-dependent on RFS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C22">Brundrett and Kendrick 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C124">Whigham 2004</xref>). The fact that temperate forest soils are strongly resource limited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C124">Whigham 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C44">Gilliam 2014</xref>) likely drives the obligate nature of the relationship for many understory herbaceous perennials. Typically these species are slow growing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C44">Gilliam 2014</xref>), exhibit high rates of RFS colonization (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C22">Brundrett and Kendrick 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C16">Boerner 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C25">Burke 2008</xref>) and have long-lived arbuscules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C23">Brundrett and Kendrick 1990</xref>). Many also lack fine roots or root hairs (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C66">LaFrankie 1985</xref>) perhaps because their associated RFS hyphae fulfil this soil resource-gathering role. Since resources supplied by RFS are intimately tied to many plant metabolic functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C105">Schweiger <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), disruption of soil mutualisms is expected to severely limit the physiological rates of forest species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). In the absence of RFS, plants generally exhibit reduced photosynthetic rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C2">Allen <italic>et al.</italic> 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C128">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C130">Zhu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) and subsequent carbon stress can curb their ability to carry out carbon-demanding functions such as growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C78">Lu and Koide 1994</xref>) and flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C63">Koide <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>).Carbon stress is the reduction of a plant's pool of total non-structural carbohydrates (NSCs) (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C3">Anderegg <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). In herbaceous perennials, chronic carbon stress can alter key vital rates including survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C46">Gremer and Sala 2013</xref>), flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C35">Crone <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and prolonged dormancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C47">Gremer <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Invaders like <italic>Alliaria</italic> that alter the soil environment and essential RFS functions could induce carbon stress or ‘carbon starvation’ (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C82">McDowell <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), ultimately diminishing the stability of populations of RFS-dependent native species.Our prior experiments on the RFS-dependent understory perennial, <italic>Maianthemum racemosum</italic> (Ruscaceae, false Solomon's seal) confirm the dramatic physiological consequences of short-term RFS disruption by <italic>Alliaria</italic>'s allelochemicals. Key physiological traits including stomatal conductance, which is known to be highly dependent on RFS colonization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C10">Augé <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>), and photosynthetic rate both significantly declined in plants exposed to fresh <italic>Alliaria</italic> leaf litter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Soil respiration, to which fungi are the primary contributors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C5">Anderson and Domsch 1975</xref>), was also reduced with <italic>Alliaria</italic> treatment. Importantly, in field plots invaded by <italic>Alliaria</italic> and in pot experiments with an <italic>Alliaria</italic> litter treatment, we demonstrated significant declines in the abundance of soil fungal hyphae relative to controls (37 % decline, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C30">Cantor <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; 29–38 % decline, A. N. Hale <italic>et al.</italic>, submitted for publication). Together these data strongly support the idea that the observed physiological declines are driven by the inhibition of the RFS hyphal network in the soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).Here we explore how the physiological stress of RFS-mutualism disruption in <italic>Alliaria</italic>-invaded forests could result in performance declines in an RFS-dependent forest perennial across two time scales. First, we ask: Given that <italic>Alliaria</italic>'s allelochemicals cause detectable shifts in the soil fungal community and alternative plant physiological rates, do they also cause declines in carbon storage in plants within a single growing season? In a greenhouse experiment we show that <italic>Alliaria-</italic>treated <italic>Maianthemum</italic> store significantly less carbon in their rhizome over one growing season relative to controls. Second, to determine the potential for short-term effects to scale up over time and affect population processes, we conducted a 7-year field experiment in an <italic>Alliaria</italic>-invaded forest in which <italic>Alliaria</italic> was weeded or left at ambient levels. We test whether <italic>Maianthemum</italic> exhibit lower growth rates consistent with carbon stress in the <italic>Alliaria</italic>-ambient plots. We also ask if <italic>Alliaria</italic> reduces size-based vital rates of <italic>Maianthemum</italic> and if so, how quickly these changes occur. We show that where <italic>Alliaria</italic> is present, <italic>Maianthemum</italic> have suppressed growth and vital rates relative to adjacent plot where <italic>Alliaria</italic> is removed.The greenhouse study was conducted during the summer of 2010 in the greenhouse facilities at the University of Pittsburgh. In May, we obtained bare-root adult <italic>Maianthemum</italic> plants (<italic>N</italic> = 42) from a native plant nursery (Prairie Moon Nursery, Winona, MN, USA). Rhizomes ranged in size from 6.7 to 39.7 g fresh weight. We potted each rhizome in a 3 : 1 mixture of autoclaved Fafard potting soil and Turface. We inoculated plants with RFS by adding 150 g of field soil collected from areas adjacent to <italic>Maianthemum</italic> plants at our experimental field site (see details below). Pots were then placed in the greenhouse and watered every 2–3 days for 1 month, allowing the plants to complete stem elongation and establish the RFS mutualism.In June, we assigned each plant to either an <italic>Alliaria</italic> treatment or a control treatment. To control for potential differences in initial carbohydrate status due to differences in plant age and/or size (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C92">Olano <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), we stratified the randomized assignment of rhizomes into the treatments to ensure that mean rhizome mass was the same in the <italic>Alliaria</italic> and control treatments. Plants in the <italic>Alliaria</italic> treatment were then exposed to <italic>Alliaria</italic> allelochemicals by placing 25 g of fresh <italic>Alliaria</italic> leaf tissue collected from a population with a recent history of invasion (&lt;20 years) on top of the soil. When these plants were watered, the glucosinolates leached out of the <italic>Alliaria</italic> leaves and into the soil (A. N. Hale <italic>et al.</italic>, submitted for publication). As in previous experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), plants in the control treatment received 25 g of fresh <italic>Hesperis matronalis</italic> (dame's rocket; Brassicaceae) leaf tissue. Like <italic>Alliaria</italic>, <italic>Hesperis</italic> is an invasive mustard in eastern North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C76">Leicht-Young <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). While <italic>Hesperis</italic> produces some glucosinolates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C75">Larsen <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>), RFS hyphae and vesicles have been observed within its root system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C37">DeMars and Boerner 1995</xref>), indicating that <italic>Hesperis</italic> chemicals are less toxic to RFS than <italic>Alliaria</italic>. In the field, the high mortality rates of <italic>Alliaria</italic> seedlings and rosettes throughout the year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C36">Davis <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>) and the mortality of adults in the summer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C6">Anderson <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>) likely result in a sustained supply of allelochemicals into the soil. Thus, we re-applied fresh leaf tissue in both treatments every 2 weeks until the end of August to simulate a season-long supply of <italic>Alliaria</italic> allelochemicals.We destructively harvested plants three times during the growing season (9 July, 6 August and at senescence) to assess the effect of the treatments on the carbohydrate status. For the last time point, we classified plants as being senesced when 40 % of the leaf tissue had yellowed and photosynthetic rates were &lt;1.0 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>. Details of the leaf gas exchange protocol for <italic>Maianthemum</italic> can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>. To harvest the plants, we carefully clipped the shoot and roots away from the rhizome. We also stained the roots of a subset of plants per treatment following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C24">Brundrett <italic>et al</italic>. (1984)</xref> to confirm RFS colonization. We then weighed the rhizome and immediately flash-froze it in liquid nitrogen. We stored samples at −80 °C until they could be lyophilized and ground. We followed the protocol of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C131">Zuleta and Sambucetti (2001)</xref> to analyse rhizome inulin (storage carbohydrate) and sucrose (mobile carbohydrate) content via high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). [Note: Starch is not present in the rhizome of <italic>Maianthemum</italic> (A. N. Hale <italic>et al.</italic>, submitted for publication).] In brief, a 0.03 g dried sample for each plant is boiled while stirring with a magnetic stir bar. Once samples cool to room temperature, they are filtered through a 0.20 μm filter, and run on HPLC (Aminex HPX-87C anion-exchange column, deionized water at 85 °C was set as the mobile phase with a flux rate of 0.6 mL min<sup>−1</sup>). Standards are used (inulin from dahlia tubers, Sigma-Aldrich; sucrose, Sigma-Aldrich) to confirm the identity of the sample peaks and to create standard curves to determine inulin and sucrose concentrations. Here, we express inulin and sucrose concentrations as a percentage of the HPLC dry sample mass. We also sum each plant's inulin and sucrose content to determine total NSC concentration (%).To explore the effect of our treatments on rhizome carbohydrate status, we use a multivariate analysis of covariance (MANCOVA). Following a significant MANCOVA, individual ANCOVA tests are conducted for inulin, sucrose and total NSC. For all models, we include harvest date as a main effect because rhizome carbohydrate concentration varies over the growing season in perennial herbs (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C73">Lapointe 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C129">Wyka 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C58">Kleijn <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). We also include initial plant mass as a covariate to account for differences in carbohydrate storage that are related to plant size/age (MANCOVA model: total NSC + inulin + sucrose = treatment + harvest date + initial plant mass; ANCOVA models: carbohydrate = treatment + harvest date + initial plant mass). We calculate least squares means and standard errors for all ANCOVA models with a significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) treatment effect. All analyses were conducted in SAS (v. 9.3, SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA).Our experimental plots are located in a beech-maple forest in southwest Pennsylvania [Trillium Trail Nature Reserve (hereafter TT), Allegheny County, PA, USA: 40°52′01.40″N; 79°90′10.75″W] with a rich herbaceous perennial understory flora (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C60">Knight <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Based on previous work at TT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C25">Burke 2008</xref>) and other temperate deciduous forests (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C22">Brundrett and Kendrick 1988</xref>), we estimate that 73 % of TT herbaceous perennials are AMF-dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). We detected <italic>Alliaria</italic> allelochemicals in the soil of TT in concentrations that are toxic to AMF spores in lab assays (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C30">Cantor <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Additionally, we showed that in soils where <italic>Alliaria</italic> occurs at TT, the density of fungal hyphae is lower (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C30">Cantor <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and the fungal community composition shifts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C26">Burke <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) relative to paired, non-invaded areas. <italic>Maianthemum</italic> plants collected at TT are heavily colonized by RFS, but their intra-root AMF community is significantly altered where <italic>Alliaria</italic> is present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C25">Burke 2008</xref>). These results motivate further investigation of mutualism disruption by <italic>Alliaria</italic> in understanding mechanisms driving native plant performance declines.We collected data on naturally occurring individuals of <italic>M. racemosum</italic> within six 14 × 14 m plots in TT from 2003 through 2013. Our six plots are split in half longitudinally so that each contains two experimental treatments: <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal (= low or no allelochemicals) or <italic>Alliaria</italic> present at ambient levels (= allelochemicals present). Annual removal of <italic>Alliaria</italic> from half of each plot (i.e. a 14 × 7 m area) began in spring 2006, ∼15 years after <italic>Alliaria</italic> became established at this site (L. Smith, pers. comm.) This time frame for TT invasion coincides with the estimated <italic>Alliaria</italic> invasion history in the region that indicates that this invader has been present locally for &lt;25 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C71">Lankau <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). We remove <italic>Alliaria</italic> concurrent with the onset of emergence of the perennial herb community. <italic>Alliaria</italic> individuals are removed as tiny seedlings, minimizing disturbance to the soil and other plants. Removed plants are discarded off site. In June of each year prior to <italic>Alliaria</italic> seed dispersal we erect a barrier at the border of the two treatments to block seed dispersal from the ambient into the <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal treatment. All <italic>Maianthemum</italic> plants emerging in the plots are permanently tagged and have annually been scored for individual size, stage (i.e. seedling, non-flowering, flowering and dormant) and deer browse status. Prior to initiation of the <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal treatment in 2006 there was no difference in <italic>Alliaria</italic> per cent cover between the plots (<italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.11, <italic>P</italic> = 0.74) or total per cent cover of all species (<italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.038, <italic>P</italic> = 0.85).We assess the effect of <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal on <italic>Maianthemum</italic> growth and three vital rates: annual flowering frequency, retrogression of flowering plants to non-flowering the following year and the frequency of prolonged vegetative dormancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C107">Shefferson 2009</xref>). We test for differences using data collected prior to the implementation of the removal treatment (2003–06) and after the removal treatment began (2007–13). All models have the general form: response variable = treatment + year + treatment × year. To estimate differences in growth rate, we investigate the differences in average size between treatments for the initial cohort of plants first observed when the experiment began in 2003. The mean size of this cohort is estimated with a linear mixed model for each year since 2006 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C132">Zuur <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). We model log(plant size) to improve normality of the residuals.Our sample for retrogression was therefore set by the number of plants that flowered the previous year (time <italic>t</italic> − 1) that emerged as either flowering or non-flowering the next year (time <italic>t</italic>).Growth and vital rate analyses are conducted in R 3.1.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C96">R Development Core Team 2014</xref>) using the <italic>lme4</italic> package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C14">Bates <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). To account for repeated measures and blocking effects, we include random intercepts for individual plants and pairs of treatments within a plot. For each response variable we test for significant differences between annual means using the <italic>multcomp</italic> package in R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C19">Bretz <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). We test for the presence of a long-term trend since 2006 in each treatment mean by specifying a trend contrast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C101">Rosenthal and Rosnow 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C49">Gurevitch and Chester 1986</xref>). All tests are planned contrasts so we do not correct for multiple comparisons. To further investigate trends in flowering frequencies, we also analyse these data using a two-level hierarchical model with time as a continuously varying main effect and year as a random effect.Results of flowering and retrogression analyses are reported as effect sizes using odds ratios (OR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C97">Rita and Komonen 2008</xref>). Odds ratios have a lower bound of zero and no upper bound. Odds ratios of 1 indicate no difference between two treatments in the odds of an event happening. Statistical tests for OR therefore test whether they are different from 1. Odds ratios and their 95 % confidence intervals (CIs) are given in the text on their normal scale but graphed on a log scale to improve interpretation (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C42">Galbraith 1988</xref>).We use mark-recapture models, a modified logistic regression approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C56">Kéry <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>), to estimate the probability of prolonged vegetative dormancy. To test for pre-existing differences in dormancy rates, we conduct separate mark-recapture analyses of the 3 years prior to implementation of the removal treatment (2003–05) and the 7 years after the treatment began (2007–13). Mark-recapture results are assessed using the small sample size corrected information criteria AICc (AICc = AIC + 2<italic>k</italic>(<italic>k</italic>+1)/(<italic>n</italic>−<italic>k</italic>−1), where <italic>k</italic> = the number of parameters and <italic>n</italic> = sample size) to rank the explanatory ability of different models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C4">Anderson 2010</xref>). To summarize the data we also analyse the entire data set (2003–13) and calculate the mean difference in dormancy rates between treatments. We first calculate dormancy rates for each treatment in each year, calculate the difference between these means and average the differences for the pre- and post-treatment time periods. We use the delta method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C95">Powell 2007</xref>) in the R package <italic>msm</italic> to combine multiple standard errors and construct 95 % CIs around our final effect size estimates. Mark-recapture models are run in the R package <italic>marked</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C65">Laake <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).Deer browse compromised our ability to gain information on some individuals. Deer preferentially browse flowering <italic>Maianthemum</italic> and flowering individuals are of larger size than non-flowering individuals (N. L. Brouwer and S. Kalisz, unpubl. data). Accordingly, in the cases where an individual was browsed before its reproductive status was determined during the 10 annual censuses (<italic>n</italic> = 103 instances across 10 years), we assumed the browsed individual was flowering. Further, if browse occurred before an individual's size data was collected or size was otherwise unavailable, we used linear imputation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C43">Gelman and Hill 2006</xref>) to estimate its size (412 instances of size imputation out of 1481 total size records). Including imputed size data for the browsed plants prevents biasing our results against detecting a treatment effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C50">Hadfield 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C89">Nakagawa and Freckleton 2008</xref>).We imputed missing size data using estimates generated from multiple rounds of linear regression based on observed size data from the years prior to and after the missing data. We averaged these multiple estimates to arrive at a final imputed size estimate for each browsed individual. Linear regression models included all available covariates, including previous size, current status, treatment and reproductive output for flowering plants. We validated our imputations by comparing mean plant size and the overall size distribution in the population with and without imputed data <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv014/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information—Table S1</ext-link>]</bold>.<italic>Maianthemum racemosum</italic> rhizome carbohydrate content (%) from <italic>Alliaria</italic> (yellow) and <italic>Hesperis</italic> (control; black) treatments in the greenhouse experiment. Total NSC content is shown in solid-coloured bars. Total NSC is a composite measure of stored sugars (inulin; bars with diagonal shading) and mobile sugars (sucrose; stippled bars). Values are least squares means from ANCOVAs ±1 standard error. *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.005.Effect of <italic>Alliaria</italic> on plant size of <italic>Maianthemum</italic> marked in the initial 2003 survey of the field experiment. (A) Mean difference (effect size) in plant size between <italic>Alliaria</italic> in ambient and removal treatments. (B) Annual mean plant sizes in both treatments and ANOVA trend contrasts. Error bars represent ±95 % CIs. Asterisk indicates a significant difference in plant size between the two treatments (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Size data were not available for 2008 and 2009.There is no significant difference in flowering probability across treatments for the first 6 years of the <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal (e.g. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F3">3</xref>; <italic>P</italic><sub>2006</sub> = 0.65, <italic>P</italic><sub>2007</sub> = 0.29, <italic>P</italic><sub>2008</sub> = 0.42). However, by 2012 the flowering probability is ‘leaning’ (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C113">Tukey 1991</xref>) in the predicted direction (OR = 1.72, CI<sub>95%</sub> = 0.84–3.52, <italic>P</italic> = 0.14) and by 2013 is significantly higher (OR = 1.96 CI<sub>95%</sub> = 1.0–3.87, <italic>P</italic> = 0.051) in the removal treatment. Across all years (2006–13) there is an increasing trend in flowering probability in the removal treatment (trend contrast <italic>P</italic> = 0.00008) but no increase in the ambient treatment (<italic>P</italic><sub>trend</sub> = 0.57).Analyses using time as a continuous variable and year as a random effect confirmed that flowering frequencies diverged between the treatments (treatment × time <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> = 6.81, <italic>P</italic> = 0.009) with a significant positive linear trend in the removal treatment (<italic>β</italic><sub>removal × time</sub> = 0.18, SE = 0.069) contrasted with evidence of a decrease in flowering probability in <italic>Alliaria</italic>-ambient plots (<italic>β</italic><sub>time</sub> = −0.10, SE = 0.072).The number of flowering individuals was too low in 2005 and 2006 to accurately estimate retrogression of flowering plants in 2006 and 2007. By 2011, there was evidence that removal-treatment plants were less likely to retrogress (OR = 0.28 CI<sub>95%</sub> = 0.052–1.57, <italic>P</italic> = 0.15) and in 2012 they were significantly less likely to retrogress (OR = 0.14 CI<sub>95%</sub> = 0.021–0.96, <italic>P</italic> = 0.045). There was a significant decreasing trend in retrogression in the removal treatment from 2008 until 2013 (<italic>P</italic><sub>trend</sub> = 0.011) but no trend in the ambient treatment (<italic>P</italic><sub>trend</sub> = 0.90).Ranking of mark-recapture models testing the effects of <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal on prolonged vegetative dormancy. Three sets of models were run over different time periods during the study: Set 1: years before <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal began (Pre-treatment); Set 2: years after the annual weeding treatment was initiated (post-treatment) and Set 3: all years. <italic>N</italic>, number of plants tracked over each time period; <italic>K</italic>, number of parameters in a model; Ln(lik), log likelihood. To calculate the mean pre-treatment and post-treatment effect size (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F5">5</xref>) we used the parameters from the ‘Removal × Year’ model in the ‘All years’ model Set 3.To our knowledge this is the first study to explore the connections between an allelopathic invasive species' impacts on the soil biotic environment and changes in individual plants' carbon status and vital rates. The results presented here in conjunction with prior studies substantiate multiple steps in a physiologically based causal pathway between invasion and population-level impacts on native plants. Our prior work demonstrates that <italic>Alliaria</italic> treatment of soil around <italic>Maianthemum</italic> reduces the density of soil fungal hyphae (A. N. Hale <italic>et al.</italic>, submitted for publication) and plant photosynthetic rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Here, our results demonstrate that treatment with <italic>Alliaria</italic> across the entire growing season results in negative effects on season-long carbon storage (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F1">1</xref>). Relative to control plants, <italic>Maianthemum</italic> exposed to <italic>Alliaria</italic> stored 17 % less inulin in their rhizomes and experienced an overall reduction in total NSCs at the end of the season. Stomatal conductance modulates carbon fixation and is a key physiological rate affected by <italic>Alliaria</italic> exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Interestingly, a recent meta-analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C10">Augé <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) comparing the effects of AMF inoculation on stomatal conductance (<italic>g<sub>s</sub></italic>) in field vs. greenhouse studies indicates that greenhouse experiments have smaller effect sizes than field studies. Thus, our carbon storage results are likely conservative estimates of the carbon impacts of mutualism disruption in the field.Effect of <italic>Alliaria</italic> on <italic>Maianthemum</italic> flowering frequency. (A) Mean difference (effect size, ES) in flowering frequency in <italic>Alliaria-</italic>ambient and removal plots. Effect size is expressed as an OR and plotted on the log scale. (B) Annual mean flowering frequencies for both treatments and ANOVA trend contrasts. Error bars represent ±95 % CIs. Asterisk indicates a significant effect of <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Effect of <italic>Alliaria</italic> on <italic>Maianthemum</italic> retrogression from flowering to non-flowering. (A) Annual mean difference in retrogression frequency (ES) in <italic>Alliaria</italic>-ambient and removal plot. Effect size is expressed as an OR and plotted on the log scale. (B) Mean retrogression frequencies in both treatments and ANOVA trend contrasts. Error bars represent ±95 % CIs. Asterisk indicates a significant effect of <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Retrogression is calculated conditional on a plant being observed above-ground and not dormant. Sample sizes for 2006 and 2007 were insufficient for vital rate calculation.Effect size of <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal on the frequency of prolonged vegetative dormancy in <italic>Maianthemum</italic> before (2003–06; yellow) and after the treatment began (2007–13; black). Calculated with mark-recapture models; error bars represent ± 95 % CIs. Asterisk indicates a significant effect of <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Other experimental studies where <italic>Alliaria</italic> and native plants are grown together in pots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C83">Meekins and McCarthy 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C126">Wixted and McGraw 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C69">Lankau 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C109">Smith and Reynolds 2014</xref>) or in the field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C79">McCarthy 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C31">Carlson and Gorchov 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C34">Cipollini <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C68">Lankau 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>) also find negative effects of <italic>Alliaria</italic> on native species. Competition, direct allelopathic phytotoxicity and allelopathic RFS-mutualism disruption are all mechanisms that could contribute to these results. Our greenhouse experiment adds support to the idea that it is <italic>Alliaria</italic>'s disruption of key belowground mutualists (RFS) rather than competition or direct phytotoxicity that accounts for its success as an invader. Below we discuss the general support or lack thereof for the likelihood of all three mechanisms.We are aware of only two studies that have attempted to quantify reciprocal competition between <italic>Alliaria</italic> and focal plants. These pot studies found that <italic>Alliaria</italic> was equal to or weaker in competitive ability than three of four species tested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C83">Meekins and McCarthy 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C76">Leicht-Young <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). However, these studies are problematic in that they cannot separate competition from phytotoxicity or mutualism disruption. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C18">Bossdorf <italic>et al</italic>. (2004)</xref> found that <italic>Alliaria</italic> individuals from the native range outcompete <italic>Alliaria</italic> plants from the invaded range, supporting the hypothesis that invasive <italic>Alliaria</italic> express a different trade-off relative to their source populations. Invasive <italic>Alliaria</italic> are armed with novel allelochemical weapons but have evolved to be less competitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C18">Bossdorf <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Further, field experiments demonstrate that native competitors can suppress <italic>Alliaria</italic> performance and abundance when the natives are not experiencing overabundant herbivore pressure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C40">Eschtruth and Battles 2009<italic>a</italic></xref>), as deer preferentially consume native plants and facilitate the high population growth and spread of <italic>Alliaria</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C55">Kalisz <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). In experimental studies that exclude deer from invaded sites, <italic>Alliaria</italic> abundance rapidly declines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C41">Eschtruth and Battles 2009<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C60">Knight <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C55">Kalisz <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). In total, these results underscore the widely held view that <italic>Alliaria</italic> is a relatively poor competitor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C99">Rodgers <italic>et al.</italic> 2008<italic>a</italic></xref>).Glucosinolates are known antimicrobial chemicals produced by members of the mustard family as defences against pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C112">Tierens <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). While <italic>Alliaria</italic>'s allelochemicals can be inhibitory to germinating seeds and inhibit new seedling root growth (lettuce and radish seed experiments: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C118">Vaughn and Berhow 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C98">Roberts and Anderson 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C93">Pisula and Meiners 2010</xref>; <italic>Impatiens</italic> and <italic>Viola</italic> seed experiments: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C94a">Prati and Bossdorf 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C13">Barto <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C33">Cipollini and Flint 2013</xref>), to our knowledge direct toxicity of <italic>Alliaria</italic> on mature plant tissues has never been demonstrated. <italic>Alliaria</italic> invades forest understories dominated by adult perennial plants dependent on RFS. The direct effect of allelochemicals is inversely proportional to target plant density or biomass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C121">Weidenhamer 2006</xref>). Single-celled fungal spores and thin fungal hyphae should be much more susceptible to <italic>Alliaria</italic> allelochemicals than mature plant tissues. Thus, while we cannot rule out direct phytotoxic effects of <italic>Alliaria</italic> on adult <italic>Maianthemum</italic> performance in our field or greenhouse experiments, a direct allelochemical effect is likely of small magnitude relative to indirect effects on RFS.Mounting evidence shows that <italic>Alliaria</italic> can exert potent indirect effects on plants by suppressing RFS. Glucosinolates, like those produced by <italic>Alliaria</italic>, have a short half-life in the soil (&lt;15 h; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C45">Gimsing <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Yet, native plants grown in soils conditioned by <italic>Alliaria</italic>, treated with <italic>Alliaria</italic> tissue extracts, or collected from <italic>Alliaria</italic>-invaded sites all express reduced growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C111">Stinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C29">Callaway <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C128a">Wolfe <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) despite the fact that the volatile allelochemicals were likely no longer present. Importantly, these studies demonstrate that <italic>Alliaria</italic> impacts are similar in magnitude to soil sterilization and that experimental soils result in lower colonization of roots by mycorrhizae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C111">Stinson <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C29">Callaway <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C128a">Wolfe <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Finally, <italic>Maianthemum</italic> plants treated with <italic>Alliaria</italic> retain RFS structures internal to their roots, while exhibiting significant declines in soil hyphae (A. N. Hale <italic>et al.</italic>, submitted for publication). Together these experiments provide strong support for RFS-mutualism disruption and that its effects are of large magnitude relative to competition or direct phytotoxicity.Mechanistically, our working model linking RFS-mutualism disruption to carbon stress is based on the following premises: If <italic>Alliaria</italic>'s allelochemicals destroy the hyphal network, yet the normally long-lived internal structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C23">Brundrett and Kendrick 1990</xref>) remain intact, then we would predict that the plant would increase carbon allocation to its RFS to provision the regrowth of the soil hyphal network, resulting in significant carbon stress for the plant. Loss of the hyphal network severely limits available soil nutrients and water to the plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C90">Newsham 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C10">Augé <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). As a result, the plants photosynthesize less (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and fix less carbon (NSC; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F1">1</xref>). With this limited carbon pool, we suggest that plants may maintain concentrations of mobile sugars in the rhizome and roots to re-establish a functional RFS hyphal network that is repeatedly destroyed by our application of fresh <italic>Alliaria</italic> tissue. While our results are consistent with this working model (e.g. we observe greater sucrose concentrations in the rhizome of <italic>Alliaria</italic> vs. <italic>Hesperis</italic>-treated plants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F1">1</xref>)), additional experiments are needed to fully explore this hypothesis.We note that the effects of allelopathic mutualism disruption by <italic>Alliaria</italic> could be amplified by additional factors. Like other invasive species of deciduous forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C39">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C94">Poulette and Arthur 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C108">Smith and Reynolds 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C64">Kuebbing <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C104">Schuster and Dukes 2014</xref>), <italic>Alliaria</italic> can affect multiple components of the soil environment. <italic>Alliaria</italic> increases soil nutrient availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C100">Rodgers <italic>et al.</italic> 2008<italic>b</italic></xref>), litter decomposition rates and nitrogen loss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C9">Ashton <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Since the RFS community in general (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C116">Van Diepen <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and specific RFS–plant interactions (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C59">Klironomos 2002</xref>) are sensitive to soil conditions, multiple invader-mediated changes to the soil environment could magnify the impacts of allelopathic RFS-mutualism disruption. These diverse and widespread consequences of invasive species for soil environments and RFS communities are alarming given the potentially central role RFS and other microbes play in the diversity, productivity and functioning of plant communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C115">van der Heijden <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>).Our greenhouse study indicates that <italic>Maianthemum</italic> carbon storage declines significantly in response to <italic>Alliaria</italic> treatment in just one growing season. In contrast, we observe a relatively slow recovery of individual size, growth and vital rates following <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal in our field study. The predicted significant trends indicative of recovery (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F3"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F4">4</xref>) emerged after a few years of <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal while significant differences within the single-year comparisons were not seen until ∼6–7 years post removal (2012 or 2013). Two, non-mutually exclusive mechanisms could underlie this lag. First, the lag could be due to <italic>Maianthemum</italic>'s habit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C66">LaFrankie 1985</xref>). In general, forest understory herbaceous perennials are light-limited, slow-growing, long-lived species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C124">Whigham 2004</xref>) with slow responses to perturbation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C86">Morris <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Our data are consistent with the idea that following <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal, <italic>Maianthemum</italic> may take multiple years to re-gain sufficient carbon stores to allow size growth, sustain flowering and maintain low dormancy rates. Second, the observed lag in <italic>Maianthemum</italic> vital rate responses may be due to slow recovery of the RFS soil community following <italic>Alliaria</italic> removal, a phenomenon observed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C7">Anderson <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C72">Lankau <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>. If populations of beneficial RFS have gone locally extinct and low dispersal distance limits RFS re-colonization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C102">Rout and Callaway 2012</xref>), then the observed time lag of <italic>Maianthemum</italic> could be due to the low abundance of effective fungal partners. Given the reciprocal obligate dependence of AMF and forest herbaceous perennial plants, declines in the native understory community may drive reciprocal declines in the RFS soil community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C72">Lankau <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).Increases in invasive species are generally correlated with declines in native biodiversity (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C27">Butchart <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). However, the mechanistic underpinnings leading to native population collapse are rarely understood yet are the subject of numerous studies and invasion hypotheses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C77">Levine <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C53">Hulme <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). The disruption of plant soil feedbacks and root fungal symbioses are common aspects of plant invasions (i.e. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C48">Grove <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C85">Meinhardt and Gehring 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C103">Ruckli <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C106">Shannon <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). As suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C51">Hale and Kalisz (2012)</xref>, chronic RFS-mutualism disruption could act as the first step in native plant biodiversity loss. In our system, the disruption of RFS by an allelopathic invader appears to begin a downward spiral in the physiological function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C52">Hale <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), carbon status (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F1">1</xref>) and ultimately vital rates (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F3"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F4"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV014F5">5</xref>) of a common native forest plant. Loss of these critical belowground mutualisms may be the proximate cause of plant mortality that is instead attributed to second-order effects (e.g. drought or herbivory) that are easier to observe (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C81">McDowell 2011</xref>). Additional studies in invaded communities that explore the links between plant physiology, carbon allocation and population demographic performance are needed to determine the generality of these results. Mutualism disruption may be a widespread mechanism that helps explain how invasive species can cause large-scale changes to forest biodiversity observed in the wake of invasion (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV014C99">Rodgers <italic>et al.</italic> 2008<italic>a</italic></xref>).Funding was supplied by a <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">United States National Science Foundation</grant-sponsor> award <grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">DEB-0958676</grant-num> to S.K., a NSF pre-doctoral fellowship to N.L.B. and a Phipps Conservatory Botany-in-Action award and an Andrew K. Mellon pre-doctoral fellowship to A.N.H.S.K. conceived, designed, implemented and led data collection of the field experiment and assisted with the conception, design and implementation of the greenhouse experiment. A.N.H. designed, implemented and analysed data from the greenhouse experiment and assisted in data collected for the field experiment from 2008 to 2011. N.L.B. managed and analysed data from the field experiment and assisted with data collection for the field experiment since 2010. All three authors collaborated on the conception and writing of this article.None declared.The following additional information is available in the online version of this article –<bold>Table S1</bold>. Validation of imputed <italic>Maianthemum</italic> size data from field experiment. Original and imputed size data are compared using <italic>t</italic>-tests and Kolmogorov–Smirnov tests.<bold>Table S2.</bold> Estimated frequency of prolonged vegetative dormancy of <italic>Maianthemum</italic> from field experiment using a Mark-Recapture model.We thank the members of the Kalisz lab for field, lab and greenhouse assistance, and two anonymous reviewers whose detailed suggestions improved the manuscript.