Impact of nitrogen availability and soil communities on biomass accumulation of an invasive speciesInvasiveness of <italic>Ammophila arenaria:</italic> release from soil-borne pathogens?Microbial population and community dynamics on plant roots and their feedbacks on plant communitiesPlant–soil feedbacks do not explain invasion success of <italic>Acacia</italic> species in introduced range populations in AustraliaSoil biota and exotic plant invasionPlant species traits are the predominant control on litter decomposition rates within biomes worldwideExperimental support for a resource-based mechanistic model for invasibilityFluctuating resources in plant communities: a general theory of invasibilityEffects of exotic plant invasions on soil nutrient cycling processEcosystem consequences of biological invasionsChanges in soil functions following invasions of exotic understory plants in deciduous forestsFeedback in the plant-soil systemLinear and non-linear impacts of a non-native plant invasion on soil microbial community structure and functionEvolutionary tradeoffs for nitrogen allocation to photosynthesis versus cell walls in an invasive plantA quicker return energy-use strategy by populations of a subtropical invader in the non-native range: a potential mechanism for the evolution of increased competitive abilityNitrogen uptake and preference in a forest understory following invasion by an exotic grassResource-use efficiency and plant invasion in low-resource systemsEmergent insights from the synthesis of conceptual frameworks for biological invasionsLeaf litter of the invasive <italic>Casuarina equisetifolia</italic> decomposes at the same rate as that of native woody species on oceanic islands but releases more nitrogenA congeneric comparison shows that experimental warming enhances the growth of invasive <italic>Eupatorium adenophorum</italic>Resource-use strategies of native and invasive plants in eastern North American forestsIndependent variations of plant and soil mixtures reveal soil feedback effects on plant community over yieldingImpacts of soil microbial communities on exotic plant invasionsVolatile chemicals from leaf litter are associated with invasiveness of a neotropical weed in AsiaEffect of invasion of <italic>Mikania micrantha</italic> on germination of rice seedlings, plant richness, chemical properties and respiration of soilCommunity impacts of <italic>Prosopis juliflora</italic> invasion: biogeographic and congeneric comparisonPlant–soil feedbacks contribute to an intransitive competitive network that promotes both generic and species diversityPositive feedbacks to growth of an invasive grass through alteration of nitrogen cyclingLeaf trait relationships of native and invasive plants: community and global-scale comparisonsNative and exotic invasive plants have fundamentally similar carbon capture strategiesFluctuating resource availability increases invasibility in microbial microcosmsNegative plant-soil feedback predicts tree-species relative abundance in a tropical forestHow invader traits interact with resident communities and resource availability to determine invasion success?Comparison of nutrient acquisition in exotic plant species and congeneric nativesReciprocal effects of litter from exotic and congeneric native plant species via soil nutrientsSoil toxicity induced by terpenes from <italic>Salvia leucophylla</italic>An invasive aster (<italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic>) invades and dominates forest understories in China: altered soil microbial communities facilitate the invader and inhibit nativesDo alien plant species profit more from high resource supply than natives? A trait-based analysisBelowground biotic complexity drives aboveground dynamics: a test of the soil community feedback modelNative and non-native grasses generate common types of plant–soil feedbacks by altering soil nutrients and microbial communitiesPlant-induced changes in soil nutrient dynamics by native and invasive grass speciesImmobilizing nitrogen to control plant invasionEvaluation of chemical and biological consequences of soil sterilization methodsSoil biota facilitates exotic <italic>Acer</italic> invasions in Europe and North AmericaSoil biota and invasive plantsSoil feedback and pathogen activity in <italic>Prunus serotina</italic> throughout its native rangeAn invasive plant paradoxInteractions between exotic invasive plants and soil microbes in the rhizosphere suggest that ‘everything is <italic>not</italic> everywhereNon-native grass alters growth of native tree species via leaf and soil microbesEffects of <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> invasion on microbial carbon and nitrogen cycling in two adjacent undisturbed arid grassland communitiesEffects of labile soil carbon on nutrient portioning between the arctic graminoid and microbesInfluencing mechanisms of several shrubs on soil chemical properties in semiarid Horqin sandy land, ChinaConsequences of plant–soil feedback in invasionPlant–soil feedback induces shift in biomass allocation in the invasive plant <italic>Chromolaena odorata</italic>Biological invasion of <italic>Myrica faya</italic> alters ecosystem development in HawaiiEcological linkages between aboveground and belowground biotaChanges in non-symbiotic nitrogen-fixing bacteria inhabiting rhizosphere soils of an invasive plant <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Exotic plant species impact belowground processes by influencing resource availability through enhanced microbial activity as a consequence of litter inputs. Soil communities cultured by <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic>, a neotropical invader in Asia, retain available N that influence the growth of the invader. Invader triggers higher microbial activities through terpene-rich litter inputs to release nitrogen, which facilitates the invasion of <italic>A. adenophora</italic>. Our results provide evidence that microbial-linked nitrogen availability exert positive impact on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation. Our work emphasizes the importance of soil communities-drive nitrogen availability in invasion success.Exotic plant species impact belowground processes by influencing resource availability through enhanced microbial activity as a consequence of litter inputs. We have little understanding of the impact of microbe-driven nutrient fluctuations on the biomass accumulation of invasive species. Here we attempt to answer the question on whether soil community-driven nitrogen availability influences invader biomass. We discovered that soil communities cultured by <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic>, a neotropical invader in Asia, retain available nitrogen that influences the biomass of the invader. Through soil manipulation experiments we found that <italic>A. adenophora</italic> grows better in soil with a higher available nitrogen content. <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic>-invaded soil had higher microbial activity and available nitrogen due to higher inputs of terpene-rich litter compared with soil not yet invaded by it. Our results provide evidence that microbe-linked nitrogen availability exerts a positive impact on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation. Our work emphasizes the importance of soil community-driven nitrogen availability in invasion success.One of the questions that interest many ecologists is how nitrogen enables exotic plants to dominate ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C58">Vitousek <italic>et al.</italic> 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C49">Rout and Callaway 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C30">Lee <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and the role of belowground factors linked to it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C46">Reinhart and Callaway 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C59">Wardle <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C20">Gurevitch <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C50">Rout and Callaway 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C41">Pendergast <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Soil microbial communities are major components of the belowground ecosystem that influence exotic plant invasion by (i) making nutrients available through litter decomposition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C58">Vitousek <italic>et al.</italic> 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C10">Davis <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C13">Ehrenfeld 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C56">Suding <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and/or (ii) exerting negative or positive plant–soil feedback (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C47">Reinhart and Callaway 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C14">Ehrenfeld 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C25">Inderjit and Van der Putten 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C4">Bever <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). These effects take place via impacts of either root exudates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C59">Wardle <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C14">Ehrenfeld 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C29">Lankau <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C37">Meisner <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C43">Perkins <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) or exotic plant litter on soil microbial activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C14">Ehrenfeld 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C36">Meisner <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), resulting in the release or retention of nutrients that may promote invasion. In some cases, exotic litter accelerates nutrient cycling, particularly nitrogen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C8">Cornwell <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The decomposition of exotic litter largely depends on the amount of litter accumulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C15">Elgersma and Ehrenfeld 2011</xref>). It has been shown that litter of the invasive species <italic>Berberis thunbergii</italic> enhances net nitrogen mineralization and nitrification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C11">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C15">Elgersma and Ehrenfeld 2011</xref>). Exotic invasives impact microbial activities in soil, which stimulates microbial nitrogen cycling. For example, <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> invasion in arid grasslands of southeastern Utah, USA, stimulates microbial nitrogen cycling by enhancing microbial activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C52">Schaeffer <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Such fluctuations in resource availability have been reported to promote the invasibility of exotic invasive species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C9">Davis and Pelsor 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C33">Li and Stevens 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C35">Mata <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).We studied the role of nitrogen and its manipulation by soil microbial communities present in the invader's rhizosphere on the biomass accumulation of <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic>, a neotropical invader in Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C26">Inderjit <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C22">He <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Biogeographic comparisons of native and introduced ranges of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> suggest that the invader exerts neutral to facilitative effects on plant species richness in its native range in Mexico, but had negative effects on plant species richness in its introduced ranges in China and India (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C26">Inderjit <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The negative impact of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> on plant species richness in the introduced ranges was linked to biogeographic variations of terpenes released by <italic>A. adenophora</italic> litter, which suggested that it might be experiencing selection based on the composition of volatile organic compounds in its introduced ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C26">Inderjit <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> was reported to allocate greater amounts of nitrogen to photosynthesis (growth) and reduced allocation to cell walls (defence), thus resulting in an increase in its growth and vigour in the introduced ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C16">Feng <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C17">2011</xref>). This is also the case for <italic>Microstegium vimineum</italic> in the southern and eastern USA, which allocates more nitrogen to the aboveground parts than the belowground parts compared with native plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C18">Fraterrigo <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). A greenhouse study found that native soil communities had a more neutral than negative soil biota effect on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> relative to local species but soil biota from invaded sites had positive effects on the invader (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C39">Niu <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). However, it remains unclear whether nitrogen availability and microbial activity influence <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation. This is an important question in invasion ecology, where the effect of soil nutrients on invader performance is subject to debate (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C19">Funk and Vitousek 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C31">Leishman <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C32">2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C23">Heberling and Fridley 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C40">Ordonez and Olff 2013</xref>), particularly under low nutrient availability conditions. Hence, the impact of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> on soil communities and microbial nitrogen retention needs further studies. <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> adds a large amount of leaf litter to the soil. We predict higher microbial activity in <italic>A. adenophora</italic> soils due to addition of terpene-rich litter, which may influence soil available nitrogen and thus the positive effects of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation.We hypothesized that higher availability of soil microbial-driven nitrogen exerts a positive impact on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation. We designed a study to test our hypothesis by (i) comparing levels of available nitrogen and <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation in its non-sterilized and sterilized rhizosphere soil, (ii) manipulating the levels of nitrogen in soil to study the impact of nitrogen on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass, and (iii) quantifying soil respiration and available nitrogen in soil collected from the <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere and from areas not yet invaded by it (open areas).The study was conducted in two sites situated in the foothills of the Himalayas, Palampur (32°7′0.12″N, 76°31′59.88″E; 1220 m a.s.l.) and Mussoorie (30°27′0″N, 78°4′48″E; 1825 m a.s.l.), which are invaded by <italic>A. adenophora</italic>. In each site we selected two microsites: a disturbed habitat and another undisturbed habitat. The first microsite in Palampur was a track of 25 km that occurred along a highway road (National Highway #21) outside the Institute of Himalayan Bioresources and Technology, and was considered a disturbed site (32°6′13.2″N, 76°33′20.6″E). Here, <italic>A. adenophora</italic> was present along roadside slopes with little natural sub-canopy vegetation along with a few trees of <italic>Populus alba</italic>, <italic>Albezia lebbeck</italic> and <italic>Pinus roxburghii</italic>. The second microsite was a closed forest 11 km from the Roadside site and was an undisturbed site (32°5′7.4″N; 76°31′4.8″E). Here <italic>A. adenophora</italic> was interspersed with trees like <italic>P. alba</italic>, <italic>Gravillea robusta</italic> and <italic>Ficus virens</italic>, and the ground was covered with <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> and some grass species. In the Roadside site of Palampur, grass species like <italic>Oplismenus</italic> sp<italic>.</italic>, <italic>Poa</italic> sp<italic>.</italic> and <italic>Cynodon</italic> sp<italic>.</italic> were present. In addition to these species, plant species such as <italic>Cirsium vulgare</italic>, <italic>Panicum clandestinum</italic>, <italic>Trifolium repens</italic>, <italic>Erigeron mucronatus</italic> and <italic>Oxalis corniculata</italic> were found only in open areas. Other plant species like <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> and <italic>Lantana camara</italic> were present in open areas as well as areas invaded by <italic>A. adenophora</italic>. In open areas of the forest site of Palampur, grass species such as <italic>Oplismenus</italic> sp<italic>.</italic> and <italic>Cynodon</italic> sp<italic>.</italic> and plants species like <italic>Lathyrus aphaca</italic>, <italic>L. sphaericus</italic>, <italic>P. clandestinum</italic>, <italic>Lotus corniculatus</italic>, <italic>Briza minor</italic> and <italic>Anagallis arvensis</italic> were found exclusively here, and species like <italic>O. corniculata</italic> and <italic>Elettaria cardamomum</italic> were present in both areas, open and invaded by <italic>A. adenophora</italic>.In Mussoorie, the microsite with the disturbed habitat was a barren hill-slope (30°28′44.6″N; 78°3′9.1″E). Its original vegetation had been wiped out and it had nearly pure stands of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> with a few individuals of <italic>Carex setigera</italic>, <italic>B. pilosa</italic>, <italic>E. mucronatus</italic> and <italic>Geranium mascatense.</italic> The adjacent side of the Hill-slope site was an area not affected by hill slides and had a thick cover of vegetation dominated by species like <italic>Quercus incana</italic>, <italic>Prunus cerasiodes</italic> and <italic>Crotoneaster bacillaris</italic>. Owing to the complete destruction of the primary vegetation in the Hill-slope microsite in Mussoorie, no plant species was found exclusively in the open areas except for <italic>Cynodon</italic> sp. Species such as <italic>Berberis aristata</italic>, <italic>Geranium lucidum</italic>, <italic>E. mucronatus</italic>, <italic>Crataegus crenulata</italic>, <italic>B. pilosa</italic> and <italic>Debregeasia hypoleuca</italic> were, however, present in both open areas and areas invaded by <italic>A. adenophora</italic>. The second microsite in Mussoorie was a closed forest (30°28′12.6″N; 78°3′41.5″E) where <italic>A. adenophora</italic> was present inside a thick forest cover dominated by species such as <italic>Q. incana</italic>, <italic>Rumex nepalensis</italic>, <italic>R. hastatus</italic>, <italic>E. mucronatus</italic>, <italic>Prinsepia utilis</italic> and <italic>B. aristata</italic>. In the forest site of Mussoorie, plant species <italic>Potentilla</italic> sp., <italic>Polytrichum</italic> sp<italic>.</italic>, <italic>Rosa macrophylla</italic> and <italic>Cirisium arvense</italic> were present only in the open areas and <italic>E. mucronatus</italic>, <italic>Rumex nepalensis</italic>, <italic>Smilax aspera</italic>, <italic>G. lucidum</italic> and <italic>T. repens</italic> were found in both the open and <italic>A. adenophora</italic>-invaded areas.To test the effect of soil communities of the <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere, a total of 40 soil samples, 10 from each microsite, were collected from the rhizosphere of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> plants in Palampur and Mussoorie (10 plants × 2 microsites × 2 sites) in May 2012. Soil attached to <italic>A. adenophora</italic> roots was collected by pulling its roots and shaking off soil loosely bound to shallow roots, and identified as <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere soil. In order to collect sufficient soil for one soil sample, ≈3–4 kg, 2–3 plants of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> were pulled. Soil was then air-dried and stored in paper bags for analysis.In order to examine any effect of soil communities cultured by <italic>A. adenophora</italic> in its rhizosphere on its growth, we used non-sterile and sterile <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere soil. Although soil sterilization is a widely employed technique to study the role of soil communities in plant invasion (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C3">Beckstead and Parker 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C7">Callaway <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C48">Reinhart <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C45">Razavi darbar and Lakzian 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C51">Rudgers and Orr 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C57">Te Beest <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C34">Mangan <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C28">Kaur <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C6">Birnbaum and Leishman 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C24">Hendriks <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), the effect of nutrient leaching after sterilization cannot be ruled out. Half of each soil sample collected from the <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere from the two sites was sterilized by autoclaving the soil at 121 °C and 103 kPa for 30 min three consecutive times. Each soil sample for sterilization was packed individually in a small bag and autoclaved followed by cooling at room temperature and then autoclaved again for three consecutive days, making a total of 80 soil samples (2 sites × 2 microsites × 10 plants × 2 treatments). Fifty grams of non-sterile or sterile <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere soil were placed in each of 240 pots (2 sites × 2 microsites × 10 plants × 2 treatments × 3 experimental replicates) of 71.5 cm<sup>3</sup> volume and irrigated with 15 mL of distilled water. <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> seeds collected from a single location in Mussoorie were sown in each pot. The seeds were allowed to germinate under controlled conditions of temperature (21/18 °C) and a day/night light regime of 12/12 h. Seedlings were thinned a week after full germination to five seedlings per pot. <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> plants including roots were harvested after 60 days of growth and dried at 50 °C for 3 days, and their biomass was measured as total dry weight of the whole plant and averaged per pot.To study the impact of soil communities cultured by <italic>A. adenophora</italic> on available nitrogen, we analysed both non-sterile and sterile soil for available nitrogen. Fifty grams of dry soil were irrigated with 15 mL of distilled water and incubated at 22 °C for 5 days to make the soil conditions the same as when freshly collected from the field. Ten grams of soil were soaked in 20 mL of 0.5 M K<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, shaken for 1 h and filtered with nitrate-free Whatman #42. The concentration of available nitrogen was estimated as NO<sub>3</sub>-N using the colorimetric method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C1">Anderson and Ingram 1993</xref>).To examine the effect of nitrogen on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass, we manipulated non-<italic>A. adenophora</italic> soil with different levels of carbon (C; glucose). An increase in microbial activity after the addition of labile C in the form of glucose results in nitrogen immobilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C53">Schmidt <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>). One hundred and fifty grams of soil from the open area were taken in 160-cm<sup>3</sup> pots and irrigated with 45 mL of 1.04, 2.08 or 4.17 mg glucose per mL, corresponding to 125, 250 and 500 µg C per g soil. Experimental conditions were temperature 21/18 °C and a 12/12 h day/night light regime. The soil was further amended with the same levels of glucose on the 30th day after the initiation of the experiment and terminated on the 60th day. Soil respiration was estimated on Day 0, and the 30th and 60th days, and available nitrogen was estimated on the 30th and 60th days from the start of the experiment from fresh soil samples. Soil respiration was measured as soil CO<sub>2</sub> release by chemical titration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C2">Anderson 1982</xref>). Fifty grams of fresh soil were taken in a 346.2-cm<sup>3</sup> box, and a 5-cm-diameter Petri dish containing 10 mL of 0.1 N NaOH was placed on the soil inside the box and sealed to avoid any loss of CO<sub>2</sub>, and incubated for 24 h. One millilitre of 0.1 N BaCl<sub>2</sub> was added to the NaOH to terminate incubation, and then titrated against 0.1 N HCl using phenolphthalein as an indicator. The amount of CO<sub>2</sub> released was calculated following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C2">Anderson (1982)</xref>. Available nitrogen in fresh soil was first extracted and analysed as described previously. Each soil sample was replicated five times for the analyses.To examine the effect of available nitrogen, manipulated by adding glucose, on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass, we sowed <italic>A. adenophora</italic> seeds and plants were allowed to grow for 60 days. Unamended soil irrigated with distilled water served as the control. There were a total of 20 pots (4 concentrations × 5 replicates). Soil was irrigated with a similar concentration of glucose after 30 days before thinning the seedlings to five seedlings per pot. The plants, both shoot and root, were harvested after 60 days. Each of the <italic>A. adenophora</italic> seedlings was weighed individually and their average/pot was obtained. They were dried at 50 °C for 3 days and their biomass estimated as their total dry weight.Field soil was collected from the rhizosphere of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> or the area not yet invaded by it (identified as open soil) in two microsites in Palampur (Forest or Roadside) and Mussoorie (Forest and Hill-slope) in March 2011. <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> roots were pulled off and shaken to collect soil. Soil from the open areas in each microsite in two sites was collected at a depth of 10 cm. Sixteen soil samples from Palampur (2 areas (open and invaded) × 2 microsites × 4 subsites) and 20 soil samples from Mussoorie (2 areas × 2 microsites × 5 subsites) with each soil sample replicated three times were analysed for available nitrogen and soil respiration. Fifty grams of soil were first irrigated with 15 mL of distilled water and incubated at room temperature for 5 days to reactivate the microbial activity in the soil and then analysed for available nitrogen and soil respiration as described above.Differences in the mean dry weights of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> seedlings and available nitrogen in non-sterile and sterile soils were tested using the Independent Samples <italic>t</italic>-Test. To test the effect of site differences and sterilization treatment given to soil on the available nitrogen and the biomass of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> plants, we performed two-way ANOVA with treatment (non-sterile and sterile soil) and microsites (disturbed and forest sites) as fixed factors, for both Palampur and Mussoorie.To see the effect of manipulation of microbial populations of soil communities when the soils were treated with different levels of C on <italic>A. adenophora</italic>, we tested the correlation between the concentrations of C added to the soil in the form of glucose and available nitrogen, and between C concentrations and soil respiration. Pearson's correlation coefficient <italic>r</italic> was calculated to find out the correlation between soil C and available nitrogen or soil respiration. The effect of addition of different levels of C on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> plant biomass was tested by calculating the differences in the biomass of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> plants grown in C-treated soil at each concentration and between those grown in untreated soil taken as the control using the Independent Samples <italic>t</italic>-Test.Differences in the soil respiration or available nitrogen in the open area and <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere soil were tested using the Independent Samples <italic>t</italic>-Test (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) except for the differences in soil respiration in Mussoorie forest where the data were not normally distributed (Shapiro–Wilk test, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05) and were tested using the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test (asymptotic significance two-tailed, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). All analyses were carried out using SPSS 16.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C54">SPSS Inc. 2008</xref>).(A) Biomass accumulation (mg) of 60-day-old <italic>A. adenophora</italic> plants grown in the non-sterile and sterile rhizosphere soil of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> from Palampur and Mussoorie. Soil from the rhizosphere of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> was collected from undisturbed (Forest) and disturbed (Roadside or Hill-slope) habitats. (B) Available nitrogen (µg NO<sub>3</sub>-N per g soil) in soil from the rhizosphere of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> in Palampur and Mussoorie or in the sterilized treatment of the same. Error bars represent <bold>+1 SE</bold> of the mean. <italic>P</italic> values above the bars represent a significant difference between <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation (A) or available nitrogen (B) in the two different soil treatments (Independent Samples <italic>t</italic>-Test; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Summary of two-way ANOVA showing the effects of soil (non-sterile and sterile) and microsite (disturbed and forest) and their interaction on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation, and on the available nitrogen in the rhizosphere soil from Palampur and Mussoorie. d.f., degrees of freedom. Significance level (in bold): *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Summary of the Independent Samples <italic>t</italic>-Test conducted for differences in <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation when grown in soil treated with 0 µg C per g soil (identified as the control) or glucose (125, 250 or 500 µg C per g soil). d.f., degrees of freedom. Significance level (in bold): *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Correlation between C concentration (µg C per g soil) and available nitrogen (µg NO<sub>3</sub>-N per 0.01 g soil, solid spheres) or soil respiration (µg CO<sub>2</sub> per g soil per h, hollow spheres), in soil from open areas treated with four levels of C, control (0 µg C per g soil), low (125 µg C per g soil), medium (250 µg C per g soil) and high (500 µg C per g soil) on the 60th day of first amendment. Double asterisks indicate that correlation coefficient <italic>r</italic> is significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01. Inset, mean (<bold>+SE</bold>) biomass of 60-day-old <italic>A. adenophora</italic> seedlings in soil from open areas treated with the above-mentioned three levels of C on the 60th day of first amendment. Asterisks above the bars represent a significant difference between the dry biomass of seedlings grown in soils amended with glucose and the unamended soil taken as the control (Independent Samples <italic>t</italic>-Test; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLT045TB2">Table 2</xref>).Available nitrogen and soil respiration in soils from open areas (hollow) and the rhizosphere of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> (solid) in microsites: Forest (square, <italic>n</italic> = 4) or Roadside (diamond, <italic>n</italic> = 4) in Palampur, and Forest (circle, <italic>n</italic> = 5) or Hill-slope (triangle, <italic>n</italic> = 5) in Mussoorie: Bars indicate ±1 SE. Differences between available nitrogen and soil respiration in soil from open areas and the rhizosphere of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> from a site were tested using the Independent Samples <italic>t</italic>-Test (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) except for the differences in soil respiration in Mussoorie forest where the data were not normally distributed (Shapiro–Wilk test, <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05) and were tested using the Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test (asymptotic significance two-tailed, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).We observed that the available nitrogen in the soil collected from the <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere was also significantly higher compared with that in soil collected from open areas in Palampur as well as Mussoorie. It was 293.9 % (Roadside, df = 22, <italic>t</italic> = −3.801, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001) and 193.96 % (Forest, df = 22, <italic>t</italic> = −9.162, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) higher in the <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere soils in Palampur. In Mussoorie, we observed an increase in the levels of available nitrogen in the <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere of 95.62 % in the Hill-slope site (df = 28, <italic>t</italic> = −4.450, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) and 510.17 % in the Forest site (df = 28, <italic>t</italic> = −4.467, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001) compared with open soils (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F3">3</xref>).We found that sterilization of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere soil exerts a positive impact on its biomass accumulation and resulted in higher levels of available nitrogen (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F1">1</xref>). The higher biomass accumulation of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> is attributed to a post-sterilization nitrogen release (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F1">1</xref>B). This could also be due to lower microbial activity (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F2">2</xref>) or could also be related to a release from soil pathogens. Soil microbes retain inorganic nitrogen and release it back to the soil upon sterilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C45">Razavi darbar and Lakzian 2007</xref>). The higher biomass accumulation of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> and higher levels of available nitrogen in sterile soil than in non-sterile <italic>A. adenophora</italic> soil (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F1">1</xref>) suggest that higher nitrogen availability has positive effects on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation. By manipulating microbial activity, we were able to determine the effect of nitrogen availability on <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation. We manipulated the levels of nitrogen by amending soil with four levels of glucose. Addition of glucose as a C source in soil lowers the nitrogen availability by enhancing microbial activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C5">Brady and Weil 2008</xref>). Soil sterilization experiments showed a higher biomass increase in sterile soils (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F1">1</xref>), which could be explained by addressing the effect of microbial activity (due to a lower activity of microbes on sterile and non-enriched soils) on biomass accumulation and nitrogen availability (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F2">2</xref>). A significant negative correlation between the glucose-driven CO<sub>2</sub> release by soil communities and available nitrogen suggests that higher microbial activity lowers the levels of nitrogen (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F2">2</xref>). We also observed that <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass was significantly lower in soil modified with different levels of C (glucose) compared with the untreated control (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F2">2</xref>, inset; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLT045TB2">2</xref>). The observed glucose dose-dependent suppression of <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass in glucose-amended soil can be linked to dose-dependent lowering of nitrogen (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F2">2</xref>, inset). This study suggests that <italic>A. adenophora</italic> grows better in soils with higher nitrogen levels. Since <italic>A. adenophora</italic> allocates higher amounts of nitrogen to its growth in introduced ranges than in native ranges where it allocates more nitrogen to defence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C16">Feng <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C17">2011</xref>), and forms mono-dominant communities in introduced ranges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C26">Inderjit <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), the higher levels of nitrogen in <italic>A. adenophora</italic> soils compared with open areas contribute to <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass accumulation (see also Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F2">2</xref>, inset).This adds to the growing evidence in the literature that available nitrogen facilitates the growth of exotic invasives.Our data on higher levels of nitrogen in <italic>A. adenophora</italic> soils compared with open soils could be explained by the higher build-up of organic C (3.3 %) below its canopies compared with open forest soil (0.8 %), which could be due to higher <italic>A. adenophora</italic> litterfall (non-forest area, 1.4–10.6 g m<sup>−2</sup>; forest area, 4.5–17.6 g m<sup>−2</sup>). <italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> litter releases a variety of mono- and sesquiterpenes into the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C26">Inderjit <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Terpenes get adsorbed onto soil particles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C38">Muller and del Moral 1966</xref>). Accumulation of terpene-rich <italic>A. adenophora</italic> litter results in higher microbial activity, leading to the release of nitrogen from <italic>A. adenophora</italic> litter. Higher accumulation of organic C triggers enhanced microbial activity that results in nitrogen release from litter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C5">Brady and Weil 2008</xref>). The litter of certain exotic species is known to release higher amounts of nitrogen compared with native litter in spite of similar decomposition rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C21">Hata <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C36">Meisner <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). For example, certain exotic species accumulate greater amounts of nutrients as a consequence of greater organic C below their canopies and in their rhizosphere, e.g. <italic>Artemisia frigida</italic> and <italic>Caraganda microphylla</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C55">Su <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C12">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>) or trees like <italic>Prosopis juliflora</italic>, an aggressive invasive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C27">Kaur <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>b</italic></xref>). Higher levels of nitrogen-fixing bacterial communities are reported in the <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere compared with open soils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C60">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) but nitrogen levels in the present study seem to link with microbial activities as evident from higher nitrogen levels in sterilized <italic>A. adenophora</italic> rhizosphere soil (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT045F1">1</xref>B). We compared <italic>A. adenophora</italic> and non-<italic>A. adenophora</italic> (open) soils in order to understand its impact on belowground processes largely because such comparisons would include long-term changes in nutrient and litter dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C37">Meisner <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Our work suggests that the invader could trigger higher microbial activities through litter inputs, which facilitate nitrogen release. Any role of soil communities needs to be integrated with litter quality and resource availability. There is a need to focus our future work on studying whether local species co-occurring with the invader also share the extra benefit that exotic species gain from the available nitrogen. This would help us to understand how nitrogen enables exotic plants to dominate.Our results show that <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass increase is affected by nitrogen availability and that this is due to its rhizosphere retaining nitrogen. The importance of nitrogen in facilitating <italic>A. adenophora</italic> biomass is established by comparing its growth in non-sterile and sterile soil from its rhizosphere. We therefore consider it important to study the impact on nitrogen availability when examining the role of soil communities in plant invasion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C42">Perkins and Nowak 2013</xref>). Our results are also important for conservation biologists because we show that nitrogen facilitates invasion of exotic species like <italic>A. adenophora</italic> through soil community. Any fertilization in the forest should be reviewed, particularly for the areas invaded by exotic species with potential soil community-driven nitrogen availability as a mechanism of success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT045C44">Perry <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).The research was funded by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Council of Scientific &amp; Industrial Research (CSIR)</grant-sponsor> and the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">University of Delhi</grant-sponsor>.D.B. and Inderjit designed the research. D.B. performed the experiments. D.B. and Inderjit analysed the data and wrote the paper.None declared.D.B. thanks the University of Delhi for providing University Teaching Assistantship (UTA). We thank Dr Kurt Reinhart and two anonymous reviewers for constructive comments on the previous draft of this paper.