 A genetically stable rooting protocol for propagating a threatened medicinal plant— Celastrus paniculatus   A rapid  in vivo  multiplication system for commercial propagation of pharmaceutically important  Cyclea peltata  (Lam) Hook &amp; Thoms. based on enhanced axillary branching  An efficient  in vitro  process for recurrent production of cloned plants of  Vitex negundo  L  Rapid  in vitro  cloning of a 40-year-old tree of  Azadirachta indica  A. Juss. (Neem) employing nodal stem segments  A micropropagation protocol for mass multiplication and off-site conservation of  Celastrus paniculatus —a vulnerable medicinal plant of India  Micropropagation of  Sapindus trifoliatus  L. and assessment of genetic fidelity of micropropagated plants using RAPD analysis  Micropropagation of  Embelia ribes  Burm f. through proliferation of adult plant axillary shoots  Isolation of plant DNA from fresh tissue   Celastrus paniculatus  seed water soluble extracts protect against glutamate toxicity in neuronal cultures from rat forebrain  Factors affecting  in vitro  propagation and field establishment of  Chlorophytum borivilianum   Mass multiplication of  Celastrus paniculatus  Willd—an important medicinal plant under  in vitro  conditions using nodal segments  An efficient micropropagation system for  Celastrus paniculatus  Willd: a vulnerable medicinal plant  A revised medium for rapid growth and bioassays with tobacco tissue cultures  Rapid  in vitro  multiplication and restoration of  Celastrus paniculatus  (Celastraceae), a medicinal woody climber  Anti-inflammatory activity of  Celastrus paniculatus  seeds  Micropropagation of  Salvadora persica —a tree of arid horticulture and forestry  An improved micropropagation of  Terminalia bellirica  from nodal explants of mature tree  Micropropagation of mature  Terminalia catappa  (Indian almond)—a medicinally important forest tree  An efficient  in vitro  regeneration and  ex vitro  rooting of  Ceropegia bulbosa  Roxb.—a threatened and pharmaceutical important plant of Indian Thar Desert   In vitro  propagation of spine gourd ( Momordica dioica  Roxb.) and assessment of genetic fidelity of micropropagated plants using RAPD analysis  Genetic homogeneity of guava plants derived from somatic embryogenesis using SSR and ISSR markers  Cytokinin-induced high frequency shoot multiplication in  Celastrus paniculatus  Willd., a red listed medicinal plant  Influence of growth hormones on adventitious root formation in semi-hardwood cuttings of  Celasturs paniculatus  Willd.: a contribution for rapid multiplication and conservation management  Micropropagation of commercially cultivated henna ( Lawsonia inermis ) using nodal explants  RAPD based genetic stability analysis among micropropagated, synthetic seed derived and hardened plants of  Bacopa monnieri  (L.): a threatened Indian medicinal herb   In vitro  shoot bud differentiation and plantlet regeneration in  Celastrus paniculatus  Willd  Cultivation prospects of endangered species  Celastrus paniculatus  Willd  Reinvigoration treatments for the micropropagation of mature chestnut trees  An efficient micropropagation protocol for  Citrus jambhiri  Lush. and assessment of clonal fidelity employing anatomical studies and RAPD markers  Regeneration of plantlets via callus cultures in  Celastrus paniculatus  Willd.—a rare endangered medicinal plant  Assessment of genetic stability in micropropagules of  Jatropha curcas  genotypes by RAPD and AFLP analysis   In vitro  plant regeneration from decapitated embryonic axes of  Clitoria ternatea  L.—an important medicinal plant  An improved micropropagation of  Spilanthes acmella  through thin cell layer culture  An improved and efficient micropropagation of  Eclipta alba  through transverse thin cell layer culture and assessment of clonal fidelity using RAPD analysis  Large scale  in vitro  propagation of  Stevia rebaudiana  (Bert) for commercial application: pharmaceutically important and antidiabetic medicinal herb   In vitro  and  ex vitro  rooting of  Siratia grosvenorii , a traditional medicinal plant  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Nodal segments, obtained from 12 years-old mature plant, were used as explants for  in vitro  propagation of  Celastrus paniculatus , an important medicinal plant of India. Shoot multiplication was achieved by repeated transfer of mother explants and subculturing of  in vitro  produced shoot clumps on MS medium supplemented with various concentrations of BAP alone or in combination with auxin (IAA or NAA).  In vitro  raised shoots were rooted under  ex vitro  condition. Genetic fidelity of the regenerated plants was assessed using random amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD).   Celastrus paniculatus , belonging to the family Celastraceae, is an important medicinal plant of India. Owing to the ever-increasing demand from the pharmaceutical industry, the species is being overexploited, thereby threatening its stock in the wild. Poor seed viability coupled with low germination restricts its propagation through sexual means. Thus, alternative approaches such as  in vitro  techniques are highly desirable for large-scale propagation of this medicinally important plant. Nodal segments, obtained from a 12-year-old mature plant, were used as explants for multiple shoot induction. Shoot multiplication was achieved by repeated transfer of mother explants and subculturing of  in vitro  produced shoot clumps on Murashige and Skoog's (MS) medium supplemented with various concentrations of 6-benzylaminopurine (BAP) alone or in combination with auxin (indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) or α-naphthalene acetic acid (NAA)). The maximum number of shoots (47.75 ± 2.58) was observed on MS medium supplemented with BAP (0.5 mg L −1 ) and IAA (0.1 mg L −1 ).  In vitro  raised shoots were rooted under  ex vitro  conditions after treating them with indole-3-butyric acid (300 mg L −1 ) for 3 min. Over 95 % of plantlets acclimatized successfully. The genetic fidelity of the regenerated plants was assessed using random amplified polymorphic DNA. No polymorphism was detected in regenerated plants and the mother plant, revealing the genetic fidelity of the  in vitro  raised plantlets. The protocol discussed could be effectively employed for large-scale multiplication of  C. paniculatus . Its commercial application could be realized for the large-scale multiplication and supply to the State Forest Department.   Celastrus paniculatus  (known as  Jyotishmati  in Sanskrit and  Malkangni  in Hindi), belonging to the family Celastraceae, is an important medicinal plant of India. Oil obtained from the seeds of this plant is a source of herbal medicine, which is used in the treatment of gout, leprosy, skin diseases, fever, rheumatism, beriberi, sores and neurological disorders ( Warrier  et al.  1994 ;  Lal and Singh 2010 ). Celapagin, celapanigin, celapanin, celastrine and paniculatine are the alkaloids found in the seed oil which are responsible for making the plant medicinally highly potent ( Parimala  et al.  2009 ). Several studies have confirmed the memory- and grasping-power-boosting properties of  C. paniculatus  ( Nair and Seeni 2001 ;  Godkar  et al.  2004 ). Apart from these therapeutic applications, its roots are also used in the treatment of cancerous tumours ( Parotta 2001 ).  Conventionally,  C. paniculatus  is propagated mainly through the seeds. However, the viability and germination (11.5 %) of the seeds are poor ( Rekha  et al.  2005 ). Increasing human and livestock populations have affected the status of wild plants, particularly those used in medicines ( Singh  et al.  2009 ). Owing to its pharmaceutical importance, this species has been overexploited and is now considered a threatened species ( Martin  et al.  2006 ;  Lal and Singh 2010 ;  Raju and Prasad 2010 ). Thus, there is an urgent need to conserve the natural stock and multiply the plants on a larger scale to reduce the dependence on the forests for the supply of raw drugs. In the past three to four decades, plant tissue culture has been exploited as a valuable tool for the conservation and large-scale propagation of medicinally important and endangered plants ( Phulwaria  et al.  2012 a  ,  2013 ;  Thiyagarajan and Venkatachalam 2012 ). However, the influence of culture conditions, for instance, culture media, type of explant, successive transfer of culture, temperature, pH, etc., leads to genomic changes in the  in vitro  raised plantlets. Thus, analysis of the genetic homogeneity of tissue culture raised plants is a prerequisite for their exploitation on a commercial scale ( Rai, M. K.  et al.  2012 ). DNA-based molecular markers are powerful tools for analysis of the genetic fidelity of micropropagated plantlets ( Ahmad and Anis 2011 ;  Sharma  et al.  2011 ).  The present paper concerns an improved and reproducible protocol for large-scale propagation of  C. paniculatus.  The multiplication rate achieved in the present investigation is better than that in earlier reports on the same taxon ( Nair and Seeni 2001 ;  Arya  et al.  2002 ;  Sharada  et al.  2003 ;  Martin  et al.  2006 ;  Rao and Purohit 2006 ;  Raju and Prasad 2007 ;  Lal and Singh 2010 ). To save time and reduce labour cost, efforts were also made to optimize the most favourable conditions for  ex vitro  rooting. Furthermore, to confirm the genetic fidelity, regenerated plants underwent molecular analysis using DNA-based molecular markers.  An approximately 12-year-old plant of  C. paniculatus , maintained in the field of the Biotechnology Unit, JNV University, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India, was used as the mother plant to collect the explants. Juvenile shoots obtained from freshly emerged sprouts were collected and nodal segments (3–5 cm) were excised. Prior to surface sterilization using 0.1 % (w/v) HgCl 2  (Hi-Media, India) for 5 min under aseptic conditions, explants were treated with 0.1 % (w/v) Bavistin (BASF India Limited, Mumbai, Maharashtra, India) for 5–7 min to reduce the chance of fungal contamination. Explants (2–3 cm) were finally rinsed (5–6 times) with sterile double-distilled water to remove any traces of the disinfectant.  Murashige and Skoog's (MS;  Murashige and Skoog 1962 ) medium supplemented with sucrose (3 %) and additives (50 mg L −1  ascorbic acid, 25 mg L −1  adenine sulfate, 25 mg L −1  arginine and 25 mg L −1  citric acid), as described by  Arya  et al.  (2002 ), was used for culture initiation. Agar-agar (Hi-Media, India) was added to the culture media as a gelling agent at a concentration of 0.8 % (w/v). The pH of the medium was adjusted to 5.8 ± 0.02 and the medium was then autoclaved for 15 min at 121 °C. Cultures were maintained at 28 ± 2 °C under a 14 h day −1  photoperiod with a light intensity of 40–50 µmol m −2 s −1  photon flux density, provided using cool white fluorescent lamps (Philips, India).  To study the effect of plant growth regulators (PGRs) on bud break, nodal explants were cultured on MS medium containing different kinds (6-benzylaminopurine (BAP) or kinetin (Kin)) and concentrations (0.0, 1.0, 2.0, 3.0 or 5.0 mg L −1 ) of cytokinins. Cultures showing bud break were further multiplied using two approaches: (i)  in vitro  produced axillary shoots were excised and the mother explants were transferred repetitively for four passages (at 3-week intervals) onto MS medium containing 1.0 mg L −1  BAP plus additives; and (ii) shoot clumps (each containing 4–5 shoots) were excised from mother cultures and transferred onto MS medium containing BAP alone (0.0, 0.25, 0.5, 1.0 or 1.5 mg L −1 ) or a combination of an optimized concentration of BAP (0.5 mg L −1 ) with different concentrations (0.0, 0.05, 0.1, 0.2 or 0.3 mg L −1 ) of indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) or α-naphthalene acetic acid (NAA) for shoot multiplication and elongation.  To induce roots under  ex vitro  conditions, shoots (5–8 cm long) were excised from  in vitro  developed multiple shoots and the basal ends were treated with different concentrations (0.0, 100, 200, 300, 400 or 500 mg L −1 ) of indole-3-butyric acid (IBA) or NAA for 3 min. The treated shoots were transferred to bottles containing sterile soil-rite (a mixture of horticulture-grade perlite with Irish peat-moss and exfoliated vermiculite; supplied by Kel Perlite, Bangalore, Karnataka, India) moistened with an aqueous solution of one-quarter strength of MS basal salts. These bottles were kept in the greenhouse near the pad section in order to maintain high relative humidity (80–90 %) and low-temperature conditions (28 ± 2 °C).  After root initiation, the caps of bottles were gradually opened over a period of 2 weeks and finally removed. Bottles containing plantlets were then shifted from the pad section towards the fan section to provide growing conditions of low humidity (60–70 %) and high temperature (32 ± 2 °C). After 4–5 weeks, acclimatized plantlets were transferred to poly-bags containing a mixture of organic manure, clay and sand (1 : 1 : 1). Such plantlets were kept in the greenhouse for 7–8 weeks, shifted to the nursery and finally transferred to the field for the evaluation of percentage survival of plants.  The genetic stability of the 13 randomly selected  in vitro  regenerated plants was assessed using polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based random amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD) analysis. Genomic DNA was extracted from the fresh juvenile leaves of the mother plant and  in vitro  regenerated plants by following the cetyl trimethyl ammonium bromide (CTAB) method ( Doyle and Doyle 1990 ). Extracted DNA was quantified using a UV–Visible Elico spectrophotometer and the quality of DNA was tested following electrophoresis on a 0.8 % agarose gel. After preliminary screening of 25 primers, 16 RAPD primers were selected for genetic fidelity of tissue culture raised plants (Table  4 ). The PCR was performed in a 15 µL reaction mixture containing 2.0 µL of template DNA (50–60 ng), 1.5 µL of 10× PCR buffer (Bangalore Genei, Bangalore, Karnataka, India), 1.5 µL of MgCl 2  (2.5 mM; Bangalore Genei), 0.3 µL of deoxyribonucleotide triphosphates (10 mM; Bangalore Genei), 0.8 µL of random primer (10 µM; Integrated DNA Technologies Inc., India), 0.5 µL of three unit Taq polymerase (Bangalore Genei) and 8.6 µL of sterile distilled water. DNA amplification was carried out in a thermal cycler (Eppendorf 5331, Germany). The PCR programme consisted of an initial denaturation for 4 min at 94 °C, then 40 cycles of 30 s denaturation at 94 °C, 1.20 min annealing at  T  a  °C and 1.30 min extension at 72 °C with a final extension at 72 °C for 10 min. The annealing temperature ( T  a ) was kept at 2 °C below the melting temperature ( T  m ) of that particular primer sequence. Amplification with each primer was repeated twice to confirm the reproducibility of the results. The amplification products for all samples were resolved on a 1.4 % agarose (A9539; Sigma, St Louis, MO, USA) gel using 1× Tris/borate/EDTA buffer and stained with ethidium bromide (0.25 µg mL −1 ). Gels were visualized using a gel documentation system (Syngene Gel Doc; Syngene, Synoptics Ltd, UK). The size of the amplicons was estimated by comparison with a 100-bp DNA ladder (Bangalore Genei).  All the experiments were conducted with a minimum of 20 replicates per treatment. Each explant was taken as a replication and all the experiments were repeated three times. The results were expressed as the mean ± SD for all experiments. The data were subjected to statistical analysis using one-way analysis of variance, and the significance between means was assessed by Duncan's multiple range test (DMRT) at  P  &lt; 0.05.  Effect of cytokinins (BAP or Kin) on multiple shoot induction from nodal explants of  C. paniculatus .  Means in each column followed by the same superscript letters are not significantly different according to DMRT at  P  &lt; 0.05.   Micropropagation of  C. paniculatus .  (A) Nodal explants showing bud break on MS medium containing 2.0 mg L −1  BAP after 1–2 weeks of culture. (B) Multiplication of shoots after repeated transfer of mother explant after two passages on MS + 1.0 mg L −1  BAP. (C) Multiplication of shoots from the transfer of excised shoot clumps (4–5 shoots) to MS + 0.5 mg L −1  BAP + 0.1 mg L −1  IAA after 4 weeks of transfer. (D) Large-scale shoot proliferation on MS + 0.5 mg L −1  BAP + 0.1 mg L −1  IAA after 4 weeks of transfer. (E)  Ex vitro  rooted shoots after treatment with 300 mg L −1  IBA for 3 min after 3–4 weeks. (F) Micropropagated plants in the greenhouse near the pad section.   Shoot multiplication by repeated transfer of mother explant for different passages on MS + 1.0 mg L −1  BAP + additives.  Mean values sharing the same letter do not differ significantly ( P  &lt; 0.05) according to DMRT.  Effect of PGRs on shoot multiplication of  C. paniculatus .  Means in each column followed by the same superscript letters are not significantly different according to DMRT at  P  &lt; 0.05.  Effect of auxins (IBA or NAA) on  ex vitro  rooting of micropropagated shoots of  C. paniculatus .  Treatment duration: 3 min. Means in each column followed by the same superscript letters are not significantly different according to DMRT at  P  &lt; 0.05.   Acclimatization of plants and DNA amplification obtained with primers.  (A) Micropropagated plants transferred to poly-bags in the greenhouse near the fan section. (B) Fully hardened plantlets loaded for transportation to the State Forest Department. (C and D) DNA amplification obtained with primers (C) OPG-07 and (D) OPQ-07. Lane P, DNA from the mother plant; lanes 1–13, DNA from micropropagated plants.  RAPD primers used for testing the genetic fidelity of micropropagated plants of  C. paniculatus .  The improved micropropagation protocol discussed here could be exploited for large-scale multiplication of  C. paniculatus , a threatened and medicinally important plant species. Continuous supply of plants through micropropagation would reduce the pressure on the species' natural population and thus help conserve it. The technique of inducing roots under  ex vitro  conditions has made the discussed protocol more efficient and economical owing to the improved survival. Apart from being rapid, the protocol was found to cause no genetic variation among the regenerants and hence could be of great practical utility.  The work was funded by the  University Grants Commission (UGC), New Delhi , through a Post Doctoral Fellowship and Dr D.S. Kothari Post Doctoral Fellowship to M.P. and M.K.R. Financial assistance provided by the  Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), New Delhi , to A.K.P. is gratefully acknowledged.  M.P. designed and performed the experiments and wrote the first draft of the manuscript. M.K.R. analysed data and organized it in figures and tables. A.K.P. performed some tissue culture experiments. V.K. and N.S.S. edited the final version of the manuscript.  None declared.  We are grateful to the anonymous reviewers for their valuable suggestions. We also thank Dr M. M. Mathur, Retired Professor Department of English, L.M. College of Science and Technology Jodhpur (India), for language improvement of the revised manuscript. 