Responses of sap flow, leaf gas exchange and growth of hybrid aspen to elevated atmospheric humidity under field conditionsControl of stomatal aperture: a renaissance of the old guardHigh relative air humidity and continuous light reduce stomata functionality by affecting the ABA regulation in rose leavesThe multisensory guard cell. Stomatal responses to blue light and abscisic acidEnvironmental controls on sap flow in a northern hardwood forestThe effect of three rootstocks on water use, canopy conductance and hydraulic parameters of apple trees and predicting canopy from hydraulic conductanceDecoupling the influence of leaf and root hydraulic conductances on stomatal conductance and its sensitivity to vapour pressure deficit as soil dries in a drained loblolly pine plantationClimate extremes: observations, modeling, and impactsDifferences in yield, biomass and their components between triticale and wheat grown under contrasting water and nitrogen environmentsEffect of relative air humidity on the stomatal functionality in fully developed leavesAvoiding high relative air humidity during critical stages of leaf ontogeny is decisive for stomatal functioningStomatal conductance and photosynthesisA biochemical model of photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation in leaves of C<sub>3</sub> speciesTranspiration responses to vapor pressure deficit in well watered ‘slow-wilting’ and commercial soybeanEffects of leaf wetting and high humidity on stomatal function in leafy cuttings and intact plants of <italic>Corylus maxima</italic>Smaller stomata require less severe leaf drying to close: a case study in <italic>Rosa hydrida</italic>Stomatal, mesophyll conductance and biochemical limitations to photosynthesis as affected by drought and leaf ontogeny in ash and oak treesSeasonal and interannual variability of photosynthetic capacity in relation to leaf nitrogen in a deciduous forest plantation in northern ItalyDrought tolerance in mulberry (<italic>Morus</italic> spp.): a physiological approach with insights into growth dynamics and leaf yield productionAn improved model of C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis at high CO<sub>2</sub>: reversed O<sub>2</sub> sensitivity explained by lack of glycerate reentry into the chloroplastTheoretical considerations when estimating the mesophyll conductance to CO<sub>2</sub> flux by analysis of the response of photosynthesis to CO<sub>2</sub>Sap flux of five co-occurring tree species in a temperate broad-leaved forest during seasonal soil droughtVariations in relative stomatal and biochemical limitations to photosynthesis in a young blackbutt (<italic>Eucalyptus pilularis</italic>) plantation subjected to different weed control regimesTranspiration from a <italic>Cryptomeria japonica</italic> plantation, Part 2: Responses of canopy conductance to meteorological factorsAn experimental facility for free air humidity manipulation (FAHM) can alter water flux through deciduous tree canopyNitrogen dynamics in oak model ecosystems subjected to air warming and drought on two different soilsEffects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> on the growth, seed yield, and water use efficiency of soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic> (L.) Merr.) under drought stressABA regulated stomatal control and photosynthetic water use efficiency of potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.) during progressive soil dryingFunctional convergence in plant responses to the environmentStomatal response characteristics of <italic>Tradescantia virginiana</italic> grown at high relative air humidityThe dual effect of abscisic acid on stomataCanopy conductance of <italic>Pinus taeda</italic>, <italic>Liquidambar styraciflua</italic> and <italic>Quercus phellos</italic> under varying atmospheric and soil water conditionsEffect of air humidity on the development of functional stomatal apparatusAdaptability of birch (<italic>Betula pendula</italic> Roth) and aspen (<italic>Populus tremula</italic> L.) genotypes to different soil moisture conditionsPartitioning of transfer and carboxylation components of intracellular resistance to photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> fixation: a critical analysis of the methods usedEuropean climate in the late twenty-first century: regional simulations with two driving global models and two forcing scenariosDynamics of adaptation of stomatal behaviour to moderate or high relative air humidity in <italic>Tradescantia virginiana</italic>Dynamics of spatial heterogeneity of stomatal closure in <italic>Tradescantia virginiana</italic> altered by growth at high relative air humidityDrought stress response in <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic>: growth and physiologyHydraulic and stomatal adjustment of Norway spruce trees to environmental stressVariation of transpiration within a canopy of silver birch: effect of canopy position and daily versus nightly water lossHumidity-driven changes in growth rate, photosynthetic capacity, hydraulic properties and other functional traits in silver birch (<italic>Betula pendula</italic>)Rapid and long-term effects of water deficit on gas exchange and hydraulic conductance of silver birch trees grown under varying atmospheric humidityPhotosynthesis in intact leaves of C3 plants: physics, physiology and rate limitationsRelative humidity is a key factor in the acclimation of the stomatal response to CO<sub>2</sub>Stomatal and non-stomatal limitations to photosynthesis in four tree species in a temperate rainforest dominated by <italic>Dacrydium cupressinum</italic> in New ZealandLeaf anatomy and stomatal morphology of greenhouse roses grown at moderate or high air humidityClimate change at Northern latitudes: rising atmospheric humidity decreases transpiration, N-uptake and growth rate of hybrid aspenShort-rotation forestry with hybrid aspen (<italic>Populus tremula</italic> L. × <italic>P. tremuloides</italic> Michx.) in Northern EuropePhotosynthetic parameters, dark respiration and leaf traits in the canopy of a Peruvian tropical montane cloud forestSome relationships between the biochemistry of photosynthesis and the gas exchange of leaves<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Tim J. BrodribbThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We demonstrate that higher air humidity mitigates the effect of low soil water availability on broadleaved trees during dry years by reducing stomatal limitation to photosynthesis, allowing higher net photosynthetic rates and supporting higher growth rates. At the same time, rising atmospheric humidity increases sensitivity of canopy conductance to water deficit and reduces the responsiveness of intrinsic water-use efficiency. The results imply that a future rise in atmospheric humidity at high latitudes may be disadvantageous in evenly rainy/humid years and expose trees to higher dehydration risk during weather extremes, although mitigating the impact of soil water deficit under moderate drought.An increase in average air temperature and frequency of rain events is predicted for higher latitudes by the end of the 21st century, accompanied by a probable rise in air humidity. We currently lack knowledge on how forest trees acclimate to rising air humidity in temperate climates. We analysed the leaf gas exchange, sap flow and growth characteristics of hybrid aspen (<italic>Populus tremula</italic> × <italic>P. tremuloides</italic>) trees growing at ambient and artificially elevated air humidity in an experimental forest plantation situated in the hemiboreal vegetation zone. Humidification manipulation did not affect the photosynthetic capacity of plants, but did affect stomatal responses: trees growing at elevated air humidity had higher stomatal conductance at saturating photosynthetically active radiation (<italic>g</italic><sub>s sat</sub>) and lower intrinsic water-use efficiency (IWUE). Reduced stomatal limitation of photosynthesis in trees grown at elevated air humidity allowed slightly higher net photosynthesis and relative current-year height increments than in trees at ambient air humidity. Tree responses suggest a mitigating effect of higher air humidity on trees under mild water stress. At the same time, trees at higher air humidity demonstrated a reduced sensitivity of IWUE to factors inducing stomatal closure and a steeper decline in canopy conductance in response to water deficit, implying higher dehydration risk. Despite the mitigating impact of increased air humidity under moderate drought, a future rise in atmospheric humidity at high latitudes may be disadvantageous for trees during weather extremes and represents a potential threat in hemiboreal forest ecosystems.With rapid increases in global industrial development, fossil fuel use and changing land-use practices, atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration ([CO<sub>2</sub>]) is expected to double within the 21st century. This increase will result in global climate changes: global mean water vapour concentration, evaporation and precipitation rates, as well as global mean surface temperature are projected to increase during the 21st century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C23">IPCC 2007</xref>). These changing climate factors along with rising [CO<sub>2</sub>] affect the physiological performance of plants: CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation, transpiration, stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) and ultimately plant growth and productivity.The impact of the most common consequences of climate change—drought, high temperature and high atmospheric vapour pressure deficit (VPD)—on photosynthesis and water use in C<sub>3</sub> plants has been quite well studied, because the occurrence of extreme temperatures, soil water deficit and high VPD, as well as their interactions, alters the physical properties and yield of plants, which are important to agriculture and forestry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C13">Fletcher <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C18">Guha <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C8">Estrada-Campuzano <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C26">Kuster <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C27">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C39">Sapeta <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Considerably less is known of the effect of increasing atmospheric humidity on plants. Increases in precipitation are considered very likely at high latitudes in the long-term perspective (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C23">IPCC 2007</xref>). Precipitation is predicted to increase in northern Europe, especially in winter, and to decrease in southern and central Europe in summer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C36">Räisänen <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). There might also be fewer dry days at higher latitudes by the end of the 21st century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C23">IPCC 2007</xref>). Increasing rainfall frequency results in higher relative air humidity at local or regional scales.The leaves of plants grown at high relative humidity (RH) have larger stomata, larger stomatal pore aperture and length, and significantly lower stomatal density due to larger epidermal cells than in plants grown at moderate RH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C47">Torre <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C30">Nejad and Van Meeteren 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C2">Arve <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Therefore, decreasing VPD may lead to increased stomatal conductance and to a consequent increase in transpiration in some plant species grown at high RH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C33">Pospíšilová 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C14">Fordham <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C30">Nejad and Van Meeteren 2005</xref>). Nevertheless, most findings suggest that a decrease in VPD generally leads to decreased steady-state leaf transpiration or sap flux density in a wide range of tree species from different habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C32">Pataki <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C29">Meinzer 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C4">Bovard <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C21">Hölscher <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Our previous studies have demonstrated decreased sap flux density in response to increased air humidity in silver birch (<italic>Betula pendula</italic>) and hybrid aspen (<italic>Populus tremula</italic> × <italic>P. tremuloides</italic>) trees in moist summers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C25">Kupper <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).Growing at high RH not only alters stomatal morphology, but stomatal functioning as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C9">Fanourakis <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C10">2011</xref>). It is known that RH is a key environmental factor mediating changes in stomatal sensitivity to CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C45">Talbott <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Moreover, RH affects stomatal response to water availability and drought. Plants grown at high RH are less hydrosensitive than plants grown at moderate RH: stomata of high-RH-grown leaves are less sensitive to decreases in leaf water potential than moderate-RH-grown leaves, and the homogeneity, speed and degree of stomatal closure are less in high-RH-grown plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C30">Nejad and Van Meeteren 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C38">Rezaei Nejad <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C37">Rezaei Nejad and Van Meeteren 2008</xref>). Therefore, plants developed under moderate RH are able to retain higher water status due to more efficient stomatal control. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C2">Arve <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> revealed that stomata developed under high RH respond to neither darkness nor drought, but remain open. Thus, high RH may even override the signals given by darkness. The stomata of plants growing in naturally waterlogged soil are also less sensitive to decreasing VPD than those of plants growing in well-drained soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C40">Sellin 2001</xref>).High RH does not change only the stomatal characteristics of plants. Our previous experiments with silver birch and hybrid aspen have shown that elevated atmospheric RH lowers leaf nutritional status by altering nutrient movement via mass flow in soil and lowering nutrient transfer through xylem flow into leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C48">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C42">Sellin <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The changes in leaf nutrient content and P : N ratio in turn cause a decline in photosynthetic capacity and ultimately changes in tree growth rate.Experiments on stomatal responses to air humidity and plant stress resistance are typically carried out in greenhouses or growth chambers with seedlings or saplings growing in pots. The objective of the present study was to investigate how artificially increased RH during leaf development affects the sap flow, stomatal responses and photosynthetic parameters of hybrid aspen (<italic>P. tremula</italic> × <italic>P. tremuloides</italic>) under free-air conditions. Hybrid aspen is a fast-growing deciduous tree species suitable for short-rotation forestry in the relatively cold climate of northern Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C49">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>b</italic></xref>). Our aim was to test the following hypotheses. (i) Trees grown at higher atmospheric humidity have higher stomatal conductance and lower water-use efficiency (WUE) than control trees. (ii) The photosynthetic capacity of leaves developed in humid air is lower because of reduced nitrogen uptake due to lower transpirational flux density. (iii) Plants grown in a more humid atmosphere are unable to adjust their WUE quickly because of acclimation to lower VPD or possible stomatal malfunction.Weather data in the growing period of 2011: the dark line indicates monthly average air temperature, and the grey bars indicate monthly precipitation.Daily average values of soil water potential at a depth of 15–30 cm in control and humidification plots from June to August in 2011. Scale bars denote SEM.Hourly average values of air VPD in control and humidification plots from June to August in 2011. Scale bars denote SEM.We sampled gasometrically nine trees (mean height 3.8 m) from <bold>C</bold> plots and nine trees (mean height 3.3 m) from <bold>H</bold> plots (i.e. three trees per sample plot) for 1 month, from mid-July to mid-August. Measurements were performed on rainless misting-free days on intact fully expanded leaves <italic>in situ</italic> with a portable photosynthesis system LCpro+ (ADC BioScientific, Great Amwell, UK) at constant air humidity (13 mbar), CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>a</sub> = 360 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup>) and temperature of the leaf chamber (25 °C). Leaf-to-air vapour pressure difference was relatively similar in the two treatments: on average 2.12 kPa for <bold>C</bold> plants and 1.99 kPa for <bold>H</bold> plants. To generate photosynthetic light response curves (<italic>A</italic>/<italic>Q</italic> curves), four leaves per tree were sampled from the middle part of the crown with an instrument equipped with an LED light source. The measurements started with photosynthetically active radiation (PAR) at 1196 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, then decreased stepwise to 9 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> and increased stepwise from 1196 to 1803 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>. Intrinsic water-use efficiency, expressed as the ratio of net photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic><sub>n</sub>) to stomatal conductance to water vapour (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>), was determined at two levels of irradiance: at 400–600 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> when IWUE was usually at a maximum (IWUE<sub>max</sub>) and at light intensities corresponding to full sunlight (IWUE<sub>sat</sub>; <italic>Q</italic>≥ 1400 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>).The response of net photosynthesis to varying intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>)—<italic>A</italic>/<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> curves—was also determined on intact leaves (four leaves per tree) <italic>in situ</italic> at constant air humidity (13 mbar), temperature of the leaf chamber (25 °C) and at saturating irradiance (1500 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>). External CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>a</sub>) was supplied in 11 steps, decreasing from 360 to 60 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> and then increasing from 450 to 1600 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup>. In addition to IWUE<sub>max</sub> and IWUE<sub>sat</sub> calculated from the data of <italic>A</italic>/<italic>Q</italic> curves, IWUE<sub>in</sub> (initial IWUE) was determined using initial values of the <italic>A</italic>/<italic>Q</italic> and <italic>A</italic>/<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> sequences when external [CO<sub>2</sub>] was 360 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup>.Tree height (<italic>H</italic>, cm) and stem diameter at 30-cm height (<italic>D</italic>, mm) of all aspen trees growing at three <bold>C</bold> and three <bold>H</bold> plots were measured before and after the 2011 growing season. <italic>H</italic> was measured with a telescopic Nedo mEssfix-S measuring rod (Nedo GmbH &amp; Co.KG, Dornstetten, Germany) and stem diameter with a LIMIT digital caliper (Luna AB, Alingsås, Sweden). Current annual increment of the trees (Δ<italic>H</italic>, Δ<italic>D</italic>) was estimated as the difference between the two measurements. Relative increment (Δ<italic>H</italic><sub>rel</sub>, Δ<italic>D</italic><sub>rel</sub>) was expressed as the ratio of Δ<italic>H</italic> and Δ<italic>D</italic> to their respective characteristics at the beginning of the growing season. The ratio of <italic>H</italic>:<italic>D</italic> was defined as tree slenderness (<italic>S</italic>).Statistical data analysis was carried out using Statistica, Ver. 7.1 (StatSoft Inc., Tulsa, OK, USA). Repeated-measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare the sap flux density (<italic>F</italic>) and canopy conductance to water vapour (<italic>g</italic><sub>C</sub>) between trees from the control and the misting treatment. The daily averages of <italic>F</italic> and <italic>g</italic><sub>C</sub> were analysed altogether on 31 days from 1000 to 1700 h from 14 June to 7 August 2011 (DOY: 165–176, 197–201, 206–219). Linear regression analysis was carried out to estimate relationships between <italic>F</italic>, <italic>g</italic><sub>C</sub>, VPD and <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub>. The normality of the regression residuals was checked using the Shapiro–Wilk test.The gasometric data were analysed with Photosyn Assistant, Ver. 1.2 software (Dundee Scientific, Dundee, UK). The <italic>A</italic>/<italic>Q</italic> curves were fitted as a non-rectangular hyperbola expressed as a quadratic equation by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C35">Prioul and Chartier (1977)</xref>. The initial slope of the curve expresses the apparent quantum efficiency (<italic>ϕ</italic>), whereas the <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> axes intercepts, respectively, correspond to the light compensation point (<italic>Q</italic><sub>comp</sub>) and apparent dark respiration (<italic>R</italic><sub>d</sub>), and the upper asymptote approximates the light-saturated rate of photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>). An additional parameter—convexity (<italic>θ</italic>)—is required to describe the rate of bending between the linear increase and the maximum value. Sub-stomatal cavity CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>) was calculated using the model of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C51">von Caemmerer and Farquhar (1981)</xref>.Soil water potential (kPa) estimates of the experimental plots: <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S_mean</sub>, mean across the growing season; <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S_Q25</sub>, lower quartile; <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S_Q75</sub>, upper quartile.Daily average values of sap flux density (<italic>F</italic>) and canopy conductance to water vapour (<italic>g</italic><sub>C</sub>) in control and humidification plots during mist fumigation from June 14 to June 25 (DOY: 165–176; A and C) and July 15 to August 7 (DOY: 197–219; B and D), 2011. Scale bars denote SEM.Variation in daily average canopy conductance to water vapour (<italic>g</italic><sub>C</sub>) depending on atmospheric VPD (A) and bulk soil water potential at a depth of 30 cm (<italic>Ψ</italic><sub>30</sub>; B). The numbers by the regression lines indicate the respective slopes.Leaf gas exchange characteristics of hybrid aspen growing under control and humidification treatment. Each value is the mean ± SE; the means are compared with Tukey's test. NS, not statistically significant.Effects of treatment, plot and soil water potential at a depth of 30 cm (<italic>Ψ</italic><sub>30</sub>) on gas exchange characteristics. NS, not statistically significant.Means of net photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic><sub>n</sub>; A), stomatal conductance to water vapour at saturating PAR (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> <sub>sat</sub>; B) and intrinsic water-use efficiency (IWUE<sub>in</sub>; C) of control (closed circles) and humidified trees (open squares) depending on soil water status. Values are means ± SE; different letters denote statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) differences.Photosynthetic WUE versus external CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in control and humidification treatment.Means of maximum rate of carboxylation by Rubisco (<italic>V</italic><sub>C max</sub>; A), PAR-saturated rate of electron transport (<italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>; B) and relative stomatal limitation to photosynthesis (<italic>L</italic><sub>S</sub>; C) of control (closed circles) and humidified trees (open squares) depending on soil water status. Values are means ± SE; different letters denote statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) differences.The mean values of relative stomatal limitation of photosynthesis (<italic>L</italic><sub>S</sub>) were lower in trees grown at elevated RH than in <bold>C</bold> trees—37.9 and 41.3 %, respectively (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU021TB2">2</xref>), although ANOVA did not establish any significant effect of the treatment (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU021TB3">3</xref>). Net photosynthesis was negatively correlated with <italic>L</italic><sub>S</sub> in control trees (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.15, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03), but the relationship lacked in the humidification treatment (<italic>P</italic> = 0.23). We found no differences in <italic>L</italic><sub>S</sub> with respect to soil water status in any treatment separately (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F8">8</xref>C).Comparison (<italic>t</italic>-test) of mean (±SE) growth parameters of individual trees growing in humidified (<bold>H</bold>) and control (<bold>C</bold>) plots. NS, not statistically significant.Results from ANOVA models describing the effect of tree size (i.e. the value of the respective parameter before the start of the growing season, <italic>C<sub>t</sub></italic><sub>−1</sub>), treatment (<italic>T</italic>), plot and soil water potential (<italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S_mean</sub>, <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S_Q25</sub>, <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S_Q75</sub>) on the growth parameters.The sap flux density in hybrid aspen trees changed considerably compared with that at the same experimental site in previous summers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C25">Kupper <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C48">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>). <italic>F</italic> in control plots was significantly greater than that in the humidification treatment during the rainy summer of 2009 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C25">Kupper <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The same tendency (not significant) was observed in the drier summer of 2010 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C48">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>). However, our current results demonstrate higher (although not statistically significant) sap flux densities in trees growing in the humidification plots (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F4">4</xref>). The canopy conductance to water vapour in the <bold>H</bold> treatment was greater (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) across the whole study period. This discrepancy is attributable to relatively low soil water potential in the control treatment owing to the very dry summer: <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> did not rise over −80 kPa in July. The total precipitation during the 2011 growing season (May–October) was 261 mm (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F1">1</xref>), 42 % less than the average of the three previous years (452 mm). As the air humidity manipulation did not affect sapwood-to-leaf-area ratio (HV), the ∼30 % greater leaf area of control trees was responsible for greater transpirational water losses causing faster depletion of soil water reserves and a greater decline in <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> despite lower overall sap flux densities in <bold>C</bold> plots (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F4">4</xref>A and B).The response of canopy conductance to changes in VPD did not vary between the treatments, suggesting that stomatal sensitivity to atmospheric evaporative demand was not affected by the experimental manipulation. In contrast to that, <italic>g</italic><sub>C</sub> decreased much faster in response to falling <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> in the <bold>H</bold> treatment than in the control (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F5">5</xref>). The differential response of <italic>g</italic><sub>C</sub> to decreasing soil water availability is probably mediated by plant hydraulic conductance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C5">Cohen and Naor 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C6">Domec <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Hydraulic measurements performed on aspen trees in 2010 revealed that both soil-to-branch and leaf hydraulic conductances expressed per unit leaf area were smaller in humidified trees, although growing in moister soil (A. Sellin, unpubl. res.). Under conditions of soil water deficit the lower hydraulic capacity probably becomes a crucial factor for <bold>H</bold> trees, limiting leaf water supply and inducing a steep decline in canopy conductance. Furthermore, an experiment with silver birch revealed that a rapid water deficit in <bold>H</bold> plants led to a faster decrease in hydraulic conductance—responsible for liquid water supply—compared with the decrease in <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>, which limits water losses, and exposed plants to a greater risk of dehydration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C43">Sellin <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).Lowering <italic>A</italic><sub>n</sub> and <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and increasing IWUE are typical responses to water stress in plant species with a drought avoidance strategy. When plants encounter a soil water deficit, abscisic acid (ABA) is synthesized in the roots and translocated to the leaf through the transpiration stream (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C3">Assmann and Shimazaki 1999</xref>); higher concentrations of ABA in leaves drive mechanisms leading to a decrease in <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and an increase in WUE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C28">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C31">Pantin <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> propose that ABA promotes stomatal closure in two ways—via its widely known biochemical effect on guard cells and via an indirect hydraulic effect through a decrease in leaf hydraulic conductance. Maintaining stable gas exchange attributes during drought development means that a plant either possesses a drought tolerance strategy or lacks adaptations with respect to drought. <italic>Populus tremula</italic>, one of the parent species, is known to act as a drought avoider (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C34">Possen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). In our case, the lack of variation in gas exchange characteristics in <bold>C</bold> plots with respect to soil water status (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F6">6</xref>) and modification of gas exchange in <bold>H</bold> plots by altering water availability can be explained by the lower <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> values in the <bold>C</bold> treatment (i.e. long-term effects mediated by ABA).Regardless of the difference in <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> between the treatments, there was still an effect of the humidity manipulation on <italic>g</italic><sub>s sat</sub> and IWUE (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU021TB3">3</xref>). In fact, the differences in leaf gas exchange between the <bold>C</bold> and <bold>H</bold> plots are attributable to the combined effects of soil water availability and increased atmospheric humidity. As such, our first hypothesis is supported by the experiment: growing at higher RH increases stomatal conductance in trees while lowering photosynthetic WUE (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU021TB2">2</xref>), while the effect is largely mediated by changes in soil water status.Soil water potential influenced both <italic>V</italic><sub>C max</sub> and <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> in hybrid aspen (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU021TB3">3</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C17">Grassi <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> found a positive relationship between <italic>V</italic><sub>C max</sub> and <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> in oak and ash trees during summer, as in hybrid aspen in this study. A simulation by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C16">Grassi and Magnani (2005)</xref> indicated that 30–40 % of the biochemical limitation could be attributed to a reduction in leaf nitrogen content during droughty summers. Plant photosynthetic capacity and leaf N content expressed per leaf area are positively correlated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C17">Grassi <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C50">van de Weg <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Previous work at the FAHM experimental site has shown that rising RH reduces the water flux in silver birch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C25">Kupper <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) and alters the nutritional status of leaves, leading to a decline in photosynthetic capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C42">Sellin <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). In this experiment, humidification increased rather than decreased water flux through the trees (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F4">4</xref>), which explains why the biochemical capacity of photosynthesis was unaffected by the manipulation, but by changes in <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU021TB3">3</xref>). The second hypothesis concerning reduced photosynthetic capacity of leaves due to the expectedly smaller N uptake in humidified trees remained unconfirmed. The absence of an impact of air humidity manipulation on photosynthetic machinery of hybrid aspen was also supported by chlorophyll fluorescence measurements performed in the droughty summer of 2012 (A. Niglas, unpubl. res.).High RH can affect stomatal sensitivity by changing stomatal morphology: plants grown at higher RH have larger stomata that close to a lesser extent when leaves dry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C15">Giday <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). In addition, long-term acclimation to high RH during growth increases heterogeneity in stomatal response characteristics to short-term exposure to stomatal closure-inducing factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C30">Nejad and Van Meeteren 2005</xref>). Experiments showing differences in stomatal sensitivity and morphology between plants grown at high and low RH have been carried out under stable/controlled environmental conditions. The conditions before a leaf is fully expanded are important determinants on whether stomatal closure capacity is affected by leaf dehydration and RH. Moreover, the degree of stomatal adaptation in expanding leaves depends on the duration and timing of the exposure to high RH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C10">Fanourakis <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The present study was performed under field conditions with natural diurnal fluctuations of RH; misting was applied when ambient RH was &lt;75 % and could be increased to as much as 18 % (versus 60 and 95 % of RH in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C10">Fanourakis <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Our data suggest that stomatal sensitivity to atmospheric VPD remained unaffected in saplings of hybrid aspen. Although we did not explore stomatal dimensions, we presume that differences in morphology and the putative morphological effect on stomatal sensitivity were rather minor as our trees grew <italic>in natura</italic>, in both diurnally and seasonally variable environments, under conditions requiring flexible stomatal adjustment.The findings that stomatal conductance decreases and photosynthesis increases with rising external CO<sub>2</sub> level are well-known phenomena (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C1">Araújo <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). A steeper <italic>A</italic><sub>n</sub> response to <italic>C</italic><sub>a</sub> in <bold>H</bold> plots is attributable to higher stomatal conductance (evidenced by <italic>g</italic><sub>s max</sub>) due to leaf development under lower VPD (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU021TB2">2</xref>). This is indirectly confirmed also by the negative correlation between <italic>A</italic><sub>n</sub> and <italic>L</italic><sub>S</sub> in the <bold>C</bold> treatment.Initial intrinsic water-use efficiency responded more sensitively to <italic>C</italic><sub>a</sub> in <bold>C</bold> plots than in <bold>H</bold> plots (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F7">7</xref>), testifying once more to the effect of elevated atmospheric humidity on leaf gas exchange. Because high IWUE is advantageous to plants under drought conditions, a slower response in high-RH-grown trees to changing ambient conditions may be disadvantageous in the case of abrupt climatic fluctuations becoming more frequent in the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C7">Easterling <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>); these plants are not able to adjust their water use as quickly as plants grown in drier air and experience greater water loss. Thus, our results support the third hypothesis on the capacity of plants to modify WUE under changing environmental conditions, albeit not directly tested with respect to air humidity.The above-ground growth response of aspen trees to humidification in 2011 demonstrated some trends in contrast to those observed in previous years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C48">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>). However, the positive effect of humidification was detectable only in current-year height increments, while overall dimensions remained smaller in <bold>H</bold> plots, where hybrid aspen trees had grown slower than in <bold>C</bold> plots in the two previous experimental years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C48">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>). The inverse growth response is also attributable to dry weather conditions prevailing in summer 2011. Generally <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> or experimental plot was the more significant factor influencing tree growth response than humidity manipulation. One must take into account that the two factors—<italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub> and treatment—are partly interrelated, as transpirational flux through trees was lower in <bold>H</bold> plots (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F4">4</xref>A; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C25">Kupper <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C48">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>) and more water was retained in the soil (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU021F2">2</xref>). However, the humidity manipulation also had an impact on growth when considering the effect of <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>S</sub>; thus, the humidification effect on tree growth was clearly not due solely to altered soil water availability. In average or rainy years, when soil water does not limit growth, lowered transpiration hinders nutrient uptake by trees in <bold>H</bold> plots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C48">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>), especially for nutrients migrating to the roots with mass flow in soil. Under these conditions increased atmospheric humidity does not improve the growth rate of hybrid aspen. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C42">Sellin <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> also showed that humidification treatment lowers the photosynthetic capacity and growth rate of silver birch in moist summers. In dry years, when soil water availability limits growth, the impact of this mechanism is obviously irrelevant.The current study demonstrates that higher air humidity mitigates the effect of low soil water availability on broadleaved trees during dry years by reducing stomatal limitation to photosynthesis, allowing higher net photosynthetic rates and supporting higher growth rates (relative height growth). At the same time, higher RH increases the sensitivity of canopy conductance to water deficit and reduces the responsiveness of IWUE to factors inducing stomatal closure. The present and our earlier results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C48">Tullus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C42">Sellin <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU021C43">2014</xref>) imply that a future rise in atmospheric humidity at high latitudes may be disadvantageous in evenly rainy/humid years and expose trees to a higher dehydration risk during weather extremes, although mitigating the impact of soil water deficit under moderate drought.This study was supported by the <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">Estonian Science Foundation</grant-sponsor> (Grant no. <grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">8333</grant-num>), by the <grant-sponsor id="cs2" rid="cn2" xlink:type="simple">Estonian Ministry of Education and Research</grant-sponsor> (target financing project <grant-num id="cn2" rid="cs2" xlink:type="simple">SF0180025s12</grant-num>), and by the <grant-sponsor id="cs3" rid="cn3" xlink:type="simple">EU through the European Social Fund</grant-sponsor> (Mobilitas postdoctoral grant <grant-num id="cn3" rid="cs3" xlink:type="simple">MJD 257</grant-num>) and the European Regional Development Fund (Project No. 3.2.0802.11-0043 ‘BioAtmos’ and Centre of Excellence in Environmental Adaptation).A.N. and A.S. designed and performed the experiment, and wrote the manuscript. P.K. and A.T. performed the experiment, analysed the data and revised the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.None declared.We are grateful to Kristina Lubenets for installing sap flow gauges, Jaak Sõber for operating the FAHM humidification system and providing weather data, and Robert Szava-Kovats for language revision.