Molecular basis of floral petaloidy: insights from androecia of <italic>Canna indica</italic>Tracking the development of the petaloid fertile stamen in <italic>Canna indica</italic>: insights into the origin of androecial petaloidy in the ZingiberalesMolecular and genetic analyses of the <italic>silky1</italic> gene reveal conservation in floral organ specification between eudicots and monocotsA novel class of MADS box genes is involved in ovule development in petuniaEvidence for the involvement of Globosa-like gene duplications and expression divergence in the evolution of floral morphology in the ZingiberalesEvolutionary conservation of angiosperm flower development at the molecular and genetic levelsGenetic interactions among floral homeotic genes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Complementary floral homeotic phenotypes result from opposite orientations of a transposon at the plena-locus of <italic>Antirrhinum</italic>Floral organ identity: 20 years of ABCsGenetic footprints of stamen ancestors guide perianth evolution in <italic>Persea</italic> (Lauraceae)The war of the whorls: genetic interactions controlling flower developmentMonocotyledon evolution—characters and phylogenetic estimationThe <italic>SEP4</italic> gene of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> functions in floral organ and meristem identityIsolation of two putative homologues of <italic>PISTILLATA</italic> and <italic>AGAMOUS</italic> from <italic>Alpinia oblongifolia</italic> (Zingiberaceae) and characterization of their expressionPollination biology of <italic>Canna indica</italic> (Cannaceae) with particular reference to the functional morphology of the styleFunction and regulation of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> floral homeotic gene <italic>PISTILLATA</italic>Regulation of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> floral homeotic gene <italic>Apetala1</italic>Bracteomania, an inflorescence anomaly, is caused by the loss of function of the MADS-box gene <italic>Squamosa</italic> in <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic>The homeotic gene <italic>Apetala3</italic> of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> encodes a MADS box and is expressed in petals and stamensControl of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flower and seed development by the homeotic gene <italic>APETALA2</italic>Identification of class B and class C floral organ identity genes from rice plantsHeterotopic expression of class B floral homeotic genes supports a modified ABC model for tulip (<italic>Tulipa gesneriana</italic>)Floral organ identity genes involved in tepal development in <italic>asparagus</italic>Class B gene expression and the modified ABC model in nongrass monocotsExpression of floral MADS-box genes in basal angiosperms: implications for the evolution of floral regulatorsA simple method for estimating evolutionary rate of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequencesFloral organogenesis in five genera of the Marantaceae and in <italic>Canna</italic> (Cannaceae)Complex patterns of gene duplication in the <italic>APETALA3</italic> and <italic>PISTILLATA</italic> lineages of the RanunculaceaeThe Phylogeny and classification of the ZingiberalesMolecular characterization of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> floral homeotic gene <italic>APETALA1</italic><italic>WAG</italic>, a wheat <italic>AGAMOUS</italic> homolog, is associated with development of pistil-like stamens in alloplasmic wheatsDiversification of C-function activity in maize flower developmentFloral vasculature and ontogeny in <italic>Canna indica</italic> LMADS about the evolution of orchid flowersWhy are orchid flowers so diverse? Reduction of evolutionary constraints by paralogues of class B floral homeotic genesCharacterization of three GLOBOSA-like MADS-box genes from maize: evidence for ancient paralogy in one class of floral homeotic B-function genes of grassesB and C floral organ identity functions require <italic>SEPALLATA</italic> MADS-box genesEvolution of zygomorphy in monocot flowers: iterative patterns and developmental constraints<italic>Deficiens</italic>, a homeotic gene involved in the control of flower morphogenesis in <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic>—the protein shows homology to transcription factorsIsolation and characterization of three MADS-box genes from <italic>Alpinia hainanensis</italic> (Zingiberaceae)Estimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions in the control region of mitochondrial DNA in humans and chimpanzeesDevelopment of floral organ identity: stories from the MADS housePlant biology—floral quartetsThe CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis toolsPhylogeny of the Scitamineae—morphological and anatomical considerations<italic>Globosa</italic>—a homeotic gene which interacts with deficiens in the control of <italic>Antirrhinum</italic> floral organogenesisFloral organogenesis in <italic>Tulipa</italic>The protein encoded by the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homeotic gene agamous resembles transcription factors<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Chelsea D. SpechtThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Floral organs usually take on the characteristics of petals in ginger plants. In <italic>Canna indica</italic>, the most ornamental parts of the flowers are considered to be staminode, which means rudimentary and sterile stamen. However, the precise nature of these petaloid organs is yet to be determined. Two floral organ identity genes GLOBOSA (GLO) and AGAMOUS (AG) are isolated from <italic>Canna indica</italic>. Their expression patterns suggest that petaloid staminodes and labellum are of androecium identity, in agreement with their position within the flower. But the current molecular, morphological and anatomical data, are still not sufficient to explain the distinct morphology observed in staminodes and fertile stamen in <italic>Canna indica</italic>.Floral organs that take on the characteristics of petals can occur in all whorls of the monocot order Zingiberales. In <italic>Canna indica</italic>, the most ornamental or ‘petaloid’ parts of the flowers are of androecial origin and are considered staminodes. However, the precise nature of these petaloid organs is yet to be determined. In order to gain a better understanding of the genetic basis of androecial identity, a molecular investigation of B- and C-class genes was carried out. Two MADS-box genes <italic>GLOBOSA</italic> (<italic>GLO</italic>) and <italic>AGAMOUS</italic> (<italic>AG</italic>) were isolated from young inflorescences of <italic>C. indica</italic> by 3′ rapid amplification of cDNA ends polymerase chain reaction (3′-RACE PCR). Sequence characterization and phylogenetic analyses show that <italic>CiGLO</italic> and <italic>CiAG</italic> belong to the B- and C-class MADS-box gene family, respectively. <italic>CiAG</italic> is expressed in petaloid staminodes, the labellum, the fertile stamen and carpels. <italic>CiGLO</italic> is expressed in petals, petaloid staminodes, the labellum, the fertile stamen and carpels. Expression patterns in mature tissues of <italic>CiGLO</italic> and <italic>CiAG</italic> suggest that petaloid staminodes and the labellum are of androecial identity, in agreement with their position within the flower and with described <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> expression patterns. Although B- and C-class genes are important components of androecial determination, their expression patterns are not sufficient to explain the distinct morphology observed in staminodes and the fertile stamen in <italic>C. indica</italic>.A landmark accomplishment in plant developmental biology was the proposition of the ABC model of flower organ identity. This model provides a framework for describing a conserved pattern of gene expressions associated with the specification of floral organs in model species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C6">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C10">Coen and Meyerowitz 1991</xref>). Soon after its proposition, other floral identity genes including D- and E-class genes were identified and the ABC model was then extended to an ABCDE model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C3">Angenent <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C37">Pelaz <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C12">Ditta <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). ABC model genes, with the exception of <italic>APETALA2</italic> (<italic>AP2</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C20">Jofuku <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>), belong to the MADS-box family of transcription factors. In angiosperms, MADS-box transcription factors are important components of various developmental processes, although the most well-characterized MADS-box genes to date are involved in floral organ identity and initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C43">Theißen and Saedler 2001</xref>).The ABC model has been extensively characterized due to molecular studies in two model plants, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C50">Yanofsky <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C19">Jack <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C30">Mandel <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C16">Goto and Meyerowitz 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C17">Gustafsonbrown <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>) and <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C39">Sommer <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C18">Huijser <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C46">Trobner <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C7">Bradley <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>). Studies in other angiosperm lineages generally support the idea that the expression patterns described by the ABC model are widely conserved, at least among eudicots. However, the extent to which the eudicot-based ABC model of flower organ identity describes floral morphologies in monocots is still not well understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C2">Ambrose <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>).The role of A-class genes appears to be conserved only in the lineage containing <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C8">Causier <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), and to date the A-function of the ABC model has not been shown to play a role in organ identity in monocots. Studies carried out in maize, rice and wheat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C32">Mena <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C21">Kang <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C2">Ambrose <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C36">Munster <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C31">Meguro <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>), however, do indicate that B- and C-class genes and gene activities are somewhat conserved between grasses and eudicots, despite evidence for gene duplication in various lineages. However, the derived morphology of grass flowers results in inconclusive debates regarding the interpretation of the lemma and palea as equivalent to sepals and petals of eudicots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C5">Bowman 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C2">Ambrose <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). Also, studies in other monocot lineages such as the Liliaceae show divergent results from those predicted by the canonical BC model. In this family, flowers have two outer whorls of almost identical petaloid organs called tepals. In order to explain such a derived pattern, a modified BC model has been proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C47">Van Tunen <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>) and ascertained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C22">Kanno <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). In this modified model, B-class genes are expressed in whorl 1 as well as whorls 2 and 3, resulting in similar expression patterns in whorls 1 and 2 and, therefore, similar petaloid structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C24">Kanno <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). However, the expression patterns of B-class genes in asparagus, for instance, do not fit this model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C23">Kanno <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>).Furthermore, the intricate morphology and unprecedented diversity of orchid floral morphology has resulted in a proposed ‘orchid code’ that builds on the BC model. This idea assumes that the identity of the different perianth organs is specified by the combinatorial interaction of four <italic>DEF</italic>-like MADS-box genes with other floral homeotic genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C34">Mondragón-Palomino and Theißen 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C35">2009</xref>).Owing to the lack of consistency regarding the conservation of the BC model in monocots, it is likely that further studies on other non-grass, petaloid monocots will provide a novel understanding of the evolution of floral organ identity specification outside the eudicots.The Zingiberales is an order of tropical monocots and consists of eight families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C45">Tomlinson 1962</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C11">Dahlgren and Rasmussen 1983</xref>). The families are often divided into two groups: the paraphyletic ‘banana group’ (including Musaceae, Streliziaceae, Heliconiaceae and Lowiaeae) with five (occasionally six) fertile stamens, and the monophyletic ‘ginger group’ (including Zingiberaceae, Costaceae, Cannaceae and Marantaceae) with one or a half fertile stamen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C29">Kress 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C38">Rudall and Bateman 2004</xref>). Thus, an impressive reduction in the number of fertile stamens occurred in the ancestor of the ginger clade.The Cannaceae family is derived within the Zingiberales with only a single fertile stamen, further reduced to a single theca (half of a fertile stamen) with a prominent, expanded petaloid appendage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C27">Kirchoff 1983</xref>). For many years, the interpretation of the androecium members of the Cannaceae has sparked much debate, especially regarding the developmental origins of the stamen and the labellum in <italic>Canna indica</italic> (see the brief review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C33">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). In recent years, this scientific problem has been the subject of both morphological observations and molecular studies. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C1">Almeida <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> combined a developmental study of the petaloid fertile stamen with data on the expression of three B-class and two C-class floral organ identity genes to elucidate the organogenesis of the petaloid stamen and staminodes. In that study, the authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C1">Almeida <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) proposed that the canonical BC model is not sufficient to explain petaloidy in the androecial whorl in <italic>Canna</italic> sp. In addition, based on floral vasculature and ontogeny, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C33">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> suggested that the labellum incorporates two androecial members from both the outer and inner whorls, one diverging from the carpellary dorsal bundle and the other from the parietal bundle. The functional stamen also incorporates two androecial members from both the outer and inner whorls. In order to obtain a better understanding of the identity of the androecium members, we carried out a molecular investigation of <italic>C. indica</italic> B- and C-class genes. Based on our molecular results, we discuss the identity of the androecium members in <italic>C. indica</italic> in the context of the current molecular, morphological and anatomical data.Complete (left) and dissected (right) mature flower of <italic>C. indica</italic>. S, sepal; P, petal; PS, petaloid staminode; L, labellum; FS, fertile stamen; St, style; C, carpel.Fresh floral materials were wrapped in aluminium foil, flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and preserved at −80 °C to avoid RNA degradation. To ensure RNase-free materials, the plastic experimental apparatus were dipped in DEPC dH<sub>2</sub>O overnight, whereas all the glass apparatus and mortar are sterilized at 180 °C in the pressure vapour sterilizer overnight before the experiment. Total RNA was extracted from at least 100 mg of floral materials using the Plant RNA Extraction Reagent kit according to the manufacturer's instructions (Bioteke, China). The RNA pellet was re-eluted in 40 μL of RNase-free ddH<sub>2</sub>O and stored at −80 °C. RNA quality was characterized by running 4 μL of extracted RNA through 1.0 % agarose gel electrophoresis. Four microlitres (∼10 μg) of RNA was used in a reverse transcription into cDNA using a poly-T primer designed with software Primer Premier 5 (3′-RACE primer: AAG CAG TGG TAT CAA CGC AGA GTA CTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT T) and M-MLV (Invitrogen SuperScriptIII First-Strand Synthesis System for RT-PCR, USA) following the manufacturer's protocol. The success of the reverse transcription reaction was assessed by amplifying 18sRNA from the cDNA, using the following primer pair: 1265S: GGC TAC CAC ATC CAA GGA AG; 1265AS: CCA TTA AAT AGG TAG GAG C.cDNA was diluted 10 times in dH<sub>2</sub>O, and 4 μL of the dilution was used in 20 μL polymerase chain reaction (PCR) reactions containing 1 μL of 20 μM of each of the forward and reverse primers, 1 U of Taq DNA polymerase (TaKaRa, Japan), 2 μL of dNTP (2 mM) and 2 μL of 10× PCR buffer. The forward primers were designed according to the MADS domain and a RACE-AP Reverse. Two degenerate primer pair combinations were designed according to the conserved region in some monocot plants and were used for each cDNA sample: RACE-AP(R): AAGCAGTGGTATCAACGCAGAGTACGCGGG; GLO-F: ATGGGGCGMGGRAAGATCGAGATCAAG; AG-F: ATGGGSMGRGGRAAGATCGAGATC.Cycling conditions were set as follows: initial denaturation at 94 °C for 3 min, touchdown procedure from 62 to 48 °C, 15 amplification cycles (94 °C for 30 s, 62 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 1 min), the cycle of 48 °C followed by another 15 amplification cycles (94 °C for 30 s, 54 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 1 min) and a final extension step carried out at 72 °C for 10 min.The full volumes of the PCR reactions were run on 1.0 % agarose gels and bands of the appropriate size (800 bp–1 kb) were excised and cloned on PMD18-T vectors (TaKaRa). Positive colonies were identified by bacterial colony PCR. Then, all the positive clones (six to eight) were picked from each cloning reaction and sequenced using T-vector-specific primers M13-47 and M13-48. All colonies were sequenced to verify identity, and two sequences were submitted to GenBank.Analyses of the obtained sequences as well as their inferred amino acid translations were performed using the NCBI Blast program (<uri xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</uri>). Alignments of the deduced amino acid sequences were carried out by ClustalX v2.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C44">Thompson <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>).Forty MADS-box B-, C- and D-class genes including the two genes of this study were downloaded from NCBI (<uri xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore</uri>) and a multiple sequence alignment was performed. Gene and species names as well as accession numbers are as follows: <italic>AG</italic> (X53579), <italic>AtSHP1</italic> (M55550), <italic>AtSHP2</italic> (M55553), <italic>AtAGL1</italic> (NM_001084842), <italic>AtAP3</italic> (M86357) and <italic>STK</italic> (U20182) of <italic>A. thaliana</italic>; <italic>AmGLO</italic> (AB516403) and <italic>PLE</italic> (S53900) of <italic>A. majus</italic>; <italic>AhMADS5</italic> (AY621154), <italic>AhMADS6</italic> and <italic>AhMADS8</italic> (AY621156) of <italic>Alpinia hainanensis</italic>; <italic>AoAP3</italic> (EF521817), <italic>AoAG</italic> (DQ286724) and <italic>AoPI</italic> (DQ286723) of <italic>Alpinia oblongifolia</italic>; <italic>FBP11</italic> (X81852), <italic>FBP6</italic> (X68675) and <italic>PMADS2</italic> (X69947) of <italic>Petunia</italic>×<italic>hybrida</italic>; <italic>TAG1</italic> (XM_004232947), <italic>TAGL1</italic> (NM_001247258) and <italic>TAGL11</italic> (NM_001247265) of <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>; <italic>WAG</italic> (AB084577) and <italic>WAG2</italic> (AB465688) of <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>; <italic>ZMM2</italic> (NM_001111456), <italic>ZmAG</italic> (NM_001112476), <italic>ZMM19</italic> (NM_001111678), <italic>ZMM29</italic> (AJ292961) and <italic>ZMM25</italic> (AJ430638) of <italic>Zea mays</italic>; <italic>BAG1</italic> (M99415) of <italic>Brassica napus</italic>; <italic>LrGLOA</italic> (AB071379) and <italic>LrGLOB</italic> (AB071380) of <italic>Lilium regale</italic>; <italic>TgGLO</italic> (AB094967) of <italic>Tulipa gesneriana</italic>; <italic>OsMADS2</italic> (L37526), <italic>OsMADS3</italic> (L37528), <italic>OsMADS13</italic> (AF151693) and <italic>OsMADS58</italic> (AB232157) of <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>; <italic>NtGLO</italic> (X67959), <italic>NAG1</italic> (L23925) and <italic>GLO</italic> (X67959) of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>; and <italic>CiAG</italic> (JQ180191) and <italic>CiGLO</italic> (JQ180192) of <italic>C. indica</italic>. The evolutionary history of the genes in the multiple sequence alignment was inferred by using maximum likelihood and the Tamura–Nei model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C41">Tamura and Nei 1993</xref>). The Kimura two-parameter model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C26">Kimura 1980</xref>) was also tested and resulted in the same tree topology. Initial trees for the heuristic search were obtained automatically by applying neighbour-joining and BioNJ algorithms to a matrix of pairwise distances estimated using the maximum composite likelihood (MCL) approach, and then selecting the topology with superior log likelihood value. Evolutionary analyses were conducted in MEGA6. Bootstrap values on the consensus trees were derived from 1000 bootstrap replicates.Because the gene sequences (accession numbers GU594899–GU594995) submitted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C4">Bartlett and Specht (2010)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C1">Almeida <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> are only partial CDS, they were not included in this phylogenetic construction.Four whorls of floral organs were dissected from <italic>C. indica</italic> flowers just before anthesis. The dissected whorls are as follows: sepals in whorl 1, petals in whorl 2, petaloid staminodes and the labellum in whorl 3o (outer androecial whorl), petaloid staminodes and a single fertile stamen in whorl 3i (inner androecial whorl) and carpels in whorl 4. These materials were then separately put into liquid nitrogen to avoid RNA degradation. Meanwhile, a fresh leaf was also collected, flash frozen and used as a reference material. RNA for real-time reverse transcription (RT)-PCR was extracted separately from the four whorls of the floral organs and leaf. RNA extraction was carried out using the Plant RNA Extraction Reagent Kit according to the manufacturer's instructions as described above (Bioteke). The RNA pellet was re-eluted in 40 μL of RNase-free ddH<sub>2</sub>O and stored at −80 °C. RNA quality was tested by running 2 μL of the extracted RNA through a 1.0 % agarose gel electrophoresis (AGE). RNA was quantified using a NanoDrop 1000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, USA). One microgram of RNA from each sample was reverse transcribed into cDNA for real-time RT-PCR following the manufacturer's protocol (TaKaRa, PrimeScript RT Master Mix Perfect Real Time).Primer pairs of the reference gene were designed according to the <italic>β-actin</italic> sequence of <italic>Musa acuminata</italic>, a member of the banana family. The primer pairs used for real-time RT-PCR are actin-F: TCCTTTCCCTCTATGCTAGTGGC; actin-R: CCTCCAATCCAGACACTGTACTTA; AG-F: TAGAGATTATGGGGCGAGGAA; AG-R: ATCCGAGTTGGAGGGCAGT; GLO-F: GAGGCACTCCAGATTGGGCTTAC; and GLO-R: TGGGAAAAGGATGACGGGAAG. Reagent concentrations were used as follows: 2× SYBR buffer solution (TaKaRa) 10 μL, RoxII 0.4 μL, dH<sub>2</sub>O 2 μL, reverse primer 0.8 μL (10 μM, 0.052 μg) and forward primer 0.8 μL (10 μM, 0.065 μg) and diluted cDNA 3 μL for the <italic>GLO</italic> reaction system and 6 μL for the <italic>AG</italic> reaction system. Owing to the already described low expression of <italic>AG</italic>, the volume of diluted cDNA was doubled for the <italic>AG</italic> reaction. Each reaction was amplified by two pairs of primers and processed with three biological replicates of the six floral organs extracted from multiple flowers: sepals, petals, petaloid staminodes, labellum, fertile stamens and carpels. <italic>β-Actin</italic> was amplified from the six floral organs as a reference. The real-time RT-PCR was run on an ABI7500 (USA) for 45 cycles, and cycling conditions were set as follows: pre-heating at 95 °C for 30 s, PCR reaction at 95 °C for 3 s followed by 60 °C for 30 s, and melt curve stage at 95 °C for 15 s, 60 °C for 60 s and 95 °C for 15 s. The relative quantization approach through a DeltaDelta CT method was used to analyse the results of real-time PCR experiments. ABI 7500 software v2.0.1 was used to collect data and carry out the statistical analysis.Two positive sequences of MADS-box genes were obtained and identified as B- and C-class MADS-box homologue genes. The cDNA clones were named <italic>CiGLO</italic> and <italic>CiAG</italic>, respectively. Both cDNA clones encode MIKC-type proteins.Alignments of deduced amino acid sequences. Identical amino acids with a consensus sequence are shaded, and a hyphen represents a gap inserted to optimize alignment. (A) <italic>CiAG</italic> and other proteins of the AG-like subfamily. (B) <italic>CiGLO</italic> and other proteins of the GLOBOSA subfamily.<italic>CiGLO</italic> cDNA is 870 bp long containing a poly-A signal encoding a protein of 210 amino acids, and the coding region is 633 bp long. <italic>CiGLO</italic> is similar in sequence to the GLOBOSA subfamily in comparison to other MADS-box genes from GenBank including <italic>Canna</italic> sp<italic>.</italic> (GU594945), <italic>A. oblongifolia</italic> (ABB92623), <italic>A. hainanensis</italic> (AAT99429), <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (NP_197524), <italic>O. sativa (</italic>NP_001045012) and <italic>N. tabacum (</italic>Q03416). The <italic>CiGLO</italic> gene shows strong homology with members in the GLO-like subfamily, and with 99 % similarity to <italic>CsGLO2</italic> (GU594945) of <italic>Canna</italic> sp. (a species located in America) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C4">Bartlett and Specht 2010</xref>) as illustrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU015F2">2</xref>B. <italic>CiGLO</italic> also has no less than 90 % similarity to <italic>PoGLO2</italic> (GU594953) of <italic>Phrynium oliganthum</italic>, <italic>HwGLO2</italic> (GU594953) of <italic>Heliconia wagneriana</italic>, <italic>SjGLO2</italic> (GU594935) of <italic>Stromanthe jacquinii</italic>, <italic>OmGLO2</italic> (GU594936) of <italic>Orchidantha maxillarioides</italic> as well as <italic>MlGLO2</italic> (GU594949.1) of <italic>Marantochloa leucantha</italic> as reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C4">Bartlett and Specht (2010)</xref>.Phylogenetic tree constructed using maximum likelihood methods in MEGA. Numbers above the internal branches give bootstrap probabilities of &gt;50. Genes of <italic>C. indica</italic> isolated in this study are underlined. Groups are indicated by the vertical bars at the right margin.Expression patterns of <italic>CiAG</italic> and <italic>CiGLO</italic> in different floral organs and leaves of <italic>C. indica</italic>. The bars on top of each lane in the histogram mean standard error (SE).<italic>CiAG</italic> expression signals were observed in both the outer and inner whorls of staminodes (including petaloid staminodes and the labellum), the fertile stamen and carpels. However, <italic>CiAG</italic> expression was not observed in sepals and petals as previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C1">Almeida <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). In other words, <italic>CiAG</italic> was expressed in floral organs of whorls 3 and 4, and not expressed in whorls 1 and 2, similar to the expression pattern of other AG-like homologues' based on the BC model. The strongest expression signal of <italic>CiAG</italic> was detected in the labellum of whorl 3o.<italic>CiGLO</italic> expression was observed in petals, the outer whorl of petaloid staminodes, the labellum and the fertile stamen as well as carpels, while it was not observed in sepals. In other words, <italic>CiGLO</italic> was expressed in the floral organs of whorls 2, 3 and 4, but was not expressed in whorl 1. The strongest expression signal of <italic>CiGLO</italic> was detected in the inner whorl where the single fertile stamen is initiated.In addition, the <italic>CiAG</italic> expression signal was also detected in the leaf, whereas no <italic>CiGLO</italic> expression signal was detected in the leaf.Morphological and anatomical studies of <italic>C. indica</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C27">Kirchoff 1983</xref>) have shown that the sequence of floral organ initiation is as follows: calyx (sepals), corolla (petals), inner androecial whorl, outer androecial whorl and gynoecium. The developmental work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C27">Kirchoff (1983)</xref> supports the hypothesis proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C13">Eichler (1875)</xref>, that the stamen, the labellum and one of the staminodes (the inner staminode) represent the inner androecial whorl while the remaining one or two petaloid staminodes represent the outer androecial whorl. The nature of the labellum was not formulated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C27">Kirchoff (1983</xref>).The most extraordinary and ornamental parts in the flower of <italic>Canna</italic> L. are staminodes, which are usually taxonomically interpreted as petals by people (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C48">Wu and Chen 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C49">2000</xref>). In the flora of China, <italic>Canna</italic> flowers are interpreted as having two whorls of petaloid staminodes, with the reflexed staminode in the inner whorl referred to as the ‘labellum’. The labellum is narrower than the outer whorl of staminodes and is useful in distinguishing among species of <italic>Canna</italic>. In the light of their statements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C48">Wu and Chen 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C49">2000</xref>), the androecium members, except for the fertile stamen, were replaced by petaloid staminodes and the labellum. However, no detailed evidence has been put forward.In the present study, two genes, <italic>CiGLO</italic> and <italic>CiAG</italic>, have been isolated from <italic>C. indica</italic>. Sequence characterization and phylogenetic relationships indicate that they belong to B- and C-class gene families, respectively. The described expression patterns in eudicot model species indicate that stamens are determined by B- and C-class genes in whorl 3, whereas C-class genes are essential for carpels in whorl 4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C42">Theißen 2001</xref>). The expression pattern in different floral organs analysed by qPCR shows that <italic>CiAG</italic> was expressed in whorl 3o of petaloid staminodes and the labellum, whorl 3i of petaloid staminodes plus the fertile stamen, and whorl 4 of carpels, while it was not expressed in whorl 1 of sepals and whorl 2 of petals. The qPCR results of <italic>CiAG</italic> are largely consistent with the expression patterns of C-class genes, as described in eudicot model species. In the study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C1">Almeida <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>, two copies of <italic>AGAMOUS</italic> genes were isolated from <italic>C. indica</italic>, and RT-PCR was used to assess the expression pattern. The genes <italic>AG-1</italic> and <italic>AG-2</italic> show an expanded pattern of expression when compared with the canonical BC model. <italic>AG-1</italic> is expressed in a gradient increasing from sepals to gynoecium while <italic>AG-2</italic> is evenly expressed in all floral parts studied except in petals. At that time, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C1">Almeida <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> did not amplify the full-length sequences for the two genes. According to the accession number, <italic>AG-1</italic> may be a part of <italic>CiAG</italic> of our study. The expression patterns of <italic>AG-1</italic> and <italic>CiAG</italic> are slighly different, which may result from the different reseach methods used. Moreover, the expression signal of <italic>CiAG</italic> has been detected in the leaf. <italic>CiAG</italic> expressed in non-floral tissue as well as in floral organs is in accordance with the research of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C25">Kim <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> in some basal angiosperms and of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C9">Chanderbali <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> in <italic>Pe.am.AG</italic> of <italic>Persea</italic> from the Lauraceae family. In this study, the authors proposed that the expression of <italic>AG</italic> in vegetative tissue is an evolutionary novelty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C9">Chanderbali <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C9">Chanderbali <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> also hypothesized that the tepals of <italic>Persea</italic> and perhaps in other Lauraceae are derived from stamen primordia on the basis of gene expression and the occasional presence of tepaloid organs in stamen whorls.<italic>CiGLO</italic> was expressed in whorl 2 of petals, whorl 3o of petaloid staminodes and the labellum, whorl 3i of petaloid staminodes and the single fertile stamen, and whorl 4 of carpels, while it was not expressed in whorl 1 of sepals. The expression of <italic>CiGLO</italic> in whorls 2, 3 and 4 seems consistent neither with the aforementioned modified monocot BC model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C47">Van Tunen AJ 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C22">Kanno <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C24">Kanno <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) nor with the shifting/sliding boundary model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C5">Bowman 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C28">Kramer <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>), although it is still consistent with the canonical BC model of eudicots. The ‘shifting boundary’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C6">Bowman <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>) and ‘sliding boundary’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C28">Kramer <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>) models allow the boundary of expression of the B-class genes to ‘slide’ from that observed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>Antirrhinum</italic> to one that includes the outer perianth whorl (outer tepals) of <italic>Ranunculus</italic>, <italic>Tulipa</italic> and other species with an entirely petaloid perianth. The extension of B-class gene expression into whorl 4 of carpels might explain the petaloidy observed in the style of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>indica</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C15">Glinos and Cocucci 2011</xref>).Two copies of <italic>GLOBOSA</italic> were studied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C1">Almeida <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>, and both <italic>GLO-1</italic> and <italic>GLO-2</italic> show an expansion in their expression domains. <italic>GLO-1</italic> and <italic>GLO-2</italic> show great similarity to <italic>CiGLO</italic> of our study, but they are only partial CDS, which makes it difficult to address the relationship between them and <italic>CiGLO</italic>. Further data are required to see whether <italic>CiGLO</italic> is a new copy due to its divergent expression patterns. Broad expression patterns observed for <italic>ZinGLO1</italic>, <italic>ZinGLO2</italic>, <italic>ZinGLO3</italic> and <italic>ZinGLO4</italic> support a combination hypothesis which supports the idea that labellum identity is a result of the combination of multiple <italic>GLO</italic> homologues rather than expression of a single orthologue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C4">Bartlett and Specht 2010</xref>). Whether the combination hypothesis is applicable in <italic>Canna</italic> needs broader investigation.In the canonical BC model, simultaneous expression of B- and C-class MADS-box genes would result in the specification of stamen identity. <italic>CiAG</italic> and <italic>CiGLO</italic> are expressed simultaneously in the labellum, petaloid staminodes and the fertile stamen in the present study. If molecular evidence is sufficient to determine organ identity, one could claim that these results suggest that the three floral organs are of the same identity. However, despite their similar expression patterns, these organs present very different morphologies. The role of B- and C-class genes in determining final organ morphology awaits further studies. Other studies, such as stage-specific <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization, would be necessary for a more complete picture of the expression profiles during development. <italic>In situ</italic> hybridization experiments carried out on a C-class gene <italic>AhMADS6</italic> and two B-class genes <italic>AhMADS5</italic> and <italic>AhMADS8</italic> of <italic>A. hainanensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C40">Song <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) have shown a case similar to the present study, which has corroborated the hypothesis that the labellum of <italic>A. hainanensis</italic> originated from stamens. Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C33">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> showed that the vascular bundle of the labellum of <italic>C. indica</italic> originates from two stamen primordia at an early developmental stage, providing anatomical evidence for the interpretation that the labellum should be regarded as a derivative of staminodes in the inner whorl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C33">Miao <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Although the molecular data presented in this study do not provide sufficient evidence to support that anatomical result, they are also not inconsistent with this interpretation. In accordance with the expression pattern of B- and C-class genes described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU015C1">Almeida <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>, our present data do not show differential expression patterns between fertile and sterile elements within the androecial whorl, and neither set of results can explain the observed petaloidy or how, mechanistically, the staminodes and the fertile stamen show distinct morphologies.Based on the expression patterns of B- and C-class genes, the molecular data presented in this study suggest that petaloid staminodes and the labellum are of androecial identity, in concordance with their position in the floral meristem and in agreement with largely described expression patterns in model species. However, these expression patterns are not sufficient to explain the distinct morphologies observed in staminodes and the fertile stamen. Broader and in-depth exploration of other copies of <italic>GLO</italic> and <italic>AG</italic> genes and sequence evolution, as well as a broader understanding of the involvement of B- and C-class genes in floral organ identity regulatory networks are required for a better understanding of the relationship between B- and C-class gene expression patterns and the floral organ morphology in <italic>Canna</italic>.Funding was provided by the Joint Fund South China Botanical Garden-Shanghai Institute of Plant Physiology &amp; Ecology, <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">National Natural Science Foundation of China</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">31200176, 31200246, 30900089</grant-num>) and Key Laboratory of Plant Resources Conservation and Sustainable Utilization, SCBG, CAS.Isolation of the sequences and real-time PCR analyses and data collection were accomplished by Q.F. following supervision by J.P.L. and the laboratory assistance of H.F.L. and P.Z. Phylogenetic analysis was performed by Y.F.K. Writing and editing and comprehensive revision of the manuscript was performed by Y.F.K. and A.M.R.A.None declared.Novel sequences have been submitted to NCBI (<uri xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov" xlink:type="simple">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</uri>). Accession numbers are <italic>Canna indica AGAMOUS</italic>, JQ180191 and <italic>Canna indica GLOBOSA</italic>, JQ180192.We thank Dr Juanjuan Song of South China Botanical Garden, Chinese Academy of Sciences for providing generous assistance in experiment design and Dr YingTong of South China Sea Institute of Oceanology, Chinese Academy of Sciences for help in using the NCBI database and MEGA software. A.M.R.A. would like to thank CAPES for her fellowship support (Bolsa Jovem Talentos, Brazil). We are also grateful to the two anonymous referees and the associate editor of the journal <italic>AoB PLANTS</italic> for their helpful comments.