Non-symbiotic haemoglobins—What's happening beyond nitric oxide scavenging?Ligand migration in nonsymbiotic hemoglobin AHb1 from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Ozone and nitric oxide interaction in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: a role for ethylene?The origin and functions of haemoglobin in plantsCloning and expression analysis of hemoglobin genes from maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic> ssp. <italic>mays</italic>) and teosinte (<italic>Zea mays</italic> ssp. <italic>parviglumis</italic>)Rice hemoglobins: gene cloning, analysis and oxygen-binding kinetics of a recombinant protein synthesized in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>The role of ascorbic acid in the control of flowering time and the onset of senescenceNitric oxide acts as an antioxidant and delays programmed cell death in barley aleurone layersThe <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> aleurone layer responds to nitric oxide, gibberellin, and abscisic acid and is sufficient and necessary for seed dormancyFunctioning haemoglobin genes in non-nodulating plantsLow oxygen sensing and balancing in plant seeds: a role for nitric oxideThe reactivity with CO of AHb1 and AHb2 from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> is controlled by the distal HisE7 and internal hydrophobic cavitiesRegulation of nonsymbiotic and truncated hemoglobin genes of <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic> in plant organs and in response to nitric oxide and hormonesNitric oxide participates in cold-responsive phosphosphingolipid formation and gene expression in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>The basic helix-loop-helix transcription factor MYC2 directly represses PLETHORA expression during jasmonate-mediated modulation of the root stem cell niche in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Nitric oxide acts downstream of auxin to trigger root ferric-chelate reductase activity in response to iron deficiency in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Nitric oxide plays a central role in determining lateral root development in tomatoNonsymbiotic hemoglobins and stress tolerance in plantsExpression of a stress-induced hemoglobin affects NO levels produced by alfalfa root cultures under hypoxic stressClass 1 hemoglobins, nitrate and NO levels in hypoxic maize cell suspension culturesHaemoglobin expression in germinating barleyStructural plasticity and functional implications of internal cavities in distal mutants of type 1 non-symbiotic hemoglobin AHb1 from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Active oxygen and cell death in cereal aleurone cellsRegulation of polar auxin transport by AtPIN1 in Arabidopsis vascular tissueA new model involving ethylene, nitric oxide and Fe to explain the regulation of Fe-acquisition genes in Strategy I plantsMolecular cloning and characterization of a moss (<italic>Ceratodon purpureus</italic>) nonsymbiotic hemoglobin provides insight into the early evolution of plant nonsymbiotic hemoglobinsPlant hemoglobins: what we know six decades after their discoveryExpression and in silico structural analysis of a rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) hemoglobin 5Cloning and characterization of a caesalpinoid (<italic>Chamaecrista fasciculata</italic>) hemoglobin: the structural transition from a nonsymbiotic hemoglobin to a leghemoglobinRegulation of tomato lateral root development by carbon monoxide and involvement in auxin and nitric oxideCarbon monoxide promotes root hair development in tomatoCrystal structure of a nonsymbiotic plant hemoglobinNitric oxide represses the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> floral transitionExpression of NO scavenging hemoglobin is involved in the timing of bolting in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Hemoglobin is essential for normal growth of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> organsArabidopsis RAP2.2: an ethylene response transcription factor that is important for hypoxia survivalThe structure and function of plant hemoglobinsNitric oxide mediates gravitropic bending in soybean rootsEarly signal transduction linking the synthesis of jasmonic acid in plantExpression and evolution of functionally distinct haemoglobin genes in plantsIncreased level of hemoglobin 1 enhances survival of hypoxic stress and promotes early growth in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Nitrate, NO and haemoglobin in plant adaptation to hypoxia: an alternative to classic fermentation pathwaysThe haemoglobin/nitric oxide cycle: involvement in flooding stress and effects on hormone signallingClass-1 hemoglobin and antioxidant metabolism in alfalfa rootsNitric oxide as an alternative electron carrier during oxygen deprivationAnoxic nitric oxide cycling in plants: participating reactions and possible mechanismsNO synthase-generated NO acts downstream of auxin in regulating Fe-deficiency-induced root branching that enhances Fe-deficiency tolerance in tomato plantsEndogenous <italic>PttHb1</italic> and <italic>PttTrHb</italic>, and heterologous <italic>Vitreoscilla vhb</italic> haemoglobin gene expression in hybrid aspen roots with ectomycorrhizal interactionStructure and reactivity of hexacoordinate hemoglobins<italic>SAUR39</italic>, a small auxin-up RNA gene, acts as a negative regulator of auxin synthesis and transport in riceDifferential response of gray poplar leaves and roots underpins stress adaptation during hypoxiaNitric oxide triggers phosphatidic acid accumulation via phospholipase D during auxin-induced adventitious root formation in cucumberMolecular cloning and characterization of cDNAs encoding hemoglobin from wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) and potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>)Transcript profiling of the anoxic rice coleoptileHRE1 and HRE2, two hypoxia-inducible ethylene response factors, affect anaerobic responses in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Synthesis of hemoglobins in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> var. Jackson) plants growing in normal and stress conditionsMapping and analysis of a hemoglobin gene family from <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>A Genome-wide analysis of the effects of sucrose on gene expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlings under anoxiaHemoglobin expression affects ethylene production in maize cell culturesOxidative stress, antioxidants and stress toleranceBiphasic ethylene production during the hypersensitive response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>: a window into defense priming mechanisms?Profiling translatomes of discrete cell populations resolves altered cellular priorities during hypoxia in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Common and distinct organ and stress responsive transcriptomic patterns in <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Ethylene regulates lateral root formation and auxin transport in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Nitric oxide, stomatal closure, and abiotic stressFactors required for the high CO<sub>2</sub> specificity of the anaerobically induced maize GapC4 promoter in transgenic tobaccoLigand migration and binding in nonsymbiotic hemoglobins of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Signal transmission in the plant immune responseInduction of class-1 non-symbiotic hemoglobin genes by nitrate, nitrite and nitric oxide in cultured rice cellsNitric oxide and cyclic GMP are messengers in the indole acetic acid-induced adventitious rooting processNitric oxide mediates the indole acetic acid induction activation of a mitogen-activated protein kinase cascade involved in adventitious root developmentA novel nonsymbiotic hemoglobin from oak: cellular and tissue specificity of gene expressionGH3-mediated auxin homeostasis links growth regulation with stress adaptation response in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Truncated hemoglobins in actinorhizal nodules of <italic>Datisca glomerata</italic><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> nonsymbiotic hemoglobin AHb1 modulates nitric oxide bioactivityAuxin and nitric oxide control indeterminate nodule formationThe GTPase ARF1p controls the sequence-specific vacuolar sorting route to the lytic vacuole<italic>GhHb1</italic>: a nonsymbiotic hemoglobin gene of cotton responsive to infection by <italic>Verticillium dahliae</italic>Ectopic expression of the cotton non-symbiotic hemoglobin gene <italic>GhHbd1</italic> triggers defense responses and increases disease tolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Legume embryos develop in a hypoxic environmentEnergy state and its control on seed development: starch accumulation is associated with high ATP and steep oxygen gradients within barley grainsDoes NO play a role in cytokinin signal transduction?Nonsymbiotic hemoglobins in rice are synthesized during germination and in differentiating cell typesActivation of the <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> non-symbiotic haemoglobin-2 promoter by the cytokinin-regulated transcription factor, ARR1A class 1 hemoglobin gene from <italic>Alnus firma</italic> functions in symbiotic and nonsymbiotic tissues to detoxify nitric oxideCytoglobin is a respiratory protein in connective tissue and neurons, which is up-regulated by hypoxiaNuclear localization of a hypoxia-inducible novel non-symbiotic hemoglobin in cultured alfalfa cellsPhytoglobins can interfere with nitric oxide functions during plant growth and pathogenic responses: a transgenic approachNO-degradation by alfalfa class 1 hemoglobin (Mhb1): a possible link to PR-1a gene expression in Mhb1-overproducing tobacco plantsSymbiotic rhizobium and nitric oxide induce gene expression of non-symbiotic hemoglobin in <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic>Overexpression of class 1 plant hemoglobin genes enhances symbiotic nitrogen fixation activity between <italic>Mesorhizobium loti</italic> and <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic>Role of phenylalanine B10 in plant nonsymbiotic hemoglobinsImmunolocalization of non-symbiotic hemoglobins during somatic embryogenesis in chicoryReview: correlations between oxygen affinity and sequence classifications of plant hemoglobinsAltering hemoglobin levels changes energy status in maize cells under hypoxiaOxygen binding to <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> AHb2 nonsymbiotic hemoglobin: evidence for a role in oxygen transportEthylene directs auxin to control root cell expansion<italic>Trema</italic> and <italic>Parasponia</italic> hemoglobins reveal convergent evolution of oxygen transport in plantsA cereal haemoglobin gene is expressed in seed and root tissues under anaerobic conditionsSeed-specific elevation of non-symbiotic hemoglobin AtHb1: beneficial effects and underlying molecular networks in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Two hemoglobin genes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: the evolutionary origins of leghemoglobinsRapid increase of NO release in plant cell cultures induced by cytokininZeatin-induced nitric oxide (NO) biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> mutants of NO biosynthesis and of two-component signaling genesExpression of symbiotic and nonsymbiotic globin genes responding to microsymbionts on <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic>Transcript and metabolite profiling of the adaptive response to mild decreases in oxygen concentration in the roots of arabidopsis plantsNon-symbiotic hemoglobin-2 leads to an elevated energy state and to a combined increase in polyunsaturated fatty acids and total oil content when over-expressed in developing seeds of transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plantsAnalysis of peroxidase activity of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) recombinant hemoglobin 1: implications for <italic>in vivo f</italic>unction of hexacoordinate non-symbiotic hemoglobins in plantsTwo tomato non-symbiotic haemoglobin genes are differentially expressed in response to diverse changes in mineral nutrient statusManipulation of hemoglobin expression affects <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> shoot organogenesisA hemoglobin from plants homologous to truncated hemoglobins of microorganismsNitric oxide: a new player in plant signalling and defence responsesThe effect of plant cytokinin hormones on the production of ethylene, nitric oxide, and protein nitrotyrosine in ageing tobacco leavesReactive oxygen species and nitric oxide mediate actin reorganization and programmed cell death in the self-incompatibility response of papaverDrought, ozone, ABA and ethylene: new insights from cell to plant to communityNitric oxide synthesis and signalling in plantsMicrobial globins<italic>Sub1A</italic> is an ethylene-response-factor-like gene that confers submergence tolerance to riceNitric oxide modulates specific steps of auxin-induced adventitious rooting in sunflowerA nonsymbiotic hemoglobin gene from maize, <italic>ZmHb</italic>, is involved in response to submergence, high-salt and osmotic stressesThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/</uri>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The ating evidence suggests non-symbiotic hemoglobins affect hormone responses by scavenging NO. Auxin, jasmonic acid, salicylic acid, ethylene and abscisic acid have altered responses when hemoglobins are expressed. Non-symbiotic hemoglobin is a factor during plant development, biotic and abiotic stress.Non-symbiotic haemoglobins have been an active research topic for over 30 years, during which time a considerable portfolio of knowledge has accumulated relative to their chemical and molecular properties, and their presence and mode of induction in plants. While progress has been made towards understanding their physiological role, there remain a number of unanswered questions with respect to their biological function. This review attempts to update recent progress in this area and to introduce a hypothesis as to how non-symbiotic haemoglobins might participate in regulating hormone signal transduction.Advances have been made towards understanding the structural nuances that explain some of the differences in ligand association characteristics of class 1 and class 2 non-symbiotic haemoglobins. Non-symbiotic haemoglobins have been found to function in seed development and germination, flowering, root development and differentiation, abiotic stress responses, pathogen invasion and symbiotic bacterial associations. Microarray analyses under various stress conditions yield uneven results relative to non-symbiotic haemoglobin expression. Increasing evidence of the role of nitric oxide (NO) in hormone responses and the known involvement of non-symbiotic haemoglobins in scavenging NO provide opportunities for fruitful research, particularly at the cellular level.Circumstantial evidence suggests that non-symbiotic haemoglobins may have a critical function in the signal transduction pathways of auxin, ethylene, jasmonic acid, salicylic acid, cytokinin and abscisic acid. There is a strong need for research on haemoglobin gene expression at the cellular level relative to hormone signal transduction.Haem proteins are critically important proteins in self-replicating organisms, with the haem iron acting as an electron transfer component in many redox reactions and/or as a chelating agent for small, biologically important ligands. The class of haem proteins known as haemoglobins are perhaps the best known of these proteins because of their major role in the animal kingdom for the transport of oxygen. The animal haemoglobins are also among the most studied due most probably to the ready supply of experimental material. Haemoglobins, however, have significant roles in other organisms ranging from bacteria to higher plants. Their biological function in these organisms can be considerably different from that of some of the animal haemoglobins. Bacterial and yeast flavohaemoglobins, with an additional domain for binding FAD and NAD(P)H, have an enzymic function to degrade nitric oxide (NO), providing protection against nitrosative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C115">Wu <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>). Much of the early research on plant haemoglobins centred around leghaemoglobin, which serves to transport oxygen in a stabilized, extremely low free oxygen concentration to symbiotic nitrogen-fixing bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C3">Appleby 1992</xref>). In the late 1980s, evidence of haemoglobin in a non-nodulating plant, <italic>Trema tomentosa</italic>, suggested that there might be another form of plant haemoglobin, distinct from leghaemoglobin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C9">Bogusz <italic>et al</italic>. 1988</xref>). A non-symbiotic haemoglobin, with a clearly distinct nucleotide sequence (∼40 % identity) from leghaemoglobins, was isolated from barley in 1994 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C98">Taylor <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>). This haemoglobin, now classified as a class 1 non-symbiotic haemoglobin, is up-regulated by low cell oxygen tension and, although possibly not being its only function, scavenges NO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C18">Dordas <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C19">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C74">Perazzolli <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Unlike flavohaemoglobins, it has no flavin and NAD(P)H domain and, therefore, must function with a reductase to regenerate haemoglobin to maintain NO breakdown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C41">Igamberdiev and Hill 2004</xref>). At least two classes of haemoglobins have been identified in several species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C5">Arredondo-Peter <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C100">Trevaskis <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C39">Hunt <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C89">Shimoda <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>), while only a class 1 haemoglobin has been identified in barley. Class 2 non-symbiotic haemoglobins have lower oxygen affinity and are induced by cold and cytokinins, but not hypoxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C100">Trevaskis <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C39">Hunt <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). A truncated haemoglobin, termed as class 3 (Hb3), has also been identified in arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C109">Watts <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). Hb3 has unusual concentration-independent O<sub>2</sub> and CO binding properties, with the association constants of the two ligands each being independent of their concentration. Hb3 is found throughout the plant and is not influenced by factors that influence other non-symbiotic haemoglobins.There have been a number of excellent reviews over the last several years that have covered specific aspects of plant haemoglobin research. A review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C17">Dordas (2009)</xref> emphasizes the metabolic and physiological research related to non-symbiotic haemoglobins, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C27">Garrocho-Villegas <italic>et al</italic>. (2007)</xref> provide a retrospective overview of the last six decades of research, examining the literature on both leghaemoglobins and non-symbiotic haemoglobins. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C93">Smagghe <italic>et al</italic>. (2009)</xref> present a comprehensive, thoughtful look at the relationship between the structural properties of the plant haemoglobins, their oxygen binding properties and the likely physiological function of the molecule. Reviews from Hargrove's laboratory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C36">Hoy and Hargrove 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C48">Kakar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) are an excellent resource for information on the structure and ligand binding characteristics of plant haemoglobins. In this review, we will attempt to focus, as much as possible, on recent advances in the area, ending on a hypothesis suggesting a biological role for plant haemoglobins in hormone signal transduction.A rice class 1 haemoglobin (Hb1) was the first non-symbiotic haemoglobin to be crystallized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C31">Hargrove <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>). The molecule exists as a dimer and has a weak hexacoordinate haem configuration in the ferrous state in comparison with class 2 haemoglobins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C93">Smagghe <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Class 1 haemoglobins exist as a mixture of the penta- and hexacoordinate forms, while class 2 haemoglobins are fully hexacoordinate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C11">Bruno <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). The haem iron is coordinated to the two histidines in a manner similar to cytochrome <italic>b5</italic>, with an unusual bis-histidyl haem coordination for a haemoglobin reversibly binding oxygen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C31">Hargrove <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>). The distal histidine, however, is rapidly displaced by ligands, resulting in high-affinity oxygen binding. Phenylalanine B10 is a regulatory element in hexacoordination, facilitating stable oxygen binding to ferrous haemoglobin and promoting binding for ligands such as azide in the ferric state by preventing tight His<sup>E7</sup> coordination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C91">Smagghe <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Studies with <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (arabidopsis) mutants support these conclusions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C21">Faggiano <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Phenylalanine B10 is conserved among haemoglobins across several kingdoms and has a direct role in ligand-binding regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C91">Smagghe <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>).There has been considerable interest in the characteristics of non-symbiotic haemoglobin ligand docking sites. There is evidence of the existence of temporary docking sites within the protein matrix for CO binding before re-binding to haem that may relate to the observed NO dioxygenase activity of the protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C1">Abbruzzetti <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). These docking sites are substantially different between arabidopsis Hb1 (AHb1) and non-symbiotic haemoglobin class 2 (AHb2), with stronger polar interactions and hydrogen bonding in AHb1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C11">Bruno <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). There are suggestions that the distal haem cavity in AHb1 is connected via a relatively open channel to the exterior, while temperature-dependent protein dynamics influence ligand migration from the distal cavity to the solvent in AHb2. Spectroscopic studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C66">Nienhaus <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) have identified two CO docking sites in AHb1, only one of which can be occupied in AHb2. Using this information, a mechanism has been proposed to account for NO dioxygenase activity by which binding of O<sub>2</sub> results in the formation of a channel through Hb1 from the distal cavity to the bulk solvent, permitting NO to occupy a docking site near the haem-bound O<sub>2</sub>, which would facilitate the reaction of the two ligands to form nitrate. Hb2 appears to lack this ability, leading to the suggestion that Hb2 is not involved in NO dioxygenase activity, at least via a mechanism that is dependent upon the supply of metabolite to internal storage sites. Two recent papers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C95">Spyrakis <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C105">Vigeolas <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) suggest a possible role for AHb2 in oxygen transport.There has been a long, continuing interest in the ancestral development of non-symbiotic haemoglobins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C93">Smagghe <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). A caesalpinoid haemoglobin (ppHb) has been cloned that has an intermediate structure between a non-symbiotic haemoglobin and a leghaemoglobin, suggesting that it may be an ancestral leghaemoglobin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C28">Gopalasubramaniam <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). There appears to have been a compaction of the CD loop in ppHb and decreased mobility of the distal histidine, leading to a pentacoordinate protein with a more compact globular structure. The moss, <italic>Ceratodon purpureus,</italic> haemoglobin (cerHb) possesses three introns, like higher plant non-symbiotic Hbs, indicating that this pattern has been retained during the ancestral development of the plant haemoglobins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C25">Garrocho-Villegas and Arredondo-Peter 2008</xref>). CerHb is predicted to have a hexacoordinate structure with high affinity for O<sub>2</sub>. It is suggested that the major evolutionary changes that have occurred in the transition from ancestral haemoglobins to non-symbiotic haemoglobins and leghaemoglobins are a hexacoordinate to pentacoordinate haem transition, decrease in the CD-loop and N- and C-termini, and protein compaction into a globular structure. Examination of haemoglobins in two closely related plants, <italic>Trema</italic> (non-nitrogen fixing) and <italic>Parasponia</italic> (nitrogen fixing), suggest distinct mechanisms for convergent evolution of oxygen transport in different phylogenetic classes of plant haemoglobins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C97">Sturms <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>).Involvement in NO metabolism is a key component in the function of non-symbiotic haemoglobins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C18">Dordas <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C19">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C74">Perazzolli <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). A mechanism by which this occurs has been proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C41">Igamberdiev and Hill 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C42">Igamberdiev <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>) and some suggestions have been presented as to how this metabolism may be integrated in the cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C45">Igamberdiev <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). There is also evidence that these haemoglobins are involved in aspects of reactive oxygen metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C43">Igamberdiev <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Alfalfa root cultures over-expressing barley Hb1 had substantially increased ascorbate levels, as well as elevated monodehydroascorbate reductase and ascorbate peroxidase activities, under both normoxic and anoxic conditions. Antisense Hb1 lines had increased levels of dehydroascorbate reductase and glutathione reductase activities under the same conditions. While there were observed decreases and increases in NO levels accompanying the changes in Hb1 expression, there was little effect on H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> levels. Aconitase, a reactive oxygen species (ROS)-sensitive enzyme, was protected by Hb1 expression apparently due to protection from NO. Research on rice Hb1 concluded that it was inefficient at scavenging H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> compared with a typical plant peroxidase and that these haemoglobins are unlikely to function as peroxidases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C106">Violante-Mota <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>).How does the relationship between haemoglobin expression and ROS at the metabolic level relate to events at the cellular and physiological level? Specific, unequivocal evidence is limited, but there are a few examples that are worth noting. Reactive oxygen species and antioxidants are significant components in a number of plant responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C59">Mittler 2002</xref>). Antioxidants have been implicated in protecting plant cells from programmed cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C22">Fath <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C59">Mittler 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C6">Barth <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>), as has NO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C7">Beligni <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). Unpublished data from our laboratory have shown that maize somatic embryogenesis can be altered by modifying expression of maize Hb1 and maize Hb2. Down-regulating Hb2 enhances somatic embryogenesis, while down-regulating Hb1 represses embryo formation. Localization of NO differed in a cell-specific fashion between the two phenotypes and programmed cell death was evident in NO-containing cells. Reactive oxygen species and NO are involved in the self-incompatibility response in pollen–pistil interactions resulting in programmed cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C112">Wilkins <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Reactive oxygen species/NO scavengers interfere with this response. Haemoglobin is an NO scavenger and, as noted above, haemoglobin expression improves antioxidant status in the cell.Changes in the expression of either AHb1 or AHb2 affect the time to bolting of arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C33">Hebelstrup and Jensen 2008</xref>). Silencing of haemoglobin expression delays bolting, while over-expression results in earlier bolting than in wild-type plants. Haemoglobin appears to be acting as a scavenger of NO in this process, as NO donors were antagonistic to the effects of haemoglobin on bolting. Nitric oxide has been shown to repress the arabidopsis floral transition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C32">He <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>), which would support the contention that haemoglobin expression reduces the time to bolting via NO scavenging. Nitric oxide and haemoglobin have also been proposed to be involved in gene regulation and lipid-based signalling during the response to chilling in arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C13">Cantrel <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Nitric oxide levels are increased after a short exposure to chilling, an effect that is not observed in plants over-expressing AHb1. Two sphingolipids, phytosphingosine phosphate and ceramide phosphate, are negatively regulated by NO during the chilling process.Nitric oxide has been shown to up-regulate haemoglobin expression in a number of species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C68">Ohwaki <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C78">Qu <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C84">Sasakura <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C12">Bustos-Sanmamed <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), some in relation to infection by micro-organisms. <italic>Alnus</italic> Hb1 is strongly induced in actinorhizal nodules by NO and cold stress, but not by hypoxia or osmotic stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C84">Sasakura <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Acetylene reduction is strongly reduced by NO, suggesting that Hb1 may support nitrogen fixation ability by scavenging NO in members of the genus <italic>Frankia</italic>. Hb1 is also up-regulated in <italic>Lotus japonicus</italic> in root nodules by NO, cold and hypoxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C12">Bustos-Sanmamed <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Because of the enhanced expression of all three classes of haemoglobin in <italic>L. japonicus</italic> symbiotic nodules, it has been suggested that they are required for symbiosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C12">Bustos-Sanmamed <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Truncated haemoglobins (Hb3) are induced by infection of <italic>Datisca glomerata</italic> by <italic>Frankia</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C73">Pawlowski <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>), leading these authors to suggest a role for the truncated haemoglobins in NO detoxification. Inoculation of <italic>L. japonicus</italic> with <italic>Mesorhizobium loti</italic> also transiently induced Hb1, while Hb2 was only induced by the application of sucrose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C89">Shimoda <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). The same laboratory reported that over-expression of Hb1 enhances symbiotic nitrogen fixation in the same system, suggesting that this occurs via removal of NO as an inhibitor of nitrogenase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C90">Shimoda <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>).Cotton Hb1 (GhHb1) is induced by NO, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, ethylene, salicylate and methyljasmonate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C78">Qu <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>), agents that have been associated with plant disease responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C60">Mur <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Ectopic expression of GhHb1 in arabidopsis increased the tolerance of the plants to NO. The transgenic plants also constitutively expressed the defence response genes, <italic>PR-1</italic> and <italic>PDF1.2</italic>. Expression of GhHb1 conferred enhanced disease resistance to <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> and tolerance to <italic>Verticillium dahliae</italic>. GhHb1 is induced in cotton roots after infection by <italic>V. dahliae</italic> or exogenous H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and is suggested to play a role in the defence responses against <italic>V. dahliae</italic> invasion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C77">Qu <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). Over-expressing an alfalfa non-symbiotic haemoglobin in tobacco led to decreased necrosis from <italic>P. syringae</italic> or tobacco mosaic virus-infected leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C86">Seregelyes <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>). This was accompanied by increased ROS and salicylic acid in haemoglobin over-expressed plants.A relationship between non-symbiotic haemoglobin gene expression and hypoxic stress has been evident since the first description of these molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C98">Taylor <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>). The response is rapid, peaking within a few hours of plant exposure to hypoxia. Altering the expression of the haemoglobin gene through constitutive expression of appropriate gene constructs in various plants provided further evidence of its role in hypoxic stress. Thus, over-expression of class 1 non-symbiotic haemoglobins has been shown to enhance tolerance to hypoxic stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C94">Sowa <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C40">Hunt <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C18">Dordas <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C118">Zhao <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), while under-expression of the gene reduced tolerance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C94">Sowa <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C18">Dordas <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>).Various microarray studies of plants under hypoxic stress have produced mixed results on non-symbiotic haemoglobin gene expression and hypoxia. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C57">Loreti <italic>et al</italic>. (2005)</xref> demonstrated a rapid increase in <italic>AHb1</italic> expression by a northern blot analysis in arabidopsis seedlings exposed to anoxia, coincident with an increase in alcohol dehydrogenase, but found no differential expression of the same haemoglobin in a microarray analysis, comparing anoxic versus normoxic tissue. They did, however, observe an almost two-fold decrease in class 2 haemoglobin transcript expression under the same conditions. In another study of the transcriptome of arabidopsis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C104">van Dongen <italic>et al</italic>. (2009)</xref> showed at least a two-fold increase in class 1 haemoglobin expression at 2 and 48 h after exposure of the roots to either 1, 4 or 8 % oxygen. Some puzzling results were found for non-symbiotic haemoglobin expression in an examination of the transcriptome patterns of <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> and arabidopsis under abiotic stress that, unfortunately, did not include hypoxia/anoxia as one of the stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C62">Narsai <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). There were changes in haemoglobin expression in both species, but in two of the rice lines there was a strong up-regulation of class 1 haemoglobin upon imposition of the stress, while in the arabidopsis line there was a down-regulation. The authors attribute the difference in response of the two species to possible differences in NO signalling between them. Since there are five known non-symbiotic haemoglobins in rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C56">Lira-Ruan <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C26">Garrocho-Villegas <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>) and three in arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C27">Garrocho-Villegas <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>), this difference may also reflect an alternative function for one of the haemoglobins in rice. Using developmentally regulated proteins and transgenic arabidopsis expressing a FLAG-epitope tagged ribosomal protein, ribosome-associated mRNAs were immunopurified from specific cell populations of intact seedlings exposed to 2 h of anoxia to identify differentially expressed mRNAs in 21 cell populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C61">Mustroph <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). No up-regulation of non-symbiotic haemoglobins in any of the cell populations was observed. An analysis of the transcriptome of grey poplar (<italic>Populus canescens</italic>) under hypoxic stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C50">Kreuzwieser <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>) found changes in only truncated haemoglobins (class 3), with up-regulation occurring after short exposure (5 h) and down-regulation apparent after 24 h hypoxia or longer. There clearly are issues to be resolved in understanding why there is such a variation in response relative to non-symbiotic haemoglobins with these microarray analyses of plant stress responses. From the perspective of specific examination of class 1 non-symbiotic haemoglobin response to hypoxia by northern blot analysis, there is unequivocal evidence of up-regulation in barley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C98">Taylor <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>), arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C40">Hunt <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>), oak (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C71">Parent <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>) and rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C55">Lira-Ruan <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). An obvious explanation for the absence of these haemoglobins in microarray screens associated with hypoxia is that they may not undergo a strong up-regulation upon application of the stress, either as a result of the short time interval of the response or due to localization to specific cells. This lack of strong up-regulation is apparent when examining the gene profiles in the supplementary data accompanying some of the above-cited manuscripts and in qualitative estimations of the northern blots in these same manuscripts, where non-symbiotic haemoglobins have been specifically examined.Several studies have examined the effect of oxygen limitation on seed development, some of which have involved the role of non-symbiotic haemoglobins in the stress response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C79">Rolletschek <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C80">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C10">Borisjuk <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C99">Thiel <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C105">Vigeolas <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Steep oxygen gradients are observed in the caryopsis during barley seed development, with highly hypoxic regions having low ATP concentrations and reduced capacity for storage starch accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C80">Rolletschek <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Legume embryo development occurs in a hypoxic environment as well, with very young embryos being most hypoxic, having low ATP and energy charge levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C79">Rolletschek <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). Hypoxia induces a nitrite-dependent increase in NO levels in seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C10">Borisjuk <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). The presence of NO results in a decrease in seed oxygen consumption, reduced ATP availability and biosynthetic activity, while increasing oxygen availability reduces NO and increases metabolic activity. This balancing of NO and oxygen is suggested to play a part in regulating seed storage activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C10">Borisjuk <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). To test this hypothesis, arabidopsis seed oxygen stress was manipulated by transformation to achieve seed-specific elevation of AHb1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C99">Thiel <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). The transformed seed did not accumulate NO under hypoxic stress and had higher respiratory activity and energy charge than the wild type. Transcript profiling revealed that AHb1 over-expression resulted in a re-arrangement of stress-related regulatory pathways under non-stress conditions. Transcription factors, such as <italic>WRKY</italic> and <italic>AP2/EREBP</italic>, and genes associated with hormones such as abscisic acid (ABA), salicylic acid and jasmonic acid were up-regulated. An auxin transporter (<italic>AUX1</italic>) and several auxin-induced genes (<italic>GH3</italic>, <italic>SAUR</italic>, <italic>IAA</italic>, <italic>ARF1</italic>) were strongly down-regulated. <italic>WRKY</italic> has been implicated in hypoxic responses in arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C61">Mustroph <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>), while members of the <italic>AP2/EREBP</italic> family, having a significant role in conferring submergence tolerance to rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C116">Xu <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>), are involved in the anaerobic response in arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C35">Hinz <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C54">Licausi <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) and have been suggested to be responsible for negative anaerobic regulation of the maize <italic>GapC4</italic> promoter in tobacco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C65">Niemeyer <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). <italic>SAUR</italic> genes have been shown to be negative regulators of auxin synthesis and transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C49">Kant <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>) and are up-regulated by anoxia in rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C53">Lasanthi-Kudahettige <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). The GH3 family of proteins catalyse the amino acid conjugation of auxins and jasmonates for hormone homeostasis during stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C72">Park <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). This all indicates a strong relationship between haemoglobin expression and cell auxin (jasmonate?) homeostasis, and suggests that this will be a fertile area for future research advances.Earlier in the review, it was established that oxyhaemoglobins are effective scavengers of NO in many biological systems, including plants. The limited studies in which sites of cellular expression of NO and non-symbiotic haemoglobins have been examined support the conclusion that this reaction occurs <italic>in situ</italic>. Thus, regions in arabidopsis leaves in which NO is highly expressed show altered NO levels when class 1 haemoglobin levels are modified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C34">Hebelstrup <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C33">Hebelstrup and Jensen 2008</xref>). Class 1 haemoglobins have been found in seed tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C20">Duff <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C39">Hunt <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C82">Ross <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C103">Uchiumi <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>), in the roots of herbaceous species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C39">Hunt <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C103">Uchiumi <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C52">Larsen 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C107">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C78">Qu <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>) and trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C47">Jokipii <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C71">Parent <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), in leaves and flowers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C34">Hebelstrup <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>), and in meristematic tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C33">Hebelstrup and Jensen 2008</xref>). Studies with a rice class 2 haemoglobin promoter:GUS fusion in arabidopsis found expression in roots, in young leaf vasculature, in flowers and at the pedicel/stem junction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C83">Ross <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). All three classes of <italic>L. japonicus</italic> non-symbiotic haemoglobins are expressed at very high levels in the symbiotic nodules of the plant in comparison with levels in other plant organs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C12">Bustos-Sanmamed <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). A sub-class of the class 1 haemoglobin had considerably higher expression in leaves than its counterpart, while a sub-class of the class 3 haemoglobin had only high expression in nodules relative to its counterpart, which was roughly uniformly expressed throughout the plant.It might be expected that non-symbiotic haemoglobins would be found within the cytoplasm of the cell as they lack gene signal sequences that would target them to organelles or export from the cell. They have, however, been reported in the nucleus of cells as well as in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C88">Seregélyes <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C82">Ross <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). This seems to be in keeping with results found for cytoglobin, a vertebrate haemoglobin having some similar properties to non-symbiotic haemoglobins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C85">Schmidt <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Cytoglobin is widely distributed in mammalian cells, but the degree of sub-cellular localization seems to be cell-type dependent, with some cell types having nuclear and cytoplasmic localization while others have it only in the cytoplasm.Hormone cross-talk is gaining increasing attention as a means of understanding how hormone action regulates plant growth and development. The term ‘cross-talk’ invokes the requirement of a mechanism by which the distinct hormone pathways can communicate with one another. In this section, the possible role of non-symbiotic haemoglobins and NO in hormonal cross-talk will be examined. The proposed hypothesis will suggest that non-symbiotic haemoglobins influence and alter the expression and site of action of auxins, jasmonates, ethylene and ABA through modulation of NO levels within the cell. The hypothesis derives from the following observations: non-symbiotic haemoglobins are widely distributed in the plant kingdom and are found in distinct locations in plant tissue; NO is found in plants and is degraded through reaction with oxyhaemoglobin; non-symbiotic haemoglobin and NO expression vary during plant development, and are affected by biotic and abiotic stress.The transition to flowering is a specific example that potentially links effects of haemoglobin on NO to physiological responses. Nitric oxide represses the floral transition in arabidopsis, where either NO or a mutant over-expressing NO delays bolting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C32">He <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Silencing AHb1 expression, which increases cellular NO levels, also delays bolting in arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C33">Hebelstrup and Jensen 2008</xref>). The arabidopsis mutant over-expressing NO has an abnormal, serrated leaf phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C32">He <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>), which is also seen in Hb1-silenced arabidopsis lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C34">Hebelstrup <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). In addition, the observed aerial rosettes observed in Hb1-silenced lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C32">He <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C34">Hebelstrup <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>) suggest possible alterations in auxin transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C23">Galweiler <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>).The relationship between NO, hormones and biological function.Nitric oxide influences plant hormonal response in a number of other stress-related situations. Nitric oxide attenuates ozone-induced salicylic acid accumulation and elevates ethylene levels in arabidopsis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C2">Ahlfors <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Ethylene and NO have been shown mutually to influence each other in up-regulating Fe-acquisition genes with respect to root micronutrient deficiencies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C24">Garcia <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). There is strong evidence linking NO, jasmonic acid and salicylic acid in the plant defence response to pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C110">Wendehenne <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C38">Hu <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). What are the potential connections with non-symbiotic haemoglobin? Class 1 non-symbiotic haemoglobins are induced in cotton by salicylic acid, methyl jasmonate, ethylene, hydrogen peroxide and NO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C78">Qu <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Over-expression of the haemoglobin leads to constitutive expression of disease response genes and conferred enhanced disease resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C86">Seregelyes <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C87">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C78">Qu <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Suppression of class 1 haemoglobin expression in maize cell cultures leads to a substantial increase in ethylene production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C58">Manac'h-Little <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>), consistent with the expected response if the increase was due to elevated cell NO levels.There is a potential role of non-symbiotic haemoglobins in ABA responses. Nitric oxide functions downstream of ABA in stomatal closure and abiotic stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C64">Neill <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), and there is reason to believe that ethylene also plays a part in the process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C113">Wilkinson and Davies 2010</xref>). Non-symbiotic haemoglobins have been found in stomatal guard cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C92">Smagghe <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>), indicating the possibility of their functioning in regulating stomatal closure. There is also evidence of the role of NO in ABA- and gibberellin (GA)-regulated events within seed tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C8">Bethke <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>), although the results are counter-intuitive to what one would expect relative to what is known about ABA, NO and stomatal closure. Nitric oxide acts as a downstream signal molecule in ABA-induced stomatal closure whereas, in seed tissue, it is suggested that it acts to reduce seed dormancy and promote germination, an action not normally associated with ABA. Regardless of the anomaly, NO is a factor in seed germination and dormancy. Non-symbiotic haemoglobins are expressed in seed tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C98">Taylor <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C20">Duff <italic>et al</italic>. 1998;</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C4">Arechaga-Ocampo <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C82">Ross <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>), particularly during germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C20">Duff <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>), making it highly probable that the protein is modulating NO levels during the germination process.Cytokinin up-regulates class 2 non-symbiotic haemoglobin expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C39">Hunt <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). The effect of this expression would be to reduce NO levels, altering downstream signalling from auxin, ethylene, jasmonic acid or salicylic acid that might be present in the cells synthesizing the protein. There is evidence that non-symbiotic haemoglobins affect cytokinin signalling. Shoot organogenesis is suppressed in AHb2 knockout lines, while over-expressing AHb1 or AHb2 enhanced both shoot formation and altered expression of genes associated with cytokinin perception and signalling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C108">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Up-regulation of Hb1 or Hb2 activated <italic>CKI1</italic> and <italic>AHK3</italic>, genes encoding cytokinin receptors and altered expression of cytokinin response regulators (ARRs). Cytokinin feedback repressors (Type-A ARRs) were repressed in haemoglobin over-expressing lines, while cytokinin activators (Type-B ARRs) were up-regulated. There have been reports that cytokinin increases NO production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C101">Tun <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C102">2008</xref>), but there are also reports that the reverse occurs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C111">Wilhelmova <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). In a study to determine whether NO is involved in cytokinin function, it was concluded that NO has no direct role in eliciting the primary cytokinin response in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS004C81">Romanov <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>).A schematic diagram of the eliciting agents and mode of action of non-symbiotic haemoglobins and NO in plants.While the relationship between non-symbiotic haemoglobins and plant hormone responses is largely theoretical at this stage, the hypothesis can be tested and there are sufficient avenues to pursue that would verify or defeat it. The most promising area of advancement would appear to be in auxin signalling where links between non-symbiotic haemoglobins, NO and responses known to be triggered by auxin already exist in the literature but require more detailed examination to establish the relationship. Shoot and root organogenesis, somatic embryogenesis and programmed cell death are fertile study areas. Nitric oxide is a significant factor in biotic stress responses and several reports have linked non-symbiotic haemoglobins with enhanced disease resistance. There remains the problem of determining how this is achieved. Examining the link between haemoglobin and jasmonic and salicylic acid signalling is a logical place to start. In the abiotic stress area, programmed cell death during aerenchyma formation in anaerobic roots is an area of interest, as would be internodal elongation during flooding. Abscisic acid has already been linked to NO in germination and stomatal responses. Assessing a role for non-symbiotic haemoglobin has potential as certain haemoglobin classes have been detected in seed and leaf tissue.There remain significant advances with respect to hormone signalling, NO and non-symbiotic haemoglobins that can be accomplished to enhance our understanding of the action of this molecule in the plant kingdom.Research support from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (Discovery Grant 1813) is gratefully acknowledged.None declared.