 Impact of nitrogen availability and soil communities on biomass accumulation of an invasive species  Invasiveness of  Ammophila arenaria:  release from soil-borne pathogens?  Microbial population and community dynamics on plant roots and their feedbacks on plant communities  Plant–soil feedbacks do not explain invasion success of  Acacia  species in introduced range populations in Australia  Soil biota and exotic plant invasion  Plant species traits are the predominant control on litter decomposition rates within biomes worldwide  Experimental support for a resource-based mechanistic model for invasibility  Fluctuating resources in plant communities: a general theory of invasibility  Effects of exotic plant invasions on soil nutrient cycling process  Ecosystem consequences of biological invasions  Changes in soil functions following invasions of exotic understory plants in deciduous forests  Feedback in the plant-soil system  Linear and non-linear impacts of a non-native plant invasion on soil microbial community structure and function  Evolutionary tradeoffs for nitrogen allocation to photosynthesis versus cell walls in an invasive plant  A quicker return energy-use strategy by populations of a subtropical invader in the non-native range: a potential mechanism for the evolution of increased competitive ability  Nitrogen uptake and preference in a forest understory following invasion by an exotic grass  Resource-use efficiency and plant invasion in low-resource systems  Emergent insights from the synthesis of conceptual frameworks for biological invasions  Leaf litter of the invasive  Casuarina equisetifolia  decomposes at the same rate as that of native woody species on oceanic islands but releases more nitrogen  A congeneric comparison shows that experimental warming enhances the growth of invasive  Eupatorium adenophorum   Resource-use strategies of native and invasive plants in eastern North American forests  Independent variations of plant and soil mixtures reveal soil feedback effects on plant community over yielding  Impacts of soil microbial communities on exotic plant invasions  Volatile chemicals from leaf litter are associated with invasiveness of a neotropical weed in Asia  Effect of invasion of  Mikania micrantha  on germination of rice seedlings, plant richness, chemical properties and respiration of soil  Community impacts of  Prosopis juliflora  invasion: biogeographic and congeneric comparison  Plant–soil feedbacks contribute to an intransitive competitive network that promotes both generic and species diversity  Positive feedbacks to growth of an invasive grass through alteration of nitrogen cycling  Leaf trait relationships of native and invasive plants: community and global-scale comparisons  Native and exotic invasive plants have fundamentally similar carbon capture strategies  Fluctuating resource availability increases invasibility in microbial microcosms  Negative plant-soil feedback predicts tree-species relative abundance in a tropical forest  How invader traits interact with resident communities and resource availability to determine invasion success?  Comparison of nutrient acquisition in exotic plant species and congeneric natives  Reciprocal effects of litter from exotic and congeneric native plant species via soil nutrients  Soil toxicity induced by terpenes from  Salvia leucophylla   An invasive aster ( Ageratina adenophora ) invades and dominates forest understories in China: altered soil microbial communities facilitate the invader and inhibit natives  Do alien plant species profit more from high resource supply than natives? A trait-based analysis  Belowground biotic complexity drives aboveground dynamics: a test of the soil community feedback model  Native and non-native grasses generate common types of plant–soil feedbacks by altering soil nutrients and microbial communities  Plant-induced changes in soil nutrient dynamics by native and invasive grass species  Immobilizing nitrogen to control plant invasion  Evaluation of chemical and biological consequences of soil sterilization methods  Soil biota facilitates exotic  Acer  invasions in Europe and North America  Soil biota and invasive plants  Soil feedback and pathogen activity in  Prunus serotina  throughout its native range  An invasive plant paradox  Interactions between exotic invasive plants and soil microbes in the rhizosphere suggest that ‘everything is  not  everywhere  Non-native grass alters growth of native tree species via leaf and soil microbes  Effects of  Bromus tectorum  invasion on microbial carbon and nitrogen cycling in two adjacent undisturbed arid grassland communities  Effects of labile soil carbon on nutrient portioning between the arctic graminoid and microbes  Influencing mechanisms of several shrubs on soil chemical properties in semiarid Horqin sandy land, China  Consequences of plant–soil feedback in invasion  Plant–soil feedback induces shift in biomass allocation in the invasive plant  Chromolaena odorata   Biological invasion of  Myrica faya  alters ecosystem development in Hawaii  Ecological linkages between aboveground and belowground biota  Changes in non-symbiotic nitrogen-fixing bacteria inhabiting rhizosphere soils of an invasive plant  Ageratina adenophora   This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Exotic plant species impact belowground processes by influencing resource availability through enhanced microbial activity as a consequence of litter inputs. Soil communities cultured by  Ageratina adenophora , a neotropical invader in Asia, retain available N that influence the growth of the invader. Invader triggers higher microbial activities through terpene-rich litter inputs to release nitrogen, which facilitates the invasion of  A. adenophora . Our results provide evidence that microbial-linked nitrogen availability exert positive impact on  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation. Our work emphasizes the importance of soil communities-drive nitrogen availability in invasion success.  Exotic plant species impact belowground processes by influencing resource availability through enhanced microbial activity as a consequence of litter inputs. We have little understanding of the impact of microbe-driven nutrient fluctuations on the biomass accumulation of invasive species. Here we attempt to answer the question on whether soil community-driven nitrogen availability influences invader biomass. We discovered that soil communities cultured by  Ageratina adenophora , a neotropical invader in Asia, retain available nitrogen that influences the biomass of the invader. Through soil manipulation experiments we found that  A. adenophora  grows better in soil with a higher available nitrogen content.  Ageratina adenophora -invaded soil had higher microbial activity and available nitrogen due to higher inputs of terpene-rich litter compared with soil not yet invaded by it. Our results provide evidence that microbe-linked nitrogen availability exerts a positive impact on  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation. Our work emphasizes the importance of soil community-driven nitrogen availability in invasion success.  One of the questions that interest many ecologists is how nitrogen enables exotic plants to dominate (  Vitousek  et al.  1987 ;  Rout and Callaway 2009 ;  Lee  et al.  2012 ) and the role of belowground factors linked to it ( Reinhart and Callaway 2004 ;  Wardle  et al.  2004 ;  Gurevitch  et al.  2011 ;  Rout and Callaway 2012 ;  Pendergast  et al.  2013 ). Soil microbial communities are major components of the belowground ecosystem that influence exotic plant invasion by (i) making nutrients available through litter decomposition ( Vitousek  et al.  1987 ;  Davis  et al.  2000 ;  Ehrenfeld 2003 ;  Suding  et al.  2013 ) and/or (ii) exerting negative or positive plant–soil feedback ( Reinhart and Callaway 2006 ;  Ehrenfeld 2010 ;  Inderjit and Van der Putten 2010 ;  Bever  et al.  2012 ). These effects take place via impacts of either root exudates ( Wardle  et al.  2004 ;  Ehrenfeld 2010 ;  Lankau  et al.  2011 ;  Meisner  et al.  2011 ;  Perkins  et al.  2011 ) or exotic plant litter on soil microbial activity ( Ehrenfeld 2010 ;  Meisner  et al.  2012 ), resulting in the release or retention of nutrients that may promote invasion. In some cases, exotic litter accelerates nutrient cycling, particularly nitrogen ( Cornwell  et al.  2008 ). The decomposition of exotic litter largely depends on the amount of litter accumulated ( Elgersma and Ehrenfeld 2011 ). It has been shown that litter of the invasive species  Berberis thunbergii  enhances net nitrogen mineralization and nitrification ( Ehrenfeld  et al.  2001 ;  Elgersma and Ehrenfeld 2011 ). Exotic invasives impact microbial activities in soil, which stimulates microbial nitrogen cycling. For example,  Bromus tectorum  invasion in arid grasslands of southeastern Utah, USA, stimulates microbial nitrogen cycling by enhancing microbial activity ( Schaeffer  et al.  2012 ). Such fluctuations in resource availability have been reported to promote the invasibility of exotic invasive species ( Davis and Pelsor 2001 ;  Li and Stevens 2012 ;  Mata  et al.  2013 ).  We studied the role of nitrogen and its manipulation by soil microbial communities present in the invader's rhizosphere on the biomass accumulation of  Ageratina adenophora , a neotropical invader in Asia ( Inderjit  et al.  2011 ;  He  et al.  2012 ). Biogeographic comparisons of native and introduced ranges of  A. adenophora  suggest that the invader exerts neutral to facilitative effects on plant species richness in its native range in Mexico, but had negative effects on plant species richness in its introduced ranges in China and India ( Inderjit  et al.  2011 ). The negative impact of  A. adenophora  on plant species richness in the introduced ranges was linked to biogeographic variations of terpenes released by  A. adenophora  litter, which suggested that it might be experiencing selection based on the composition of volatile organic compounds in its introduced ranges ( Inderjit  et al.  2011 ).  Ageratina adenophora  was reported to allocate greater amounts of nitrogen to photosynthesis (growth) and reduced allocation to cell walls (defence), thus resulting in an increase in its growth and vigour in the introduced ranges ( Feng  et al.  2009 ,  2011 ). This is also the case for  Microstegium vimineum  in the southern and eastern USA, which allocates more nitrogen to the aboveground parts than the belowground parts compared with native plants ( Fraterrigo  et al.  2011 ). A greenhouse study found that native soil communities had a more neutral than negative soil biota effect on  A. adenophora  relative to local species but soil biota from invaded sites had positive effects on the invader ( Niu  et al.  2007 ). However, it remains unclear whether nitrogen availability and microbial activity influence  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation. This is an important question in invasion ecology, where the effect of soil nutrients on invader performance is subject to debate (e.g.  Funk and Vitousek 2007 ;  Leishman  et al.  2007 ,  2010 ;  Heberling and Fridley 2013 ;  Ordonez and Olff 2013 ), particularly under low nutrient availability conditions. Hence, the impact of  A. adenophora  on soil communities and microbial nitrogen retention needs further studies.  Ageratina adenophora  adds a large amount of leaf litter to the soil. We predict higher microbial activity in  A. adenophora  soils due to addition of terpene-rich litter, which may influence soil available nitrogen and thus the positive effects of  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation.  We hypothesized that higher availability of soil microbial-driven nitrogen exerts a positive impact on  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation. We designed a study to test our hypothesis by (i) comparing levels of available nitrogen and  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation in its non-sterilized and sterilized rhizosphere soil, (ii) manipulating the levels of nitrogen in soil to study the impact of nitrogen on  A. adenophora  biomass, and (iii) quantifying soil respiration and available nitrogen in soil collected from the  A. adenophora  rhizosphere and from areas not yet invaded by it (open areas).  The study was conducted in two sites situated in the foothills of the Himalayas, Palampur (32°7′0.12″N, 76°31′59.88″E; 1220 m a.s.l.) and Mussoorie (30°27′0″N, 78°4′48″E; 1825 m a.s.l.), which are invaded by  A. adenophora . In each site we selected two microsites: a disturbed habitat and another undisturbed habitat. The first microsite in Palampur was a track of 25 km that occurred along a highway road (National Highway #21) outside the Institute of Himalayan Bioresources and Technology, and was considered a disturbed site (32°6′13.2″N, 76°33′20.6″E). Here,  A. adenophora  was present along roadside slopes with little natural sub-canopy vegetation along with a few trees of  Populus alba ,  Albezia lebbeck  and  Pinus roxburghii . The second microsite was a closed forest 11 km from the Roadside site and was an undisturbed site (32°5′7.4″N; 76°31′4.8″E). Here  A. adenophora  was interspersed with trees like  P. alba ,  Gravillea robusta  and  Ficus virens , and the ground was covered with  Cannabis sativa  and some grass species. In the Roadside site of Palampur, grass species like  Oplismenus  sp . ,  Poa  sp .  and  Cynodon  sp .  were present. In addition to these species, plant species such as  Cirsium vulgare ,  Panicum clandestinum ,  Trifolium repens ,  Erigeron mucronatus  and  Oxalis corniculata  were found only in open areas. Other plant species like  Bidens pilosa  and  Lantana camara  were present in open areas as well as areas invaded by  A. adenophora . In open areas of the forest site of Palampur, grass species such as  Oplismenus  sp .  and  Cynodon  sp .  and plants species like  Lathyrus aphaca ,  L. sphaericus ,  P. clandestinum ,  Lotus corniculatus ,  Briza minor  and  Anagallis arvensis  were found exclusively here, and species like  O. corniculata  and  Elettaria cardamomum  were present in both areas, open and invaded by  A. adenophora .  In Mussoorie, the microsite with the disturbed habitat was a barren hill-slope (30°28′44.6″N; 78°3′9.1″E). Its original vegetation had been wiped out and it had nearly pure stands of  A. adenophora  with a few individuals of  Carex setigera ,  B. pilosa ,  E. mucronatus  and  Geranium mascatense.  The adjacent side of the Hill-slope site was an area not affected by hill slides and had a thick cover of vegetation dominated by species like  Quercus incana ,  Prunus cerasiodes  and  Crotoneaster bacillaris . Owing to the complete destruction of the primary vegetation in the Hill-slope microsite in Mussoorie, no plant species was found exclusively in the open areas except for  Cynodon  sp. Species such as  Berberis aristata ,  Geranium lucidum ,  E. mucronatus ,  Crataegus crenulata ,  B. pilosa  and  Debregeasia hypoleuca  were, however, present in both open areas and areas invaded by  A. adenophora . The second microsite in Mussoorie was a closed forest (30°28′12.6″N; 78°3′41.5″E) where  A. adenophora  was present inside a thick forest cover dominated by species such as  Q. incana ,  Rumex nepalensis ,  R. hastatus ,  E. mucronatus ,  Prinsepia utilis  and  B. aristata . In the forest site of Mussoorie, plant species  Potentilla  sp.,  Polytrichum  sp . ,  Rosa macrophylla  and  Cirisium arvense  were present only in the open areas and  E. mucronatus ,  Rumex nepalensis ,  Smilax aspera ,  G. lucidum  and  T. repens  were found in both the open and  A. adenophora -invaded areas.  To test the effect of soil communities of the  A. adenophora  rhizosphere, a total of 40 soil samples, 10 from each microsite, were collected from the rhizosphere of  A. adenophora  plants in Palampur and Mussoorie (10 plants × 2 microsites × 2 sites) in May 2012. Soil attached to  A. adenophora  roots was collected by pulling its roots and shaking off soil loosely bound to shallow roots, and identified as  A. adenophora  rhizosphere soil. In order to collect sufficient soil for one soil sample, ≈3–4 kg, 2–3 plants of  A. adenophora  were pulled. Soil was then air-dried and stored in paper bags for analysis.  In order to examine any effect of soil communities cultured by  A. adenophora  in its rhizosphere on its growth, we used non-sterile and sterile  A. adenophora  rhizosphere soil. Although soil sterilization is a widely employed technique to study the role of soil communities in plant invasion (e.g.  Beckstead and Parker 2003 ;  Callaway  et al.  2004 ;  Reinhart  et al.  2005 ;  Razavi darbar and Lakzian 2007 ;  Rudgers and Orr 2009 ;  Te Beest  et al.  2009 ;  Mangan  et al.  2010 ;  Kaur  et al.  2012 a  ;  Birnbaum and Leishman 2013 ;  Hendriks  et al.  2013 ), the effect of nutrient leaching after sterilization cannot be ruled out. Half of each soil sample collected from the  A. adenophora  rhizosphere from the two sites was sterilized by autoclaving the soil at 121 °C and 103 kPa for 30 min three consecutive times. Each soil sample for sterilization was packed individually in a small bag and autoclaved followed by cooling at room temperature and then autoclaved again for three consecutive days, making a total of 80 soil samples (2 sites × 2 microsites × 10 plants × 2 treatments). Fifty grams of non-sterile or sterile  A. adenophora  rhizosphere soil were placed in each of 240 pots (2 sites × 2 microsites × 10 plants × 2 treatments × 3 experimental replicates) of 71.5 cm 3  volume and irrigated with 15 mL of distilled water.  Ageratina adenophora  seeds collected from a single location in Mussoorie were sown in each pot. The seeds were allowed to germinate under controlled conditions of temperature (21/18 °C) and a day/night light regime of 12/12 h. Seedlings were thinned a week after full germination to five seedlings per pot.  Ageratina adenophora  plants including roots were harvested after 60 days of growth and dried at 50 °C for 3 days, and their biomass was measured as total dry weight of the whole plant and averaged per pot.  To study the impact of soil communities cultured by  A. adenophora  on available nitrogen, we analysed both non-sterile and sterile soil for available nitrogen. Fifty grams of dry soil were irrigated with 15 mL of distilled water and incubated at 22 °C for 5 days to make the soil conditions the same as when freshly collected from the field. Ten grams of soil were soaked in 20 mL of 0.5 M K 2 SO 4 , shaken for 1 h and filtered with nitrate-free Whatman #42. The concentration of available nitrogen was estimated as NO 3 -N using the colorimetric method ( Anderson and Ingram 1993 ).  To examine the effect of nitrogen on  A. adenophora  biomass, we manipulated non- A. adenophora  soil with different levels of carbon (C; glucose). An increase in microbial activity after the addition of labile C in the form of glucose results in nitrogen immobilization ( Schmidt  et al.  1997 ). One hundred and fifty grams of soil from the open area were taken in 160-cm 3  pots and irrigated with 45 mL of 1.04, 2.08 or 4.17 mg glucose per mL, corresponding to 125, 250 and 500 µg C per g soil. Experimental conditions were temperature 21/18 °C and a 12/12 h day/night light regime. The soil was further amended with the same levels of glucose on the 30th day after the initiation of the experiment and terminated on the 60th day. Soil respiration was estimated on Day 0, and the 30th and 60th days, and available nitrogen was estimated on the 30th and 60th days from the start of the experiment from fresh soil samples. Soil respiration was measured as soil CO 2  release by chemical titration ( Anderson 1982 ). Fifty grams of fresh soil were taken in a 346.2-cm 3  box, and a 5-cm-diameter Petri dish containing 10 mL of 0.1 N NaOH was placed on the soil inside the box and sealed to avoid any loss of CO 2 , and incubated for 24 h. One millilitre of 0.1 N BaCl 2  was added to the NaOH to terminate incubation, and then titrated against 0.1 N HCl using phenolphthalein as an indicator. The amount of CO 2  released was calculated following  Anderson (1982) . Available nitrogen in fresh soil was first extracted and analysed as described previously. Each soil sample was replicated five times for the analyses.  To examine the effect of available nitrogen, manipulated by adding glucose, on  A. adenophora  biomass, we sowed  A. adenophora  seeds and plants were allowed to grow for 60 days. Unamended soil irrigated with distilled water served as the control. There were a total of 20 pots (4 concentrations × 5 replicates). Soil was irrigated with a similar concentration of glucose after 30 days before thinning the seedlings to five seedlings per pot. The plants, both shoot and root, were harvested after 60 days. Each of the  A. adenophora  seedlings was weighed individually and their average/pot was obtained. They were dried at 50 °C for 3 days and their biomass estimated as their total dry weight.  Field soil was collected from the rhizosphere of  A. adenophora  or the area not yet invaded by it (identified as open soil) in two microsites in Palampur (Forest or Roadside) and Mussoorie (Forest and Hill-slope) in March 2011.  Ageratina adenophora  roots were pulled off and shaken to collect soil. Soil from the open areas in each microsite in two sites was collected at a depth of 10 cm. Sixteen soil samples from Palampur (2 areas (open and invaded) × 2 microsites × 4 subsites) and 20 soil samples from Mussoorie (2 areas × 2 microsites × 5 subsites) with each soil sample replicated three times were analysed for available nitrogen and soil respiration. Fifty grams of soil were first irrigated with 15 mL of distilled water and incubated at room temperature for 5 days to reactivate the microbial activity in the soil and then analysed for available nitrogen and soil respiration as described above.  Differences in the mean dry weights of  A. adenophora  seedlings and available nitrogen in non-sterile and sterile soils were tested using the Independent Samples  t -Test. To test the effect of site differences and sterilization treatment given to soil on the available nitrogen and the biomass of  A. adenophora  plants, we performed two-way ANOVA with treatment (non-sterile and sterile soil) and microsites (disturbed and forest sites) as fixed factors, for both Palampur and Mussoorie.  To see the effect of manipulation of microbial populations of soil communities when the soils were treated with different levels of C on  A. adenophora , we tested the correlation between the concentrations of C added to the soil in the form of glucose and available nitrogen, and between C concentrations and soil respiration. Pearson's correlation coefficient  r  was calculated to find out the correlation between soil C and available nitrogen or soil respiration. The effect of addition of different levels of C on  A. adenophora  plant biomass was tested by calculating the differences in the biomass of  A. adenophora  plants grown in C-treated soil at each concentration and between those grown in untreated soil taken as the control using the Independent Samples  t -Test.  Differences in the soil respiration or available nitrogen in the open area and  A. adenophora  rhizosphere soil were tested using the Independent Samples  t -Test ( P  &lt; 0.05) except for the differences in soil respiration in Mussoorie forest where the data were not normally distributed (Shapiro–Wilk test,  P  &gt; 0.05) and were tested using the Mann–Whitney  U  test (asymptotic significance two-tailed,  P  &lt; 0.05). All analyses were carried out using SPSS 16.0 ( SPSS Inc. 2008 ).  (A) Biomass accumulation (mg) of 60-day-old  A. adenophora  plants grown in the non-sterile and sterile rhizosphere soil of  A. adenophora  from Palampur and Mussoorie. Soil from the rhizosphere of  A. adenophora  was collected from undisturbed (Forest) and disturbed (Roadside or Hill-slope) habitats. (B) Available nitrogen (µg NO 3 -N per g soil) in soil from the rhizosphere of  A. adenophora  in Palampur and Mussoorie or in the sterilized treatment of the same. Error bars represent  +1 SE  of the mean.  P  values above the bars represent a significant difference between  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation (A) or available nitrogen (B) in the two different soil treatments (Independent Samples  t -Test;  P  &lt; 0.05).  Summary of two-way ANOVA showing the effects of soil (non-sterile and sterile) and microsite (disturbed and forest) and their interaction on  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation, and on the available nitrogen in the rhizosphere soil from Palampur and Mussoorie. d.f., degrees of freedom. Significance level (in bold): * P  &lt; 0.05.  Summary of the Independent Samples  t -Test conducted for differences in  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation when grown in soil treated with 0 µg C per g soil (identified as the control) or glucose (125, 250 or 500 µg C per g soil). d.f., degrees of freedom. Significance level (in bold): * P  &lt; 0.05.  Correlation between C concentration (µg C per g soil) and available nitrogen (µg NO 3 -N per 0.01 g soil, solid spheres) or soil respiration (µg CO 2  per g soil per h, hollow spheres), in soil from open areas treated with four levels of C, control (0 µg C per g soil), low (125 µg C per g soil), medium (250 µg C per g soil) and high (500 µg C per g soil) on the 60th day of first amendment. Double asterisks indicate that correlation coefficient  r  is significant at  P  &lt; 0.01. Inset, mean ( +SE ) biomass of 60-day-old  A. adenophora  seedlings in soil from open areas treated with the above-mentioned three levels of C on the 60th day of first amendment. Asterisks above the bars represent a significant difference between the dry biomass of seedlings grown in soils amended with glucose and the unamended soil taken as the control (Independent Samples  t -Test;  P  &lt; 0.05,  Table 2 ).  Available nitrogen and soil respiration in soils from open areas (hollow) and the rhizosphere of  A. adenophora  (solid) in microsites: Forest (square,  n  = 4) or Roadside (diamond,  n  = 4) in Palampur, and Forest (circle,  n  = 5) or Hill-slope (triangle,  n  = 5) in Mussoorie: Bars indicate ±1 SE. Differences between available nitrogen and soil respiration in soil from open areas and the rhizosphere of  A. adenophora  from a site were tested using the Independent Samples  t -Test ( P  &lt; 0.05) except for the differences in soil respiration in Mussoorie forest where the data were not normally distributed (Shapiro–Wilk test,  P  &gt; 0.05) and were tested using the Mann–Whitney  U  test (asymptotic significance two-tailed,  P  &lt; 0.05).  We observed that the available nitrogen in the soil collected from the  A. adenophora  rhizosphere was also significantly higher compared with that in soil collected from open areas in Palampur as well as Mussoorie. It was 293.9 % (Roadside, df = 22,  t  = −3.801,  P  = 0.001) and 193.96 % (Forest, df = 22,  t  = −9.162,  P  &lt; 0.0001) higher in the  A. adenophora  rhizosphere soils in Palampur. In Mussoorie, we observed an increase in the levels of available nitrogen in the  A. adenophora  rhizosphere of 95.62 % in the Hill-slope site (df = 28,  t  = −4.450,  P  &lt; 0.0001) and 510.17 % in the Forest site (df = 28,  t  = −4.467,  P  = 0.001) compared with open soils (Fig.  3 ).  We found that sterilization of  A. adenophora  rhizosphere soil exerts a positive impact on its biomass accumulation and resulted in higher levels of available nitrogen (Fig.  1 ). The higher biomass accumulation of  A. adenophora  is attributed to a post-sterilization nitrogen release (Fig.  1 B). This could also be due to lower microbial activity (Fig.  2 ) or could also be related to a release from soil pathogens. Soil microbes retain inorganic nitrogen and release it back to the soil upon sterilization ( Razavi darbar and Lakzian 2007 ). The higher biomass accumulation of  A. adenophora  and higher levels of available nitrogen in sterile soil than in non-sterile  A. adenophora  soil (Fig.  1 ) suggest that higher nitrogen availability has positive effects on  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation. By manipulating microbial activity, we were able to determine the effect of nitrogen availability on  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation. We manipulated the levels of nitrogen by amending soil with four levels of glucose. Addition of glucose as a C source in soil lowers the nitrogen availability by enhancing microbial activity ( Brady and Weil 2008 ). Soil sterilization experiments showed a higher biomass increase in sterile soils (Fig.  1 ), which could be explained by addressing the effect of microbial activity (due to a lower activity of microbes on sterile and non-enriched soils) on biomass accumulation and nitrogen availability (Fig.  2 ). A significant negative correlation between the glucose-driven CO 2  release by soil communities and available nitrogen suggests that higher microbial activity lowers the levels of nitrogen (Fig.  2 ). We also observed that  A. adenophora  biomass was significantly lower in soil modified with different levels of C (glucose) compared with the untreated control (Fig.  2 , inset; Table  2 ). The observed glucose dose-dependent suppression of  A. adenophora  biomass in glucose-amended soil can be linked to dose-dependent lowering of nitrogen (Fig.  2 , inset). This study suggests that  A. adenophora  grows better in soils with higher nitrogen levels. Since  A. adenophora  allocates higher amounts of nitrogen to its growth in introduced ranges than in native ranges where it allocates more nitrogen to defence ( Feng  et al.  2009 ,  2011 ), and forms mono-dominant communities in introduced ranges ( Inderjit  et al.  2011 ), the higher levels of nitrogen in  A. adenophora  soils compared with open areas contribute to  A. adenophora  biomass accumulation (see also Fig.  2 , inset).This adds to the growing evidence in the literature that available nitrogen facilitates the growth of exotic invasives.  Our data on higher levels of nitrogen in  A. adenophora  soils compared with open soils could be explained by the higher build-up of organic C (3.3 %) below its canopies compared with open forest soil (0.8 %), which could be due to higher  A. adenophora  litterfall (non-forest area, 1.4–10.6 g m −2 ; forest area, 4.5–17.6 g m −2 ).  Ageratina adenophora  litter releases a variety of mono- and sesquiterpenes into the environment ( Inderjit  et al.  2011 ). Terpenes get adsorbed onto soil particles ( Muller and del Moral 1966 ). Accumulation of terpene-rich  A. adenophora  litter results in higher microbial activity, leading to the release of nitrogen from  A. adenophora  litter. Higher accumulation of organic C triggers enhanced microbial activity that results in nitrogen release from litter ( Brady and Weil 2008 ). The litter of certain exotic species is known to release higher amounts of nitrogen compared with native litter in spite of similar decomposition rates ( Hata  et al.  2012 ;  Meisner  et al.  2012 ). For example, certain exotic species accumulate greater amounts of nutrients as a consequence of greater organic C below their canopies and in their rhizosphere, e.g.  Artemisia frigida  and  Caraganda microphylla  ( Su  et al.  2004 ;  Ehrenfeld  et al.  2005 ) or trees like  Prosopis juliflora , an aggressive invasive ( Kaur  et al.  2012 b  ). Higher levels of nitrogen-fixing bacterial communities are reported in the  A. adenophora  rhizosphere compared with open soils ( Xu  et al.  2012 ) but nitrogen levels in the present study seem to link with microbial activities as evident from higher nitrogen levels in sterilized  A. adenophora  rhizosphere soil (Fig.  1 B). We compared  A. adenophora  and non- A. adenophora  (open) soils in order to understand its impact on belowground processes largely because such comparisons would include long-term changes in nutrient and litter dynamics ( Meisner  et al.  2011 ). Our work suggests that the invader could trigger higher microbial activities through litter inputs, which facilitate nitrogen release. Any role of soil communities needs to be integrated with litter quality and resource availability. There is a need to focus our future work on studying whether local species co-occurring with the invader also share the extra benefit that exotic species gain from the available nitrogen. This would help us to understand how nitrogen enables exotic plants to dominate.  Our results show that  A. adenophora  biomass increase is affected by nitrogen availability and that this is due to its rhizosphere retaining nitrogen. The importance of nitrogen in facilitating  A. adenophora  biomass is established by comparing its growth in non-sterile and sterile soil from its rhizosphere. We therefore consider it important to study the impact on nitrogen availability when examining the role of soil communities in plant invasion ( Perkins and Nowak 2013 ). Our results are also important for conservation biologists because we show that nitrogen facilitates invasion of exotic species like  A. adenophora  through soil community. Any fertilization in the forest should be reviewed, particularly for the areas invaded by exotic species with potential soil community-driven nitrogen availability as a mechanism of success ( Perry  et al.  2010 ).  The research was funded by the  Council of Scientific &amp; Industrial Research (CSIR)  and the  University of Delhi .  D.B. and Inderjit designed the research. D.B. performed the experiments. D.B. and Inderjit analysed the data and wrote the paper.  None declared.  D.B. thanks the University of Delhi for providing University Teaching Assistantship (UTA). We thank Dr Kurt Reinhart and two anonymous reviewers for constructive comments on the previous draft of this paper. 