Regression analysis of growth responses to water depth in three wetland plant speciesPlant zonation and the effects of the spring–neap tidal cycle on soil aeration in a Humber salt marshConvective gas-flows in wetland plant aerationFlooding stress: acclimations and genetic diversityPreference of wet dune species for waterlogged conditions can be explained by adaptations and specific recruitment requirementsDifferences in flooding tolerance between species from two wetland habitats with contrasting hydrology: implications for vegetation development in future floodwater retention areasInternal pressurization and convective gas flow in some emergent freshwater macrophytesA gentle introduction to quantile regression for ecologistsEstimating effects of limiting factors with regression quantilesUnderwater photosynthesis and respiration in leaves of submerged wetland plants: gas films improve CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> exchangeFlooding tolerance: suites of plant traits in variable environmentsThe influence of water level fluctuations on the growth of four emergent speciesResponses to a fluctuating environment: effects of water depth on growth and biomass allocation in <italic>Eleocharis cellulosa</italic> Torr. (Cyperaceae)Field techniques for measuring wetland soil parametersEffect of minor water depth treatments on competitive effect and response of eight wetland plantsDistribution, productivity and reproductive phenology of emergent macrophytes in relation to water regimes at wetlands of South-western AustraliaPlasticity in root/shoot portioning: optimal, ontogenetic, or bothEffects of water depth on <italic>Typha latifolia</italic> and <italic>Typha domingensis</italic>Depth distribution of three <italic>Typha</italic> species, <italic>Typha orientalis</italic> Presl., <italic>Typha angustifolia</italic> L. and <italic>Typha latifolia</italic> L., in an artificial pondFlooding induces a suite of adaptive plastic responses in the grass <italic>Paspalum dilatatum</italic>Control of plant species richness and zonation of functional groups along a freshwater flooding gradientImpact of competition on plant performances along a flooding gradient: a multi-species experimentFlood tolerance in wetland angiosperms: a comparison of invasive and noninvasive speciesComputing regression quantilesThe effect of long-term submergence on functional properties of <italic>Eleocharis cellulosa</italic> TorrEffects of inundation on growth and nutrient allocation of six major macrophytes in the Florida EvergladesResponses of native and invasive wetland plants to hydroperiod and water depthEcological consequences of phenotypic plasticityUnderwater photosynthesis in flooded terrestrial plants: a matter of leaf plasticityProductivity–decomposition dynamics of <italic>Typha orientalis</italic> at Kaitoke Swamp, Great Barrier Island, New ZealandPlants and flooding stressThe importance of water regimes operating at small spatial scales for the diversity of wetland vegetationConstraints on the establishment of plants along a fluctuating water-depth gradientThe ups and downs of life on the edge: the influence of water level fluctuations on biomass allocation in two contrasting aquatic plantsConvective gas flow and the maximum depths achieved by helophyte vegetation in lakesHow does your wetland grow? Growth and morphological responses of emergent wetland plants to water depthWater-depth tolerances of the dominant emergent macrophytes of the Delta Marsh, ManitobaUse of non-linear regression techniques for describing concentration-response relationships of plant species exposed to contaminated site soilsEcology of freshwater shore zonesEcological limits to plant phenotypic plasticityThe effect of environmental factors on floating fresh marsh end-of-season biomassPhenotypic plasticity in <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> as a functional response to water depthThe influence of ventilation systems on water depth penetration of emergent macrophytesA systematic review of published evidence linking wetland plants to water regime componentsA heteroskedasticity-consistent covariance matrix estimator and a direct test for heteroskedasticityThe influence of convective flow on rhizome length in <italic>Typha domingensis</italic> over a water depth gradientHow frequent storms affect wetland vegetation: a preview of climate-change impactsThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Variability in plant flooding tolerance is often associated with differential growth responses to increasing water depth. This study highlights how morphological responses conferring flooding tolerance differ, using non-linear and quantile regression to quantitatively compare flooding-related growth responses of three species.Plant species composition in wetlands and on lakeshores often shows dramatic zonation, which is frequently ascribed to differences in flooding tolerance. This study compared the growth responses to water depth of three species (<italic>Phormium tenax, Carex secta</italic> and <italic>Typha orientalis</italic>) differing in depth preferences in wetlands, using non-linear and quantile regression analyses to establish how flooding tolerance can explain field zonation.Plants were established for 8 months in outdoor cultures in waterlogged soil without standing water, and then randomly allocated to water depths from 0 to 0.5 m. Morphological and growth responses to depth were followed for 54 days before harvest, and then analysed by repeated-measures analysis of covariance, and non-linear and quantile regression analysis (QRA), to compare flooding tolerances.Growth responses to depth differed between the three species, and were non-linear. <italic>Phormium tenax</italic> growth decreased rapidly in standing water &gt;0.25 m depth, <italic>C. secta</italic> growth increased initially with depth but then decreased at depths &gt;0.30 m, accompanied by increased shoot height and decreased shoot density, and <italic>T. orientalis</italic> was unaffected by the 0- to 0.50-m depth range. In <italic>P. tenax</italic> the decrease in growth was associated with a decrease in the number of leaves produced per ramet and in <italic>C. secta</italic> the effect of water depth was greatest for the tallest shoots. Allocation patterns were unaffected by depth.The responses are consistent with the principle that zonation in the field is primarily structured by competition in shallow water and by physiological flooding tolerance in deep water. Regression analyses, especially QRA, proved to be powerful tools in distinguishing genuine phenotypic responses to water depth from non-phenotypic variation due to size and developmental differences.Plant species zonation is a characteristic feature of water depth gradients in wetland environments and lake shorelines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C35">Seabloom <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C41">Strayer and Findlay 2010</xref>). Zonation develops due to competitive interactions, grazing and disturbance by animals, physical disturbance by water movement and wave action, and differences in physiological flooding tolerance adaptations that support growth in standing water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C24">Keddy 2010</xref>). The factors associated with flooding that stress plants in deep water include the limited ability of most wetland species to assimilate inorganic carbon from water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C9">Colmer and Pedersen 2008</xref>), light attenuation and its effects on photosynthesis and development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C31">Mommer and Visser 2005</xref>), and oxygen deprivation in below-ground rhizomes and roots growing in anaerobic sediments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C3">Bailey-Serres and Voesenek 2008</xref>). These abiotic stresses, and the extent to which they can be avoided or tolerated due to ecophysiological adaptations that confer flooding tolerance, become increasingly growth limiting as water depth increases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C37">Sorrell and Hawes 2010</xref>). A wide range of morphological, anatomical and biochemical responses that are induced when plants are either waterlogged or submerged have been described over the last 40 years, and shown to contribute to survival and growth in natural wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C10">Colmer and Voesenek 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C46">Webb <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>).A notable feature of wetland zonation is the persistence and dominance of helophytes (emergent species with underwater buds) at all depths when standing water is present. Plants in standing water require the same below-ground adaptations for dealing with oxygen deprivation (e.g. aerenchyma formation in roots) as all wetland species growing in permanently anoxic soils, but face the additional challenge of transporting oxygen from the atmosphere to the below-ground tissue through the water, via the shoot aerenchyma. This challenge is not trivial, as the flux of oxygen delivered by gas-phase diffusion decreases rapidly with transport distance (Armstrong <italic>et al.</italic> 1991). Less oxygen delivered by shoots means less below-ground growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C48">White and Ganf 1998</xref>) and, coupled with the much greater fraction of the shoot unable to participate in photosynthetic C assimilation, forces plants to respond to deep water by altering shoot morphology to a smaller number of taller shoots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C44">Vretare <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). These responses are seen even in species such as <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> and <italic>Typha</italic> spp., which have internal convective gas flows that provide much greater internal oxygen flux than diffusion (Armstrong <italic>et al.</italic> 1991), and such responses are strongly linked to depth penetration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C37">Sorrell and Hawes 2010</xref>), as plants approach their depth limits. Fewer, taller shoots with depth is an extremely common feature of helophyte depth responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C46">Webb <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), so quantifying this development can provide valuable insight into how wetland plants become stressed and ultimately killed by standing water.Many species also respond differently to fluctuating water levels and to sudden increases in water depth than they do to deep but stable water levels. Although growth can be enhanced by fluctuating water levels in fast-growing, phenotypically plastic species such as <italic>Phalaris arundinacea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C29">Miller and Zedler 2003</xref>), many species are less productive in fluctuating than in stable water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C12">Edwards <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C11">Deegan <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>), and most also suffer significantly decreased growth in response to a large, sudden depth increase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C33">Perata <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Current climate models are predicting a much greater frequency of sudden storm events accompanied by rapid water depth increases in lowland wetland habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C50">Zedler 2010</xref>), but very few studies have attempted to compare the effects of sudden depth increases on the growth and morphological responses of species adapted to different elevations in shoreline zonation.Growth responses to environmental stresses often feature non-linear relationships in which variances are highly heterogeneous, especially when confounded with factors other than the stress factor under consideration. In flooding tolerance studies, it can be particularly difficult to distinguish genuine phenotypic responses to depth from non-phenotypic variation associated with size and development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C44">Vretare <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). This study therefore features a regression-based non-categorical comparison of depth responses between three species differing in flooding tolerance, and analysis by non-linear regression and quantile regression analysis (QRA). The benefits of QRA are explored given its recent growing popularity in ecology for detecting functional relationships in data for all portions of a probability distribution, especially when multiple factors affect morphology and biomass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C43">Visser and Sasser 2009</xref>). The aim of the study was therefore to explore how various regression techniques can be applied to water depth–plant response data, to provide greater insight into growth responses than categorical analysis of variance (ANOVA)-based experimental designs.Three wetland species with well-documented differences in flooding tolerance adaptations, depth preferences and responses to water depth were used. All three species are native to New Zealand, and widespread and common in lowland minerotrophic wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C22">Johnson and Gerbeaux 2004</xref>) and have previously had their flooding tolerance adaptations investigated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C6">Brix <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C38">Sorrell <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). <italic>Phormium tenax</italic> is a facultative wetland species that thrives under intermittent waterlogging and flooding, but has reduced growth and greater mortality in permanent standing water. <italic>Carex secta</italic> is a large tussock sedge that tolerates prolonged waterlogging and flooding, albeit with conspicuously reduced growth in permanent standing water. <italic>Typha orientalis</italic> is an obligate wetland helophyte indefinitely tolerant of waterlogging and of flooding to water depths &gt;1 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C37">Sorrell and Hawes 2010</xref>). All three species have aerenchymatous shoots and roots, but root porosity is much lower (&lt;20%) in <italic>P. tenax</italic> than the other two species (ca. 40–50% porosity; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C38">Sorrell <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). There is also well-developed internal pressurization and convective gas flow in <italic>T. orientalis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C6">Brix <italic>et al</italic>. 1992</xref>), but no pressurization or flow in either <italic>C. secta</italic> or <italic>P. tenax</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C38">Sorrell <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>).One-month-old seedlings of the three species were obtained from a specialist native plant nursery (Motukarara Conservation Nursery, Christchurch, New Zealand) and established as monospecific experimental cultures in a common garden design at the Silverstream Research Facility, 15 km north of Christchurch, New Zealand (43°33′S, 172°47′E). Each culture was established from a single seedling planted in the centre of a plastic crate (0.5 × 1.0 × 0.5 m) containing 0.20 m<sup>3</sup> floodplain soil (total nitrogen = 700 mg N kg<sup>−1</sup> dry weight (DW), total phosphorus = 400 mg P kg<sup>−1</sup> DW), initially flooded to the surface in a concrete runway under a continuous through-flow of water from the adjacent spring-fed Kaiapoi River (constant temperature = 12 °C). The soils were flooded for 5 months prior to planting to ensure wetland soil anoxia and reducing conditions, which was determined from redox potentials (Eh) measured with permanently installed (0.25 m depth) welded platinum wire electrodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C13">Faulkner <italic>et al</italic>. 1989</xref>), using a saturated Ag/AgCl reference electrode with +199 mV added to correct to Eh readings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C1">Armstrong <italic>et al</italic>. 1985</xref>). All populations were then allowed to establish at the same water depth (flooded to soil surface, i.e. water depth = 0 m) for 8 months over the austral autumn–winter–spring months of May–November. At this time the mean Eh value in the 27 cultures was 185 ± 16 mV, typical of permanently waterlogged, anoxic and moderately wetland soils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C13">Faulkner <italic>et al</italic>. 1989</xref>). The experiment was then initiated by randomly allocating the crates to nine new depths between 0 and 0.5 m for the nine cultures of each species.<bold>Summary of repeated-measures ANCOVAs on sequential morphological measurements for <italic>P. tenax, C. secta</italic> and <italic>T. orientalis</italic>.</bold> The repeated measure (Time) based on measurements on Days 0, 16, 27, 40 and 54 after the establishment of new depths, with depth of cultures as the covariate. <italic>F</italic> values shown with degrees of freedom are in parentheses. Positive (+) and negative (−) main effects of time and depth are shown after significant <italic>P</italic> values (denoted by bold text). Variables that did not satisfy homogeneity assumptions (<italic>C. secta</italic>, number of live shoots; <italic>T. orientalis</italic>, number of ramets) were log-transformed before analysis.On Day 54, plants were removed from boxes by gentle washing of the substrate free from roots and rhizomes, and were separated into live (green) and dead (yellow/brown) tissue and biomass fractions (leaves, shoots, shoot base, rhizome, roots) within individual ramets. Material was dried at 70 °C for 48 h before weighing.<bold>Summary of the QRA for <italic>P. tenax</italic> and <italic>T. orientalis</italic>.</bold> All models are single-parameter quantile fits with depth as the independent variable <italic>x</italic> and determined at <italic>τ</italic> = 0.90 and <italic>τ</italic> = 0.95. DM, dry mass. Models are functions of the measured dependent variables vs. depth, with <italic>t</italic> and <italic>P</italic> statistics. All quantile regressions with <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.10 are shown; regressions with <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.10 are identified as n.s. (not significant).All three species had 100% survival in their nine cultures at all water depths. Soil Eh readings remained stable between +115 and +198 mV throughout the experiment and were unaffected by flooding depth (<italic>P</italic> = 0.65).<bold>Effect of water depth on (A) cumulative leaf extension and (B) change in number of live leaves of <italic>P. tenax</italic>.</bold> Each line represents one of the nine cultures at randomly allocated flooding depths (depths in metres) shown in the key in (A). Negative values in (A) occur when cultures had less total leaf length than at the start of the flooding treatment. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS043TB1">Table 1</xref> for ANCOVA analysis.<bold>Effect of water depth on (A) cumulative increase in shoot number and (B) final total shoot number of <italic>C. secta</italic>.</bold> In (A) each line represents one of the nine cultures at randomly allocated flooding depths (depths in metres shown in the key). Negative values in (A) occur when cultures had fewer shoots than at the start of the flooding treatment. Data in (B) are total number of live and dead shoots in each culture. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS043TB1">Table 1</xref> for ANCOVA analysis.<bold>Effect of water depth on total dry mass in the nine cultures of each species.</bold> Each point is the sum of all material in each of the nine cultures of each species after harvest at the end of the experiment (54 days). Non-linear regression models are curves of best fit for the three species (models with lowest variance of residuals). For <italic>P. tenax</italic>, the sigmoidal logistical model described the depth response, for <italic>C. secta</italic> a logistic model with hormesis best described the response, and for <italic>T. orientalis</italic> there was no significant effect of depth on biomass according to any models.<bold>Effect of water depth on dry mass at final harvest of individual leaves of <italic>P. tenax</italic>.</bold> (A) Plot of leaf dry mass (<italic>n</italic> = 44) at different depths analysed by LSR (bold line) and with 0.50, 0.60, 0.70, 0.80, 0.90 and 0.95 quantile estimates of the depth vs. dry mass relationship. (B) and (C) Functions of slope and intercept vs. <italic>τ</italic> of the quantile regression lines, and significance level (<italic>P</italic>, open circles). See <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS043TB2">Table 2</xref> for QRA statistics.<bold>Effect of water depth on the total leaf length of ramets of <italic>P. tenax</italic> and <italic>T. orientalis.</italic></bold> Plots of total leaf length for individual ramets (<italic>n</italic> = 44 <italic>P. tenax</italic> ramets, <italic>n</italic> = 40 T<italic>. orientalis</italic> ramets) vs. depth analysed by LSR (bold line) and quantile regression (with <italic>τ</italic> = 0.90 and 0.95). The LSR is not significant for either species (<italic>P</italic> = 0.21 for <italic>P. tenax</italic>, <italic>P</italic> = 0.28 for <italic>T. orientalis</italic>) See <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS043TB2">Table 2</xref> for QRA statistics.The QRA of depth responses of morphological parameters is summarized for <italic>P. tenax</italic> and <italic>T. orientalis</italic> in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS043TB2">2</xref>. It shows the effect of depth on <italic>P. tenax</italic> is to reduce numbers of leaves per ramet, and thereby total leaf length and both live and dead dry mass, but not the length or width of individual leaves. Together with the time series in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS043F1">1</xref>, this reveals how the sudden depth increase imposed by the experiment had little effect on the pre-existing leaves, which the plants were able to maintain, but inhibited new leaf growth, especially at depths ca. &gt;0.2 m (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS043F1">1</xref>, cf. Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS043F3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS043F4"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS043F5">5</xref>). This is in contrast to <italic>T. orientalis</italic>, in which growth remained unaffected over the 0.5 m depth increase range of this experiment, with no significant regressions with either LSR or at any quantile level (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS043TB2">2</xref>).<bold>Effect of water depth on the shoot height of <italic>C. secta</italic>.</bold> (A) Least-squares regression analysis (bold line) with 95% confidence intervals (solid lines) and prediction intervals (dashed lines). Closed circles are mean numbers of shoots at each depth (±1 standard deviation), open circles show upper and lower 95% quantiles of data identified by QRA (LSR = 0.064 + 0.011 × depth, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.07, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). (B) Histogram of shoot heights from all <italic>Carex</italic> plants in the experiment (bars are 0.01 m intervals), with fitted normal distribution. (C) Quantile regression analysis showing change in slope of quantile regression estimates (filled circles) at increasing <italic>τ</italic> with upper and lower 95% confidence intervals (open circles). The slope estimates are not significant at <italic>τ</italic> &lt; 0.15, but are always significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) at <italic>τ</italic> ≥ 0.15. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS043TB2">Table 2</xref> for QRA statistics.The present study of emergent plant development after a sudden increase in water depth revealed that growth and morphological responses differed between the three species over the 0.5 m depth gradient, in accordance with their documented field zonation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C22">Johnson and Gerbeaux 2004</xref>) and flooding tolerance adaptations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C38">Sorrell <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). Applying the same depth range for all three species can highlight differences in species' responses that suit them to a particular water regime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C11">Deegan <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), and treating depth as a continuous rather than a categorical variable revealed its non-linear effect on morphological and growth responses. Although the greatest water depth applied in this study was not lethal for any of the species over the timeframe of this experiment, the repeated-measures ANOVA and regressions clearly allowed their flooding tolerances to be contrasted. Furthermore, the non-linear regression approach allowed depth thresholds beyond which the less flood-tolerant species were negatively affected by standing water to be clearly identified (ca. 0.25 and 0.30 m depth for <italic>P. tenax</italic> and <italic>C. secta</italic>, respectively), and can also be extrapolated to allow predictions of maximum lethal depths. Regressions were also successful in identifying which growth features were <italic>not</italic> affected by flooding, especially allocation patterns, as expressed by parameters such as below : above-ground ratios, and leaf and root mass allocation. Flooding increases shoot : root ratios and allocation to leaves in many wetland taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C25">Kercher and Zedler 2004</xref>), although this is most often observed in small, young plants, and the lack of response of such parameters in our experiment is likely to be a consequence of our experimental units being larger, well-established cultures where some of the pre-existing biomass did not respond to the depth increase. Many flooding tolerance studies are carried out using relatively small plants, and this approach has yielded much valuable information about growth responses, especially during establishment (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C36">Smith and Brock 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C14">Fraser and Miletti 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C5">Banach <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Our study highlights how larger, established cultures can provide alternative information that may be more relevant to field responses of pre-existing vegetation. A disadvantage of using larger experimental units is that often, less replication is possible due to practical limitations; the regression approach is particularly valuable in such experiments as it does not rely on replicated units at an individual depth. Instead, it can establish significant responses by taking a population approach to ramets and shoots over the entire depth range studied.A clear qualitative difference in the nature of the flooding stress is evident when comparing regressions in the three species: reduced growth and failure to elongate above-ground leaves in <italic>P. tenax</italic>, reduced growth offset by shoot elongation, particularly of the tallest pre-existing shoots, in <italic>C. secta</italic>, and little effect of depth on <italic>T. orientalis. Typha</italic> species are among the deepest growing of helophytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C37">Sorrell and Hawes 2010</xref>), and the expectation in this study was that the maximum depth of 0.5 m would not cause a flooding-related stress response in <italic>T. orientalis</italic>, in contrast to <italic>P. tenax</italic> and <italic>C. secta. Typha</italic> species differ in their depth responses, but most initially increase shoot length and biomass with depth, and then become stressed by standing water when depth exceeds ca. 0.9–1.0 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C17">Grace 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C19">Inoue and Tsuchiya 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C28">Miao and Zou 2012</xref>). <italic>Typha orientalis</italic> has received less attention than many other <italic>Typha</italic> species, but is capable of accumulating very high biomass in the field in environments ranging from waterlogged soil without standing water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C32">Pegman and Ogden 2005</xref>) to water depths up to 1.0 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C15">Froend and McComb 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C19">Inoue and Tsuchiya 2009</xref>). In controlled experiments, it appears to grow equally well in waterlogged soils with or without standing water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C38">Sorrell <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; this study), unlike some other <italic>Typha</italic> species which appear to grow better in standing water than waterlogged soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C17">Grace 1989</xref>).The ability of <italic>T. orientalis</italic> and other <italic>Typha</italic> spp. to dominate wetland vegetation at depths of 0.5–2.0 m is strongly associated with their development of convective gas flow, as very few species lacking convective flow can persist in water &gt;0.5 m depth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C45">Vretare Strand 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C37">Sorrell and Hawes 2010</xref>). <italic>Phorium tenax</italic> and <italic>C. secta</italic> do not have convective flow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C38">Sorrell <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>), and lack of flow is implicated as the explanation for the rapid decrease in growth they suffered in this experiment as water depth increased above 0.25–0.3 m. Convective flow greatly increases internal oxygen concentrations and below-ground growth over the long distances that oxygen must be transported when there is standing water (Armstrong <italic>et al.</italic> 1991; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C48">White and Ganf 1998</xref>). Aeration differences may also explain the greater flooding tolerance of <italic>C. secta</italic> than <italic>P. tenax</italic>. Both species have relatively limited shoot aerenchyma development, but root porosity is much greater in the former than in the latter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C38">Sorrell <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>), and a greater root aeration capacity may allow oxygen deprivation caused by the limited shoot oxygen supply to be avoided more in <italic>C. secta</italic> than in <italic>P. tenax</italic>.The wide variety of growth forms present in most wetland and shoreline vegetation is an important consideration complicating the understanding of depth effects. Rhizomatous perennials with cylindrical leafless culms (common in genera such as <italic>Eleocharis</italic>, <italic>Juncus</italic> and <italic>Schoenoplectus</italic>), broad-leaved species such as <italic>Typha</italic> spp. and narrower-leaved genera such as <italic>Carex</italic> that may be variously tussock- or sward-forming have different morphological constraints controlling their depth responses, and hence may be difficult to compare directly in growth experiments. The three species in this study differed considerably in their morphology, but relative responses of specific morphological parameters relevant for each taxon to similar depth ranges were able to distinguish their depth preferences and tolerances. Like most wetland monocots, all three species are clonal and QRA could be applied on a population basis to shoots produced across the depth gradient. The great benefit of QRA is that the change in slope and its significance with increasing <italic>τ</italic> identifies which subset of the population of shoots is being affected by depth, independently of any differences in shoot length or weight that are not depth related. In plant development, size itself and ontogenetic change can confound attempts to link apparent growth responses to specific environmental factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C16">Gedroc <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C44">Vretare <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>), and with QRA the upper and lower quantiles can provide more relevant information than a conventional regression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C8">Cade <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>). During development, newly formed shoots and leaves may show less response to environmental stressors than older material that has been exposed to the stressor longer. Quantile regression analysis therefore provides a more nuanced insight into flooding responses than LSR, including responses identified here such as depth affecting numbers of leaves per ramet rather than length of individual leaves in <italic>P. tenax</italic>, and the tallest existing shoots in <italic>C. secta</italic> being those most positively affected by increased depth.An increase in shoot length accompanied by a decrease in shoot density is perhaps the most ubiquitous of all growth responses distinguishing flood-tolerant from flood-sensitive species. It is a particularly characteristic response of the deepest-growing helophytes in wetland communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C12">Edwards <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C27">Macek <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C36">Smith and Brock 2007</xref>), and is usually interpreted as a response that maintains gas exchange with the atmosphere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C44">Vretare <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C11">Deegan <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). It also improves light penetration to the underwater tissues, which may assist those species able to photosynthesize under water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C9">Colmer and Pedersen 2008</xref>). This was the most consistent response to increased water depth in a recent meta-analysis by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C46">Webb <italic>et al</italic>. (2012)</xref>, whereas biomass and allocation responses to flooding were more variable. The inability of <italic>P. tenax</italic> to adjust morphologically to depth, in contrast to the depth accommodation response in <italic>C. secta</italic> and robust growth at all depths in <italic>T. orientalis</italic>, is consistent with the depths at which the three species are observed in the field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C22">Johnson and Gerbeaux 2004</xref>). However, all three species grew very well in waterlogged soil without flooding, supporting the contention by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C24">Keddy (2010)</xref> that wetland plants tolerate extremes of flooding but do not physiologically require them, and that the apparent requirement for flooding in these species is more ecological than physiological. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C24">Keddy (2010)</xref> further suggests that most wetland species have broader physiological tolerance to flooding than the depths at which they occur in the field, zonation therefore being driven by competition in shallow water and physiological tolerance in deeper water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C17">Grace 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C21">Lenssen <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C23">Jung <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The three species in this study fit this model; even <italic>C. secta</italic> which, despite having better growth at 30 cm than at 0 cm depth, rapidly decreased growth at greater depths. Preference for waterlogged soil or very shallow water is characteristic of a number of other clonal wetland monocots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C20">Insausti <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C4">Bakker <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C5">Banach <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Species zonation and vegetation composition in several recent studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C29">Miller and Zedler 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C4">Bakker <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C34">Raulings <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) also support the flooding tolerance–competition depth gradient proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C24">Keddy (2010)</xref>, which is also consistent with broader competition–stress models in plant communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C18">Grime <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>).The responses to flooding depth of these three species differ both quantitatively and qualitatively, and responses are non-linear. The shallow species <italic>P. tenax</italic> has reduced growth at depths &gt;0.25 m, predominantly associated with lower leaf production rather than any change in numbers of ramets produced; the intermediate species <italic>C. secta</italic> displays a depth accommodation response with increasing height and biomass up to 0.30 m depth, but dramatically reduced shoot production and reduced growth at &gt;0.30 m depth; the deep species <italic>T. orientalis</italic> is unaffected by water depths from 0 to 0.5 m. All three species grew well in waterlogged soil without standing water, supporting the principle that competition is the major factor driving zonation in shallow water but physiological tolerance controls zonation in deep water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C21">Lenssen <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C23">Jung <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The depth accommodation response of <italic>C. secta</italic>, which also becomes apparent in <italic>Typha</italic> spp. at depths &gt;0.7 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C17">Grace 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C39">Squires and van der Valk 1992</xref>), demonstrates that phenotypic plasticity (i.e. the production of multiple phenotypes from a single genotype, depending on environmental conditions; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C30">Miner <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>) is an important functional strategy for flood-tolerant wetland plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C44">Vretare <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). We suggest that the regression methods used in our study, especially QRA, are valuable in distinguishing genuine plasticity from non-plastic (i.e. developmental or size-induced) variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C44">Vretare <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>), and that accurate assessments of plasticity need to be incorporated further in interpretation of wetland flooding tolerance experiments, given the increasing awareness of the role that phenotypic plasticity plays in structuring both abiotic responses and community structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS043C42">Valladeres <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>).<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">The New Zealand Ministry of Science and Innovation</grant-sponsor> provided funding for this project (Contract <grant-num xlink:type="simple">C09X1002</grant-num>) and the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Danish Council for Independent Research—Natural Sciences</grant-sponsor> (Project Number <grant-num xlink:type="simple">272-07-0633</grant-num>) funded the research visit of H.B. to New Zealand.B.K.S. undertook the experimental work; all authors contributed to the planning of the research and to the manuscript.None declared.We thank the staff of the Silverstream Research Facility for helpful assistance in caring for plants and maintaining the experiment.