Ethylene is involved in maintaining tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) pollen quality under heat-stress conditionsTranscriptome and selected metabolite analyses reveal multiple points of ethylene control during tomato fruit developmentA versatile stain for pollen, fungi, yeast and bacteriaPectin secretion and distribution in the anther during pollen development in LiliumGlass formation in plant anhydrobiotes: survival in the dry stateThe involvement of ethylene in in vitro maturation of mid-binucleate pollen of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>How ethylene works in the reproductive organs of higher plants. A signaling update from the third millenniumPollen grains of heat tolerant tomato cultivars retain higher carbohydrate concentration under heat stress conditionsTranscriptional profiling of maturing tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L.) microspores reveals the involvement of heat shock proteins, ROS scavengers, hormones and sugars in the heat-stress responseEGY1 plays a role in regulation of endodermal plastid size and number that are involved in ethylene-dependent gravitropism of light-grown Arabidopsis hypocotylsDesiccation tolerance of <italic>Papaver dubium</italic> L. pollen during its development in the anther: possible role of phospholipid composition and sucrose contentRole of sucrose phosphate synthase in sucrose biosynthesis in ripening bananas and its relationship to the respiratory climactericExploring the temperature-stress metabolome of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>TomatoEthylene signal transduction. Moving beyond ArabidopsisEthylene is involved in the control of male gametophyte development and germination in petuniaThe <italic>Never ripe</italic> mutation blocks ethylene perception in tomatoThermotolerance and antioxidant systems in <italic>Agrostis stolonifera</italic>: involvement of salicylic acid, abscisic acid, calcium, hydrogen peroxide, and ethyleneProtection against heat stress induced oxidative damage in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> involves calcium, abscisic acid, ethylene, and salicylic acidCore genome responses involved in acclimation to high temperatureHeat stress phenotypes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutants implicate multiple signaling pathways in the acquisition of thermotoleranceMolecular genetics of heat tolerance and heat shock proteins in cerealsA new model system for tomato geneticsEffects of season-long high temperature growth conditions on sugar-to-starch metabolism in developing microspores of grain sorghum (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> L. Moench)Supra-optimal temperatures are detrimental to peanut (<italic>Arachis hypogaea</italic> L.) reproductive processes and yield at ambient and elevated carbon dioxideAdverse high temperature effects on pollen viability, seed-set, seed yield and harvest index of grain sorghum [<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> (L.) Moench] are more severe at elevated carbon dioxide due to higher tissue temperaturesInfluence of low night temperatures on sweet pepper flower quality and the effect of repeated pollinations, with viable pollen, on fruit setThe effect of heat stress on tomato pollen characteristics is associated with changes in carbohydrate concentration in the developing anthersThe effect of high temperatures on the expression and activity of sucrose cleaving enzymes during tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>) anther developmentTomato response to heat stress: focus on pollen grainsMicrosporogenesis in the normal and male-sterile stamenless-2 mutant of tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>)Occurrence of mono- or disaccharides and polysaccharide reserves in mature pollen grainsThe effects of heat stress on cereal yield and qualityMannitol metabolism in celery stressed by excess macronutrientsEnhanced tolerance to environmental stress in transgenic plants expressing the transcriptional coactivator multiprotein bridging factor 1cThe transcriptional co-activator MBF1c is a key regulator of thermotolerance in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Changes in cytoplasmic carbohydrate content during <italic>Helleborus</italic> pollen presentationTemperature stress and plant sexual reproduction: uncovering the weakest linksThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The paper supports the view that ethylene plays a significant role in maintaining tomato pollen thermotolerance. Interfering with the ethylene signalling pathway or reducing ethylene levels and increased tomato pollen sensitivity to heat stress. On the other hand, increasing ethylene levels before heat-stress improved pollen quality.Exposure to higher-than-optimal temperatures reduces crop yield and quality, mainly due to sensitivity of developing pollen grains. The mechanisms maintaining high pollen quality under heat-stress conditions are poorly understood. Our recently published data indicate high heat-stress-induced expression of ethylene-responsive genes in tomato pollen, indicating ethylene involvement in the pollen heat-stress response. Here we elucidated ethylene's involvement in pollen heat-stress response and thermotolerance by assessing the effects of interfering with the ethylene signalling pathway and altering ethylene levels on tomato pollen functioning under heat stress.Plants of the ethylene-insensitive mutant <italic>Never ripe</italic> (<italic>Nr</italic>)—defective in an ethylene response sensor (ERS)-like ethylene receptor—and the corresponding wild type were exposed to control or heat-stress growing conditions, and pollen quality was determined. Starch and carbohydrates were measured in isolated pollen grains from these plants. The effect of pretreating cv. Micro-Tom tomato plants, prior to heat-stress exposure, with an ethylene releaser or inhibitor of ethylene biosynthesis on pollen quality was assessed.<italic>Never ripe</italic> pollen grains exhibited higher heat-stress sensitivity, manifested by a significant reduction in the total number of pollen grains, reduction in the number of viable pollen and elevation of the number of non-viable pollen, compared with wild-type plants. Mature <italic>Nr</italic> pollen grains accumulated only 40 % of the sucrose level accumulated by the wild type. Pretreatment of tomato plants with an ethylene releaser increased pollen quality under heat stress, with an over 5-fold increase in the number of germinating pollen grains per flower. Pretreatment with an ethylene biosynthesis inhibitor reduced the number of germinating pollen grains following heat-stress exposure over 5-fold compared with non-treated controls.Ethylene plays a significant role in tomato pollen thermotolerance. Interfering with the ethylene signalling pathway or reducing ethylene levels increased tomato pollen sensitivity to heat stress, whereas increasing ethylene levels prior to heat-stress exposure increased pollen quality.Exposure to higher-than-optimal temperatures reduces the yield and quality of many crops, including cereals, grain legumes and vegetable crops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C13">Kinet and Peet 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C21">Maestri <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C25">Prasad <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C26">2006</xref>). This problem is crucial in tomato because, to avoid insect-transmitted virus infections, a significant proportion of production is achieved in greenhouses, where the daily mean temperatures are high, especially during the warmer seasons. Short waves of high temperature may also be detrimental. We have shown that in tomato, developing pollen grains are most sensitive to both mild chronic and short-term acute heat-stress (HS) conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C7">Firon <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C29">Pressman <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>): heat-tolerant tomato genotypes exhibiting higher yield under HS produced larger numbers of high-quality pollen grains under these conditions compared with all tested heat-sensitive genotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C7">Firon <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). However, the physiological and molecular bases for pollen grains' heat-stress response (HSR) and heat tolerance (thermotolerance) are poorly understood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C30">Pressman <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C38">Zinn <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>).Recently, using two high-throughput transcriptomic approaches—cDNA amplified fragment length polymorphism and the Affymetrix GeneChip<sup>®</sup> (Affymetrix Inc., Santa Clara, CA, USA) Tomato Genome Array—we identified genes that are associated with pollen HSR and may contribute to pollen thermotolerance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C8">Frank <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Contradicting the previous notion that pollen is unable to mount a ‘significant’ HSR, our results (corroborated by reverse transcriptase–polymerase chain reaction and immunoblot analyses) revealed high HS regulation of 11 members of the small heat-shock protein (HSP) gene family, <italic>HSP70</italic> and <italic>HSP90</italic> family members, the HS transcription factors A2 (<italic>HSFA2</italic>) and <italic>HSFA3</italic>, the reactive oxygen species (ROS) scavenger ascorbate peroxidase (<italic>APX</italic>) and factors other than the classical HS-responsive genes. Remarkably, our recently published data indicated HS induction of several ethylene-responsive genes in developing tomato pollen grains, including ethylene-responsive gene 5 (<italic>ER5</italic>), <italic>ER21</italic>, <italic>LeJERF1</italic> and <italic>ER24</italic>, as well as the gene encoding 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) synthase (exhibiting 4-, 63-, 9-, 156- and 6-fold induction following HS, respectively; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C8">Frank <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), pointing to the involvement of ethylene in pollen HSR.To the best of our knowledge, data on the involvement of ethylene in pollen development and pollen HSR are scarce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C6">De la Torre <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). The involvement of ethylene in petunia anther and pollen development was recently demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C15">Kovaleva <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), suggesting the need for tight control of ethylene levels at the different developmental stages. Ethylene was also recently implicated as one of the factors involved in <italic>in-vitro</italic> maturation of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> pollen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C5">Chibi and Mattilla 2010</xref>).With respect to vegetative tissues, evidence for the involvement of ethylene in plant thermotolerance has been reported in numerous studies. For example, pretreatment of a cool-season grass (<italic>Agrostis stolonifera</italic> var. <italic>palustris</italic>) with ACC (a precursor of ethylene) prior to the exposure of plants to HS increased their heat tolerance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C17">Larkindale and Huang 2004</xref>). Similarly, exogenous addition of ACC was shown to protect <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against heat-induced oxidative damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C18">Larkindale and Knight 2002</xref>). In addition, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C20">Larkindale <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> showed that the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ethylene-signalling mutants <italic>ein2</italic> and <italic>etr1</italic> are defective in basal thermotolerance. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C36">Suzuki <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> suggested that a member of the transcriptional coactivator multiprotein bridging factor 1 (MBF1) gene family in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>—<italic>MBF1c</italic>—may act as a regulator of thermotolerance upstream of salicylic acid and ethylene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C36">Suzuki <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Testing the effect of the ethylene biosynthesis and signalling inhibitors aminoethoxyvinylglycine (AVG) and silver thiosulfate, respectively, on heat-stressed wild-type and transgenic plants over-expressing (OE) <italic>MBF1c</italic> demonstrated these inhibitors' suppression of HS tolerance in the <italic>MBF1c</italic> OE plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C35">Suzuki <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). The authors suggested that MBF1c expression enhances the tolerance of transgenic plants to heat by perturbing or partially activating the ethylene-response signal transduction pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C36">Suzuki <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).The objective of the present study was to determine whether ethylene has a role in tomato pollen thermotolerance. The effects of interfering with the ethylene signalling pathway (using plants of a tomato mutant defective in the ethylene receptor, <italic>Never ripe</italic> (<italic>Nr</italic>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C14">Klee 2004</xref>, and references therein), and altering ethylene levels (by pretreating plants with an ethylene releaser or an inhibitor of ethylene biosynthesis), on tomato pollen quality under HS conditions were tested. Results pointed to ethylene's involvement in increasing pollen quality under HS.The following tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) lines were used: <italic>Nr</italic>, a tomato mutant defective in the ethylene receptor; a semidominant ethylene receptor mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C14">Klee 2004</xref>, and references therein) and its background line Pearson (a gift from Professor H. Klee, University of Florida, USA); and the tomato cultivar Micro-Tom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C23">Meissner <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>), which is small, has a short life cycle and produces a relatively high number of flowers. Plants were grown in two temperature-controlled greenhouses at The Volcani Center in Bet Dagan, Israel, under natural light conditions (day length of 13.5–14 h) and day/night temperatures of 28/22 ± 2 °C (designated control conditions) for 2 months. These environmental conditions have been found to ensure high pollen quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C28">Pressman <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). Then one of the greenhouses, containing <italic>Nr</italic> and Pearson plants, was set to day/night temperatures of 32/26 ± 2 °C (designated mild chronic HS conditions; MCHS) and the plants were kept, in both greenhouses, for three additional months, with continuous production of flowers and fruits. Mature pollen grains were sampled from plants growing under the two temperature regimes after at least 14 days of exposure to MCHS, to determine the number of viable (stained purple) and non-viable (stained green) pollen grains, using Alexander dye (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C2">Alexander 1980</xref>). Data were collected during four summer seasons (2008–2011).Micro-Tom plants grown at day/night temperatures of 28/22 ± 2 °C were exposed to short-term HS conditions (STHS; 50 °C for 2 h) at specific flower developmental stages (detailed below). During the heat treatment, to avoid drought stress and wilting, plants were kept in a humid environment. Short-term HS was applied to flower buds 3 and 0 days before flower opening, corresponding to developmental stages A-3 (early binucleate stage) and A (anthesis) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C31">Sawhney and Bhadula 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C28">Pressman <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). Following calibration of effective concentrations, 1 μL L<sup>−1</sup> (1 p.p.m.) ethephon (2-chloroethyl phosphonic acid), an ethylene-releasing compound, or 0.3 mM AVG, was applied to plants containing flower buds 4 days (between vacuolated and early binucleate stage of microspore development) and 1 day before flower opening, by soaking the plants in the respective solution for 18 or 4 h, respectively, before exposure to STHS. In the control treatment, plants were treated with an equal amount of water. Each treatment consisted of at least six replicates.To determine whether tomato pollen has the capacity for acquired thermotolerance (ATT), plants bearing inflorescences with flowers at different developmental stages were exposed for 1 h to 32 °C, followed by 1 h recovery at 25 °C, prior to exposing them to STHS. To determine pollen quality, microspores were allowed to mature and pollen grains were collected at anthesis from the HS and control plants. Total number, and the number of viable, non-viable and germinating pollen grains, were determined as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C27">Pressman <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref> and detailed below.At least six flowers at first day of anthesis were sampled from each treatment. One anther was removed from each flower and placed in a microfuge tube containing 0.5 mL of germination solution consisting of 100 g L<sup>−1</sup> sucrose, 2 mM boric acid, 2 mM calcium nitrate, 2 mM magnesium sulfate and 1 mM potassium nitrate, and the tubes were shaken well to release the pollen grains. The tubes were placed in an incubator at 25 °C for 4 h, after which a drop of Alexander dye was added to the solution. This method enables the number of germinating grains to be recorded while simultaneously analysing the number of non-viable (stained green) and viable (stained purple) pollen grains. Drops of the solution were mounted in a haemocytometer and the grains were counted with a light microscope, eight fields for each sample. This procedure was repeated three times and average results were calculated.Anthers collected from at least 50 flowers were dissected according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C3">Aouali <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref>. Pollen grains were obtained by slicing the anthers transversely and vortexing them in cold, sucrose-free germination solution. The solution was then filtered through cheesecloth to remove the anther walls, and pollen grains were separated by centrifugation for 10 min at 8000 <italic>g</italic>. The released pollen grains were immediately suspended in 80 % ethanol at 75 °C for 30 min. The carbohydrate concentrations in pollen samples were analysed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C11">Hubbard <italic>et al.</italic> (1990)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C34">Stoop and Pharr (1994)</xref>. Freeze-dried or ethanol-suspended samples were extracted three times in hot 80 % (v/v) ethanol. The supernatant was dried <italic>in vacuo</italic> at 40 °C and resolubilized in water. Soluble sugars were determined by HPLC with a Fast Carbohydrate column (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) operated at 85 °C with deionized, degassed water as eluent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C34">Stoop and Pharr 1994</xref>) and detection by a refractometer. The insoluble residue that remained after ethanolic extraction was resuspended in 2 mL of 30 mM HCl and boiled for 30 min. After cooling, the pH was adjusted to 4.5 with KOH. The gelatinized starch was digested for 60 min at 50 °C with ∼36 units of amyloglucosidase from <italic>Aspergillus oryza</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C11">Hubbard <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>). The reaction mixture was incubated at 25 °C for 30 min and absorbance at 340 nm was measured.All pollen quality results are the means of at least six biological replicates. The results of starch and carbohydrate analyses are the means of three experiments; in each experiment, samples were prepared from pollen collected from 50 flowers. Data are presented as mean ± SE. Multiple comparison Tukey's honestly significant difference (HSD) test was used to test for mean values that are significantly different (<italic>α</italic> = 0.05).Effect of heat stress on pollen number and quality of wild-type and <italic>Nr</italic> mutant tomato plants. Mature pollen grains were collected from wild-type (Pearson) and ethylene receptor mutant (<italic>Nr</italic>) tomato plants which were exposed for at least 14 days to either control (28/22 °C day/night) or mild chronic heat stress (MCHS; 32/26 °C day/night) conditions. Pollen quality is presented as mean values (<italic>n</italic> = 4 independent experiments carried out in four summer seasons, at least six biological replicates each) of number of total, viable and non-viable pollen grains per flower.In each pollen-quality category (total, viable, non-viable), values followed by different letters are significantly different by multiple comparison Tukey's HSD test (<italic>α</italic> = 0.05).Effect of heat stress on starch concentration in pollen grains at different stages of flower development from wild-type and <italic>Nr</italic> mutant tomato plants. Pollen grains were collected from wild-type (Pearson) and ethylene receptor mutant (<italic>Nr</italic>) tomato plants exposed for at least 14 days to either control (28/22 °C day/night) or mild chronic heat stress (MCHS; 32/26 °C day/night) conditions. Starch concentrations (mg g DW<sup>−1</sup>) are presented as mean values of three experimental replicates (<italic>n</italic> = 3 independent experiments; pooled from at least 50 flowers each). A–<italic>n</italic> = flower buds <italic>n</italic> days before anthesis (A = flower opening).Values in a row followed by different letters are significantly different (<italic>α</italic> = 0.05) by multiple comparison Tukey's HSD test.<bold>Effect of heat stress on levels of sucrose, glucose and fructose in pollen grains of wild-type and <italic>Nr</italic> mutant tomato plants.</bold> Mature pollen grains at anthesis were collected from wild-type (Pearson) and ethylene receptor mutant (<italic>Nr</italic>) tomato plants which were exposed for at least 14 days to either control (28/22 °C day/night) or mild chronic heat stress (MCHS; 32/26 °C day/night) conditions. Carbohydrate concentrations are presented as mean values ± SE (<italic>n</italic> = 3 independent experiments; pooled from at least 50 flowers each). In each category (control, black bars; MCHS, white bars), bars with different letters are significantly different by multiple comparison Tukey's HSD test (<italic>α</italic> = 0.05).<bold>Effect of ethephon and AVG pretreatments of tomato plants on pollen quality following exposure of the plants to short-term heat stress (STHS).</bold> (A) and (B) Tomato plants (Micro-Tom) were either pretreated with ethephon (+Eth; 1 p.p.m. for 18 h before HS application) or not pretreated (−Eth). (C) and (D) Tomato plants were either pretreated with AVG (+AVG; 0.3 mM for 4 h before HS application) or not pretreated (−AVG). Short-term heat stress conditions were 2 h exposure to 50 °C. Control (C)—plants maintained at 25 °C. STHS treatment was applied (A) and (C) 3 days before flower opening—developmental stage A-3, or (B) and (D) at anthesis—developmental stage A. ATT—acquired thermotolerance conditions were 1 h exposure to 32 °C followed by 1 h recovery at 25 °C. Acquired thermotolerance conditions were applied prior to HS exposure. Mature pollen grains were collected and pollen quality determined. Data are presented as mean values ± SE (<italic>n</italic> = 12 biological replicates; collected in two experiments) of number of germinating, viable and non-viable pollen grains per flower. In each pollen-quality category (germinating, black bars; viable, white bars; non-viable, grey bars), bars with different letters are significantly different by multiple comparison Tukey's HSD test (<italic>α</italic> = 0.05).To determine whether tomato pollen grains have the capacity for ATT, plants of cv. Micro-Tom were exposed to mild HS (1 h at 32 °C, followed by 1 h recovery at 25 °C) prior to exposure to STHS conditions (2 h at 50 °C) and the effect on pollen quality was tested. The ATT treatment caused an over 3-fold increase in the number of germinating pollen grains compared with non-treated controls following exposure of the plants to STHS conditions, at both stages of flower development (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS024F2">2</xref>C and D; increase from 4.2 × 10<sup>3</sup> and 9.0 × 10<sup>3</sup> to 32 × 10<sup>3</sup> and 33 × 10<sup>3</sup> at developmental stages A-3 and A, respectively). These results thus show that maturing and mature pollen grains (at developmental stages A-3 and A, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS024F2">2</xref>C and D, respectively) have the capacity for ATT.Pretreating plants with the ethylene biosynthesis inhibitor AVG before exposing them to STHS conditions caused a reduction in the number of germinating pollen grains (from 4.2 × 10<sup>3</sup> and 9 × 10<sup>3</sup> to zero, at developmental stages A-3 and A, respectively, as demonstrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS024F2">2</xref>C and D, respectively), and affected the capacity for ATT (reduction from 32 × 10<sup>3</sup> and 33 × 10<sup>3</sup> to 3.7 × 10<sup>3</sup> and 13 × 10<sup>3</sup> germinating pollen grains), at developmental stages A-3 and A, respectively, as demonstrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS024F2">2</xref>C and D, respectively. It should be noted that AVG pretreatment, applied at either stage A-3 or A of pollen development, affected pollen quality, even under optimal growing conditions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS024F2">2</xref>C and D), indicating the involvement of endogenous ethylene in pollen development and germination.Impaired pollen development under high-temperature conditions has been implicated in reduced yields in a large number of crop systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C33">Stone 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C7">Firon <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C26">Prasad <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C24">Mukesh <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). In tomato, developing pollen grains are highly sensitive to HS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C28">Pressman <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C29">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C7">Firon <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Despite the anticipated frequency of HS problems and despite accumulated data on the high HS sensitivity of developing pollen grains, data on the mechanisms involved in pollen HSR and thermotolerance are very limited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C30">Pressman <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). The results presented in this study indicate that perturbation of the tomato ethylene signalling pathway, by a mutation in the ERS-like ethylene receptor, increases the sensitivity of pollen grains to MCHS conditions, as manifested by a reduction in the total number of pollen grains produced, an increase in the number of non-viable pollen grains and a significant reduction in the number of viable pollen grains in <italic>Nr</italic> mutant plants (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS024TB1">1</xref>). Previous studies analysing this mutant indicated that the <italic>Nr</italic> mutation inhibits tomato fruit ripening, and influences fruit morphology, seed number, ascorbate accumulation, carotenoid biosynthesis, ethylene evolution and expression of many genes during fruit maturation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C1">Alba <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). The presented results, together with the known activity of <italic>Nr</italic> in regulating ethylene signalling, suggest a role for ethylene and the ethylene signalling pathway in maintaining higher pollen quality under HS conditions.We previously demonstrated that a higher quality of pollen in heat-tolerant tomato genotypes is associated with higher levels of starch accumulated during pollen maturation and higher levels of sucrose in the mature pollen grains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C7">Firon <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). We therefore tested the levels of starch, as well as sucrose, glucose and fructose, in maturing and mature pollen grains, respectively, of wild-type and <italic>Nr</italic> mutant plants. Starch levels did not differ significantly between pollen of wild-type and <italic>Nr</italic> plants (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS024TB2">2</xref>). However, the <italic>Nr</italic> mutation was shown to affect pollen carbohydrate metabolism by causing an over 2-fold reduction in the sucrose levels accumulated in mature pollen grains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS024F1">1</xref>). Since starch levels did not differ between wild-type and <italic>Nr</italic> maturing pollen, the lower sucrose levels accumulated in mature <italic>Nr</italic> pollen grains might be due to lower sugar transport to the developing pollen and lower sucrose synthesis, rather than a direct result of starch degradation.The significantly lower sucrose levels detected in mature pollen grains of <italic>Nr</italic> mutant plants might contribute to their higher sensitivity to HS. High sucrose content in pollen has previously been suggested to be associated with the acquisition of germination capacity and desiccation tolerance, as it provides the necessary osmolality for cell expansion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C10">Hoekstra and van Roekel 1988</xref>) or is related to pollen longevity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C32">Speranza <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C4">Buitink and Leprince (2004)</xref> suggested that sucrose participates in the formation of intracellular glass, which protects membranes during dehydration. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C37">Vesprini <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> suggested a role for cytoplasmic pollen carbohydrates in resistance to low-temperature exposure. Indeed, we previously showed, in pepper, that both pollen quality and yield are correlated with pollen sucrose levels, being affected by different temperature regimes (with low night temperatures decreasing mature pollen sucrose levels, pollen germination capacity and yield; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C29">Pressman <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C12">Kaplan <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> pointed out a relationship between HS and cold-stress responses at the metabolite level, suggesting the possible involvement of signalling molecules and compatible solutes in temperature-stress tolerance.It is interesting to note that exposing tomato plants to HS caused a 32-fold increase in expression of an ethylene-dependent gravitropism-deficient and yellow–green-like (<italic>ATEGY3</italic>) gene (homologous to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> AT1G17870, 2E-43; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C8">Frank <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>) in developing tomato microspores. Molecular studies have revealed that a member of this gene family is involved in controlling the size and number of plastids, and encodes a metalloprotease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C9">Guo <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). This gene may link the HS-regulated ethylene response to pollen amyloplast biology and carbohydrate metabolism.The involvement of ethylene in maintaining tomato pollen quality under HS is further demonstrated by: (i) the 2.6- to 10-fold increase in the number of germinating pollen grains and (ii) the significant decrease in the number of non-viable pollen grains, due to pretreatment of the plants with an ethylene releaser, prior to exposing them to STHS. This beneficial effect of ethylene pretreatment was manifested at two different stages of pollen development: 3 days before flower opening (stage A-3) and at the mature pollen stage (A), suggesting ethylene's involvement in thermotolerance of developing/maturing pollen grains as well as in pollen germination, respectively. We obtained similar results with developing pollen of <italic>Nicotiana sylvestris</italic>, another member of the Solanaceae (N. Firon <italic>et al</italic>., ARO, Israel, unpubl. res.).Thermotolerance is generally divided into acquired (i.e. the ability to acquire tolerance to otherwise lethal HS) and basal (i.e. the inherent ability to survive temperatures above optimal growth temperatures) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C36">Suzuki <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref> and references therein). The capacity for ATT may be achieved by elevating expression levels of ‘protective’ genes prior to HS exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C19">Larkindale and Vierling 2008</xref>). The results, summarized in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS024F2">2</xref>C and D, indicate that tomato pollen has the capacity for ATT, and that pretreating the plants with mild HS before exposing them to STHS significantly increases the number of germinating pollen grains. This suggests the activation of genes or proteins that may protect pollen germination capacity under HS.The established ATT conditions were used to determine whether ethylene is involved in basal or acquired thermotolerance, or both, in pollen. Pretreatment of tomato plants with the ethylene biosynthesis inhibitor AVG indicated an 8.5- and 2.5-fold reduction in pollen ATT capacity at developmental stages A-3 and A, respectively, and complete inhibition of pollen germination following exposure to STHS conditions. Taken together, the results indicate involvement of ethylene in both basal and acquired thermotolerance.The results presented in this work indicate that interfering with the ethylene signalling pathway or reducing ethylene levels increases tomato pollen sensitivity to HS, whereas increasing ethylene levels prior to HS exposure increases pollen quality. It is thus suggested that ethylene increases pollen tolerance to HS, thereby improving pollen functioning under those conditions.In addition, involvement of ethylene in the normal course of pollen development and germination is suggested based upon the results showing a reduction in pollen quality under optimal growing conditions following pretreatment of the plants with AVG. The role of ethylene synthesis in the development and germination of tobacco pollen has previously been shown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS024C6">De la Torre <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref> and references therein).Perturbation of the tomato ethylene signalling pathway by a mutation in the ERS-like ethylene receptor was found to affect pollen carbohydrate metabolism—manifested by a reduction in mature pollen sucrose levels—and to increase pollen sensitivity to HS conditions. Increasing ethylene levels by applying an ethylene releaser prior to exposing the plants to HS increased pollen thermotolerance, manifested by an increase in the number of germinating pollen grains. On the other hand, application of an inhibitor of ethylene biosynthesis affected basal as well as acquired thermotolerance in pollen, as reflected by a reduced number of germinating pollen grains. The accumulated data thus point to ethylene's involvement in tomato pollen thermotolerance. Additional work is needed to identify and characterize the mechanisms involved. The scavenging of ROS that accompany the HSR, and accumulation of compatible solutes, such as sucrose, may be part of such mechanisms. The established pollen ATT conditions may be further used for the identification of molecular mechanisms involved in pollen ATT, including pollen-expressed components of the ethylene signalling pathway, by employing next-generation sequencing methods at the pollen cDNA level.This work was supported in part by the European <grant-num xlink:type="simple">FP7-PEOPLE-2011-ITN</grant-num> (<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Initial Training Networks</grant-sponsor>) programme, <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Solanaceae Pollen Thermotolerance, SPOT-ITN</grant-sponsor>, Number <grant-num xlink:type="simple">PITN-GA-2011–28922</grant-num>.All authors contributed to the research by participating in setting up the experiments and performing the measurements. The senior author was responsible for the data analysis and preparation of the manuscript. All authors reviewed and contributed comments to the manuscript.None declared.