Leucocyte profiles of Arctic marine birds: correlates of migration and breeding phenologyArctic climate impact assessmentEffect of dexamethasone on differential white blood cell counts and heterophil/lymphocyte ratio in Japanese quails (<italic>Coturnix coturnix japonica</italic>)Flight speeds among bird species: allometric and phylogenetic effectsEcoimmunologyHaematology and blood chemistry of healthy and clinically abnormal great black-backed gulls (<italic>Larus marinus</italic>) and herring gulls (<italic>Larus argentatus</italic>)The normal haematology of Great Skuas (<italic>Catharacta skua</italic>) in the wildSimple techniques for making avian blood smearsOne problem, many solutions: simple statistical approaches help unravel the complexity of the immune system in an ecological contextHematologic parameters and hemoparasites of nonmigratory Canada geese (<italic>Branta canadensis</italic>) from Greensboro, North Carolina, USAMigration ecology of Sabine&apos;s Gulls (<italic>Xema sabini</italic>) from the Canadian high ArcticThe use of leukocyte profiles to measure stress in vertebrates: a review for ecologistsReproductive effort decreases antibody responsivenessDo leucocyte profiles reflect temporal and sexual variation in body condition over the breeding cycle in Southern Rockhopper Penguins?The prudent parent &ndash; energetic adjustments in avian breedingVariation in baseline haematology of northern fulmars (<italic>Fulmarus glacialis</italic>) in the Canadian high ArcticTracking of Arctic terns <italic>Sterna paradisaea</italic> reveals longest animal migrationHigh flight costs, but low dive costs, in auks support the biomechanical hypothesis for flightlessness in penguinsHematology and absence of hemoparasites in breeding common terns (<italic>Sterna hirundo</italic>) from Cape Cod, MassachusettsEffects of climate-induced changes in parasitism, predation and predator-predator interactions on reproduction and survival of an Arctic marine birdChanges in seasonal events, peak food availability and consequent breeding adjustment in a marine bird: a case of progressive mis-matchingModeling foraging range for breeding colonies of thick-billed murres <italic>Uria lomvia</italic> in the Eastern Canadian Arctic and potential overlap with industrial developmentGeographic variation in haematological variables in adult and prefledgling herring gulls (<italic>Larus argentatus</italic>) and possible associations with organochlorine exposureReduced immunocompetence and cost of reproduction in common eidersSex differences in body condition and hematological parameters in little auk <italic>Alle alle</italic> during the incubation periodEmerging parasitic infections in arctic ungulatesLinking immune defenses and life history at the levels of the individual and the speciesSimple quantification of blood and plasma antimicrobial capacity using spectrophotometryInside the Redbox: applications of haematology in wildlife monitoring and ecosystem health assessmentDoes sea-ice constrain the breeding schedules of High Arctic Northern Fulmars?Autumn migration and wintering of northern fulmars (<italic>Fulmarus glacialis</italic>) from the Canadian High ArcticSeabirds as indicators of marine ecosystem conditions: a case for gathering multiple proxies of seabird healthImplications of climate change for parasitism of animals in the aquatic environmentAn introduction to ecological immunologyA hemolysis&ndash;hemaglutination assay for characterizing constitutive innate humoral immunity in wild and domestic birdsQuantifying and comparing constitutive immunity across avian speciesYear-round movements of Northern Common Eiders <italic>Somateria mollissima borealis</italic> breeding in Arctic Canada and West Greenland followed by satellite telemetryHematological and plasma biochemical reference ranges of Alaskan seabirds: their ecological significance and clinical importanceEcological immunology: life history trade-offs and immune defense in birdsSeasonal differences in immunological condition of three species of thrushesWild immunology&Iacute;slenskar teistur endurheimtar vi&eth; Gr&aelig;nland and erlend teista vi&eth; &Iacute;sland. [Icelandic Black Guillemots (<italic>Cepphus grylle islandicus</italic>) recovered in Greenland and Mandt&apos;s Guillemot (<italic>C. g. mandtii</italic>) recorded in Iceland.]Leucocytes in adult burrowing parrots <italic>Cyanoliseus patagonus</italic> in the wild: variation between contrasting breeding seasons, gender, and individual conditionBreeding distribution and numbers of black guillemots in Jones Sound, N.W.TOn the adaptive significance of stress-induced immunosuppressionComparison of pigeon guillemot, <italic>Cepphus columba</italic>, blood parameters from oiled and unoiled areas of Alaska eight years after the <italic>Exxon Valdez</italic> oil spillEcological immunology: costly parasite defences and trade-offs in evolutionary ecologyTree swallow reproductive investment, stress, and parasitesHematology, plasma biochemistry, and serosurvey for selected infectious agents in southern giant petrels from Patagonia, ArgentinaA matter of history: effects of tourism on physiology, behaviour and breeding parameters in Magellanic Penguins (<italic>Spheniscus magellanicus</italic>) at two colonies in ArgentinaStress, corticosterone, and heterophil to lymphocyte ratios in free-living Adelie PenguinsLeg abnormalities and leucocyte profiles in the European Storm-petrel (<italic>Hydrobates p. pelagicus</italic>) from the Faroe IslandsWeights, hematology, and serum chemistry of seven species of free-ranging tropical pelagic birds<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeWe examined white blood cell profiles of marine birds breeding in the Arctic, as an index of stress. Within species, birds that had to migrate farther had higher heterophil:lymphocyte ratios during incubation (i.e., residual stress) than those that migrated short distances. These reference values will be important as global warming and anthropogenic activities change the Arctic marine landscape.Most Arctic marine birds are migratory, wintering south of the limit of annual pack ice and returning north each year for the physiologically stressful breeding season. The Arctic environment is changing rapidly due to global warming and anthropogenic activities, which may influence the timing of breeding in relation to arrival times following migration, as well as providing additional stressors (e.g. disturbance from ships) to which birds may respond. During stressful parts of their annual cycle, such as breeding, birds may reallocate resources so that they have increased heterophil-to-lymphocyte ratios in their white blood cell (leucocyte) profiles. We analysed leucocyte profiles of nine species of marine birds to establish reference ranges for these species in advance of future Arctic change. Leucocyte profiles tended to cluster among taxonomic groups across studies, suggesting that reference values for a particular group can be established, and within species there was evidence that birds from colonies that had to migrate farther had higher heterophil-to-lymphocyte ratios during incubation than those that did not have to travel as far, particularly for species with high wing loading.Influences of environmental stressors on animals are key areas of research in ecology and conservation. A fundamental premise of this research is that a stimulus in the environment places a stress on animals, which causes a behavioural or physiological change from baseline conditions (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C61">Vleck <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C53">Plischke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C60">Villanueva <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Detecting these reactions can be difficult, however, owing to a lack of baseline information for many species and because many baseline metrics, such as white blood cell (leucocyte) profiles, vary through the annual cycle and in response to environmental variation over a range of time scales (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C34">Lee, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C53">Plischke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C15">Dehnhard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Consequently, sound use of these metrics requires corresponding information on environmental conditions and stage of the annual cycle of the species, as well as baseline measures, for proper interpretation.For many animals, breeding can be the most physiologically stressful part of their annual cycle, which can manifest itself as a trade-off between investment of body resources in self-maintenance vs. reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C36">Drent and Daan, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C101">Stearns, 1992</xref>). One place where animals might adjust investment is in their immune system. Although this system protects individuals against various diseases and parasites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C58">Sheldon and Verhulst, 1996</xref>), the immune system may be adjusted during breeding to reallocate resources to other systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C14">Deerenberg <italic>et al</italic>., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C55">R&aring;berg <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C27">Hanssen <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C34">Lee, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C13">Davis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Leucocytes are a key component of an animal&apos;s immune system, with different white blood cells offering protection against a variety of stressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C38">Maceda-Veiga <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). In homeotherms, acquired immunity is provided by lymphocytes, tends to be pathogen specific and leads to antibody responses. In contrast, innate immunity is provided by monocytes and granulocytes (eosinophils, basophils and, especially, heterophils in birds and neutrophils in mammals) and is usually the first line of immune defense through phagocytosis of pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C56">Roitt <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>). During periods of stress, reallocation of immunity resources leads to increased heterophil-to-lymphocyte (H:L) ratios in avian white blood cell profiles and occurs in numerous domestic and wild birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C100">Shutler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C11">Davis, 2009</xref>). Thus, leucocyte profiles (also called white blood cell differentials) are commonly used by veterinarians to assess animal health (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C10">Charles-Smith <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C62">Wojczulanis-Jakubas <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Evidence also suggests that elevated H:L ratios may be associated with deleterious effects, such as slower growth, increased risk of infection and decreased survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C11">Davis, 2009</xref>).The Arctic is home to millions of migratory birds and is a relatively pristine region, which is now experiencing rapid environmental change due to a more variable climate. A warmer climate may lead to higher parasitism rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C42">Marcogliese, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C33">Kutz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C20">Gaston and Elliott, 2013</xref>), and increased investment in immunity may result. Many parts of the Arctic are expected to experience increased industrial activity, shipping and tourism in the near future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C1">ACIA, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C4">Arctic Council, 2009</xref>). Elsewhere in Arctic regions, scientists have conducted sampling to establish reference ranges for haematological parameters in marine birds, as baseline metrics by which the possible effects of environmental perturbation can be assessed (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C47">Newman <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C7">Bearhop <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). However, few studies have been undertaken in the Canadian Arctic (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C16">Edwards <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) or Iceland; therefore, establishing current reference values is important. In this study, we had the following two objectives: (i) to generate reference ranges for leucocyte profiles of breeding Arctic marine birds in Canada and Iceland; and (ii) to assess whether differences occur within species among breeding sites. Typical environmental conditions mean that many Arctic birds have a short window of time in which to breed; indeed, the time spent gathered at a colony between arrival and initiation of breeding may be dramatically reduced compared to conspecifics breeding farther south (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C39">Mallory and Forbes, 2007</xref>). Given that physical stresses of migration can also elevate H:L ratios in birds (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C49">Owen and Moore, 2006</xref>), we predicted that for species sampled from multiple colonies that varied in (i) the distance travelled by individuals for pre-breeding migration and (ii) the distance flown by individuals from their foraging ground to their breeding colony, H:L ratios would be higher for birds that had to travel farther to reach their breeding colony.Leucocyte profiles of Arctic marine bird speciesRegions are generalized as High (Canadian High Arctic), Low (Canadian Low Arctic), Iceland, Maritimes (Canada) and Alaska; within these regions, colony is the specific colony location where samples were taken. Abbreviations: CV (&percnt;), coefficient of variation; and H:L ratio, heterophil-to-lymphocyte ratio.Colony locations (black dots) for all marine birds sampled in this study.In preparation for conducting leucocyte differential counts, slides were stained using Wright&apos;s staining method. Leucocyte counts were conducted at &times;1000 magnification using oil immersion. To assess ratios of leucocyte cell types, we counted 100 leucocytes for each blood smear and categorized leucocytes using morphological characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C37">Lucas and Jamroz, 1961</xref>). Heterophils, eosinophils, basophils, lymphocytes and monocytes were all included in the counts, but thrombocytes were excluded. Slides were counted principally by C.M.L. (68&percnt; of total) and E.S.B. (15&percnt;), both of whom were trained by D.S., although kittiwakes and 2011 murres (17&percnt;) were counted by K.H.E. E.S.B. recounted a subset of slides (<italic>n</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;39) initially counted by C.M.L. to assess repeatability; recount values for heterophils and lymphocytes were within 4.0&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.7&percnt; SEM and 3.5&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.7&percnt; SEM, respectively. Other blood cell types were less common and repeatability counts were less reliable (i.e. error between counts &gt;50&percnt; of mean occurrence), and thus we present proportional occurrence data but do not include these in analyses. Collectively, we obtained 578 readable slides from nine marine bird species.We compared natural logarithmically transformed H:L ratios among species and among locations using Welch&apos;s <italic>t</italic>-tests or Mann&ndash;Whitney Wilcoxon tests for pairwise comparisons, or Kruskal&ndash;Wallis tests (followed by Dunn&apos;s multiple comparison test) or ANOVA (followed by Tukey&ndash;Kramer multiple comparisons test; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C23">GraphPad Software, Inc., 2009</xref>). We also completed a principal component analysis on all arcsine&ndash;square root-transformed leucocyte profile data from northern seabirds to examine overall patterns among species and functional groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C9">Buehler <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). Means are presented &plusmn;SEM.The proportion of different leucocytes exhibited considerable variation within species and years (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref>). For example, common eiders sampled at four colony locations exhibited significantly different H:L ratios (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref> and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV028F2">2</xref>; ANOVA, <italic>F</italic><sub>3,187</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;14.5, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001), with eiders at each location having different mean H:L ratios from all other locations (all <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&le;&emsp14;0.05), except for eiders at Nasaruvaalik Island and East Bay, which did not differ significantly from each other. When we compared H:L ratios with migration distance, birds that migrated farther had higher H:L ratios (<italic>r</italic><sub>s188</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.48, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001). Moreover, we saw some consistency among years for eiders; H:L ratios at Easy Bay in 2005 (1.56&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.49) were similar to those from 2008 (1.84&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.91; <italic>t</italic><sub>58</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;1.6, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.12). Murres also exhibited intercolony differences, with H:L ratios higher at Digges (2.17&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.36) than Coats (1.19&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.06, <italic>t</italic><sub>90</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;4.51, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001) and higher at Coats in 2011 than 2008 (2.97&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;0.49, <italic>t</italic><sub>128</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;8.29, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001). Guillemots breeding in the high Arctic had a higher mean H:L ratio than those breeding in Iceland (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref>; Welch&apos;s <italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>t</italic><sub>24</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;3.0, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.006). For Arctic terns sampled at East Bay and Nasaruvaalik Island in 2007 and 2008, significant differences in H:L ratios were found (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref>; <italic>F</italic><sub>3,71</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;3.3, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05), but this was attributable to low ratios (and low variation) in 2007 and high values in 2008 at Nasaruvaalik Island (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05). However, for the other species, H:L ratios did not differ statistically among locations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref>; Sabine&apos;s gulls: <italic>t</italic><sub>12</sub>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.9, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.37), despite a twofold difference in mean H:L ratios for fulmars between some site-years (Kruskal&ndash;Wallis test, KW&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;1.2, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;0.54), presumably because of high annual, within-site variation.<fig id="COV028F2"><label>Figure 2:</label><caption><p>Mean (SEM) heterophil-to-lymphocyte ratios for common eiders (<italic>Somateria mollissima</italic>) sampled across the western North Atlantic and Canadian Arctic as follows: IS, Iceland; NS, Nova Scotia (Canada); LA, Canadian Low Arctic; and HA, Canadian High Arctic. The right-hand <italic>y</italic>-axis is the approximate migration distance (in kilometres) from wintering to breeding grounds, represented by the line in the graph; sample sizes are above bars. Bars significantly different from each other denoted with different letters.The proportion of different leucocytes also exhibited high variation among species, although there were some overall similarities (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref>). For most species, proportions of basophils were low (medians of 0&ndash;1&percnt;); fulmars had the highest median proportion of 5&percnt;. For eosinophils, median proportions differed among species, with the highest values for murres and terns (6&percnt;) and lowest for puffins (1&percnt;). Median proportions of monocytes were high in murres and guillemots (11&percnt;), with other species having proportions between 5 and 8&percnt; (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV028F3">3</xref>). Overall, H:L ratios among species were fairly variable; the mean coefficient of variation for species&prime; H:L ratios was 66&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;28&percnt;. We found significant differences in H:L ratios among marine bird species (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref>; KW&emsp14;&equals;&emsp14;96.4, <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001). Puffins, murres, eiders, kittiwakes and Sabine&apos;s gulls all had mean H:L ratios &gt;1 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV028F3">3</xref>). Fulmars had the lowest H:L ratios, which were significantly lower than those of murres, eiders and Sabine&apos;s gulls (all <italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001). Murres also had higher H:L ratios than terns (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001), guillemots (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.01) and skuas (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.05), and eider H:L ratios were also higher than those of terns (<italic>P</italic>&emsp14;&lt;&emsp14;0.001). Collectively, these analyses allowed us to produce reference ranges (mean&emsp14;&plusmn;&emsp14;2SD; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV028F3">3</xref>) for the main leucocytes and H:L ratios for these species, against which future comparisons can be made.<fig id="COV028F3"><label>Figure 3:</label><caption><p>Mean (2SD) reference ranges of proportions of heterophils, eosinophils, basophils lymphocytes, monocytes and heterophil-to-lymphocyte ratios for nine different marine bird species sampled across the western North Atlantic and Canadian Arctic, as follows: Atlantic puffin (<italic>Fratercula arctica</italic>; ATPU), Arctic tern (<italic>Sterna paradisaea</italic>; ARTE), black guillemot (<italic>Cepphus grylle</italic>; BLGU), black-legged kittiwake (<italic>Rissa tridactyla</italic>; BLKI), common eider (<italic>Somateria mollissima</italic>; COEI), great skua (<italic>Stercorarius skua</italic>; GRSK), northern fulmar (<italic>Fulmarus glacialis</italic>; NOFU), Sabine&apos;s gull (<italic>Xema sabini</italic>; SAGU) and thick-billed murre (<italic>Uria lomvia</italic>; TBMU). Sample sizes are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref>.Leucocyte profiles of species from selected studies on species in the northern hemispherePrincipal component analysis of average seabird leucocyte profiles. Each represents the average value for a particular study, from Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB2">2</xref>. Guilds were grouped as follows: puffins [ATPU, Atlantic puffin; TOPU, tufted puffin (<italic>Fratercula cirrhata</italic>); and HOPU, horned puffin (<italic>F. corniculata</italic>)]; small Pacific auks [PAAU, parakeet auklet (<italic>Cyclorrhynchus psittacula</italic>); MAMU, marbled murrelet (<italic>Brachyramphus marmoratus</italic>); ANMU, ancient murrelet (<italic>Synthliboramphus antiquus</italic>); and CAAU, crested auklet (<italic>Aethia cristatella</italic>)]; Alcini [TBMU, thick-billed murre; and DOVE, dovekie (<italic>Alle alle</italic>)]; guillemots [BLGU, black guillemot; and PIGU, pigeon guillemot (<italic>Cepphus columba</italic>)]; Procellariformes [NOFU, northern fulmar]; ducks [COEI, common eider]; terns [ARTE, Arctic tern; COTE, common tern (<italic>Sterna hirundo</italic>); and SOTE, sooty terns (<italic>Onychoprion fuscatus</italic>)]; and gulls [HERG, herring gull (<italic>Larus argentatus</italic>); BLKI, black-legged kittiwake (<italic>Rissa tridactyla</italic>); GBBG, great black-backed gull (<italic>Larus marinus</italic>); GWGU, glaucous-winged gull (<italic>Larus glaucescens</italic>); SAGU, Sabine&apos;s gull (<italic>Xema sabini</italic>); and GRSK, great skua (<italic>Stercorarius skua</italic>)].Our study is the largest reported haematological sampling of marine birds in northern waters to date, and our results share some similarities with earlier work. For example, fulmars appear to have consistently low H:L ratios compared with other species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C47">Newman <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C16">Edwards <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; present study), which may be characteristic of the family Procellariidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C63">Work, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C59">Uhart <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>); however, albatrosses appear to have high proportions of heterophils (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C63">Work, 1996</xref>), and thus low H:L ratios are not consistent within the entire Order Procellariiformes. Across many marine birds, basophils tend to be the least common of the leucocytes, consistent with our results, but among our species we found median proportions of 5&ndash;11&percnt; monocytes, generally higher than reported elsewhere (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C13">Davis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C11">Davis, 2009</xref>). We also observed high variation among individuals within a species, as has been reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C47">Newman <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref>. Moreover, we found considerable variation among studies, even for the same species or closely related species. As pointed out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C7">Bearhop <italic>et al.</italic> (1999)</xref>, sex, age, stage of season and various environmental differences all influence bird blood metrics, making comparisons among studies challenging. Nonetheless, many taxonomic groups clustered together across studies and sites (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="COV028F4">4</xref>), suggesting that with additional data our reference values for a particular group can be verified. Exceptions were common eiders and guillemots that had particularly large latitudinal ranges; perhaps one reason that those species could exist in such variable climates is that their physiology is particularly adaptable.Despite these challenges, our first priority was to generate a set of reference values for the various species, as a baseline against which future samples can be compared. This rationale has been adopted in other studies where there is potential for future industrial activity that could affect marine birds (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C47">Newman <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C7">Bearhop <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). In other cases, haematological parameters have been applied as one metric by which to measure long-term effects of marine pollution accidents on local bird populations (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C57">Seiser <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). In the present study, birds sampled from High and Low Arctic populations are effectively na&iuml;ve to industrial activity during their breeding season, but that will change in the near future with proposed increases in shipping activity as part of industrial expansion for ore extraction, supply shipping and tourism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C4">Arctic Council, 2009</xref>). In generating these reference values, it is clear that there is variation in mean blood cell counts among specific sampling sites or regions, and thus applying average values from a different study, or even a different colony, may not be entirely appropriate, although we believe that this may vary by taxon (see above). We propose that the variation may be due, at least in part, to migration distances and resulting time constraints experienced by northern birds.We found some support for our hypothesis that H:L ratios would be elevated at colonies where individuals migrated or commuted farther than conspecifics at other colonies. Eiders that had the longest migrations (High and Low Arctic birds, &gt;1500&emsp14;km; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C46">Mosbech <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) had higher H:L ratios than those that had shorter migrations (Nova Scotia, 700&emsp14;km; M. L. Mallory, unpublished data). These, in turn, had higher ratios than those that hardly migrated at all (Iceland, &sim;100&emsp14;km; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C52">Petersen, 1998</xref>). Likewise, High Arctic guillemots, presumably migrating as far as the eiders due to ice patterns, had higher ratios than guillemots in Iceland (some of which migrate to Greenland but many of which do not; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C51">Petersen, 1977</xref>). However, we found no significant differences in H:L ratios for birds from different colonies of Sabine&apos;s gulls, fulmars or terns, despite an approximate 3000&emsp14;km difference in average migration distance between the locations that we sampled (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C40">Mallory <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C17">Egevang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C12">Davis, 2015</xref>). Unlike eiders and guillemots, however, these species are all long-distance migrants; the 3000&emsp14;km difference represents &sim;20&percnt; or less of the total migration distance from wintering to breeding sites of each of these species compared with an increase of 1500&emsp14;km (two to 10 times greater than the migration distance of eiders from the other colonies). Eiders and guillemots also have higher wing loadings and are less efficient fliers than the other species (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C25">Greenwalt, 1962</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C3">Alerstam <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C18">Elliott <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>); an increase of 1500&emsp14;km may create greater stress for those species. In addition, H:L ratios were higher at the larger Digges Island colony, where birds commute almost twice as far due to stronger intraspecific competition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C22">Gaston <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Murres have the highest relative flight costs of any bird studied to date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C18">Elliott <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) and would therefore be expected to be particularly susceptible to activity stress. Thus, we suggest that efficiency of flight and the distance flown must influence stress levels in these species, which may be reflected in increased H:L ratios during incubation.Other than simply the stress of having to migrate farther, differences in environmental conditions on the breeding grounds and migration distance among colonies may have indirect effects on H:L ratios of eiders and other High Arctic nesters; birds at the High Arctic colony may arrive with less time before they start laying. This could leave birds with less time to invest resources in immunity on the breeding grounds (i.e. to reallocate resources that have been shunted to deal with energetic needs of migration) and would thus result in H:L ratios that may be diminishing, but would be relatively high post-migration compared with those of birds at southern colonies that arrived long before breeding. We do not know how long it takes H:L ratios to return to &lsquo;normal&rsquo; after prolonged stress in these wild species, but in one experimental study it took 10&emsp14;days for quail H:L ratios to return to normal after short-term exposure to a corticosteroid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C2">Aengwanich and Chinrarsi, 2003</xref>). Arctic birds have a short window of time in which to breed and, moreover, may arrive when there is still ice and snow covering their breeding habitats. Thus, they often adjust their breeding schedules to accommodate annual variation. In fulmars, pre-breeding activities at High Arctic colonies are markedly reduced compared with fulmars elsewhere in the range, including Alaska (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C39">Mallory and Forbes, 2007</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C47">Newman <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref> found that mean H:L ratios in Alaskan marine birds, including many alcids, were generally less than one (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB2">2</xref>). Those sites in Alaska are generally ice free, and some of the species have very short migrations (e.g. crested auklet, <italic>Aethia cristatella</italic>). In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C28">Jakubas <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> found H:L ratios near one in dovekies (<italic>Alle alle</italic>) from Svalbard, a location where birds would have to deal with sea ice, at least early in the season. In our study, the only diving bird with mean H:L ratios less than one were guillemots, even the High Arctic birds (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV028TB1">1</xref>). That High Arctic colony may be a special case, however, because it was situated in a polynya where birds may exploit the early open water and arrive at the breeding grounds months before breeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C54">Prach and Smith, 1992</xref>).Collectively, we believe that our data provide key baseline references for colony-level comparisons of stress in the various marine bird species. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C15">Dehnhard <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> suggested that leucocyte profiles were blunt tools, but were sufficient to look at population (colony) level changes in stress, and we suggest a similar interpretation of our data. If researchers gather basic data on marine bird health regularly as part of standard protocols (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C41">Mallory <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), annual variation in leucocyte profiles may be detected and factors contributing to increased stress indicators can be more easily identified. In particular, reductions in sea ice leading to earlier nesting by some species (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C21">Gaston <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) will change the dynamic between migration departure and nest initiation, presumably altering residual effects of migration stress on breeding birds and their H:L ratios proposed in this study. As evidence, the highest H:L ratios in the present study were from murres near their southern range limit, at Coats Island in 2011. That year was a particularly warm year and a period of high stress when polar bears (<italic>Ursus maritimus</italic>) and mosquitoes combined caused a 20&percnt; reduction in reproduction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C20">Gaston and Elliott, 2013</xref>). Furthermore, water loss due to heat stress and mosquitoes caused very low haematocrits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C20">Gaston and Elliott, 2013</xref>). Conducting such observations for 3&emsp14;weeks was logistically difficult and time consuming; H:L ratios may be a simple and quick method for assessing population stress in response to a warmer climate. We believe that future investigations should test the following predictions: (i) across colonies and among individuals at a colony, the duration of pre-breeding periods at a colony is negatively related to H:L ratios during incubation; (ii) H:L ratios are lower for individual birds that initiate nesting later in the breeding season (controlling for body condition); and (iii) a progressive increase in H:L ratios during incubation will occur at Arctic colonies through time, as birds try to initiate nesting earlier to keep pace with earlier seasonal phenology of food supplies (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C21">Gaston <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>).Our research focused on leucocyte profiles and stress, but there are many other metrics of immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C44">Matson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C45">Millet <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C35">Liebl <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>) and many other questions in the field of ecological immunology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C5">Ardia and Schat, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C43">Martin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C50">Pedersen and Babayan, 2011</xref>). Blood smears are one of the easiest metrics to collect in field conditions, and leucocyte profiles are one of the most inexpensive metrics to use. For some investigations, leucocytes have drawbacks in interpretation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C48">Norris and Evans, 2000</xref>), but H:L ratios are quite robust to evaluation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV028C13">Davis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). In any case, future work should compare other metrics of immune function with results generated by blood smears.Financial support was provided by <funding-source>Environment Canada</funding-source>, the <funding-source>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council</funding-source>, the <funding-source>Nova Scotia Department of Natural Resources</funding-source> and the <funding-source>Polar Continental Shelf Project</funding-source>.We are grateful to many field personnel who assisted in collecting blood samples and, in particular, Kelly Boadway, Isabel Buttler, Darryl Edwards, Rob Kelly, Ellen Magnusdottir, Carolyn Mallory, Mike O&prime;Brien, Glen Parsons, Molly Tomlik and Emma Vost. Andy Davis and an anonymous reviewer provided valuable suggestions that improved the manuscript.