Fibre wall and lumen fractions drive wood density variation across 24 Australian angiospermsFunctional strategies of chaparral shrubs in relation to seasonal water deficit and disturbanceThe role of wood mass density and mechanical constraints in the economy of tree architecturePathogen mortality of tropical tree seedlings: experimental studies of the effects of dispersal distance, seedling density, and light conditionsWood specific gravity in species from two tropical forests in MexicoRadial variation in wood properties of naturally and plantation grown light red meranti (<italic>Shorea</italic>, Dipterocarpaceae)Functional convergence in hydraulic architecture and water relations of tropical savanna trees: from leaf to whole plantSafety and streamlining of woody shoots in wind: an empirical study across 39 species in tropical AustraliaTowards a worldwide wood economics spectrumCell wall and lumen percentages in relation to wood density of <italic>Nothofagus nervosa</italic>Allometric scaling of production and life-history variation in vascular plantsVariation of cellular proportions in sweetgum and their relation to other wood propertiesHydraulic conductivity traits predict growth rates and adult stature of 40 Asian tropical tree species better than wood densityWood anatomical variables in tropical trees and their relation to site conditions and individual tree morphologyPreparation of thin sections of synthetic resins and wood-resin composites, and a new macerating method for woodAnatomy and properties of Japanese hardwoods II. Variation of dimensions of ray cells and their relation to basic densityAnatomy and properties of Japanese hardwoods. I. Variation of fibre dimensions and tissue proportions and their relation to basic densityJuvenile wood of hardwoods judged by density variationStem xylem conductivity is key to plant water balance across Australian angiosperm speciesAllocation to leaf area and sapwood area affects water relations of co-occurring savanna and forest treesInterprétation anatomique des composantes d'un modèle mixte de densité du bois chez le Chêne sessile (<italic>Quercus petraea</italic> Liebl.): âge du cerne compté depuis la moelle, largeur de cerne, arbre, variabilité interannuelle et duraminisationTrends in wood density and structure are linked to prevention of xylem implosion by negative pressureIAWA list of microscopic features for hardwood identificationDo xylem fibers affect vessel cavitation resistance?Xylem density, biomechanics and anatomical traits correlate with water stress in 17 evergreen shrub species of the Mediterranean-type climate region of South AfricaCavitation resistance among 26 chaparral species of Southern CaliforniaComparative community physiology: nonconvergence in water relations among three semi-arid shrub communitiesThe relationship between wood density and mortality in a global tropical forest data setRethinking the value of high wood densityBetween- and within-tree variation in the anatomy and specific gravity of wood in Oregon white oak (<italic>Quercus garryana</italic> Dougl.)Testing hypotheses that link wood anatomy to cavitation resistance and hydraulic conductivity in the genus <italic>Acer</italic>Wood anatomy and wood density in shrubs: responses to varying aridity along transcontinental transectsWood specific gravity and anatomy in <italic>Helicarpus appendiculatus</italic> (Tiliaceae)Whole-tree water transport scales with sapwood capacitance in tropical forest canopy treesConstraints on physiological function associated with branch architecture and wood density in tropical forest treesUsing multiple trait asociations to define hydraulic functional types in plant communities of south-western AustraliaInterspecific and inter-site variation in wood specific gravity of tropical treesAre functional traits good predictors of demographic rates? Evidence from five Neotropical forestsThe importance of wood traits and hydraulic conductance for the performance and life history strategies of 42 rainforest tree speciesRelationships among xylem transport, biomechanics and storage in stems and roots of nine Rhamnaceae species of the California chaparralWood density and vessel traits as distinct correlates of ecological strategy in 51 California coast range angiospermsUprooting and snapping of trees: structural determinants and ecological consequencesFunctional anatomy of five endangered tropical timber wood species of the family DipterocarpaceaeEffects of stem anatomical and structural traits on responses to stem damage: an experimental study in the Bolivian AmazonAnatomical features associated with water transport in imperforate tracheary elements of vessel-bearing angiospermsLeaf photosynthetic traits scale with hydraulic conductivity and wood density in Panamanian forest canopy treesBiophysical properties and functional significance of stem water storage tissues in Neotropical savanna treesDer Anteil der einzelnen Zellarten an dem Holz der RotbucheCharacter convergence, diversity, and disturbance in tropical rain forest in GuyanaProportions of wood elements in stem, branch, and root wood of black oak (<italic>Quercus velutina</italic>)Stem water storage capacity and efficiency of water transport: their functional significance in a Hawaiian dry forestEcological and evolutionary determinants of a key plant functional trait: wood density and its community-wide variation across latitude and elevationThe effect of ray tissue on the specific gravity of woodWood property variation of Mississippi delta hardwoodsProportions and types of cells in stems, branches, and roots of European black alder (<italic>Alnus glutinosa</italic> L. Gaertn.)Plant ecological strategies: some leading dimensions of variation between speciesGeographic variation in wood specific gravity: effects of latitude, temperature, and precipitationA more rational climatic moisture indexThe worldwide leaf economics spectrumFunctional traits and the growth-mortality trade-off in tropical treesAngiosperm wood structure: global patterns in vessel anatomy and their relation to wood density and potential conductivitySpatial patterns of wood traits in China are controlled by phylogeny and the environmentThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Wood density is often considered to be a key plant functional trait. But it is not clear what actually wood density is? We rigorously quantified anatomical underpinnings of wood density variation. We found that density was mainly driven by properties of mechanical tissue such as fibre wall fraction and fibre lumen fraction. However, there was also a substantial anatomical variation independent of density. This variation suggests that different plant ecological strategies may be available to woods with the same density. Our results imply that density is a complex characteristic of wood rather than a straightforward indicator of plant ecological strategies.Wood density is considered a key plant trait, affecting mechanical and physiological performance, yet its biological meaning is still rather unclear. Accordingly we investigated the anatomical underpinnings of wood density in trees and shrubs. We measured wood density and anatomical traits in distal stems 4–10 mm diameter under bark in 24 Australian species. Proportions of wood components that are functionally distinct were analysed, including fibre wall and lumen, vessel wall and lumen, and axial and ray parenchyma. Wood density was mainly driven by the density of wood outside vessel lumens (density<sub>NV</sub>) rather than by vessel lumen fraction. In turn, density<sub>NV</sub> variation was chiefly affected by fibre wall and lumen fractions. Considerable anatomical variation was observed at a given density<sub>NV</sub>, especially among medium-density<sub>NV</sub> species (0.60–0.85 g cm<sup>−3</sup>); this range of medium density<sub>NV</sub> roughly translates to 0.50–0.75 g cm<sup>−3</sup> of overall density. The anatomy of these species formed a continuum from low fibre lumen and medium parenchyma fractions to medium fibre lumen and low parenchyma fractions. Our data suggest that wood density is an emergent property influenced by a complex anatomy rather than an unambiguous functional trait, particularly in medium-density species. With much anatomical variation, they likely represent a wide range of ecological strategies.Plants vary significantly in their ecological, physiological and mechanical properties or ‘traits’ both across climate and even within a site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C61">Westoby <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C65">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C8">Chave <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). This indicates that there are multiple solutions to the problem of how to be a successful plant and maintain species continuity. Different solutions can be called plant ecological strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C61">Westoby <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>).Wood density has been suggested as a key player in plant ecological strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C8">Chave <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Firstly, wood density has been linked with hydraulic strategies. Denser woods tend to operate at more negative water potentials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C1">Ackerly 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C6">Bucci <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C50">Santiago <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C27">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C28">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C23">Gotsch <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and to have greater cavitation resistance than low-density woods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C68">Hacke <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C69">Jacobsen <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C43">Pratt <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C70">Lens <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Wood density has been studied in relation to hydraulic conductivity but the results are inconclusive, showing either a negative relationship between the two traits (measured conductivity, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C55">Stratton <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C6">Bucci <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C50">Santiago <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>) or no relationship (theoretical conductivity, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">Poorter <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C14">Fan <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Also, density has been found to correlate negatively with capacitance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C37">Meinzer <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C36">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C43">Pratt <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C51">Scholz <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Secondly, wood density has been associated with plant mechanical strategies where denser woods tend to be stiffer and more resistant to breakage at a given wood diameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C8">Chave <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). However, it has also been suggested that plants can build thicker stems to compensate for their lower density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C2">Anten and Schieving 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C31">Larjavaara and Muller-Landau 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C7">Butler <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Thirdly, denser woods might be more resistant to pathogen attacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C3">Augspurger and Kelly 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C47">Romero and Bolker 2008</xref>). Wood density has also been widely discussed in relation to life-history strategies. For example, species with denser wood tend to experience lower stem mortality rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C45">Putz <italic>et al.</italic> 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C30">Kraft <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Growth rate is another important component of life history. Growth rate can be expected to negatively relate to wood density on the basis that higher investment in mass per volume should slow down growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C11">Enquist <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>) and, while generally true, the correlation is not always strong (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C42">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C8">Chave <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C64">Wright <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C14">Fan <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Across species, wood density can vary with environmental factors such as temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C62">Wiemann and Williamson 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C56">Swenson and Enquist 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and precipitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C4">Barajas-Morales 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C62">Wiemann and Williamson 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C56">Swenson and Enquist 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C67">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), although not in all studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C53">Ter Steege and Hammond 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C62">Wiemann and Williamson 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C39">Muller-Landau 2004</xref>). Despite this broad climate-related patterning, wood density also tends to vary quite widely among co-occurring species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C62">Wiemann and Williamson 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C39">Muller-Landau 2004</xref>).Thus there are many potential functional roles for wood density but also a number of unresolved questions about each potential role. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C31">Larjavaara and Muller-Landau (2010)</xref> argued that some observed correlations may not be causal, but rather may reflect correlated selection on other traits. Further, if wood density has multiple functions, then it might not be a very good predictor of any one of them. In any event, a useful step towards resolving this problem is to ask what are the structural underpinnings of wood density variation. The premise of the work reported here was that if structural underpinnings of wood density variation were rigorously quantified and better understood, this might help to explain complexities in the functional implications of wood density.Most studies of anatomical components of angiosperm wood density span only one or a few species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C52">Schulz 1957</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C58">Taylor 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C59">Taylor and Wooten 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C13">Ezell 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C60">Vurdu and Bensend 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C20">Fukuzawa 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C5">Bosman <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C54">Stokke and Manwiller 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C35">McDonald <italic>et al</italic>. 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C32">Lei <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C10">Denne and Hale 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C46">Rana <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) or focus on commercial woods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C17">French 1923</xref> as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C40">Panshin and de Zeeuw 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C33">Manwiller 1973</xref> as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C29">Koch 1985</xref>). Fewer studies make comparisons across a broad number of species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C19">Fujiwara <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C15">Fichtler and Worbes 2012</xref>).Wood is a complex tissue composed of three main cell types: vessels that transport water, fibres responsible for mechanical strength, and parenchyma that stores and transports nutrients. These tissues have different structural characteristics and their relative proportions within wood influence wood density. Vessel lumens have essentially zero density; fibre and vessel walls and parenchyma have positive density. Vessel fraction has variously shown either negative or no correlation with wood density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C44">Preston <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C38">Mitchell <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C66">Zanne <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C22">Gleason <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Parenchyma is another commonly occurring tissue, which has been reported to have positive, negative or no relationship with density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C57">Taylor 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C18">Fujiwara 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C46">Rana <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Wood density is generally well correlated with fibre properties, especially fibre wall fraction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C19">Fujiwara <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). However, it is unclear how these different fibre traits are interrelated with each other and consequently how these interrelations influence wood density.Most previous work linking anatomy with density has concentrated on vessels with relatively little attention given to the other tissues. Furthermore, among the studies investigating all the major tissues (vessels, parenchyma and fibres) only one focused on the wood of twigs in 17 species studied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al</italic>. (2007<italic>a</italic>)</xref>. Twigs are important, being in direct spatial and functional contact with leaves and having been commonly subjected to physiological and ecological measurements. In this paper, we investigate wood from twigs from a wide range of angiosperm tree and shrub species growing in various environments (24 species from four sites in eastern Australia). We address two main unresolved issues: (i) Which fibre properties have the most decisive effect on wood density and how are those properties interrelated with each other? (ii) How do vessel and parenchyma proportions influence wood density?Four sites were chosen that spanned a wide range of temperature and aridity in eastern Australia <bold>[see</bold> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plt046/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information</bold></ext-link><bold>]</bold>. The objective of site selection was to generate a broad range of trait values rather than to enable site comparisons. All carried natural, undisturbed vegetation growing on oligotrophic soils on flat to slightly sloping terrain. Two locations in Tasmania, at ∼43°S, represented low mean annual temperature (MAT; 10.6 °C), and two locations in Queensland near 18°S represented higher MAT (<italic>c</italic>. 22.5 °C). Within each latitude, two locations were chosen so as to differ markedly in aridity index (AI; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C63">Willmott and Feddema 1992</xref>), the ratio of mean annual precipitation (MAP) to potential evapotranspiration (PET). In both Queensland and Tasmania the wetter site had an AI <italic>c</italic>. 1.0 and the drier site <italic>c</italic>. 0.6. MAP, MAT and PET were obtained from GIS (geographic information system) layers from the Australian Bureau of Meteorology.Sampled sites, species names and families.Wood density was measured on segments 3–5 cm long for each twig sample. Bark and pith were removed and measurements were carried out on xylem only. In this paper we refer to xylem as ‘wood’. After removing bark and pith, wood pieces were soaked in water for at least 48 h prior to volume measurement. Then a beaker filled with water was placed on a balance (0.0001 g, Mettler AE 160). A thin wire platform was suspended in water so that it did not touch the side or bottom of the beaker. The balance was tared before each measurement and a sample was gently placed on the platform. The mass of displaced water was read from the balance. From standard water density of 1 g cm<sup>−3</sup> and knowing the mass of displaced water, we calculated sample volumes applying Archimedes' buoyancy principle (e.g. 1 g of displaced water equals 1 cm<sup>3</sup> volume). Samples were then placed in paper envelopes and dried at 70 °C for at least 72 h. Wood density was calculated as the dry mass divided by water saturated volume (g cm<sup>−3</sup>).To obtain anatomical cross-sections the material was first fixed in formalin–acetic acid–alcohol (FAA) for 4 weeks. The FAA was prepared in proportions of 5 : 5 : 90 (formalin : glacial acetic acid : 70 % ethanol; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C21">Gerlach 1972</xref>). After 4 weeks, the fixative was replaced with 70 % ethanol. This 70 % ethanol was then replaced two more times within 10 days to further wash the fixative out. Final replacement of alcohol was used as a long-term storage medium. Segments for image analysis were rehydrated by immersion in 50 % ethanol and after 2–5 days in 30 % ethanol. Cross-sections were cut with a sledge microtome (Reichert, Vienna, Austria) at 10–20 µm thickness using disposable blades (Model A35, Feather Safety Razor Co. Ltd, Japan). For better contrast and tissue identification, sections were stained with safranin O (Gurr Microscopy Materials, BDH Chemicals Ltd, UK) for lignified cell walls (10 min) and with Janus green B (Gurr's, London, UK) for cytoplasm (10 min). Safranin O solution used 2 g of stain in 100 mL of distilled water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C48">Ruzin 1999</xref>) and Janus green B used 0.1 g of stain and 1 mL of glacial acetic acid in 100 mL of distilled water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C9">Conn <italic>et al.</italic> 1960</xref>). Sections were rinsed in distilled water after each staining session. Afterwards, they were mounted in glycerol on a slide, covered with a cover slip and sealed with nail polish. Measurements were made only on cross-sections, but to assist in interpreting and identifying cell types, longitudinal tangential and radial sections and macerations were also made. For macerations, small shavings were placed in vials filled with Franklin's solution: glacial acetic acid and 6 % hydrogen peroxide in proportions of 1 : 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C16">Franklin 1945</xref>). These vials were loosely covered with Parafilm tape and heated in the oven at 60 °C for 1–2 days. Tissues were then rinsed with distilled water, stained with safranin O (10 min) and gently squashed onto a microscope slide.A twig cross-section of <italic>Grevillea parallela</italic>, Proteaceae. The radial sector of the stained section is shown on the left side and the processed image on the right. Colours in the processed image denote different tissue types: blue, vessel lumen; purple, vessel wall; green, rays; orange, axial parenchyma; brown, fibres. The scale bar corresponds to 100 µm.Proportions of all major wood cell types (vessel wall and lumen, fibre wall and lumen, axial parenchyma, rays and tracheids) and their properties (mean vessel lumen area and mean fibre lumen and wall area) were quantified. Here, mean vessel lumen area is also called ‘mean vessel area’ for brevity. Mean vessel area, fibre lumen area and wall area were calculated as the arithmetic mean across all relevant cells (vessels or fibres) measured within a given radial sector of a sample. In addition to these traits we calculated theoretical maximum hydraulic conductivity (called here ‘theoretical conductivity’; also known as ‘potential conductivity’). Conductivity for the lumen of each conduit was calculated from the Hagen–Poiseuille expression (π<italic>r</italic><sup>4</sup>)/(8<italic>µ</italic>), where <italic>r</italic> represents mean vessel lumen radius and <italic>µ</italic> represents water dynamic viscosity (assuming a standard viscosity value of 1 at 20 °C). The sum of all vessel lumen conductivities per unit cross-section is theoretical conductivity. This quantity expresses conductivity variation across species due to conduit diameters, but it should be thought of as the <italic>theoretical</italic> maximum since it does not capture effects of end-wall resistances, blockage by tyloses, effects of emboli, etc.Traditionally, wood is considered a complex tissue composed of several cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C12">Evert 2006</xref>). However, we refer to those cell types as ‘tissues’ for brevity and also because they perform distinctly different functions. Anatomical terminology follows the ‘IAWA list of microscopic features for hardwood identification’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C25">IAWA Committee 1989</xref>). Vascular and/or vasicentric tracheids occurred in 13 species and are referred to hereafter as tracheids. Tracheids were first determined in macerated wood and then identified on a cross-section on the basis of the number of pits and size of the pit border (both resembling that of vessel pits) and cell size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C25">IAWA Committee 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C49">Sano <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Axial apotracheal and paratracheal parenchyma were collectively measured as axial parenchyma. None of the species studied here had storied rays. Tissue types were expressed as the fraction of a tissue per cross-sectional area (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT046F1">1</xref>). Tissue fractions of the area outside vessel lumen (non-vessel area) were calculated as tissue fraction multiplied by non-vessel area fraction. The term ‘non-vessel’ area is used for brevity and it includes vessel walls, fibre walls and lumens, axial and ray parenchyma, and tracheids. Non-vessel-lumen quantities are hereafter denoted by subscript ‘NV’, e.g. fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub>, wood density<sub>NV</sub>, etc. Fibre wall proportion in a given fibre was expressed as a proportion of the total fibre area. Fibre wall fraction was obtained by multiplying mean fibre wall proportion in a fibre by the fibre fraction per cross-section. Fibre lumen fraction was similarly calculated from mean fibre lumen proportion in a fibre multiplied by fibre fraction.We collected measurements for 23 species, one of which occurred at two sites and was considered as two entities, giving a total of 24 data points analysed. Measurements were carried out on three replicate individuals per species and the trait values were averaged for comparisons across species. Wood density, vessel lumen, sum of ray and axial parenchyma, ray parenchyma and fibre wall fractions of total wood area as well as non-vessel wood area were all approximately normally distributed (Shapiro–Wilk test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Vessel wall, axial parenchyma, tracheids and fibre lumen fractions of total wood area as well as of non-vessel wood area were right-skewed and were transformed to generate approximately normally distributed variables. Log<sub>10</sub> transformations normalized all distributions with the exception of tracheid fraction and tracheid non-vessel fraction. We used ordinary least-squares regression to assess bivariate relationships (SigmaPlot, Systat, San Jose, CA, USA).Tissue fractions for 24 species arranged in order of increasing wood density (from bottom to top). Large wood density numbers indicate total wood density whereas small numbers indicate non-vessel density (density<sub>NV</sub>). Mean tissue fractions across all species are shown in the bar at the top of the figure. <italic>Leucopogon ericoides</italic> occurred in two sites and is treated here as two separate entities. An asterisk denotes <italic>L. ericoides</italic> from the cold-wet site as opposed to <italic>L. ericoides</italic> from the cold-dry site with no indicator.Relationship between fraction of wood outside vessel lumens (fraction<sub>NV</sub>) and the density of that non-vessel fraction (wood density<sub>NV</sub>) among 24 Australian species. Fraction<sub>NV</sub> = 1−vessel fraction. Each circle represents a different species (mean value from three replicates). Diagonal isolines represent contours of overall wood density, which increases towards the upper right. All axes are log scaled.Relationship between non-vessel density (wood density<sub>NV</sub>) and fibre fraction in non-vessel fraction (fibre fraction<sub>NV</sub>). Each ‘donut’ circle symbolizes one species. The width of the donut border (black) represents fibre wall proportion within an individual fibre and the width of the hole (white) represents fibre lumen proportion. These proportions were estimated from individual fibres (as fibre wall area—or lumen area—divided by total fibre area), for 75–314 fibres per replicate (mean 170), and then across three replicates per species.Relationships between non-vessel density (wood density<sub>NV</sub>) and (A) fibre wall fraction in non-vessel fraction (fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub>) and (B) fibre lumen fraction in non-vessel fraction (fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub>). Each circle represents a different species (mean value from three replicates). ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.Relationship between the fraction of the non-vessel fraction that is fibre wall or is fibre lumen. Each symbol represents a different species (mean value from three replicates). Symbol diameter is proportional to non-vessel wood density (wood density<sub>NV</sub>), with the biggest symbol indicating highest density<sub>NV</sub> (0.92 g cm<sup>−3</sup>) and the smallest symbol indicating lowest density<sub>NV</sub> (0.44 g cm<sup>−3</sup>).The second most abundant tissue, parenchyma, was not correlated with density<sub>NV</sub> nor were its components, rays and axial parenchyma (all <italic>P</italic>&gt; 0.7). Similarly, vessel wall fraction<sub>NV</sub> was unrelated to density<sub>NV</sub>. Nevertheless, both parenchyma and vessel wall fractions<sub>NV</sub> indirectly affected density<sub>NV</sub>. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT046F6">6</xref> illustrates that there was considerable variation in density<sub>NV</sub> (indicated by symbol size) at a given fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub>, especially at lower wall fraction<sub>NV</sub> (lower half of the graph), and considerable variation in density<sub>NV</sub> at a given fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub>, especially at lower lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub> (left half of the graph). These variations in density<sub>NV</sub> could be partially explained by parenchyma and vessel wall fractions<sub>NV</sub>. At a given fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub>, density<sub>NV</sub> was positively correlated with parenchyma and vessel wall fractions<sub>NV</sub> (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.15, <italic>P</italic> = 0.064 and <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.29, <italic>P</italic> = 0.007, respectively) and negatively with fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub> (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.45, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; all relationships tested against residuals from a regression of wood density<sub>NV</sub> on fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub>). Conversely at a given fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub> (i.e. tested against residuals from a regression of wood density<sub>NV</sub> on fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub>), wood density<sub>NV</sub> was negatively correlated with parenchyma fraction<sub>NV</sub> (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.28, <italic>P</italic> = 0.008), not correlated with vessel wall fraction<sub>NV</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.29) and positively correlated with fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub> (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.40, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Additionally, parenchyma fraction<sub>NV</sub> was tightly negatively correlated with total fibre fraction<sub>NV</sub> (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.74, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). The only remaining tissue, tracheids, occupied on average a very small fraction<sub>NV</sub> and was not subjected to detailed analysis.Relationships between wood density and (A) mean vessel area and (B) theoretical conductivity. Each circle represents a different species (mean value from three replicates). *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.This study aimed to describe the anatomical components of wood density in twigs of 24 Australian tree and shrub species. Properties of fibres, the most abundant tissue, had the strongest effect on wood density variation, as has been shown in some previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C19">Fujiwara <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). However, our results contribute to a more comprehensive understanding of wood structure and its influence on density in twigs. Here, we discuss in detail the properties of fibres and other tissues as components of density.Density of tissue outside vessel lumens (density<sub>NV</sub>), rather than vessel lumen fraction, was the main driver of overall wood density variation. This result agrees with a comparison made across 584 species that considered main stem wood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C66">Zanne <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>), implying that density<sub>NV</sub> determines overall density in both twigs (this study) and main stems similarly. Accordingly, the discussion here is directed towards density<sub>NV</sub> and individual tissue fractions within the non-vessel part of the wood (indicated by subscript ‘NV’, e.g. fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub>). We compare these results with the results for overall wood density reported by other studies, on the basis that overall wood density and density<sub>NV</sub> are closely correlated (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.95, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, this study).All tissue fractions<sub>NV</sub> influence density<sub>NV</sub> but fibre wall and lumen fractions<sub>NV</sub> are the most important. The strong influence of fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub> was due both to its high proportion and its variability, while the influence of fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub> was associated chiefly with its high variability (<italic>c</italic>. 60-fold). Other studies have consistently found a positive relationship between fibre wall fraction and density: in trunk wood among 50 Japanese trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C19">Fujiwara <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>) and 61 North and South American shrubs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>); and in twig wood of 17 South African shrubs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>). Fibre lumen fraction has received less attention but has also been shown (in concordance with our study) to have a negative relationship with wood density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C46">Rana <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The second most abundant tissue, parenchyma, did not correlate with density<sub>NV</sub> in our study nor in tree and shrub trunks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C15">Fichtler and Worbes 2012</xref>) but correlated negatively with twig wood density across 17 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>). These discrepancies might be caused by variable densities of parenchyma tissue itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C57">Taylor 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C18">Fujiwara 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C24">Guilley and Nepveu 2003</xref>) or by varied correlations between parenchyma and fibre wall and lumen fractions (see below). Plausibly, these discrepancies could also stem from different relationships between ray and axial parenchyma. We did not find any cross-correlation between those two components of parenchyma nor were they individually related to density. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> reported that ray and axial parenchyma were negatively correlated with each other and individually correlated with density (axial parenchyma positively correlated, rays—negatively). In that study these links were strongly associated with environmental variables (MAP, MAT and AI). These findings imply that different functional trade-offs can be related to ray and axial parenchyma individually and also that their link is affected by climate. Possibly these trade-offs may be more pronounced in trunk wood, as opposed to the twig wood studied here.We did not find a direct relationship between parenchyma and density<sub>NV</sub>. Nevertheless, our results imply that parenchyma together with fibre lumens can influence density<sub>NV</sub> variation in a less direct way. At a given fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub>, density<sub>NV</sub> depended on the parenchyma fraction<sub>NV</sub> relative to fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub>. Density<sub>NV</sub> was marginally positively correlated with parenchyma fraction<sub>NV</sub> and negatively with fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub>. Parenchyma has higher density than fibre lumen, which has zero density. Therefore, higher parenchyma fraction<sub>NV</sub> relative to fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub> increases density<sub>NV</sub>, and conversely higher fibre lumen fraction<sub>NV</sub> decreases density<sub>NV</sub>. We note that parenchyma fraction<sub>NV</sub> was only weakly correlated with density<sub>NV</sub> at a given fibre wall fraction<sub>NV</sub>. This weak correlation possibly stems from variable parenchyma tissue densities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C57">Taylor 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C18">Fujiwara 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C24">Guilley and Nepveu 2003</xref>).Fibre fraction<sub>NV</sub> (sum of fibre wall and lumen fractions<sub>NV</sub>) was not associated with density<sub>NV</sub> because of wide variation in wall proportion within a fibre (top right to low right in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT046F4">4</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> suggested a similar explanation, but as far as we are aware, this issue has not been quantitatively clarified until now.Anatomical traits that are not expressed as fractions of wood volume have less direct effects on density. We found that density<sub>NV</sub> was correlated with fibre wall proportion within a fibre. Previous studies have also shown that density can be related to fibre lumen diameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>), fibre wall thickness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C19">Fujiwara <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and fibre wall to lumen ratio (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). We believe those traits would deliver a more insightful understanding of wood density when combined with information about fractions, e.g. the relationship among density<sub>NV</sub>, fibre fraction<sub>NV</sub> and fibre wall proportion in a fibre, as described above. Similarly for mean vessel area, which in this study was weakly negatively correlated with wood density. Mean vessel area <italic>per se</italic> should not affect wood density. Rather, vessel fraction (vessel area multiplied by vessel number per area) should be causally linked with density variation.A schematic representation of the graph in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT046F6">6</xref> flipped clockwise by 45°. The actual graph from Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT046F6">6</xref> is repeated here in an inset and also flipped 45° clockwise. The diagram represents four cross-sections of potential anatomical structures in low-, medium- and high-density species. Each hexagon within the three squares indicates a fibre cell consisting of dark fibre wall and bright fibre lumen. The green area on the right of each square indicates parenchyma. Wood density<sub>NV</sub> increases towards the top of the diagram.Cross-sections through twigs of four species. The triangle arrangement corresponds to the one in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT046F8">8</xref> and so the cross-sections are examples of respective anatomies drawn in that figure. (A) <italic>Bossiaea cinerea</italic> (Fabaceae, wood density<sub>NV</sub> 0.92 g cm<sup>−3</sup>), (B) <italic>Grevillea parallela</italic> (Proteaceae, wood density<sub>NV</sub> 0.74 g cm<sup>−3</sup>), (C) <italic>Corymbia intermedia</italic> (Myrtaceae, wood density<sub>NV</sub> 0.78 g cm<sup>−3</sup>), (D) <italic>Alphitonia excelsa</italic> (Rhamnaceae, wood density<sub>NV</sub> 0.44 g cm<sup>−3</sup>). V, vessel; FW, fibre wall; FL, fibre lumen; A, axial parenchyma; R, ray parenchyma. Fibre lumens are indistinct in (A) due to their small sizes.It has been shown that denser woods tend to operate at more negative minimum water potentials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C1">Ackerly 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C6">Bucci <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C50">Santiago <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C27">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C28">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C23">Gotsch <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and have higher cavitation resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C68">Hacke <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C69">Jacobsen <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C43">Pratt <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C70">Lens <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). However, we and previous literature have shown that wood density is most strongly related to fibre properties, not vessel properties. Thus, the relationship among wood density, minimum water potential and cavitation resistance does not appear to be directly influenced by wood density, but rather by a third, unexplained factor. Another element of hydraulic strategies is capacitance, which tends to be negatively correlated with wood density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C37">Meinzer <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C36">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C43">Pratt <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C51">Scholz <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Our results imply that capacitance water could be stored in fibre lumen or in parenchyma but the exact mechanism of this water storage and release is not known, nor is it clear what might be the advantage or disadvantage of fibre lumen capacitance compared with parenchyma capacitance. Density also plays a role in the mechanical behaviour of wood. It is a good predictor of mechanical strength and elasticity at a given wood diameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C8">Chave <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). However, it has also been shown that plants can compensate for mechanically weak wood by building thicker stems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C2">Anten and Schieving 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C31">Larjavaara and Muller-Landau 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C7">Butler <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Thick, low-density stems could be mechanically strong but their maintenance costs would be higher due to large surface area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C31">Larjavaara and Muller-Landau 2010</xref>). Additionally, our results suggest that in similar density woods maintenance costs per sapwood cross-sectional area could vary depending on wood anatomical structure. Namely, woods with high fraction of living parenchyma would presumably incur higher maintenance costs than woods with high fraction of non-living fibres. What then would be the advantage of high parenchyma fraction? Hypothetically, high parenchyma fraction could ensure high nutrient storage capacity, which may be beneficial in some ecological strategies. This issue and other questions about causal links between wood anatomical structure and ecological strategies require further investigation and open interesting pathways for future research.Caution is needed when comparing results from twigs with results from main trunks. It is not proven that the relationships of wood density and anatomy are the same at the twig level as at the trunk level. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C59">Taylor and Wooten (1973)</xref> found that in five species vessel and fibre fractions shifted in the same direction with plant height, but this was not the case for ray fraction. Other studies examining association between vessel lumen fraction and wood density across a large number of species showed no relationship in the main trunks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C34">Martínez-Cabrera <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C41">Poorter <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C66">Zanne <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) but a negative relationship in twigs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C44">Preston <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C26">Jacobsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C38">Mitchell <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C22">Gleason <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Such disparities indicate that the relationship between wood density and tissue fractions may conceivably be different in main trunks than in twigs, yet it is unclear how generally this is so.Wood density has been proposed as a key plant functional trait and is related to ecological strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT046C8">Chave <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) but relatively little is known about the underpinnings of these relationships. This study clarifies the anatomical basis for wood density variation across species. It shows that wood density depends on anatomical structure, but also that a range of very different structures can result in very similar wood density, especially among species with medium density<sub>NV</sub> (here, 0.60–0.85 g cm<sup>−3</sup>). This conclusion suggests that there may be a wider range of ecological strategies among such species. Taken together, these findings imply that twig wood density should not be considered as an unambiguous indicator of plant ecological strategies. We hope this research will enhance the interpretation and design of ecological studies related to wood density.This work has been supported by the Macquarie University Research Excellence Scholarship (Australia) and the Australian Research Council Discovery Project grant <grant-num xlink:type="simple">DP0877064</grant-num> awarded, respectively, to K.Z. and M.W.All authors contributed to the analysis of the results, writing and editing of the manuscript. D.W.B devised site selection. K.Z., D.W.B and S.M.G. carried out fieldwork. K.Z. performed anatomical work.None declared.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plt046/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">The following Supporting Information is available in the online version of this article –</ext-link><bold>File 1.</bold> Table. Details of the four sites sampled in this study.<bold>File 2.</bold> Table. Species traits: wood density and tissue fractions.<bold>File 3.</bold> Table. Species traits: wood density and tissue fractions of non-vessel fraction.<bold>File 4.</bold> Table. Species traits: mean vessel area and theoretical conductivity.We thank Judy and Eddie Howitt, John and Jill Bignell, and National Parks and State Forests staff in Queensland and Tasmania for their hospitality and sites access. Parks and Wildlife Service of Tasmania and Queensland gave permission for plant material collection. Macquarie University Microscopy Unit kindly provided facilities to carry out anatomical work. Many thanks to Steven Jansen, editor Tim Brodribb and two anonymous reviewers for constructive comments on earlier versions of this manuscript. Wendy Noble and Luen-Hsien Chang also provided useful feedback on earlier versions of this manuscript. We are grateful to Comparative Ecology Lab members for constructive conversations about the research presented here.