Extractable nitrogen and microbial community structure respond to grassland restoration regardless of historical context and soil compositionHierarchical responses of plant–soil interactions to climate change: consequences for the global carbon cycleGermination and seedling establishment in California annual grasslandTwo invasive plants alter soil microbial community composition in serpentine grasslandsPlant species and soil type cooperatively shape the structure and function of microbial communities in the rhizosphereMicrobial immobilization of ammonium and nitrate in relation to ammonification and nitrification rates in organic and conventional cropping systemsIncorporating the soil community into plant population dynamics: the utility of the feedback approachEcology of California grasslandsTimber harvesting alters soil carbon mineralization and microbial community structure in coniferous forestsLong-term ecosystem impacts of an introduced grass in the northern Great PlainsRestoration of a native shrubland impacted by exotic grasses, frequent fire, and nitrogen deposition in Southern CaliforniaInternal cycling of N-15 in shortgrass prairieChapter 6: ecology of non-native invasivesInvasive plant–soil feedbacks and ecosystem resistance and resilience: a comparison of three vegetation types in CaliforniaSoil nitrogen cycling is resilient to invasive annuals following restoration of coastal sage scrubEffects of exotic plant invasions on soil nutrient cycling processesPlant traits that influence ecosystem processes vary independently among speciesFunctional matrix: a conceptual framework for predicting multiple plant effects on ecosystem processesMechanisms determining patterns of nutrient dynamicsMicrobial biomass measured as total lipid phosphate in soils of different organic contentFire and competition in a southern California grassland: impacts on the rare forb <italic>Erodium macrophyllum</italic>Selective influence of plant species on microbial diversity in the rhizospherePlant invasion alters nitrogen cycling by modifying the soil nitrifying communityArbuscular mycorrhizal assemblages in native plant roots change in the presence of invasive exotic grassesInvasive plant species and soil microbial response to wildfire burn severity in the cascade range of OregonMeasuring soil microbial community diversity using polar lipid fatty acid and denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis dataPatterns of growth and soil-water utilization in some exotic annuals and native perennial bunchgrasses of CaliforniaEffects of plant composition and diversity on nutrient cyclingGrowth patterns of Mediterranean annual and perennial grasses under simulated rainfall regimes of southern France and CaliforniaPlant and soil-nitrogen dynamics in California annual grasslandShort-term partitioning of ammonium and nitrate between plants and microbes in an annual grasslandFloristic and soil organic matter changes after five and thirty-five years of native tallgrass prairie restorationMechanisms of plant species impacts on ecosystem nitrogen cyclingInvasions of non-native grasses causes a drop in soil carbon storage in California grasslandsDecoupling plant-growth from land-use legacies in soil microbial communitiesLong-term plant growth legacies overwhelm short-term plant growth effects on soil microbial community structureChemotaxonomic use of lipids: an overviewLandscape-level patterns of microbial community composition and substrate use in upland forest ecosystemsRestoration of <italic>Stipa pulchra</italic> grasslands: effects of mycorrhizae and competition from <italic>Avena barbata</italic>Soil microbial community composition as affected by restoration practices in California grasslandBelow and above ground responses to lupine and litter mulch in a California grassland restored with native bunchgrassesNutrient dynamics and nitrogen trace gas flux during ecosystem development in montane rain-forestExtending the leaf economics spectrum to decomposition: evidence from a tropical forestNutrient cycling and plant–soil feedbacks along a precipitation gradient in lowland PanamaJMPComparative structure and function in a California annual and native bunchgrass communityFluctuations in the annual vegetation of CaliforniaLipid analysis in microbial ecology—quantitative approaches to the study of microbial communitiesEcological linkages between aboveground and belowground biotaQuantitative comparisons of <italic>in situ</italic> microbial biodiversity by signature biomarker analysisBreaking new ground: soil communities and exotic plant invasionN-15 uptake by mycorrhizal native and invasive plants from a N-eutrophied shrubland: a greenhouse experimentFatty acid patterns of phospholipids and lipopolysaccharides in the characterization of microbial communities in soil: a reviewFatty-acid patterns of phospholipids and lipopolysaccharides in environmental-samples<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> InderjitThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Exotic plants have the capacity to establish positive plant-soil feedbacks facilitating invader persistence often at the cost of native plant species success. We compared the plant communities, soil chemical and microbial communities and nutrient turnover rates between invaded and restored plots in inland and coastal grasslands. Greater extractable N, slower N cycling rates and differing microbial community composition resulted from restoration. These differences indicate that grassland soils are responsive to vegetation change, and therefore not resistant to invasion-caused feedbacks. It also suggests these soils are resilient to invasion and may be capable of recovery following vegetative restoration.Grasslands have a long history of invasion by exotic annuals, which may alter microbial communities and nutrient cycling through changes in litter quality and biomass turnover rates. We compared plant community composition, soil chemical and microbial community composition, potential soil respiration and nitrogen (N) turnover rates between invaded and restored plots in inland and coastal grasslands. Restoration increased microbial biomass and fungal : bacterial (F : B) ratios, but sampling season had a greater influence on the F : B ratio than did restoration. Microbial community composition assessed by phospholipid fatty acid was altered by restoration, but also varied by season and by site. Total soil carbon (C) and N and potential soil respiration did not differ between treatments, but N mineralization decreased while extractable nitrate and nitrification and N immobilization rate increased in restored compared with unrestored sites. The differences in soil chemistry and microbial community composition between unrestored and restored sites indicate that these soils are responsive, and therefore not resistant to feedbacks caused by changes in vegetation type. The resilience, or recovery, of these soils is difficult to assess in the absence of uninvaded control grasslands. However, the rapid changes in microbial and N cycling characteristics following removal of invasives in both grassland sites suggest that the soils are resilient to invasion. The lack of change in total C and N pools may provide a buffer that promotes resilience of labile pools and microbial community structure.The effects of exotic plant invasions on terrestrial ecosystems vary temporally and spatially and span scales ranging from the plant rhizosphere to changes in nutrient flux that occur at the ecosystem level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C16">Ehrenfeld 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C44">Potthoff <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Previously, the impacts of exotic invasive plants on soil microbial communities and nutrient fluxes have received considerable attention (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C30">Jackson <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C31">1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C6">Bever <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C23">Hawkes <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C24">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C57">Wolfe and Klironomos 2005</xref>). However, belowground responses to restoration practices and studies on the legacy effects of plant invasions are relatively new areas of research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C43">Potthoff <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C44">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C35">Kulmatiski and Beard 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C36">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C14">Dickens 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C15">Dickens and Allen 2014</xref>). The capacity of invaded systems to recover from short-term and legacy effects of exotic plants is unknown. In addition, the role of legacy effects of exotic invasion and exotic species identity in the success of restoration is unclear, greatly limiting the knowledge base needed for strategic restoration of invaded lands.One mechanism by which exotic plants impact ecosystems is by decoupling plant–soil feedback loops that previously functioned in soils under native vegetation. We define decoupling here and the interruption of interactions between plants and soil via soil inputs and microbial community responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C1">Bardgett <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Feedback loops describe how plants, soils and microorganisms interact through resources. For example, a plant species may produce particular soil inputs via senescent biomass and exudates that become resources for soil microbes. Microbes that use these resources determine rates of nutrient cycling and thus nutrient availability to plants. Through this feedback loop, plants and microbes may exert selective pressure on one another (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C54">Wardle 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C18">Eviner and Chapin 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C48">Santiago <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C47">Santiago 2007</xref>). In the case of plant invasion, a new species' arrival may alter the microbial community, leading to further modifications of belowground processes such as nutrient turnover or the introduction of microbial species associated with this novel plant. The end result can be inhibition of native plant species and/or the facilitation of the invading, exotic plant species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C6">Bever <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C16">Ehrenfeld 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C57">Wolfe and Klironomos 2005</xref>).Introductions of plant species that differ in litter quality, phenology and relative distribution of above and belowground biomass may result in especially strong plant–soil feedbacks. Exotic species may introduce novel nutrient uptake or litter deposition traits that could create positive feedbacks with the soil microbial community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C22">Grayston <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C17">Eviner 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C3">Batten <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Exotics may shift the seasonal availability of extractable nitrogen (N) by introducing phenologies with earlier germination and growth rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C30">Jackson <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C14">Dickens 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C15">Dickens and Allen 2014</xref>) and changes in soil properties that drive the selection and composition of microbial communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C16">Ehrenfeld 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C55">Wardle <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C4">Berg and Smalla 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C44">Potthoff <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Additionally, exotic plant invasion can change cycling and availability of C, N and other nutrients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C10">Christian and Wilson 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C16">Ehrenfeld 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C58">Yoshida and Allen 2004</xref>). Litter with high C : N promotes immobilization of N by microbes resulting in reduced available N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C8">Brady and Weil 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C22">Grayston <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C11">Cione <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C44">Potthoff <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Invasion of exotic, annual grasses into a perennial bunchgrass grassland would be expected to introduce litter of lower C : N compared with native perennials which would increase decomposition and N cycling rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C19">Eviner and Firestone 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C44">Potthoff <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).California grasslands are highly invaded by exotic annuals and undergoing restoration in many locations, and thus an ideal system for studying plant–soil feedbacks through decoupling exotic plant species' plant–soil feedbacks using restoration. Plant biomass in grasslands turns over annually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C30">Jackson <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>) so grassland soils are likely to respond to altered plant inputs over a relatively short time scale. Due to the almost complete conversion of native perennial grasslands with annual forbs to exotic annual grassland with annual forbs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C7">Biswell 1956</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C13">D'Antonio 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C38">Minnich 2008</xref>), native California grasslands are a system of high conservation value and concern. Annual plant invasions began &gt;200 years ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C38">Minnich 2008</xref>), and invasion is so widespread that there are no true relic grasslands to use as reference sites. However, even without relic grasslands, differences in soil microbial community structure, soil chemistry and nutrient flux rates between unrestored and restored soils can be used to evaluate the capacity of grassland soils to respond to changes in vegetation type.Invasion of original, native grasslands introduced new, exotic plant–soil feedbacks (solid black arrows represent native feedbacks and dotted black arrows represent plant soil feedbacks of exotics). Through restoration efforts plant–soil feedbacks can be altered leading to (A) a restored grassland experiencing no exotic feedbacks and moderate native feedbacks from the re-establishing native community or (B) a partially restored grassland experiencing a much higher proportion of native plant–soil feedbacks than exotic. Thickness of arrows indicates the degree to which feedbacks are influencing the system.Comparison of site abiotic properties, land-use history and restoration methodologies.Plant species richness, per cent cover by individual species and per cent of litter cover were measured annually by visual estimation in gridded 1 m<sup>2</sup> frames in each treatment at the peak of the growing season (March) in 2007–09. Net annual productivity of annuals was determined by harvesting biomass in four functional groups (native forb, native grass, exotic forb and exotic grass) clipped at the soil level from 0.25 m<sup>2</sup> sub-plots and scaled up to the 1 m<sup>2</sup> plot size using regression of plant biomass and per cent cover in 0.25 m<sup>2</sup> and per cent cover of 1 m<sup>2</sup> plots. Additional biomass was collected for chemical analysis of the vegetative plant tissue at peak plant growth. All biomass was oven dried at 60 °C and weighed. Biomass for tissue analysis was ground and analysed for total C and N on a soil combustion analyser system (Flash AlllZ, Thermo-Finnigan).To determine the effects of restoration on soil biological and chemical characteristics, three soil cores of 2.5 cm diameter and 10 cm depth were collected per plot, composited to the plot level and then transported on ice to the laboratory where a portion of each sample was stored at −20 °C until processed for chemical analyses and the remaining portion of the sample at −80 °C for microbial analyses. Soils were analysed for total C and N by combustion, KCl-extractable NO<sub>3</sub> and NH<sub>4</sub>, and bicarbonate-extractable phosphorus (Olsen P) by the University of California Analytical Laboratory at UC Davis (anlab.ucdavis.edu). Soil pH was measured using a 2 : 1 soil : water slurry. Soil cores were collected once annually in 2007 and 2009 at peak growth, and three times annually (at germination, peak plant growth and plant senescence) during 2007–08 for analysis of KCl-extractable N (<inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>).Phospholipid fatty acid (PLFA) analysis was used to determine whether microbial community structure was affected by restoration of the native vegetation. With the exception of Archaea, all other living organisms contain PLFAs as a component of their cellular membranes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C56">White <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C26">Hedrick <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). These compounds can be used as biomarkers to identify functional groups of microbes such as Gram-positive bacteria or arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C60">Zelles and Bai 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C56">White <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C26">Hedrick <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). Phospholipid fatty acids are preferable to the use of fatty acids alone as fatty acids can persist in soils for long periods of time representing a legacy of past microbial communities. Phospholipid fatty acid represent living organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C56">White <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>), thus ensuring capture of the current microbial community response to a disturbance such as exotic plant invasion or restoration activities. Samples were collected within 24 h of rainfall or wetting of soils to a 10-year average rainfall volume. Soil samples were passed through a 2-mm sieve and lyophilized prior to extraction. Phospholipid fatty acids were extracted from 6 g of soil following the modified Bligh–Dyer method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C20">Frostegard <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>). Quantification of fatty acids was obtained using a gas chromatograph (HP6980; Hewlett Packard, Palo Alto, CA, USA) with a flame ionization detector and HP3365 ChemStation Software. Phospholipid fatty acid peaks were converted to PLFA identities and abundances using MIDI Sherlock Microbial Identification System (MIDI, Inc., Newark, NJ, USA) followed by comparison of peak areas with a known internal standard 19 : 0 of known concentration. Bacterial biomarkers included: 14 : 0, 15 : 0 iso, 15 : 0 antiso, 16 : 0 iso, 16 : 0 iso G, 16 : 1 w9c, 16 : 1 w7c, 16 : 0, 16 : 1 2OH, 17 : 1 alcohol, 17 : 0 iso, 17 : 0 antiso, 17 : 0 cyclo, 17 : 1 w8c, 18 : 1 w5c, 18 : 0, 19 : 0 cyclo c11–12, 22 : 0 and 24 : 0 and fungi: 18 : 2 w6c, 18 1w9c and 17 : 0 and AM fungi: 16 : 1 w5c. Nomenclature for PLFAs followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C37">Lechevalier and Lechevalier (1988)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C53">Vestal and White (1989)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C59">Zelles (1999)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C39">Myers <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C25">Hebel <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>.Laboratory incubations for potential N mineralization were performed over a 30-day period in soil samples maintained at 25 °C and 60 % humidity. <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> were extracted with a 2-M KCl 4 : 1 solution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C45">Riley and Vitousek 1995</xref>) and shipped on dry ice for analysis at the University of California Analytical Laboratory at UC Davis (anlab.ucdavis.edu). Net mineralization was calculated as the change in <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> minus the change in <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> over time, and net nitrification was calculated as the change of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> over time following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C45">Riley and Vitousek (1995)</xref>. Potential soil respiration rates were determined using laboratory incubations. Soils were maintained at 20 % soil moisture and 25 °C in sealed glass jars for 10 days. Jar headspace concentrations of CO<sub>2</sub> (ppm) were determined using a LiCor 800 infrared gas analyser (Lincoln, NE, USA) and converted to a rate function of μmol CO<sub>2</sub>-C/g soil × day (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C9">Chatterjee <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).Plant species per cent cover and richness were analysed using repeated-measures multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) to assess how the vegetative community responded to restoration. Plant biomass and litter, soil chemistry, soil-extractable N, potential soil respiration and N mineralization data were analysed with ANOVA followed by Tukey's HSD to determine whether restoration altered soil chemical pools and cycling rates. Non-normal data were log(<italic>x</italic>+ 1) or square root transformed when appropriate and a Kruskal-Wallis nonparametric test was performed in cases where the data could not be transformed to normality. Microbial biomass and F : B were analysed using ANOVA to determine coarse microbial community compositional shifts between treatments. Principal component analysis (PCA) was used to create ordination diagrams to compare microbial community compositions, which were then further analysed by ANOVA of PC1 and PC2 values to determine if community composition differed following restoration and across sampling dates. The analyses were conducted using JMP9 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C61">SAS Institute 2009</xref>) with an alpha level of <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05.Common species mean per cent cover of inland and coastal grassland plant functional groups during the peak of the 2007–08 season. Repeated-measures MANOVA were conducted to assess differences in plant composition between treatments of unrestored and restored grasslands over 3 years during the 2006–09 growing seasons.Plant leaf tissue chemical composition for some of the most common species encountered at the two project sites. Five samples of each plant species were analysed and averaged per species.The common PLFA biomarkers (μmol PLFA g<sup>−1</sup> soil) and corresponding microbial taxa from the inland and coastal grasslands and between sites during the 2007–08 season. Means are shown for biomarkers making up &gt;2 % of total PLFA abundance. Asterisks indicate the level of significance between treatments. *<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.1, **<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05 and ***<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.001 determined with ANOVA.Principal component analysis results for PLFA microbial community analysis at the inland site (A and C) and the coastal site (B and D) during the 2007–08 growing season. Restored data points of graph (A) refer to restored-burned treatments of the inland site and those of graph (B) refer to restored-weeded treatments of the coastal site. Graphs (A) and (B) assess differences between treatment while (C) and (D) assess differences between sampling dates. PC1 explains 83 % variation and PC2 has a cumulative per cent variation of 91 % for the inland site, while the coastal site cumulative variance explained by PC1 is 59 % and PC2 is 70 %. Ellipses indicate statistically different microbial communities determined by ANOVA of PC values.Soil-extractable N during the 2007–08 season at the inland site (A) and the coastal site (B). Treatments are: UN = unrestored, REB = restored by burning at the inland site and REW = restored by weeding and mowing at the coastal site. Letters indicate significant differences using ANOVA followed by Tukey–Kramer HSD test: NO<sub>3</sub> = A and B, NH<sub>4</sub> = C and D and total extractable N = E and F. Bars indicate standard error and letters significant differences (<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05).Soil chemical data (means and standard errors) for the burned, inland site and the coastal site collected the summer of 2006. ANOVA was conducted to assess differences in soil chemical characteristics between treatments of unrestored and restored grasslands during the 2006–07 growing season.Potential N mineralization and nitrification from 30-day laboratory incubations from the inland site (A and C) and the coastal site (B and D) for soils collected in the March (peak) and August (end of the summer dry season) of 2008. Letters indicate significant differences using the Tukey–Kramer HSD test following ANOVA (<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05). Bars indicate standard error.Microbial shifts in community structure and altered extractable N pools and N cycling indicate that exotic plant–soil feedbacks were decoupled following restoration at both sites regardless of differences in soil properties between sites. Decoupling is used here to mean that established interactions between exotic plants and soil organisms were disrupted and replaced to some degree by interactions between native plants and soil organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C1">Bardgett <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Native grasses increased at both sites and exotics were reduced leading to shifts in plant inputs, particularly by reducing the proportion of exotic species litter having higher C : N in both sites and increasing the proportion of <italic>S. pulchra</italic> litter with intermediate quality. The reduction of exotic plant inputs followed by replacement by native plant inputs altered the microbial community, increased NO<sub>3</sub>-N availability and nitrification rates and decreased NH<sub>4</sub>-N availability and N mineralization rates. Although no uninvaded grasslands are available as reference sites, these rapid changes indicate that these grasslands have some capacity for soil resilience.Differences in microbial community biomass, F : B and individual markers (indicated by concentrations of PLFA biomarkers) between unrestored and restored soils support our hypothesis that restoration of the native plant community would decouple the previously existing exotic plant–soil feedbacks and allow for establishment of native plant–soil feedbacks. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C44">Potthoff <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> found similar shifts in PLFA profiles that they interpreted to indicate resilience of the soil microbial community to disturbance. Restoration reduced microbial biomass values during germination indicating a stronger response of soil microbes in unrestored soils following the first rains, likely due to higher root activity of germinating exotics, rapid decomposition of exotic annual grassland seedlings due to self-thinning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C2">Bartolome 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C49">Savelle 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C19">Eviner and Firestone 2007</xref>) or decomposition of the previous year's microbial biomass. Shifts in microbial community in response to seasonal changes in temperature and moisture, such as those found here, are expected due to species-specific growth requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C42">Pommerville 2007</xref>). Mycorrhizal fungi may decline in perennial grassland soils invaded by exotic annual grasses, so we expected fungal biomarkers to be lower in unrestored plots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C24">Hawkes <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). The grasslands of this experiment had reduced fungal biomarkers, 18 : 2 w6c, 18 : 1w9c and 16 : 1 w5cat germination, but increased fungal markers 18 : 2 w6c and 18 : 1w9c the remainder of the season. Similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C24">Hawkes’ <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> findings, our coastal grassland site had lower AM fungi PLFA markers in unrestored plots dominated by exotic annuals, but this did not occur until late in the growing season (i.e. plant senescence). Native plant species tend to have a later phenology than exotics in the semi-arid grasslands and thus experience peak growth rates later into the season than exotic plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C29">Jackson and Roy 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C27">Holmes and Rice 1996</xref>). AM fungi associated with exotics have reduced abundance earlier in the season when their exotic, annual host plants senesce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C41">Nelson and Allen 1993</xref>). Other fungal groups were also in high concentration during senescence at both sites. Therefore, phenology of the dominant plant species either annual exotics or native annuals to native perennial grassland species was related to the activity of soil microorganisms.The anticipated shift in N availability occurred and also showed seasonal patterns corresponding to plant phenologies. Total extractable N and NO<sub>3</sub>-N increased with restoration during peak and senescence periods of the growing season as also observed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C30">Jackson <italic>et al.</italic> (1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C31">1989</xref>). One of the more striking results was that extractable N concentrations at the inland site were higher in unrestored soils at plant germination but quickly became significantly lower within 2–3 months, suggesting increased rates of N uptake by plants in the unrestored plots. Plants may take up as much <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation7" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> as becomes available (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C30">Jackson <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C31">1989</xref>). This effect of exotic plant removal on increased mineral N has been observed in both grassland and coastal sage scrub in other studies of semi-arid environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C14">Dickens 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C15">Dickens and Allen 2014</xref>). In this study, plant uptake of N was still low at germination, but began to increase rapidly as plant growth reached its maximum rates. The peak and senescence sampling dates at these sites correspond to the periods of maximum annual growth and transition to reproduction phases during which their N use would be highest. California grassland natives tend to germinate and complete their life cycles later than exotic annuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C29">Jackson and Roy 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C27">Holmes and Rice 1996</xref>) and likely have continued nutrient uptake closer to the senescence sampling date. <italic>Stipa pulchra</italic> recycles about half its annual N internally and thus may not take up N as soon or at rates as high as those observed for exotic annuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C12">Clark 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C30">Jackson <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C28">Hooper and Vitousek 1998</xref>). <italic>Stipa pulchra</italic> is the dominant native so less rapid and total uptake rates would translate to greater overall extractable N left in the soil throughout the season. Restoration led to reduced NH<sub>4</sub>-N and N mineralization but increased nitrification, indicating greater immobilization of N following restoration. In other grasslands, exotic grass invasion is associated with increased N mineralization, which is attributed to a greater abundance of ammonia-oxidizing bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C23">Hawkes <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Here, the biomass of bacteria was higher in unrestored soils, although our PLFA assay could not identify whether these ammonia-oxidizing bacteria were reduced by restoration.Long-term invasion and anthropogenic disturbance may be one mechanism explaining the resistance of soil total C and N pools and potential respiration to changes under restored plant community conditions. Total soil C and N pools and C cycling may show resistance or may only be slowly responsive to changes in vegetation. These soils have likely been invaded by exotic annual grasses for more than a century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C38">Minnich 2008</xref>), so sufficient time has likely passed for total C and N pools to change in response to invasion. Similar resistance of C and N pools were observed in grasslands of northern California when community composition was altered to test legacy effects of plant–soil interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C44">Potthoff <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). However, decreased soil C was found in invaded grasslands in central California compared with reference patches of native grassland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C34">Koteen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C32">Kindscher and Tieszen (1998)</xref> found that tall grass prairie soils may require &gt;35 years to recover C from agricultural use following restoration. The shifts in litter input at our grasslands may not have been great enough to lead to altered C and N pools. Differences and variability in litter quality in grasslands are often subtle making responses to changes in litter difficult to detect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C19">Eviner and Firestone 2007</xref>). This suggests that our grasslands could have been resistant to impacts of the initial exotic annual invasion or that restoration must occur for a longer time than 9 years to detect total soil N and C responses. Another contributing factor is the reinvasion of exotic grass following restoration. While native vegetation continued to dominate, exotic species had a continuous impact on the soil.Between-site differences in restoration responses of extractable N availability and microbial community structure were primarily seasonal. This corresponded with our hypothesis that soil responses are sensitive to environment. In this case, the important environmental influences included soil nutrient and climatic differences. Greater immobilization at the coastal than the inland site may be the result of a 15 % lower soil C : N ratio and 5 % greater soil organic matter content than at the inland site. Higher organic matter in conjunction with lower C : N soil values would allow for higher rates of N mineralization while also leading to increased immobilization overall in restored plots of the coastal site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C33">Knops <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C5">Berger and Jackson 2003</xref>). Instead, the inland site had a more stable microbial community (F : B was unchanged) and a steady use of nutrients over the season followed by a second peak of microbial activity at senescence. So while differences in soil nutrient conditions, timing of responses to restoration and specific PLFA concentrations occurred between sites, the patterns of increased NO<sub>3</sub>-N and nitrification, reduced N mineralization and altered microbial community composition following restoration occurred at both sites. This indicates that grassland soils were responsive to changes in vegetation and may therefore be resilient to invasion.Restoration of invaded grasslands decoupled exotic plant–soil feedbacks related to microbial community structure, extractable N and N cycling. This study indicates that the soils of these systems are dynamic and change in response to exotic or native vegetation type and seasonal variation in soil moisture. Semi-arid grasslands in general are known to be unstable in productivity and reliant on seasonal precipitation patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU085C52">Talbot <italic>et al.</italic> 1939</xref>). Measured changes in extractable soil N and microbial characteristics in response to removal of exotic plants indicated that grassland soils are not resistant to the impacts of plant community shifts, but have the capacity for resilience regardless of the method of exotic plant control (i.e. prescribed burn, mowing and weeding). This indicates that the method of exotic plant removal is not important in these grasslands, but that removal of exotic plants and decoupling exotic plant–soil feedbacks are required for grassland soils to diverge from invaded conditions. In contrast, the lack of change in total soil C and N pools and potential soil respiration may be an indication that, for these soil characteristics, these grasslands are resistant to invasion. Stable pools of C and N may buffer these soils, enabling resilience of the more labile and rapidly responding mineral N and microbial characteristics. However, the absence of uninvaded grasslands does not allow us to rule out changes in C and N pools that may have occurred long ago or will require a more complete restoration and longer time frames for recovery. The differences between sites regarding the timing of microbial activity and N cycling highlight the importance of matching sampling efforts to seasonality of plant and microbial growth patterns. Overall NO<sub>3</sub>-N use and net N cycling differences between restored and unrestored plots were similar between the coastal and inland sites, indicating that shifts in plant community composition from exotic to native-dominated communities produce the same impact on N regardless of site history, restoration methods and differences in soil type.This work has been funded by the University of California-Riverside and specifically the Department of Botany and Plant Sciences and the Center for Conservation Biology, the <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">Shipley-Skinner Riverside County Endowment, the UC Fisher Vegetation Scholarship, The Nature Conservancy and the National Science Foundation</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">DEB 04-21530</grant-num>).S.J.M.D. and E.B.A. formed the research questions and all authors contributed to the development, analysis of data and manuscript drafting. S.J.M.D. implemented the project in the field and laboratory.None declared.The following Supporting Information is available in the online version of this article –<bold>Table S1.</bold> The common phospholipid fatty acid (PLFA) biomarkers (μmol PLFA g<sup>−1</sup> soil) and the corresponding microbial functional groups from the inland site during the 2007–08 season. Asterisks indicate the level of significance between treatments. **<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05.<bold>Table S2.</bold> The common PLFA biomarkers (μmol g<sup>−1</sup> soil) and the corresponding microbial functional groups from the coastal site during the 2007–08 season. Asterisks indicate the level of significance between treatments. *<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.001, **<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05.<bold>Table S3.</bold> Soil microbial PLFA principal component (PC) per cent weights at both locations. Positive and negative signs indicate the direction of the weighting along the corresponding PC. Cumulative per cent explained equals the variance within the PLFA data explained by successive PCs.The authors extend their gratitude to Dr Jodie Holt, Dr Mike Allen and Dr Darrel Jenerette for thoughtful discussions. For assistance in data collection they thank Christopher True, Dr Robert Cox, Dr Leela Rao, Dr Robert (Chip) Steers, Dr Heather Schneider, Dr Mike Bell and Dr Kris Weathers, as well as Andrew Sanders for assistance with plant identification. They also thank their funding sources: The University of California-Riverside and specifically the Department of Botany and Plant Sciences and the Center for Conservation Biology, the Shipley-Skinner Riverside County Endowment, the UC Fisher Vegetation Scholarship, The Nature Conservancy and the National Science Foundation (DEB 04-21530).