 Contemporary reliance on bicarbonate acquisition predicts increased growth of seagrass  Amphibolis antarctica  in a high-CO 2  world  Effects of CO 2  enrichment on photosynthesis, growth, and nitrogen metabolism of the seagrass  Zostera noltii   Ocean acidification and the loss of phenolic substances in marine plants  Photosynthesis and inorganic carbon usage by the marine cyanobacterium,  Synechococcus  sp  Transplantation as a method for restoring the seagrass  Posidonia australis   Ecological implications of microalgal and cyanobacterial CO 2  concentrating mechanisms, and their regulation  Biodiversity of marine plants in an era of climate change: some predictions based on physiological performance  Photosynthesis and photorespiration of marine angiosperms  Photosynthesis of marine macroalgae and seagrasses in globally changing CO 2  environments  Carbon metabolism in seagrasses. I. Utilization of exogenous inorganic carbon species in photosynthesis  Measuring photosynthetic rates in seagrasses by pulse amplitude modulated (PAM) fluorometry  Inorganic carbon utilization in marine angiosperms (seagrasses)  Geocarb III: a revised model of atmospheric CO 2  over phanerozoic time  The influence of oxygen concentration on photosynthesis in marine plants  Activation of the carbon concentrating mechanism by CO 2  deprivation coincides with massive transcriptional restructuring in  Chlamydomonas reinhardtii   Nutrient exposure causes epiphytic changes and coincident declines in two temperate Australian seagrasses  Photorespiration and carbon limitation determine productivity in temperate seagrasses  Non-structural carbohydrate reserves of eelgrass  Zostera marina   Eutrophication offsets increased sea urchin grazing on seagrass caused by ocean warming and acidification  Effects of in situ CO 2  enrichment on the structural and chemical characteristics of the seagrass  Thalassia testudinum   Mechanisms of bicarbonate use influence the photosynthetic carbon dioxide sensitivity of tropical seagrasses  A methodological comparison of photosynthetic oxygen evolution and estimated electron transport rate in tropical  Ulva  (Chlorophyceae) species under different light and inorganic carbon conditions  Photosynthetic utilization of bicarbonate in  Zostera marina  is reduced by inhibitors of mitochondrial ATPase and electron transport  The value of the world's ecosystem services and natural capital  The future of seagrass meadows  Photosynthetic light utilization efficiency, photosystem II heterogeneity, and fluorescence quenching in  Chlamydomonas reinhardtii  during the induction of the CO 2 -concentrating mechanism  Quantitative evaluation of the role of a putative CO 2 -scavenging entity in the cyanobacterial CO 2 -concentrating mechanism  Water quality measurement methods for seagrass habitat  Volcanic carbon dioxide vents show ecosystem effects of ocean acidification  A buffer sensitive inorganic carbon utilisation system in  Zostera marina   Relative effects of grazers and nutrients on seagrasses: a meta-analysis approach  Bicarbonate utilization in seagrass photosynthesis: role of carbonic anhydrase in  Posidonia oceanica  (L) delile and  Cymodocea nodosa  (Ucria) Ascherson  A century of failure for habitat recovery  Restoring coastal plants to improve global carbon storage: reaping what we sow  Photosynthetic inorganic carbon acquisition of  Posidonia australis   New spectrophotometric equations for determining chlorophylls A, B, C1 and C2 in higher plants, algae and natural phytoplankton  Effects of CO 2  enrichment on photosynthesis, growth, and biochemical composition of seagrass  Thalassia hemprichii  (Ehrenb.) Aschers  Pattern and process in southern Western Australian seagrasses  Climate change and ocean acidification effects on seagrasses and marine macroalgae  The interaction between inorganic carbon acquisition and light supply in  Palmaria palmata  (Rhodophyta)  Gaseous movement in seagrasses  Photosynthesis and metabolism in seagrasses at the cellular level  Freshwater angiosperm carbon concentrating mechanisms: processes and patterns  Effects of experimental reduction of light availability on the seagrass  Amphibolis griffithii   Effects of light and temperature on the photosynthesis of temperate meadow-forming seagrasses in Western Australia  Induction of CO 2  and bicarbonate transport in the green alga  Chlorella ellipsoidea : 1. Time course of induction of the two systems  Global climate projections  The effect of pH on the inorganic carbon source for photosynthesis in the seagrass  Zostera muelleri  Irmisch ex Aschers  The effect of temperature on the survival, growth, photosynthesis, and respiration of young seedlings of eelgrass  Zostera marina  L  Effects of sediment burial on tropical ruderal seagrasses are moderated by clonal integration  A global crisis for seagrass ecosystems  Response of eelgrass  Zostera marina  to CO 2  enrichment: possible impacts of climate change and potential for remediation of coastal habitats  Photoinhibition of photosynthesis in natural assemblages of marine phytoplankton  In situ seagrass photosynthesis measured using a submersible, pulse-amplitude modulated fluorometer  Energy costs of carbon acquisition  Algal and aquatic plant carbon concentrating mechanisms in relation to environmental change  Fitting light saturation curves measured using modulated fluorometry  Future seagrass beds: can increased productivity lead to increased carbon storage?  Photosynthetic utilisation of carbon and light by two tropical seagrass species as measured  in situ   Can chlorophyll fluorescence be used to estimate photosynthetic production in the seagrass  Zostera noltii ?  Measuring seagrass photosynthesis: methods and applications  Photosynthesis is required for induction of the CO 2  concentrating system in  Chlamydomonas reinhardii   Photometric, radiometric, and quantum light units of measure: a review of procedures for interconversion  Overview of the physiological ecology of carbon metabolism in seagrasses  Bioturbation as a potential mechanism influencing spatial heterogeneity of North Carolina seagrass beds  An experimental assessment of the temperature responses of two sympatric seagrasses,  Amphibolis antarctica  and  Amphibolis griffithii , in relation to their biogeography  Accelerating loss of seagrasses across the globe threatens coastal ecosystems  Impacts of CO 2  enrichment on productivity and light requirements of eelgrass   Editor:  Lawren Sack  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  We find energetically costly bicarbonate pathways exist in three temperate seagrasses and then provide evidence that indicates greater growth and photosynthetic efficiency for bicarbonate users in a high CO2 world. Greater growth might enhance the future prosperity and rehabilitation of these important habitat forming plants, which have experienced declines of global significance.  Rising atmospheric CO 2  is increasing the availability of dissolved CO 2  in the ocean relative to HCO 3  − . Currently, many marine primary producers use HCO 3  −  for photosynthesis, but this is energetically costly. Increasing passive CO 2  uptake relative to HCO 3  −  pathways could provide energy savings, leading to increased productivity and growth of marine plants. Inorganic carbon-uptake mechanisms in the seagrass  Amphibolis antarctica  were determined using the carbonic anhydrase inhibitor acetazolamide (AZ) and the buffer tris(hydroxymethyl)aminomethane (TRIS).  Amphibolis antarctica  seedlings were also maintained in current and forecasted CO 2  concentrations to measure their physiology and growth. Photosynthesis of  A. antarctica  was significantly reduced by AZ and TRIS, indicating utilization of HCO 3  − -uptake mechanisms. When acclimated plants were switched between CO 2  treatments, the photosynthetic rate was dependent on measurement conditions but not growth conditions, indicating a dynamic response to changes in dissolved CO 2  concentration, rather than lasting effects of acclimation. At forecast CO 2  concentrations, seedlings had a greater maximum electron transport rate (1.4-fold), photosynthesis (2.1-fold), below-ground biomass (1.7-fold) and increase in leaf number (2-fold) relative to plants in the current CO 2  concentration. The greater increase in photosynthesis (measured as O 2  production) compared with the electron transport rate at forecasted CO 2  concentration suggests that photosynthetic efficiency increased, possibly due to a decrease in photorespiration. Thus, it appears that the photosynthesis and growth of seagrasses reliant on energetically costly HCO 3  −  acquisition, such as  A. antarctica , might increase at forecasted CO 2  concentrations. Greater growth might enhance the future prosperity and rehabilitation of these important habitat-forming plants, which have experienced declines of global significance.  Seagrasses are habitat-forming marine plants that provide a number of critical ecological services to coastal zones, such as stabilization of sediments, support of trophic food webs, nutrient cycling and carbon sequestration ( Costanza  et al. , 1997 ;  Duarte, 2002 ;  Waycott  et al. , 2009 ;  Irving  et al. , 2011 ). When angiosperms first entered the aquatic realm nearly 90 million years ago, atmospheric CO 2  levels were much greater (approximately three to seven times) than today ( Beer and Koch, 1996 ;  Beardall  et al. , 1998 ;  Berner and Kothavala, 2001 ). Since that time, atmospheric CO 2  concentrations have generally declined ( Berner and Kothavala, 2001 ), a trend which has resulted in potential carbon limitation for many marine plants. This low atmospheric CO 2  has reduced the availability of inorganic carbon (C i ) for photosynthesis, which is compounded in marine systems by the slow diffusion of CO 2  in seawater and the slow rate of conversion of HCO 3  −  to CO 2  when uncatalysed ( Beer, 1989 ;  Larkum  et al. , 1989 ;  Schwarz  et al. , 2000 ). The recent spike in atmospheric CO 2  linked to anthropogenic activities is changing C i  availability in marine systems and is thus likely to affect carbon acquisition and growth in primary producers, such as seagrasses ( Koch  et al. , 2013 ).  While HCO 3  −  is more readily available than dissolved CO 2  in marine systems, it cannot diffuse passively across the cell plasma membrane, and therefore, extracellular mechanisms have evolved to aid aquatic plants in the acquisition of CO 2  from HCO 3  −  for photosynthesis, thereby reducing C i  limitation ( Larkum,  et al. , 1989 ;  Invers  et al. , 1999 ;  Hellblom  et al. , 2001 ). Three primary extracellular HCO 3  −  acquisition systems have been described for seagrasses ( Beer and Koch, 1996 ;  James and Larkum, 1996 ;  Hellblom  et al. , 2001 ;  Beer  et al. , 2002 ). First, the enzyme carbonic anhydrase (CA) can catalyse the rapid conversion of HCO 3  −  to CO 2  to restore CO 2 /HCO 3  −  equilibrium at the plasma membrane or concentrate CO 2  at the chloroplast level (System A,  sensu   Beer  et al. , 2002 ). Second, the outward pumping of protons (H + ) from cells can create H +  gradients to aid the cotransport of H +  and HCO 3  −  back across the plasma membrane (System B). Finally, the combination of extracellular CA-catalysed dehydration of HCO 3  −  to CO 2  within acidified zones created by the extrusion of H +  across the plasma membrane can concentrate CO 2  and encourage diffusion into cells (System C). For a full review of these mechanisms, see  Beer  et al.  (2002) .  All seagrasses tested to date appear to be reliant, to some extent, on the extracellular activity of CA for carbon acquisition, suggesting that they could experience some degree of carbon limitation at current atmospheric CO 2  concentrations ( Larkum  et al. , 2006 ;  Koch  et al. , 2013 ). Also, there is an energetic cost associated with both the production of extracellular CA and the more active mode of carbon acquisition using H +  extrusion ( Spalding and Ogren, 1982 ;  Raven and Lucas, 1985 ;  Falk and Palmqvist, 1992 ;  Kübler and Raven, 1995 ;  Fridlyand  et al. , 1996 ). As atmospheric, and thus oceanic, CO 2  continues to accumulate, this energetic cost could diminish if reliance on these carbon-acquisition mechanisms decreases, relative to direct CO 2  usage ( Beardall and Giordano, 2002 ;  Raven  et al. , 2011 ;  Koch  et al. , 2013 ). For example, some lower order marine producers (i.e. cyanobacteria and eukaryotic algae) can adjust their HCO 3  − -acquisition strategies within a number of hours of exposure to different CO 2  conditions ( Falk and Palmqvist, 1992 ;  Matsuda and Colman, 1995 ;  Brueggeman  et al. , 2012 ). Seagrasses may have a similar ability to regulate energetically costly C i  acquisition, but our understanding of this has advanced slowly relative to lower order producers (i.e. cyanobacteria and eukaryotic algae) that have shorter generation times and can therefore be manipulated more easily for genetic expression studies ( Larkum,  et al. , 2006 ).  Increasing CO 2  availability and any down-regulation of HCO 3  −  acquisition could result in improved photosynthetic efficiency as the energy required to acquire carbon decreases, which may also translate to greater photosynthetic rates ( Badger and Andrews, 1982 ;  Raven  et al. , 2011 ;  Koch  et al. , 2013 ). Likewise, if CA-mediated HCO 3  −  mechanisms are maintained, they may become more efficient at lower ambient pH levels ( Koch  et al. , 2013 ). However, this potential for more efficient and greater photosynthesis may be accompanied by a net gain in leaf growth or energy storage only when other resources, such as light or nitrogen, are not limiting ( Zimmerman  et al. , 1997 ;  Palacios and Zimmerman, 2007 ;  Alexandre  et al. , 2012 ). In many seagrass species with a heavy reliance on HCO 3  −  for C i  acquisition, it is unknown whether they will undergo subsequent changes in growth as dissolved CO 2  increases.  In the present study, the reliance of  Amphibolis antarctica  (Labill.) Sonder et Ascherson on HCO 3  −  pathways of C i  acquisition was investigated by using an inhibitor of the enzyme CA (i.e. acetazolamide, AZ) and the biological buffer (i.e. tris(hydroxymethyl)aminomethane, TRIS). Having established that  A. antarctica  has a significant reliance on energetically costly HCO 3  −  acquisition, a second experiment was conducted in which juvenile  A. antarctica  were grown in the presence of ambient (∼390 ppm) and forecasted CO 2  concentrations (∼900 ppm). It was hypothesized that photosynthesis and growth would increase for  A. antarctica  when CO 2  was enriched, because the greater availability of CO 2  relative to HCO 3  −  might increase the photosynthetic efficiency of plants, as they may partition relatively fewer resources to energetically costly processes, such as HCO 3  − -uptake mechanisms or photorespiration.  Mature seagrasses were collected from a depth of 4 m at Marino Rocks in the Gulf St Vincent, South Australia (35°02.806 S, 138°30.350 E). Seagrasses were transported to The University of Adelaide and kept in recirculating aerated aquaria with lighting conditions similar to the collection site (∼60 µmol m −2  s −1 ) in a 12 h–12 h light–dark cycle for 1 week, during which time experiments to determine C i -uptake mechanisms took place.  The C i -uptake mechanisms of seagrasses were investigated by inhibiting HCO 3  −  pathways to carbon acquisition. Seagrasses were exposed to the inhibitor AZ or the biological buffer TRIS, either separately or in combination. The primary seagrass of interest was  A. antarctica , but to identify the generality of the mechanism within and across genera, C i -uptake mechanisms were also investigated for two other co-occurring seagrass species, the congener  Amphibolis griffithii  (Black) den Hartog and the species  Posidonia sinuosa  (Cambridge and Kuo), using the same methodology.  Oxygen evolution rates were determined using a Clark-type oxygen electrode and the logging program Biograph (Axword Software, Adelaide, South Australia). An entire leaf of  A. antarctica  (∼20 mm long) that was free of epiphyte growth was placed in the electrode chamber in 4 ml of seawater filtered to 0.45 µm. The fourth or fifth youngest leaf on each leaf head was chosen because these leaves were mature and consistently free of epiphytes and other biota, as well as being the correct length to fit the photosynthetic chamber. The chamber was illuminated using a fibre-optic light, which delivered a photon flux density (PFD) of ∼500 µmol m −2  s −1  at the leaf surface that was sufficient to saturate photosynthesis in  A. antarctica . This light level was chosen to represent peak irradiances previously recorded in  A. antarctica  meadows (A. D. Irving, unpublished data;  Bryars  et al. , 2011 ), but below levels shown to have a photoinhibitory effect on  A. antarctica  and other co-occurring species ( Masini  et al. , 1995 ;  Ralph  et al. , 1998 ). Light between 380 and 710 nm was measured by positioning the fibre quantum sensor of a diving pulse amplitude modulated (PAM) fluorometer (Walz, Effeltrich, Germany) in the electrode chamber. The PAM fluorometer fibre quantum sensor was calibrated against a LI-COR quantum sensor (Li-192SA; Lincoln, NE, USA). The electrode chamber was maintained at a constant temperature of 20°C using a transparent recirculating water jacket and was constantly mixed using a magnetic stirrer.  Seagrass leaves were sealed in the chamber and covered with a black cloth to measure dark respiration. Respiration rates were allowed to stabilize for 3 min before recording. The chamber was then illuminated, and where necessary, the appropriate stock solutions (see below) were injected into the chamber using micro-syringes. Photosynthetic rates were allowed to stabilize for 2 min before recording. Photosynthetic and respiration rates were averaged over 3 min and are expressed on a chlorophyll basis (as micromoles of oxygen per gram of chlorophyll per minute).  Sea water chemistry in the oxygen electrode chamber during buffer/inhibitor experiments ( a ; see Figs  1  and S1), during 12 week growth experiments ( b ; see Figs  2 a and  3 ) and reciprocal switch measurements ( c ; Fig.  2 b)  Abbreviations: AZ, acetazolamide; TRIS, tris(hydroxymethyl)aminomethane. L[CO 2 ] = low CO 2 , H[CO 2 ] = high CO 2 . Measurements of pH, total alkalinity ( A  T ), salinity and temperature (fixed at 20°C during photosynthetic trials) were used to calculate carbonate chemistry. Salinity was fixed at 38‰ during inhibitor experiments.  Juvenile  A. antarctica  seedlings were collected at the same depth and location as described above for adult plants and transported to an outdoor glasshouse at The University of Adelaide. Four individual seedlings were planted in sediment from the collection site in each of 12 transparent 2 litre microcosms (25 cm depth). Seagrasses were maintained at two CO 2  concentrations, representing current atmospheric CO 2  levels (∼390 ppm) and forecasted future CO 2  levels (∼900 ppm) under emission scenario A1FI for the year 2100 ( Meehl  et al. , 2007 ), hereafter referred to as low CO 2  (L[CO 2 ]) and high CO 2  (H[CO 2 ]), respectively. Carbon dioxide was enriched by aerating the microcosms with a combination of ambient air and pure CO 2  using a two-channel gas mixer (Columbus Instruments, Columbus, OH, USA), which is equivalent to maintaining treatments within an enriched CO 2  atmosphere. Aeration helps to accelerate the diffusion of CO 2  into seawater, also minimizing any variation driven by plant photosynthesis or respiration. The accuracy of the mixed gas aerating treatments can vary slightly dependent on ambient atmospheric conditions, but any such changes are minor and occur naturally whenever ambient air is used for aeration; ambient CO 2  treatments are also subject to such natural fluctuations. Experimental conditions, including carbonate chemistry, in experimental microcosms were monitored throughout the experiment (Table  1 b). Seventy per cent of seawater was replaced twice weekly to maintain salinity and alkalinity.  Microcosms were in an outdoor glass house and they were shaded from full surface irradiance using a combination of 50 and 70% shade cloth. HOBO ®  waterproof light loggers (Onset, Wareham, MA, USA) were used to record light in lux, which was then converted to give an approximation of photosynthetically active radiation using the constant for natural sunlight (1 lux = 54 µmol m −2  s −1 ) recommended by  Thimijan and Heins (1983 ). Average daily PFD was 42.5 µmol m −2  s −1  over a 12 h photoperiod, with an average daily maximum of 111.3 ± ’11.7 µmol m −2  s −1  recorded at 13.00 h. Shading was designed to replicate closely the light conditions recorded during a monitoring study on the Adelaide metropolitan coast, which found average daily PFD of ∼44 µmol m −2  s −1  over a 12 h photoperiod ( Irving, 2009 ). One specific 40 day light monitoring deployment at ∼2 m (low tide) on the Adelaide metropolitan coast found average daily maximal PFD of 155.95 ± 20.54 µmol m −2  s −1  (A. D. Irving, unpublished data), which is comparable to the peak levels recorded in our acclimation study. The daily maximum in this monitoring study ranged from 7 to 453 µmol m −2  s −1 , highlighting the dynamic nature of the light climate in the shallow sub-tidal near-shore zone, where the swell direction, wind direction, rainfall, runoff and topography can all influence turbidity and thus light attenuation.  A submersible diving PAM fluorometer (Walz, Effeltrich, Germany) was used to record rapid light curves (RLCs) and maximal quantum yield (QY max ). Seagrasses were measured  in situ  in microcosms at L[CO 2 ] and H[CO 2 ] after 12 weeks. The photon flux densities used during the RLCs were 0, 18, 37, 62, 92, 125, 186, 256 and 400 µmol m −2  s −1 , each of 10 s duration, followed by a saturating pulse of light, to record the effective quantum yield (Φ PSII ). All RLC measurements were taken between 11.00 and 12.30 h. The light absorbance of every sample leaf was measured by placing a quantum sensor directly behind the leaf and recording the percentage of ambient light that was absorbed. The electron transport rate (ETR) was calculated as follows: ETR = Φ PSII  × PFD × leaf absorbance × 0.5. For quantitative comparisons of RLCs [i.e. initial slope (α), maximal electron transport rate (ETR max ) and light saturation ( I  k )], the ETR data were fitted with a least-squares non-linear regression curve based on the exponential difference equation from  Platt  et al.  (1980)  using the Microsoft Excel (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA) solvers provided by  Ritchie (2008) . Light saturation was calculated as ETR max  /α, where α is the initial slope of the non-inhibited section of the fitted curve. The value of QY max  was determined from pre-dawn fluorescence measurements.  Following 12 weeks at experimental CO 2  levels, photosynthesis and respiration rates were measured as described above, but without the addition of buffers and inhibitors. Reciprocal measurements were made, where individuals from each CO 2  treatment were measured at both low and high CO 2 , to determine whether physiological acclimation had occurred over the course of the experiment (see Table  1 c for a description of chamber conditions). Electron transport rates at 400 µmol m −2  s −1  and maximal gross photosynthetic rates were then used to calculate ETR-to-O 2  ratios (i.e. moles of electrons per mole of O 2  evolved). This was done for L[CO 2 ] and H[CO 2 ] plants tested in their respective growth treatments.  Growth parameters were measured after 12 weeks. Leaves and shoots (above ground) were separated from roots and rhizomes (below ground) and dried for 48 h at 60°C to measure dry mass (DM). Above-ground components were then washed in 5% HCl to remove any calcified epiphytes, redried for 48 h at 60°C and reweighed.  Leaf initiation was recorded by trimming the corner of the second youngest leaf on the highest leaf head of each seedling at the commencement of the growth experiment. On juveniles, this method of monitoring leaf growth is less obtrusive than sheath marking or using leaf ties, which can impact meristem growth and plant buoyancy (O. W. Burnell, personal observation). The total number of leaves on each leaf head was recorded before planting and again after 12 weeks to calculate the change in total leaf number, which accounted for different rates of leaf shedding and production from any new meristems.  Chlorophyll content was measured to enable expression of photosynthesis and respiration per unit of chlorophyll. Following oxygen electrode measurements, seagrass material was removed from the chamber, rinsed in milliQ water, and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. Samples were then stored at −80°C until extractions were conducted. Chlorophyll concentrations were determined using the methodology of  Granger and Lizumi (2001) . Briefly, leaves were soaked in 1 ml of 100% acetone in dark, refrigerated conditions for 1 h. Seagrass and acetone were then transferred to a chilled mortar and pestle and ground using an additional 1 ml of 86.7% acetone and acid washed sand until they were reduced to a flocculent slurry. Two drops of 1% MgCO 3  were added before diluting to 4 ml with 86.7% acetone to achieve a final sample concentration of 90% acetone. Samples were then centrifuged for 5 min at 670.8  g  of relative centrifugal force. Absorbance of the supernatant was measured in a spectrophotometer (Jenway 6405, Stone, Staffordshire, UK) at 647, 664 and 725 nm. Chlorophyll concentrations were calculated using equations from  Jeffrey and Humphrey (1975) .  ANOVA for the effects on photosynthesis in  A. antarctica  of buffer/inhibitor ( a ; in seawater/control, TRIS, AZ and TRIS + AZ; see Fig.  1 ) and reciprocal switch ( b ; i.e. plants were grown at either L[CO 2 ] or H[CO 2 ] and then measured at both L[CO 2 ] and H[CO 2 ]; see Fig.  2 b)  Abbreviations: d.f., degrees of freedom;  F , f-statistic; MSE, mean squared error. No significant differences were found between respiration rates; therefore, analyses are not presented.  The effects of inhibitors [tris(hydroxymethyl)aminomethane (TRIS), acetazolamide (AZ) and TRIS + AZ] on rates of photosynthesis and respiration in  Amphibolis antarctica  measured in seawater. Bars are means ± SEM ( n  = 8).  ( a ) Rapid light curves of electron transport rate for  A. antarctica  grown and measured at 390 (L[CO 2 ]) or 900 ppm (H[CO 2 ]). Filled circles indicate L[CO 2 ] and filled triangles H[CO 2 ]. Data points are means ± SEM ( n  = 6). ( b ) Rates of photosynthesis and respiration in  A. antarctica  measured at either low (shaded bars) or high CO 2  (open bars) and grown at either low (G L[CO 2 ]) or high CO 2  (G H[CO 2 ]). Bars are means ± SEM ( n  = 5).  When plants were reciprocally switched between CO 2  treatments, measurement CO 2  had a significant effect on photosynthesis of both L[CO 2 ] and H[CO 2 ] grown plants (Fig.  2 b and Table  2 b). In contrast, there was no effect of growth CO 2 ; that is, seagrasses photosynthesis was responding primarily to measurement conditions (i.e. dissolved CO 2 ), rather than exhibiting significant physiological acclimation to growth in the different CO 2  treatments. Molar ratios between ETR and gross oxygen evolution based on leaf area were 9.51 mol electrons (mol O 2 ) −1  for L[CO 2 ] plants and 8.08 mol electrons (mol O 2 ) −1  for H[CO 2 ] plants.  Effect of growth [CO 2 ] on total dry mass (DM;  a ), above-ground DM ( b ), below-ground DM ( c ), leaf initiation ( d ) and change in leaves per plant ( e ) for  A. antarctica  grown in L[CO 2 ] and H[CO 2 ] conditions for 12 weeks. Bars are means ± SEM ( n  = 6).  Correlations between below-ground biomass (expressed as DM per seagrass) and above-ground growth parameters (expressed as DM biomass per seagrass, leaf initiation per meristem and change in leaves per seagrass) for  A. antarctica . Data points are the average in each microcosm ( n  = 6).  The three seagrass species tested were sensitive to the inhibition of HCO 3  − -uptake mechanisms, indicating that at or under contemporary CO 2  concentrations they are reliant on energetically costly C i  acquisition. Seagrasses are commonly known to use these HCO 3  −  pathways for photosynthesis ( Beer  et al. , 1977 ;  Millhouse and Strother, 1986 ;  James and Larkum, 1996 ;  Beardall,  et al. , 1998 ;  Hellblom  et al. , 2001 ); however, we have a limited understanding of how they regulate these mechanisms when faced with environmental variation ( Larkum,  et al. , 2006 ) and any implications of this for long-term growth. Any increase in the proportion of direct CO 2  uptake relative to energetically costly HCO 3  −  acquisition could benefit their carbon balance and thus growth rate ( Beardall and Giordano, 2002 ;  Raven  et al. , 2011 ;  Koch  et al. , 2013 ). In accordance with such predictions, we found that increased photosynthesis and growth of  A. antarctica  was accompanied by lower ETR-to-O 2  ratios, indicating that not only growth but also photosynthetic efficiency could increase at forecasted CO 2  concentrations.  Greater availability of CO 2  increased the ETR max  in  A. antarctica , as has been reported in other seagrass species ( Jiang  et al. , 2010 ;  Alexandre  et al ., 2012 ). However, changes in ETR at forecasted CO 2  concentrations were small relative to increases in light-saturated photosynthesis measured by O 2  evolution (i.e. 1.4-fold for ETR vs. 2.1-fold for O 2  evolution). This difference translated to lower ETR-to-O 2  ratios calculated for H[CO 2 ] plants when compared with L[CO 2 ] plants (i.e. 8.08 vs. 9.51 mol electrons (mol O 2 ) −1 , respectively). This molar ratio is also commonly referred to in its inverse form, which would equate to 0.105 and 0.124 mol O 2  (mol electrons) −1  for L[CO 2 ] and H[CO 2 ] plants, respectively. While these values differ from the theoretical maximum of 0.25 mol O 2  (mol electrons) –1  that is based on the minimal number of electrons needed to produce a given amount of O 2  during photosynthesis (i.e. 4 mol electrons (mol O 2 ) −1 ;  Walker, 1987 ), recorded values for different seagrass species are known to vary widely ( Beer  et al. , 1998 ;  Silva  et al. , 2009 ). Given that ETR-to-O 2  ratios were measured at relatively high light intensities, it is likely that processes such as photorespiration contributed to these high ETR-to-O 2  ratios. Photorespiration increases in conditions of low C i  availability, where plants fix O 2  rather than CO 2  ( Black  et al . 1976 ;  Buapet  et al . 2013 ). It is well known that the usually linear relationship between ETR and O 2  evolution can deteriorate at high light intensities, at which photorespiration or other processes that can act as sinks for electrons increase ( Beer  et al. , 1998 ;  Carr and Bjork, 2003 ;  Silva and Santos 2004 ).  Photorespiration may also have contributed to the treatment differences that we observed between ETR-to-O 2  ratios for L[CO 2 ] and H[CO 2 ] plants. Importantly, the finding that L[CO 2 ] plants transported more electrons per mole of O 2  evolved than H[CO 2 ] plants could indicate greater photorespiration where plants were CO 2  limited. In such circumstances, photorespiration is likely to have acted as a greater sink for electrons measured using fluorescence in L[CO 2 ] plants. Thus, O 2  evolution measurements may provide a better estimate of changing photosynthetic efficiency than ETR at higher irradiances, because photorespiration in CO 2 -limited individuals remains undetected by fluorescence measurements. However, photorespiration is generally low in seagrasses with effective carbon concentrating mechanisms that maintain high concentrations of CO 2  around rubisco ( Beer, 1989 ;  Touchette and Burkholder, 2000 ). It is also possible that greater ETR-to-O 2  ratios at low CO 2  might be consistent with a greater proportion of electron flow supporting C i -uptake mechanisms. However, this may be of greater consequence at lower irradiances, where plants are forced to partition limited energetic resources between photosynthesis and CO 2  acquisition.  Despite greater photosynthesis and growth at forecasted CO 2  concentrations, there was limited evidence to suggest any down-regulation of HCO 3  − -uptake mechanisms in  A. antarctica  grown at H[CO 2 ], because when seagrasses were switched to L[CO 2 ] to measure photosynthesis, there was no effect of CO 2  growth conditions. This suggests that, on transition to a different CO 2  concentration, the photosynthetic rate was determined by changing dissolved CO 2 , rather than by different affinities for HCO 3  −  acquired during the 3 month growth period. If H[CO 2 ]-grown plants were no longer able to acquire CO 2  from HCO 3  − , much lower O 2  production would have been expected when they were switched back to L[CO 2 ]. Shorter-term studies have likewise found that the relative level of HCO 3  −  uptake by seagrass is often maintained across pH gradients ( James and Larkum, 1996 ;  Campbell and Fourqurean, 2013b ). Thus, it appears that changes in growth and photosynthesis may have occurred based primarily on greater passive uptake of CO 2 , not on down-regulation of HCO 3  − -uptake mechanisms. Alternatively, down-regulation may have been masked if plants rapidly modified HCO 3  − -acquisition rates during the brief reciprocal CO 2  transitions, although this appears unlikely. While rapid re-establishment (2–5 min) of HCO 3  −  acquisition can occur following dark-to-light transitions ( Carr and Axelsson, 2008 ), the time for activation and deactivation for HCO 3  −  mechanisms with CO 2  transitions would appear to be much greater. Studies of lower order producers (i.e. cyanobacteria and eukaryotic algae) and freshwater angiosperms show hours to days for full re-activation and down-regulation following CO 2  transitions ( Spalding and Ogren, 1982 ;  Falk and Palmqvist, 1992 ;  Matsuda and Colman, 1995 ;  Maberly and Madsen, 2002 ).  The greater increase in below-ground biomass at H[CO 2 ] suggests that  A. antarctica  may preferentially allocate resources to roots and rhizomes for growth and energy storage. These findings are consistent with studies of natural and  in situ  CO 2  enrichment that indicate disproportionate accumulation of below-ground biomass in other seagrasses, relative to above-ground tissue ( Hall-Spencer  et al. , 2008 ;  Russell  et al. , 2013 ;  Campbell and Fourqurean, 2013a ). However, the significant correlation between below-ground biomass and the three above-ground growth parameters could suggest that the former simply responds more rapidly to CO 2  enrichment, and this could later translate to changes in above-ground parameters. This translation to greater above-ground biomass would appear possible given that seagrass at H[CO 2 ] also showed a greater increase in leaf number; nonetheless, with potentially greater carbon fixation per leaf area at enriched CO 2  levels, there may be limited need for large increases in above-ground biomass.  The increase in below-ground biomass could offer seagrasses greater resistance to environmental perturbations in an era when anthropogenic influences have been reported to be almost exclusively negative ( Orth  et al. , 2006 ). Greater below-ground energetic resources could sustain juveniles during periods of physiological stress, including reduced light availability ( Burke  et al. , 1996 ;  Mackey  et al. , 2007 ;  Ooi  et al. , 2011 ), high temperature ( Walker and Cambridge, 1995 ;  Niu  et al. , 2012 ;  Koch  et al ., 2013 ) and grazing pressure ( Hughes  et al. , 2004 ). Preferential allocation to below-ground resources that are protected from herbivores might be particularly beneficial given that enriched CO 2  conditions can result in seagrass that is more palatable to grazers owing to a reduction of phenolic deterrents ( Arnold  et al. , 2012 ). Likewise, faster establishment of below-ground structures could lower the vulnerability of seagrass to physical disturbances, such as wave action and bio-turbation/erosion ( Townsend and Fonseca, 1998 ;  Bastyan and Cambridge, 2008 ). An increase in recruitment success resulting from reproduction could be particularly beneficial, given that most seagrasses are heavily reliant on clonal growth for meadow expansion, with low rates of seed or seedling survival and natural recolonization ( Kirkman and Kuo, 1990 ;  Irving, 2013 ). Any prolonged increase in seagrass growth, however, will require other favourable conditions, such as adequate light, nutrients and facilitative interactions with other biota (i.e. grazer activity and epiphyte abundance), all of which are known to limit seagrass biomass where CO 2  is enriched (O. W. Burnell, unpublished data;  Palacios and Zimmerman, 2007 ;  Alexandre,  et al. , 2012 ;  Burnell  et al. , 2013 ).  As historically high CO 2  levels potentially aided the initial transition of angiosperms into the aquatic realm ( Beer and Koch, 1996 ;  Beardall,  et al. , 1998 ), forecasted increases in CO 2  could return such benefits, by increasing the availability of dissolved CO 2 . We found that  A. antarctica  has a contemporary reliance on HCO 3  − -uptake mechanisms, as well as greater photosynthesis and growth with prolonged acclimation to forecasted CO 2  conditions. Importantly, any lasting increase in productivity and growth could enhance the host of ecosystem benefits provided by seagrass meadows.   Supplementary material is available at  Conservation Physiology  online .  S.D.C. and B.D.R. were funded by an ARC grant and S.D.C. by an ARC Future Fellowship.  We would like to thank members of the Plant Ecophysiology Laboratory at The University of Adelaide for welcoming us into their laboratory, as well as Julie Francis for assistance with oxygen electrodes. 