 Pollinator limitation on reproductive success in  Iris tuberosa   Short- and long-term limitations to fruit production in a tropical orchid  Expanding the limits of the pollen-limitation concept: effects of pollen quantity and quality  Patterns of genetic and phenotypic variation in  Iris haynei  and  I. atrofusca  ( Iris  sect.  Onocyclus  = the royal irises) along an ecogeographical gradient in Israel and the West Bank  Sull'  Hermodactylus tuberosus   Understanding the basis of pollinator selectivity in sexually dimorphic  Fragaria virginiana   Pollen limitation of plant reproduction: ecological and evolutionary causes and consequences  Pollinator limitation of plant reproductive effort  Pollen limitation and pollinator preferences in  Scorzonera hispanica   Effects of flower size and number on pollinator visitation to wild radish,  Raphanus raphanistrum   Variation in fruit set within and among natural populations of the self-incompatible herb  Centaurea scabiosa  (Asteraceae)  Floral symmetry is associated with flower size and pollen production but not insect visitation rates in  Geranium robertianum  (Geraniaceae)  Pollen limitation in the alpine: a meta-analysis  Pollinator responses to variation in floral display and flower size in dioecious  Sagittaria latifolia  (Alismataceae)  Phylogeny and classification of Iridaceae  Radiation of pollination systems in the Iridaceae of sub-Saharan Africa  Changes in pollinator fauna cause spatial variation in pollen limitation  Pollen–pistil interactions in  Hermodactylus tuberosus  Mill. (Iridaceae)   Hermodactylus tuberosus  L. (Iridaceae) pollen organization before and after anther dehiscence  On limits to seed production  Floral adaptation and diversification under pollen limitation  Reproductive biology and colour polymorphism in the food-deceptive  Iris lutescens  (Iridaceae)  Implications of geitonogamous pollination for floral longevity in  Iris gracilipes   Mechanisms and evolution of deceptive pollination in orchids  The effect of petal-size manipulation on pollen removal, seed set, and insect-visitor behavior in  Campanula americana   Effect of flower number on the pollinator attractiveness and the threshold plant size for flowering in  Pertya triloba  (Asteraceae)  Taxonomical revision of genus  Iris  L. (Iridaceae Juss.) in the flora of Central Asia  Effects of plant size, plant density and sex differential nectar reward on pollinator visitation in the pretandrous  Echium vulgare  (Boraginaceae)  Pollen limitation of plant reproduction: ecological and evolutionary causes and consequences  Are pollinators the agents of selection for the extreme large size and dark color in  Oncocyclus  irises?  Self-fertilization and cross-fertilization in plants. 1. Functional dimensions  Pollinator limitation in a deceptive orchid,  Pogonia japonica , on a floating peat mat  Consequences of plant population size and density for plant–pollinator interactions and plant performance  Effects of variation in flower number on pollinator visits in  Cirsium purpuratum  (Asteraceae)  Reproductive biology and pollination limitation of  Serapias vomeracea  (Burm.) Briq. (Orchidaceae)  Double floral mimicry and the magnet species effect in dimorphic co-flowering species, the deceptive orchid  Dactylorhiza sambucina  and rewarding  Viola aethnensis   Pollen quantity and quality affect fruit abortion in small populations of a rare fleshy-fruited shrub  The effects of floral display size on pollinator service to individual flowers of  Myosotis  and  Mimulus   Visitation, effectiveness, and efficiency of 15 genera of visitors to wild radish,  Raphanus raphanistrum  (Brassicaceae)  Pollinator-mediated selection on floral display and flowering time in the perennial herb  Arabidopsis lyrata   Morning floral heat as a reward to the pollinators of the  Oncocyclus  irises  Fragmentation and pollination crisis in the self-incompatible  Iris bismarkiani  (Iridaceae), with implications for conservation  The noncentral chi-squared distribution with zero degrees of freedom and testing for uniformity  The endangered  Iris atropurpurea  (Iridaceae) in Israel: honey-bees, night-sheltering male bees and female solitary bees as pollinators  Pollinator limitation, autogamy and minimal inbreeding depression in insect-pollinated plants on a boreal island  Floral stages, ovule development, and ovule and fruit success in  Iris tenax , focusing on var. gormanii, a taxon with low seed set  Relationships between floral morphology and pollinator fauna in insular and main island populations of  Hosta longipes  (Liliaceae)   Associate Editor:  James F. Cahill  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  In this paper I measured the effect of varying pollinator visits on fruit production in order to understand pollination strategy in  Iris tuberosa , and assessed the effects of plant and floral display size on pollination to understand how these factors influence reproductive success. This study found that  I. tuberosa  were pollinated exclusively by hymenopteran species, mainly during sunny days, and that plant and floral size did not affect fruit set and pollinator attraction. Thus, the sexual reproduction of  I. tuberosa  is fairly limited by pollinators and not by resource limitation.  Variation in plant and floral size can have conflicting effects on pollination and fruit production in flowering plants. This research examines the contributions of plant height, flower size and pollinator visitation to reproductive success in four populations of  Iris tuberosa . The plants were pollinated exclusively by hymenopteran species, primarily during sunny days. Pollination supplementation increased the proportion of flowers that matured into fruit, with 95 % fruit set for hand-pollinated compared with 74.15 % for naturally pollinated flowers. The pollinator visitation rate and the proportion of fruit produced were not significantly different between tall and short plants or between small and large flowers. Furthermore, the increase in plant size and floral display did not increase the frequency of pollinator visitations and so did not increase the fruit set. Thus, despite the widespread effects of flowering plant size on pollinator attraction and plant reproduction in other species, these effects are lacking in  I. tuberosa . This study quantifies the role of pollinators in the reproductive success of  I. tuberosa . Pollinators visited tall/short plants and large/small flowers in equal proportion, suggesting that plant and floral display size do not affect pollinator attraction and reproductive success in  I. tuberosa . These results suggest that sexual reproduction of  I. tuberosa  is fairly limited by pollinators and not by resource limitation.  Plants should invest in flower production until visitation yields the amount of pollen necessary to produce the maximum number of seeds that resources can support ( Haig and Westoby 1988 ), and thus plants would be simultaneously limited by resources and by pollen. The frequency and potential consequences of pollen limitation for plant populations and communities have been intensely explored during the last few decades ( Ashman  et al.  2004 ;  García-Camacho and Totland 2009 ;  Gómez  et al.  2010 ;  Harder and Aizen 2010 ). Pollinator limitation of female reproduction occurs when an inadequate supply of pollen limits fruit set below the level possible given the plant's available resources. A decrease in pollinator frequency (i.e. number of visits) is likely to decrease the quantity of pollen deposited onto the stigma ( Ashman  et al.  2004 ), reducing fruit and seed set ( Bierzychedek 1981 ;  Matsui  et al.  2001 ;  Pellegrino  et al.  2005 ;  Aizen and Harder 2007 ). Moreover, the plant's ability to attract the pollinators by means of flowers can be a crucial component of fitness. Indeed, studies have generally found a significant relationship between the response of pollinators and increasing plant and flower size ( Conner and Rush 1996 ;  Ohashi and Yahara 1998 ;  Ashman  et al.  2000 ;  Glaettli  et al.  2008 ). In fact, limitation of fruit and seed production by insufficient pollinator visitation is common and ubiquitous across angiosperms ( Ashman  et al.  2004 ;  Knight  et al.  2005 ).  Although the family Iridaceae is a well-defined assemblage of ∼1800 species belonging to the Liliidae, little information is available on the role of pollinators in their reproductive success. The derived features of Iridaceae include two morphological characters, a unifacial isobilateral leaf and the presence of only three stamens ( Goldblatt 1990 ). Except for the Tasmanian genus  Isophysis , the flowers of Iridaceae also have an inferior ovary, and both septal and perigonal nectaries ( Goldblatt 1990 ). The majority of species of Iridaceae are pollinated by Hymenoptera (mostly bees). It is now evident that pollination systems are predominantly specialist; plants rely on a single species or a few ecologically analogous species for pollination ( Goldblatt and Manning 2006 ). Attractants are primarily perianth pigmentation, complemented by a range of floral odours in many species, but flower shape and tepal orientation, in particular functional floral symmetry, may be equally important for some pollinators.   Iris , the largest genus of the Iridaceae with ∼250 species ( Mathew 1981 ), extends across the Earth's North Temperate Zone to North America, and in Europe and Asia ( Khassanov and Rakhimova 2012 ). Early studies on pollination in  Iris  showed that the species were visited by bumblebees ( Segal  et al.  2006 ;  Imbert  et al.  2014 ). Each outer tepal and its opposed petaloid style crests function as a bilabiate pollination unit, and thus to a bee appear as a single gullet flower. A pollinator visiting the flower in search of nectar alights on the lower lip (outer tepal limb) and pushes its head and mouthparts into the gullet (the space between the tepal claw and style branch). In doing so its upper thorax passively brushes against the anther, becoming dusted with pollen. Visiting another flower, its thorax will brush against the stigmatic lobe transferring any pollen onto the receptive tissue.  Iris tuberosa  (subfamily Iridoideae) has received very little attention. It has a characteristic floral morphology: every flower has three units, each containing one stamen and a stigma enclosed by a petaloid style and a sepal. To date, no information is available on the pollination strategy of  I. tuberosa ; however, the plant needs an appropriate pollinator visiting the flower to gather the nectar located at the base of tepals, as observed by  Arcangeli (1895) , who identified the hymenopterous  Xylocopa violacea  as a pollinator of  Hermodactylus tuberosus  (synonym of  I. tuberosa ). In  I. tuberosa , self-pollination is very difficult due to the location of the anthers under stigma lobes.  In this paper, I measured the effect of varying pollinator visits on fruit production in order to understand the pollination strategy in  I. tuberosa , and assessed the effects of plant and floral display size on pollination to understand how these factors influence reproductive success. The aims of this research were to: (i) determine the pollinators and the fruit production under natural conditions, (ii) evaluate the influence of pollinators on reproductive success, (iii) test if plant and floral size affect pollinator attraction and fruit set and (iv) define the breeding system of  I. tuberosa .  Location of four populations: Cassano (1), Corato (2), Acquarola (3) and Lucignano (4) of  I. tuberosa  in central-southern Italy.  To test the effects of plant size on pollinator attraction and fruit set, at the peak of the blooming season (March–April) I measured phenotypic traits of 20 plants in each site. Plant height (the distance from the ground to the top of the flower) was measured using a ruler. Flowers were photographed under a binocular microscope with a digital camera. The length and width of the outer brownish tepals (platform for pollinators) were measured from these images using the program Analysis (Soft Imaging Systems, Münster, Germany). For each population, plants were divided into two groups as ‘tall’ and ‘short’ plants, which were taller or shorter than the mean height, respectively.  Insect visitation was recorded during the peak flowering season, from 2 March to 16 April 2012 and from 6 March to 21 April 2013, for a total of 80 h for sites in each year. Sampling of flower-visiting insects was restricted to 7–8 days at each location in order to minimize any negative impact on the local insect fauna and to minimize negative effects on the fruit set. The sites were intermittently visited during the daytime (daily between 0800 and 1800 h). Pollinators found on  I. tuberosa  flowers were captured with a hand net and checked for pollen. A visitor was considered a pollinator if the insect touched either the anther or the stigma of the flower and had  Iris  pollen on its body. The insects were then put down with ethyl acetate and stored individually for later identification. The species for each specimen was then identified using the taxonomic keys from  Schmid-Egger and Scheuchl (1997) , and the voucher specimens deposited in the Laboratory of Plant Biosystems of DiBEST of University of Calabria.  As unmanipulated open-pollinator controls, 15–20 smaller than average plants and the same number of larger plants were left unbagged to pollinators in each site, each year. At the end of the flowering period (April–May), the flowers that produced fruits were recorded and reproductive success was calculated as the ratio between the number of fruits produced and the number of available flowers.  Hand-pollination treatments to determinate the breeding system of  I. tuberosa  were performed from 20 March to 10 April 2012 and from 16 March to 10 April 2013. In each population, ∼30 plants were bagged with a fine-meshed cloth to exclude pollinators. For hand pollination, the cover was removed, flowers were pollinated, marked with cotton thread and the cover replaced. Each flower was randomly assigned to one of four hand-pollination treatments: (i) covered but without manipulation to test for spontaneous autogamy, (ii) emasculated to test for agamospermy, (iii) artificially self-pollinated and (iv) outcrossed or by induced xenogamy. For self-pollination, the pollen was transferred using a cotton stick from the same flower (induced autogamy). For outcrossing, pollen was transferred with a cotton stick from a flower to the stigma of another flower, previously emasculated and located at a distance of at least 10 m. In May, the number of capsules was counted and the ratio between the number of flowers treated/fruit produced was determined for each hand-pollination treatment.  Standard descriptive statistics and one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) were performed for each quantitative parameter for morphological data. Morphological data were normally distributed and thus were not transformed. When the  F  test was significant, means were compared using the Tukey test at 5 % error probability. The effects of plant and floral size on measures of reproductive success (number of produced fruits) and the attraction of pollinators were compared with a  χ  2  test ( Siegel 1979 ). The statistical program package SPSS (version 10, SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) was used. I calculated self-compatibility indices (SCI) following  Lloyd and Schoen (1992) : SCI = fruit set after hand selfing/fruit set after hand outcrossing.  Self-compatibility index ranges from 0 to 1, with 1 representing full self-compatibility.  This index compares the difference between the fruit set following supplementary hand pollination and the fruit set following natural pollination, divided by the former, and represents the potential for fruit production when pollination is not limited. Pollen limitation index values above zero indicate pollen limitation.  Summary of plant and floral size, and comparison of fruit set between ‘tall’ plants (taller than local mean height) and ‘short’ plants (shorter than local mean height) of four  I. tuberosa  populations. Data are presented as means ± standard deviation.  Number of pollinators in four populations (blue scale bars, Cassano; red scale bars, Corato; green scale bars, Acquarola; yellow scale bars, Lucignano) of  I. tuberosa  divided into time intervals (ns: not significant; *** P  &lt; 0.001).  Pollinator species in four populations (blue scale bars, Cassano; red scale bars, Corato; green scale bars, Acquarola; yellow scale bars = Lucignano) and total (black scale bars) of  I. tuberosa  (ns: not significant; *** P  &lt; 0.001).  Fruit set after hand selfing and hand outcrossing, SCI and PLI of four  I. tuberosa  populations.  Fruit set in four populations of  I. tuberosa  and mean value for hand-pollination treatments: artificial selfing (red scale bars), outcrossing (green scale bars) and natural open-pollinated (blue scale bars). Spontaneous autogamy and agamospermy are not represented in the figure because the fruit set was 0 % in all populations (ns: not significant; *** P  &lt; 0.001).  This study showed that  I. tuberosa  were pollinated exclusively by hymenopteran species, mainly during sunny days, and that plant and floral size did not affect fruit set and pollinator attraction.  Field observations revealed that hymenopteran insects belonging to  Andrena ,  Anthophora ,  Colletes ,  Lasioglossum  and  Xylocopa  were common pollinators of  I. tuberosa.  During morning observations on rainy or windy days, I did not observe any insects within flowers, excluding pollination by sheltering as suggested in  Iris atropurpurea  ( Watts  et al.  2013 ). These data are consistent with previous studies, indeed  Xylocopa violacea  was identified as a pollinator of  I. tuberosa  ( Arcangeli 1895 ), and small ( Apis  sp.) and large ( Bombus  sp. and  Xylocopa  sp.) apoids, such as solitary bees ( Anthophora  sp. and  Eucera  sp.), were the most common pollinators of other Mediterranean  Iris  species ( Sapir  et al.  2006 ;  Segal  et al.  2006 ;  Imbert  et al.  2014 ).  Hand pollinations and field observations indicated that capsules were produced only from open or hand, cross-pollinated flowers, while fruit set did not occur by apomictic processes, in which stigmas of emasculated flowers were covered to avoid pollen contamination. Moreover, the low number of capsules produced by hand self-pollination, as well as low values of self-compatibility index, suggests that  I. tuberosa  is rather self-incompatible. Other Mediterranean  Iris  species are largely self-incompatible ( Arafeh  et al.  2002 ;  Sapir  et al.  2006 ;  Imbert  et al.  2014 ), while selfing rates in other  Iris  species range from 21.4 to 74.1 % ( Wilson 2001 ;  Wheelwright  et al.  2006 ;  Imbert  et al.  2014 ). In  I. tuberosa , self-incompatibility is expressed within the ovary where ovarian grooves have enlarged epidermal cells that produce a floccular secretion that evidently provides discriminatory activity to incoming pollen tubes. In some cases, an indication of post- as well as prezygotic self-incompatibility is expressed within the ovule where embryos abort early in their development ( Grilli Caiola and Brandizzi 1997 ).  The lower values of natural fruit set compared with supplementary artificial pollination treatments in all populations, the low selfing rates and the high values of PLI emphasize the dependence of  I. tuberosa  on insect pollination for its reproductive success. Hand pollination produced more fruits than naturally pollinated plants, and thus, sexual reproduction in  I. tuberosa  is essentially limited by pollinators, not by energy resource availability. This was unexpected, since this plant species is pollinated by many different species of insects, while it is widely assumed that specialized plants will be more prone to experiencing pollen limitation than generalized plants ( Knight  et al.  2005 ). These results contradict other studies ( Ehlers 1999 ;  Červenková and Münzbergová 2013 ) but, on the contrary, are in agreement with many studies using similar experimental methods to detect pollen limitation in Rosaceae and Brassicaceae ( Pflugshaupt  et al.  2002 ;  Sandring and Agren 2009 ). Moreover, these results confirm that pollen limitation is more common in self-incompatible species than in species that are self-compatible ( Mustajarvi  et al.  2001 ).  Wheelwright  et al.  (2006)  found pollinator limitation to be common in  Iris versicolor  in which fruit set was increased compared with open-pollinated controls. I was also unable to assess pollinator limitation over the course of a plant's entire lifetime. Some species may appear pollinator limited in one reproductive season while effectively being resource limited over the course of several seasons ( Ackerman and Montalvo 1990 ).  Numerous studies have shown that an increase in plant size and floral size makes the plant more attractive, increasing the frequency of pollinator visitations ( Sahli and Conner 2007 ;  Frey and Bukoski 2014 ;  Yamada and Masayuki 2014 ) and leading to an increase in fruit set ( Johnson  et al.  1995 ;  Kawarasaki and Hori 1999 ). In many plant species, there is a positive correlation between the degree of pollinator attractiveness and the display size of plants ( Klinkhamer and De Jong 1990 ;  Kawarasaki and Hori 1999 ;  Sahli and Conner 2007 ). Contrary to this expectation, I found no evidence for pollinator-mediated selection based on plant and floral size. Indeed, little difference in the number of captured insects was found between ‘tall’ and ‘short’ plants, and I found that fruit set was not correlated with plants having different display sizes. These findings suggested that display size did not seem to influence pollination success of  I. tuberosa . Similar results were shown for  Iris haynei , while in populations of  I. atropurpurea  and  I. gracilipes  the selection noted on floral size suggested an advantage for larger flowers and taller plants in attracting pollinators ( Ishii and Sakai 2001 ;  Lavi and Sapir 2015 ). In particular  Ishii and Sakai (2001)  showed that the number of pollinator visits per plant increased with display size, while the number of pollinator visits per flower did not increase. Their findings suggest that a larger display size promotes successive visits within the plant, but does not increase pollinator visits to individual flowers. Moreover, this relationship between plant size and pollinator visitations was not constant across years and populations ( Lavi and Sapir 2015 ), suggesting that different factors may obscure this selection. For example,  Robertson and Macnair (1995)  suggested that when plant density is relatively high, pollinators visit flowers on the plants in the population at an equal rate, irrespective of display size. In addition, the extreme floral size of  I. atropurpurea  (floral diameter &gt;64 mm and floral length &gt;78 mm) relative to the smaller floral size of  I. tuberosa  could explain the presence of pollinator-mediated selection only in  I. atropurpurea.  Plants such as  I. atropurpurea  with larger floral displays and growing in patches contain up to hundreds of flowers that attract pollinators from greater distances, while the presence of a single flower and isolated plants ( I. tuberosa ) discourage pollinator visitation, limiting any increase in female reproductive success that would otherwise occur in a multi-flowered species ( Jersáková  et al.  2006 ).  This study quantifies the role of pollinators on reproductive success in  I. tuberosa . Pollinators visited tall/short plants and large/small flowers in equal proportion, thus suggesting that plant and floral display size do not affect pollinator behaviour and reproductive success in this species. I hypothesize that additional selection factors can act on floral traits to explain the lack of pollinator-mediated selection based on floral size. Further studies are needed to verify the relative importance of pollinator limitation. For example, the surrounding vegetation context (i.e. the presence of rewarding co-flowering species which could have either negatively, through competition for pollinators, or positively by means of a magnet species effect and floral mimicry,  Pellegrino  et al.  2008 ) or different pollination strategies (i.e. the scent production or night-sheltering that can help to attract pollinators) are important, relatively understudied components that should be considered to understand the evolution and functional significance of floral traits.  This research was made possible, in part, through a grant from the  Italian Ministry of Education, University and Research  (ex MURST 60 %).  None declared.  The author thanks A. Musacchio for helpful discussion on an earlier version of the manuscript and two anonymous reviewers for their important suggestions. 