Genome downsizing and karyotype constancy in diploid and polyploid congeners: a model of genome size variationOn least squares and linear combinations of observationsThe chromosomes of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, <italic>Amaryllis</italic> and <italic>Phycella</italic> (Amaryllidaceae)Cytogenetica de angiospermas coletadas em PernambucoNuclear DNA amounts in angiospermsMechanisms of recent genome size variation in flowering plantsThe chromosomes of the Liliaceae II. Polyploidy and karyotype variation in the AloineaeEvolution in a stable chromosome systemChromosomal relationships between the genera <italic>Amaryllis</italic> and <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> (Amaryllidaceae)Genome size variation in the Aloaceae, an angiosperm family displaying karyotypic orthoselectionAllopolyploidy a shaping force in the evolution of wheat genomesThe plant nucleus at war and peace: genome organization in the interphase nucleusThe evolution of nuclear genome structure in seed plantsCytotaxonomical studies in eight genera of AmaryllidaceaeGenome downsizing in polyploid plantsGenome size diversity and evolution in land plantsPhylogenetic analysis of DNA C-value provides evidence for a small ancestral genome size in flowering plantsNomenclature for centromeric position on chromosomesTiming and rate of genome variation in <italic>Triticale</italic> following allopolyploidizationPhylogeny of the American Amaryllidaceae based on nrDNA ITS sequencesCariotipo de nueve especies argentinas de <italic>Rhodophiala</italic>, <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, <italic>Zephyrantes</italic>, <italic>Habranthus</italic> (Amaryllidaceae)El cariotipo fundamental del género <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> Herb. (Amaryllidaceae)A comparison of karyotype, Ag-NOR bands and DNA contents in <italic>Amaryllis</italic> and <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> (Amaryllidaceae)Karyotype, DNA content and meiotic behaviour in five South American species of <italic>Vicia</italic> (Fabaceae)Karyotype analysis of four <italic>Vicia</italic> species using <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization with repetitive sequencesNumeros de cromossomos dos genero <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> HerbQuantitative DNA variation between and within chromosome complements of <italic>Vigna</italic> species (Fabaceae)Karyotype asymmetry: again, how to measure and what to measure?Chromosome diversity and evolution in LiliaceaeNuclear DNA variation in diploid and polyploid taxa of <italic>Larrea</italic> (Zygophyllaceae)Chromosome studies in <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> (Amaryllidaceae): variation in genome sizeA new method for estimating karyotype asymmetryKaryotype alteration and phylogeny. IV. Karyotypes in Amaryllidaceae with special reference to the SAT-chromosomeAdvances in the study of polyploidy since plant speciationEvolutionary DNA variation in <italic>Papaver</italic>Cytogenetic studiesin genus <italic>Zea</italic> 3. DNA content and heterochromatin in species and hybridsOn chromosome uniformity, bimodality and evolution in the tribe Aloineae (Asphodelaceae)Karyotype diversity and evolutionary trends in angiospermsThe karyotype analysis of <italic>Hippeastrum rutilum</italic>Associate Editor: Kermit RitlandThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.In several genus evolutionary chromosome change involves variation in DNA amount in diploids and genome downsizing in polyploids. The constancy of bimodal karyotypes, even with changes in ploidy level and DNA content per basic genome indicate that the distribution of DNA within the complement is not at random and suggest the presence of mechanisms selecting for constancy, or against changes, in the karyotype morphology.Evolutionary chromosome change involves significant variation in DNA amount in diploids and genome downsizing in polyploids. Genome size and karyotype parameters of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> species with different ploidy level were analysed. In <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, polyploid species show less DNA content per basic genome than diploid species. The rate of variation is lower at higher ploidy levels. All the species have a basic number <italic>x</italic> = 11 and bimodal karyotypes. The basic karyotypes consist of four short metacentric chromosomes and seven large chromosomes (submetacentric and subtelocentric). The bimodal karyotype is preserved maintaining the relative proportions of members of the haploid chromosome set, even in the presence of genome downsizing. The constancy of the karyotype is maintained because changes in DNA amount are proportional to the length of the whole-chromosome complement and vary independently in the long and short sets of chromosomes. This karyotype constancy in taxa of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> with different genome size and ploidy level indicates that the distribution of extra DNA within the complement is not at random and suggests the presence of mechanisms selecting for constancy, or against changes, in karyotype morphology.The diversity of plant genomes is manifested through a wide range of chromosome number and genome size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C17">Leitch and Leitch 2013</xref>). The partitioning of total DNA in chromosomes is a complex level of structural and functional organization of nuclear genomes. Each species has a characteristic chromosome complement, its karyotype, which represents the phenotypic appearance of somatic chromosomes. Karyotype features more commonly recorded for comparative evolutionary analysis are number and size of the chromosomes, position and type of primary and secondary constrictions, karyotype symmetry and genome size, among others. Genome size does not necessarily reflect chromosome number variation since mechanisms producing changes in total DNA amount are different for those leading to changes in chromosome number. The increases in genome size arise predominantly through polyploidy and amplification of non-coding repetitive DNA, especially retrotransposons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C5">Bennetzen <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). These mechanisms are counterbalanced by processes that result in a decrease in genome size such as unequal recombination and illegitimate recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C17">Leitch and Leitch 2013</xref>). Genome size changes (amplification or deletions) are correlated with karyotype parameters and can affect the entire chromosome complement or they may be restricted to a subset of chromosomes.Different patterns of distribution of DNA among chromosomes or chromosome arms, even in the absence of chromosomal rearrangements, could lead to important changes in the karyotype parameters, mainly in the asymmetry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C30">Peruzzi <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). This parameter refers to karyotypes with a predominance of chromosomes with terminal/subterminal centromeres (intrachromosomal asymmetry) and highly heterogeneous chromosome sizes (interchromosomal asymmetry) (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C29">Peruzzi and Eroglu 2013</xref>). It is interesting to point out that evolutionary chromosome change involving alteration in DNA amount does not always lead to changes in the morphology of the karyotype, given that in several groups of plants karyotype orthoselection has been found (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C41">White 1973</xref>), as was described in Asparagaceae, Xanthorrhoeacae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C6">Brandham 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C9">Brandham and Doherty 1998</xref>) and <italic>Vicia</italic> (Fabaceae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C25">Naranjo <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>), among others.The bimodal karyotype represents a special case of asymmetry and is characterized by the presence of two sharply distinct classes of chromosomes without a gradual transition. The bimodal karyotype has been reported in monocots such as Xanthorrhoeacae (<italic>Aloe</italic>, <italic>Haworthia</italic>, <italic>Gasteria</italic>), Asparagaceae (<italic>Agave</italic>, <italic>Yucca</italic>) and Amaryllidaceae (<italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, <italic>Rodophiala</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C22">Naranjo 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C6">Brandham 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C23">Naranjo and Andrada 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C2">Arroyo 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C24">Naranjo and Poggio 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C9">Brandham and Doherty 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C39">Vosa 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C32">Poggio <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C40">Weiss-Schneeweiss and Schneeweiss 2013</xref>). Taxonomic groups with bimodal karyotypes and genome size variation offer the opportunity to analyse the nature and distribution of changes between chromosome arms and among members of the haploid chromosome set.<italic>Hippeastrum</italic> Herb. is a genus of perennial and bulbous plants of the tribe Hippeastreae of Amaryllidaceae J.St.-Hil. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C21">Meerow <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>) with <italic>ca.</italic> 60 species inhabiting tropical and subtropical America from Mexico and the Antilles to central Argentina. Their species have economic value as ornamentals and are used in the pharmaceutical industry due to their high content of alkaloids. In the genus <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, chromosomes of about 41 species have been studied and all presented bimodal karyotypes and a basic number <italic>x</italic> = 11. The karyotypes consist of four short metacentric (m) chromosomes and seven large chromosomes (four submetacentric—sm and three subtelocentric—st) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C22">Naranjo 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C23">Naranjo and Andrada 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C2">Arroyo 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C8">Brandham and Bhandol 1997</xref>). This genus is an interesting model to analyse how and where gain or loss of DNA occurs, and how these changes affect karyotype morphology.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C32">Poggio <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> found, in 12 <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> diploid species from South America, karyotypes similar to that previously described but significant differences in nuclear DNA content. These authors report that karyotype constancy is a product of changes in DNA content occurring in the whole-chromosome complement, and that DNA addition to the long and short sets of chromosomes varies independently. The authors state that the evolutionary changes in DNA amount are proportional to chromosome length, maintaining karyotype uniformity. They found that in diploid species with higher DNA content, the short chromosomes add equal DNA amounts to both arms, maintaining their metacentric morphology, whereas the long chromosomes add DNA only to the short arm, increasing chromosome symmetry.Several authors reported variation in ploidy level (3<italic>x</italic> to 7<italic>x</italic>) in several species of the genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C35">Sato 1938</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C27">Neto 1948</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C22">Naranjo 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C15">Lakshmi 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C2">Arroyo 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C3">Beltrao and Guerra 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C42">Zou and Quin 1994</xref>). It is interesting to point out that several polyploids previously analysed were considered to be autopolyploids, because they have similar basic bimodal karyotypes to those described in diploid species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C22">Naranjo 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C23">Naranjo and Andrada 1975</xref>). The genome size of the polyploid species of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> has not yet been reported. It has been frequently documented that the major trend in vascular plants is a decrease in the genome size per haploid genome (1Cx), when a polyploidization event occurs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C16">Leitch and Bennett 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C17">Leitch and Leitch 2013</xref>). This genome downsizing, which could be involved in the genetic and cytogenetic diploidization of polyploids, consists in non-random deleting of coding and non-coding sequences, changes in retroelements, chromosome reorganization, gain or loss of chromosomes or entire genomes, altered patterns of gene expression and epigenetic modifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C11">Feldman and Levy 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C20">Ma and Gustafson 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C13">Jones and Langdom 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C17">Leitch and Leitch 2013</xref>).In the present work, variation of DNA amount in species of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> with different ploidy level is presented with the aim to evaluate if genome size per haploid genome decreases when a polyploidization event occurs. Besides, karyotype parameters are evaluated to analyse if bimodality and karyotype' constancy detected in diploids can still take place in different ploidy levels, even in the presence of genome downsizing. Finally, the variation in DNA content and correlated karyotype parameters will be discussed in the different ploidy levels studied.Origin, accession numbers and ploidy level of the <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> species.For squashing, root tips were pretreated for 2.5 h in 0.002 M 8-hydroxyquinoline at 20 °C, fixed in 3 : 1 absolute ethanol : acetic acid and stained in Feulgen solution. The average of centromeric indices, for small and large chromosomes (CI<sub>S</sub> and CI<sub>L</sub>), was calculated according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C32">Poggio <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>. The nomenclature used for chromosome morphology is that proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C19">Levan <italic>et al.</italic> (1964)</xref>. To estimate karyotype asymmetry, the coefficient of variation of chromosome length (CV<sub>CL</sub>) and the mean centromeric asymmetry (M<sub>CA</sub>) were calculated according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C29">Peruzzi and Eroglu (2013)</xref>. The A1 and A2 indices from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C34">Romero Zarco (1986)</xref> were also calculated for comparison with previously published data in <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> and related genera. Chromosomal parameters were measured using the freeware program MicroMeasure 3.3 (<uri xlink:href="http://www.colostate.edu/Depts/Biology/MicroMeasure/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.colostate.edu/Depts/Biology/MicroMeasure/</uri>). Mean values for the karyotype parameters were measured from a minimum of five scattered metaphase plates in each accession.Root tips were fixed in 3 : 1 absolute ethanol : acetic acid for 1–4 days. The staining method was performed as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C38">Tito <italic>et al.</italic> (1991)</xref>. The amount of Feulgen staining per nucleus, expressed in arbitrary units, was measured at a wavelength of 550 nm using the scanning method on a Vickers M85 Microspectrophotometer (Jodrell Laboratory, RBG, Kew, UK). The DNA content per basic genome expressed in picograms (pg) was calculated using <italic>Allium cepa</italic> var. <italic>Ailsa Craig</italic> as a standard (2C = 33, 55 pg; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C4">Bennett and Smith 1976</xref>). DNA content was measured in 25–50 telophase nuclei (2C) per accession.The differences between species in 1Cx DNA content were tested through an analysis of variance (ANOVA) using generalized linear mixed models. The mean values of genome sizes were calculated and multiple contrasts were performed with the LSD Fisher method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C12">Fisher 1932</xref>). These statistical analyses were considered significant if their <italic>P</italic> values were &lt;0.05.The relationship between total DNA content and ploidy level was studied by fitting a weighted least-squares linear regression. This method compensates for the variable number of DNA measurements available for each species and ploidy level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C1">Aitken 1935</xref>).The statistical analyses were performed using the Infostat program, FCA, National University of Córdoba (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C10">Di Rienzo <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) and the R programming language (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C33">R Development Core Team 2004</xref>).Chromosome numbers, genome sizes and karyotype parameters of the <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> species. 2C DNA, total genomic DNA; 1Cx DNA, DNA per basic genome; CI<sub>S</sub>, average of centromeric index of short chromosomes; CI<sub>L</sub>, average of centromeric index of long chromosomes; A1, intrachromosomal asymmetry index; A2, interchromosomal asymmetry index; M<sub>CA</sub>, mean centromeric asymmetry; CV<sub>CL</sub>, coefficient of variation of chromosome length; CV<sub>S</sub>, volume of short chromosomes as a percentage of the volume of all chromosomes. Means with the same letter are not significantly different (<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05). *Data taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C32">Poggio <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>, except for M<sub>CA</sub> and CV<sub>CL</sub> values.Mitotic metaphases of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> species: (A) <italic>H. rutilum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 22), (B) <italic>H. puniceum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 33), (C) <italic>H. rutilum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 44), (D) <italic>H. blossfeldiae</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 44), (E) <italic>H. cybister</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 55) and (F) <italic>H. puniceum</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 66). Scale bar: 10 µm.Relative chromosome and arm sizes per haploid complement (<italic>x</italic> = 11): (A) <italic>H. solandriflorum</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (B) <italic>H. tucumanum</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (C) <italic>H. parodii</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (D) <italic>H. correiense</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (E) <italic>H. rutilum</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (F) <italic>H. morelianum</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (G) <italic>H. puniceum</italic> (3<italic>x</italic>), (H) <italic>H. rutilum</italic> (4<italic>x</italic>), (I) <italic>H. blossfeldiae</italic> (4<italic>x</italic>), (J) <italic>H. cybister</italic> (5<italic>x</italic>), (K) <italic>H. rutilum</italic> (5<italic>x</italic>) and (L) <italic>H. puniceum</italic> (6<italic>x</italic>). S, short arm; L, long arm; m, metacentric; sm, submetacentric; st, subtelocentric; t, telocentric.Continued.Asymmetry parameters (M<sub>CA</sub> and CV<sub>CL</sub>) plotted against DNA content. The bars represent the total DNA amount (2C) and the black zone indicates the basic DNA amount (1Cx). (A) <italic>H. solandriflorum</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (B) <italic>H. tucumanum</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (C) <italic>H. parodii</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (D) <italic>H. correiense</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (E) <italic>H. rutilum</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (F) <italic>H. morelianum</italic> (2<italic>x</italic>), (G) <italic>H. puniceum</italic> (3<italic>x</italic>), (H) <italic>H. rutilum</italic> (4<italic>x</italic>), (I) <italic>H. blossfeldiae</italic> (4<italic>x</italic>), (J) <italic>H. cybister</italic> (5<italic>x</italic>), (K) <italic>H. rutilum</italic> (5<italic>x</italic>) and (L) <italic>H. puniceum</italic> (6<italic>x</italic>). M<sub>CA</sub>, mean centromeric asymmetry; CV<sub>CL</sub>, coefficient of variation of chromosome length.Total DNA content (2C) plotted against ploidy level. Solid line, linear fit; broken line, extrapolated from diploids.DNA content per basic genome (1Cx) plotted against ploidy level. Solid line, linear fit/ploidy level (<italic>x</italic>); broken line, extrapolated from diploids/ploidy level (<italic>x</italic>).In the present work, genome size and karyotype parameters of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> species with different ploidy level were analysed and compared with previous data.Total DNA (2C) varies from 26.80 to 34.17 pg among diploids and increases with ploidy level, reaching a value of 64.67 pg in the hexaploid species. This genus has large genomes, since according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C18">Leitch <italic>et al.</italic> (1998)</xref> most angiosperms actually have small 1C values (from 0.1 to 3.5 pg).DNA per basic genome (1Cx), calculated from total DNA content, varies from 17.08 to 13.40 pg in diploids. The difference between these extreme values is significant. In polyploids there is a gradual decrease in the 1Cx value when ploidy level increases, varying from 12.90 pg in triploids to 10.78 pg in hexaploids. In <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> the polyploids studied show less DNA content per basic genome than diploids. Considering the average of basic DNA content for diploids, the triploid diminishes by 16.77 % while the decrease among 3<italic>x</italic>–4<italic>x</italic>, 4<italic>x</italic>–5<italic>x</italic> and 5<italic>x</italic>–6<italic>x</italic> ploidy levels is lower, varying between 5.5 and 6.5 %. These results show that in <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, DNA per haploid genome decreases in polyploids, the rate of variation being lower at higher ploidy levels. Many examples are found in the literature where polyploidy is associated with decreasing genome size, in terms of DNA content per haploid genome. Moreover, comparative genome studies have shown that the downsizing of the genome can take place even in a few generations and could be involved in the genetic and cytogenetic diploidization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C36">Soltis <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C14">Kellogg and Bennetzen 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C16">Leitch and Bennett 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C11">Feldman and Levy 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C20">Ma and Gustafson 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C17">Leitch and Leitch 2013</xref>). While polyploidy, joined with transposable element amplification, is widely considered to play a role in generating increased genome size, mechanisms that generate small deletions such as unequal homologous recombination and illegitimate recombination could be involved in genome downsizing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C5">Bennetzen <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C17">Leitch and Leitch 2013</xref>). To explain this widespread phenomenon it could be postulated that at polyploid level, the DNA elimination leads to a more adequate balance between total DNA content and certain cellular parameters. Moreover, at polyploid level, the partial elimination of DNA sequences is more easily tolerated. However, in some cases, as in genus <italic>Larrea</italic> (Zygophyllaceae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C31">Poggio <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>) or <italic>Aloe</italic> (Xanthorrhoeacae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C9">Brandham and Doherty 1998</xref>), differences in 1Cx at different ploidy levels are not statistically significant.The diploid and polyploid species of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> here studied presented <italic>x</italic> = 11 and despite possessing significant differences in their genome size, all have a basic bimodal karyotype with four small m and seven large sm/t chromosomes. The constancy of the karyotype in taxa of <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> with different genome size and ploidy level indicates that the distribution of extra DNA within the complement is not at random and suggests the presence of mechanisms selecting for constancy, or against changes, in karyotype morphology, processes named by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C41">White (1973)</xref> as karyotype constancy or karyotype orthoselection, respectively. Several studies have shown that karyotype orthoselection in diploid species with significant differences in genome sizes involves proportional changes in all chromosomes, preserving the morphology of the complement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C9">Brandham and Doherty 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C25">Naranjo <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Chromosomal parameters such as centromeric indices and karyotype asymmetry provide some insights into how the additional DNA is distributed in the genome, between small and large chromosomes as well as between arms of individual chromosomes. In this work we use M<sub>CA</sub> and CV<sub>CL</sub> to estimate the intrachromosomal and interchromosomal asymmetries, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C29">Peruzzi and Eroglu 2013</xref>). Moreover, we also employ the A1 and A2 indices from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C34">Romero Zarco (1986)</xref> only for comparative purposes with previous work in the <italic>Hippeastrum</italic> species and related genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C24">Naranjo and Poggio 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C32">Poggio <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).Different patterns of addition of DNA amount in a chromosome complement were reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C30">Peruzzi <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>. For ‘proportional increase’, the amount of DNA added to each chromosome arm is proportional to its length. This pattern does not result in a change in karyotype asymmetry when genome size changes. This pattern has been observed in several genera, including <italic>Aloe</italic> and <italic>Gasteria</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C9">Brandham and Doherty 1998</xref>). For ‘equal increase’, the same amount of DNA is added to each chromosome arm regardless of its size. This will result in an increase in the intrachromosomal karyotype symmetry. Examples of genera showing this pattern include <italic>Vigna</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C28">Parida <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>) and <italic>Papaver</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C37">Srivastava and Lavania 1991</xref>). In many genera of Liliaceae, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C30">Peruzzi <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> found an ‘unequal increase’, i.e. the amount of DNA added varies between longer and shorter chromosome arms unequally.In <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, with two sets of chromosomes that differ in size and morphology, a different pattern was observed. In diploid species the evolutionary changes in DNA amount occur in the whole-chromosome complement and are proportional to chromosome length, maintaining karyotype uniformity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C32">Poggio <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). These authors analysed separately the CI of short and long chromosomes and proposed a model of genome size change where the DNA increase or decrease to the long and short sets of chromosomes varies independently.In the diploid and polyploid species analysed here, the volume of short chromosomes as a percentage of the volume of all chromosomes (CV<sub>S</sub>) is very similar, indicating that the volume of long and short chromosomes remains in a similar proportion among species. As previously discussed, this karyotype uniformity occurs if changes are proportional to the relative length of each chromosome arm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C7">Brandham 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C25">Naranjo <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C32">Poggio <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). In diploid and polyploid species the CI<sub>S</sub> are similar and did not show any relationship with DNA amount, varying from 42.60 to 46.80. This could be explained if the short chromosomes add or lose equal DNA amounts to both arms, maintaining their metacentric morphology. Diploid species with lower DNA content have minor CI<sub>L</sub> indices and have more asymmetric karyotypes, with a greater number of long chromosomes st or t, i.e. the changes in DNA amount in the long chromosomes affect mainly in their short arms. Among the triploids, tetraploids and pentaploids variation in CI<sub>L</sub> was not detected, being similar to that of the diploid species with lower DNA content. This could be attributed to the lower downsizing at higher ploidy level.In the hexaploid species analysed here, CV<sub>S</sub> and the bimodality are maintained, and CI<sub>S</sub> values are similar to those of the diploid and polyploid species. However, a different pattern of changes is observed in the long chromosomes of its karyotype. CI<sub>L</sub> is greater than that of the other studied species, indicating that centromeres have a more median position. While the number of chromosomes sm–st, st and t varies from 3 to 7 from diploids to pentaploids, the hexaploids have just one st chromosome. Moreover, it is the only species with m–sm long chromosomes, i.e. the subset of long chromosomes is more symmetrical. This could be explained if there is a threshold for the distribution of changes in the larger chromosomes when the chromosome number is &gt;55. This threshold could be related to nuclear organization at the chromosome level, arrangement of nuclear territories, interactions among genomes to sharing a nucleus and disturbances during cell division. Anyway, still very little is known about the mechanisms and sequences involved in genome downsizing in <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU029C26">Navrátilová <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref> reported that amplification of retroelement sequences is likely to increase the size of all chromosomes within the karyotype in an approximately equal manner. In <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, the absence of notorious C and DAPI bands (unpubl. res.), joined to the presence of conserved bimodal karyotypes, even with changes in ploidy level and 1Cx value, strongly suggests that DNA changes could occur by amplification or deletion of retroelement sequences, which are generally dispersed in the genome.In the genus <italic>Hippeastrum</italic>, evolutionary chromosome change involves variation in DNA amount in diploids and genome downsizing in polyploids. Besides, the bimodal karyotype is preserved maintaining the relative proportions of members of the haploid chromosome set by karyotype orthoselection. The presence of conserved karyotypes, even with changes in ploidy level and DNA content per basic genome, is strongly susceptible to an adaptive interpretation, suggesting the existence of mechanisms that select for constancy in karyotype morphology.Funding was provided by grants from the <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">CONICET-PIP 00342</grant-num>), <grant-sponsor id="cs2" rid="cn2" xlink:type="simple">Universidad de Buenos Aires</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num id="cn2" rid="cs2" xlink:type="simple">UBACYT 20020100100859</grant-num>) and <grant-sponsor id="cs3" rid="cn3" xlink:type="simple">Agencia Nacional de Producción Científica y Tecnológica—SECyT</grant-sponsor> (<grant-num id="cn3" rid="cs3" xlink:type="simple">PICT 2010-1665</grant-num>).All authors contributed to the experimental design, data analysis and manuscript preparation.None declared.We thank Agr. Bch. M.F. Schrauf for statistical contributions and Mr D. Fink for assistance with the image analysis. We are also grateful to the anonymous referees and the associate editor of the journal <italic>AoB PLANTS</italic> for their helpful comments.