 A simple and efficient protocol for the mass propagation of  Cymbidium mastersii : an ornamental orchid of Northeast India  The reintroduction of  Plantanthera ciliaris  in Canada  Physiology of germinating orchid seeds  Formation of protocorm-like bodies (PLBs) and shoot development through  in vitro  culture of outer tissue of  Cymbidium  PLB  Plant regeneration from callus culture of  Cymbidium ensifolium  var.  misericors   Orchid diversity in North-East India  Asymbiotic germination of  Cymbidium ensifolium . II. Effects of several supplements to the medium, pH values and light and/or dark culture periods on growth of rhizome and organogenesis for rhizome  Propagation of  Cymbidium giganteum  Wall. through high frequency conversion of encapsulated protocorms under  in vivo  and  in vitro  conditions  Protocorm regeneration, multiple shoot induction and  ex vitro  establishment of  Cymbidium devonianum  Paxt  Optimization of nutrient requirements for asymbiotic seed germination of  D. longicornu  and  D. formosumi  Roxb  Effects of benzyladenine and α-naphthalineacetic acid on the formation of protocorm like bodies (PLBs) from explants of outer tissue of  Cymbidium  PLBs cultured  in vitro   Silver nitrate influences  in vitro  shoot multiplication and root formation in  Vanilla planifolia  Andr  The use of indoleacetylamino acids in the  in vitro  propagation of  Phalaenopsis  orchids   Cymbidium  culture techniques and trade  Seed germination and tissue culture of  Cymbidium giganteum  Wall. ex Lindl  Effects of red and blue light emitting diodes on callus induction, callus proliferation, and protocorm-like body formation from callus in  Cymbidium  orchid  Callus induction from protocorm-like body segments and plant regeneration in  Cymbidium  (Orchidaceae)   In vitro  seed culture and seedling development of  Calopogon tuberosus   Effect of plant growth regulators on organ formation in the  Cymbidium  shoot apex culture  in vitro   Nonsymbiotic germination of orchid seeds  A new nutrient solution for germination of orchid seed  Effects of combination of growth regulating substances, and of organic matter on the proliferation and organogenesis of  Cymbidium  protocorms cultured  in vitro    Agrobacterium tumefaciens -mediated transformation of an  Oncidium  orchid  Shoot tip transverse thin cell layers and 2,4-epibrassinolide in the micropropagation of  Cymbidium bicolor  Lindl  Vitamins and nitrogen requirements of  Orchis laxiflora  Lamk  Tissue culture—a new means of clonal propagation of orchids  A revised medium for rapid growth and bioassay with tobacco tissue culture . Physiologia Plantarum    In vitro  propagation of three epiphytic orchids,  Cymbidium aloifolium  (L.) Sw.,  Dendrobium aphyllum  (Roxb.) Fisch. and  Dendrobium moschatum  (Buch-Ham) Sw. through thidiazuron-induced high frequency shoot proliferation   In vitro  propagation of  Paphiopedilum  orchid through formation of protocorm-like bodies  Artificial seeds for preservation and propagation of  Cymbidium  spp   In vitro  multiplication of  Cymbidium pendulum  orchids via embryo culture  Micropropagation of terrestrial  Cymbidium  species using rhizomes developed from seeds and pseudobulbs  Rhizome induction and plantlet regeneration of  Cymbidium goeringii  from flower bud cultures  in vitro    In vitro  seed germination and greenhouse cultivation of  Encyclia boothiana  var.  erythronoides , an endangered Florida orchid  Asymbiotic seed germination and  in vitro  seedling development of  Habenaria macroceratitis  (Orchidaceae), a rare Florida terrestrial orchid  Effects of different factors on immature embryo culture, PLBs differentiation and rapid mass multiplication of  Coelogyne suaveolens  (Lindl.) Hook  Priming abiotic factors for optimal hybrid  Cymbidium  (Orchidaceae) PLB and callus induction, plantlet formation and their subsequent cytogenetic stability analysis  Some pH change in nutrient solution   In vitro  germination of some Western European orchids  Regeneration competence of  Cymbidium  Great Waltz × Valey flower roots: a study  in vitro   Tissue culture of  Cymbidium : plant and flower induction  in vitro   This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  The present investigation was undertaken to mass propagate  Cymbidium mastersii , an ornamental orchid of Northeast India by  in vitro  propagation method. This approach could also help for the conservation as well as commercialization of  C. mastersii  and other threatened and ornamental orchids.   Cymbidium mastersii  is an epiphytic orchid distributed mainly in Northeast India. Owing to its high commercial value in the floricultural industry, natural populations are under threat from over-exploitation. Mass propagation provides an alternative means of satisfying the demand. Unfortunately, conventional propagation is slow and difficult, suggesting  in vitro  methods for mass multiplication may be more appropriate. The objective of this study was to develop an efficient protocol.  Four nutrient media were evaluated for seed germination and early protocorm development: Murashige and Skoog (MS), half-strength MS, Knudson ‘C’ (KC), and Vacin and Went (VW). In addition, the effects of plant growth regulators 6-benzylaminopurine (BAP), kinetin (KN), α-naphthalene acetic acid (NAA) and indole-3-butyric acid (IBA) were studied alone and in combination. The maximum percentage seed germination (93.58 ± 0.56) was obtained in MS basal medium after 8–9 weeks of culture. Secondary protocorms (protocorm-like bodies) were developed from primary protocorms on MS medium fortified with different concentrations and combinations of cytokinins (BAP and KN) and auxins (NAA and IBA). The highest numbers of secondary protocorms (20.55 ± 0.62)/primary protocorms were obtained in MS medium supplemented with 5.0 µM BAP and 2.5 µM NAA. The most effective auxin source promoting root production (7.46 ± 0.09 per shoot) was 10.0 µM IBA. The plants were acclimatized effectively (survival percentage 88 %) in a greenhouse using a rooting medium of crushed sterile brick and charcoal (1 : 1 v/v) and vermicompost (leaf litter + cow dung, 1 : 1 v/v).  An efficient protocol was established for  in vitro  propagation of  C. mastersii  using seed as the starting material. The percentage seed germination varied with the composition of the nutrient media and was highest in full-strength MS basal medium. The number of secondary protocorms that developed from primary protocorms was increased by the addition of 5.0 µM BAP and 2.5 µM NAA.  In vitro  raised plantlets acclimatized in a greenhouse were closely similar to the mother plants in morphology.  The Orchidaceae represents a peak in the evolution of monocots and is one of the most successful families of flowering plants, as is clear from its wide distribution and numerous species (20 000–30 000) ( Chowdhery 2001 ). Increased globalization of the floriculture trade has made orchids the most popular cut flower and potted floriculture crop with a wholesale value estimated at $126 million ( United States Department of Agriculture 2004 ).  Cymbidium  comprises more than 70 natural species and hundreds of manmade hybrids. This rich variety has contributed significantly to the development of the international trade in orchid cut flowers ( Vij  et al . 2004 ).  Cymbidium mastersii  is an epiphytic orchid found principally in the Sikkim-Himalayas and the Khasi Hills of Meghalaya, India, at an altitude of 1700–2300 m ( Bose and Bhattacharjee 1980 ). Its beautiful sweet-scented white flowers explain its high commercial value. Currently, ruthless collection of this species from its natural habitat, linked to unauthorized trading, fulfils market demand. As a consequence, it is becoming increasingly rare in the wild ( Hedge 1999 ). An alternative source of these plants is clearly needed and mass propagation offers a solution ( Stanberg and Kane 1998 ).  The regeneration and multiplication of orchids through seeds in nature are limited due to suppressed endosperm and requirements of fungal partners ( Sungkumlong and Deb 2008 ).  In vitro  asymbiotic seed germination of orchids has been frequently used for the production of commercially important orchids and shown to be an efficient tool for the production of orchids for conservation and rehabilitation ( Kauth  et al.  2006 ). The  in vitro  asymbiotic seed germination of orchids by  Knudson (1922)  and shoot tip culture in  Cymbidium  by  Morel (1964)  laid the milestone of orchid tissue culture. Mass propagation protocols of different C ymbidium  spp. using different explants such as mature seeds ( Chung  et al.  1985 ;  Hossain  et al.  2010 ), immature seeds ( Shimasaki and Uemoto 1990 ;  Das  et al.  2007 ), flower stalks ( Wang 1988 ), pseudobulbs ( Shimasaki and Uemoto 1990 ), shoot segments ( Nayak  et al.  1997 ), flower buds ( Shimasaki and Uemoto 1991 ), protocorms ( Corrie and Tandon 1993 ), protocorm-like bodies (PLBs) ( Begum  et al.  1994 ), thin cell layers (TCLs) of PLBs ( Malabadi  et al.  2008 ) and artificial seeds based on PLBs ( Nhut  et al.  2005 ) have been standardized.  In vitro  seed germination of orchids is greatly influenced by several factors like seed age, nutrient media and organic carbon source, etc. The development of protocorms from germinated seeds and the subsequent induction of secondary protocorms or PLBs, from different tissues as explants has become a reliable method for breeding orchids. Propagation by the formation of PLBs is a preferred option because a large number of PLBs can be obtained in a short period of time. Protocorm-like bodies can proliferate and regenerate rapidly into complete plantlets ( Liau  et al.  2003 ). Moreover, PLBs are well-differentiated tissues that are sometimes regarded as orchid embryos that can develop two distinct bipolar structures, namely, the shoot and root meristem. Thus, these structures are able to convert to plantlets easily when grown on appropriate nutrient medium ( Ng and Saleh 2011 ).  Although  C. mastersii  faces rapid destruction due to exploitation and also urbanization and habitat loss, there is, to date, no published information on how it may be effectively mass propagated  in vitro . We have addressed this shortcoming by developing an efficient protocol for rapid propagation of  C. mastersii  starting with  in vitro  asymbiotic seed germination, leading to PLB induction followed by plantlet development and successful  ex vitro  acclimation. Our present study constitutes the first report of the large-scale production of  C. mastersii .  Seven-month-old fruit capsules of  C. mastersii  were collected from plants grown in the greenhouse of the Plant Biotechnology Laboratory, Department of Botany, North-Eastern Hill University, Shillong, India. Capsules were washed with 2–3 drops of Tween 20 and surface-disinfected in 0.1 % mercuric chloride solution for 2 min followed by 70 % ethanol for 30 s and surface flaming. Finally, the capsules were rinsed five times with sterile distilled water and dried. All subsequent work was carried out aseptically in laminar flow cabinets. The capsules were then dissected longitudinally with a surgical blade and extracted seeds were spread thinly over the surface of liquid culture medium contained in 25 × 150 mm glass test tubes (20 test tubes per capsule) each containing 10 ml of medium.  Four nutrient media were compared for their suitability as germination media and for protocorm development: Murashige and Skoog (MS), half-strength MS, Knudson ‘C’ (KC), and Vacin and Went (VW) ( Murashige and Skoog 1962 ;  Knudson 1946 ;  Vacin and Went 1949 ) .  All media were supplemented with 3 % sucrose (w/v) and solidified with 0.8 % agar (‘Hi media’, India). The pH was adjusted to 5.8 prior to autoclaving at 121 °C, 15 p.s.i. for 15 min. The cultures were maintained at 25 ± 2 °C and 75 % relative humidity under cool fluorescent light at 50 µmol m −2  s −1  (Philips, India) with a 14-h photoperiod. Seed germination data were recorded 60 days after inoculation of seeds, whereas different developmental stages of protocorms (i.e. percentage of protocorms with vegetative apex, plantlets with 2–3 leaves and 1–2 roots) were recorded every 30 days.  The most effective medium for seed germination and protocorm development was supplemented with different concentrations of 6-benzylaminopurine (BAP), kinetin (KN), α-naphthalene acetic acid (NAA) and indole-3-butyric acid (IBA) (2.5, 5.0, 10.0 µM) alone and in combination to study their effectiveness in promoting proliferation of protocorms and subsequent plantlet development. Sixty-day-old primary protocorms (one protocorm per test tube) were used for the experiment. Data were recorded after 60 days in culture. Means of 20 test tubes were taken for each treatment and all experiments were repeated three times.  For root induction, 6-month-old plantlets without roots obtained from the above experiments were cultured on full-strength MS medium supplemented with different concentrations (5.0, 10.0 and 15.0 µM) of IBA or NAA. Well-rooted plantlets were rinsed thoroughly with sterile water to remove the residual medium, and transplanted to 8-cm-diameter thermocol/plastic pots containing a potting mixture of coarsely crushed sterile brick and charcoal at 1 : 1 (v/v) and vermicompost (leaf litter + cow dung, 1 : 1 v/v) and kept in the greenhouse of the Plant Biotechnology Laboratory, Department of Botany, North-Eastern Hill University, Shillong, at 25 ± 2 °C and 70–80 % relative humidity. Plantlets were watered on alternate days. The percentage survival of plantlets was calculated after 90 days in the greenhouse.  All results were analysed by one-way analysis of variance. Comparisons of the mean and standard error were determined by Duncan's multiple range test at  P  ≤ 0.05. Statistical tests used the SPSS statistical package version 15.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).  Comparative effect of four culture media on asymbiotic germination of seeds and protocorm development of  C. mastersii .  Stage (1): vegetative apex stage. Stage (2): 2–3 leaves stage. Stage (3): 1–2 roots stage.  Mean values within a column followed by the same letters are not significantly different at  P  &lt; 0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range test;  n  = 20 per treatment conducted in triplicate.   Different stages in the germination of seeds of  C. mastersii.   (A) Mature seeds containing embryos inside the integuments, bar = 100 µm. (B) Rounded protocorms after 9 weeks of culture. (C) Young protocorm with a vegetative apex at the upper side (arrow), bar = 1 mm. (D) Complete plantlet with 2–3 leaves and 1–2 roots, bar = 5 mm.  Production of secondary protocorms from primary protocorms in  C. mastersii  after 60 days of culture in MS medium supplemented with different plant growth regulators.  Mean values within a column followed by the same letters are not significantly different at  P  &lt; 0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range test;  n  = 20 per treatment conducted in triplicate.   Development of plants via PLB.  (A) Development of secondary protocorms (PLBs) from a single primary protocorm. (B) Protocorm-like body developing growth appendicle (arrow). (C) Development of plantlets from PLBs. (D) Complete plants with leaves and roots. (E) Well-rooted plants ready for hardening, bar = 1 cm. (F) Hardened plants under greenhouse conditions, bar = 1 mm.  Effect of different concentrations of two auxins on root induction of  C. mastersii  seedlings after 60 days of culture.  Values are the mean ± SE. Mean values within a column followed by the same letters are not significantly different at  P  &lt; 0.05 according to Duncan's multiple range test;  n  = 10 per treatment conducted in triplicate.  We show that an  in vitro  asymbiotic seed germination technique is an effective tool for the mass propagation of  C. mastersii . If adopted commercially this will reduce the demand for wild-grown material and thus should benefit conservation of the surviving natural populations.  Nutrient requirements for orchid seed germination are thought to be species specific ( Arditti and Ernst 1984 ;  Kauth  et al.  2008 ). It was, therefore, not surprising that the various asymbiotic media used in this present study, with their different compositions and concentrations of mineral salts, organic supplements and vitamins, varied in their suitability for  in vitro  germination. The full-strength MS medium tested contained higher concentrations of macro and micro elements than the half-strength MS, KC and VW media with which we compared it. The nitrogen source plays a major role in effecting orchid seed germination ( Van Waes and Debergh 1986 ;  Anderson 1996 ;  Stewart and Kane 2006 ). This may explain the superior seed germination on MS. It was reported by  Kramer and Kozlowaski (1979)  that nitrogen present in MS medium greatly influences the growth and differentiation of cells. According to  Dohling  et al.  (2008) , the presence of nitrate in the form of ammonium nitrate in MS medium is the most suitable source for seed germination and plantlet development of  Dendrobium longicornu  and  Dendrobium formosum.  Also, pyridoxine, thiamine and nicotinic acid, as vitamins, are absent from KC and VW media but present in the MS media. This, too, may have promoted germination in  C. mastersii . Our findings parallel those obtained for  Catteleya  spp. by  Mead and Bulard (1979) . These additional factors included in full-strength MS may also have aided protocorm development.  According to  Teixeira da Silva  et al.  (2006) , the development of plantlets from orchid seed can either be direct or indirect through secondary protocorms/PLBs. These PLBs are the outcome of continuous division of the outer tissues of protocorms ( Huan and Tanaka 2004 a  ,   b  ) or pseudobulbs, rhizomes, roots and shoot segments ( Chang and Chang 1998 ). Protocorm origin holds advantages because a large number of plantlets can be obtained from a single protocorm. Protocorms were shown by  Griesbach (1983)  to be the most effective explants for PLB regeneration in several orchid species. This may be ascribed to the presence of highly meristematic tissues. In the case of  C. mastersii , we observed that protocorms cultured on the MS basal medium alone did not give rise to PLBs. This was perhaps because endogenous auxins and cytokinins are insufficient for PLB development since the addition of auxins and cytokinins resulted in PLB proliferation. Our results revealed optimal concentrations of auxins (NAA or IBA) for PLB generation with yield decreasing at higher levels. The yield of PLBs tended to increase with the cytokinin concentration (BAP and KN), which agrees with findings by  Kim and Kako (1982) . Primary protocorms responded significantly to a combination of 5.0 µM BAP and 2.5 µM NAA, yielding the highest numbers of PLBs, suggesting a synergistic effect which was also observed in the case of  Cymbidium nativity  and  C. lapine dancer  ( Fujii  et al.  1999 ).  Kusumoto (1978)  suggested that the negative effect of NAA on PLB proliferation in the case of cymbidiums was overcome by BA. This was paralleled in our results. In  Cymbidium , PLBs were found to regenerate complete plantlets that were closely similar to those arising from somatic embryos ( Teixeira da Silva  et al.  2006 ). This was also observed in  C. mastersii . Indole butyric acid was found to be the superior auxin for promoting rooting. The maximum number (7.46 ± 0.09) of roots per shoot was recorded in the medium supplemented with 10.0 µM IBA.  Giridhar  et al . (2001 ) and  Nongdam  et al . (2006 ) have also reported the effectiveness of IBA in the case of the medicinal orchids Vanilla  planifolia  and  Cymbidium pendulum .   Cymbidium mastersii  is an endangered epiphytic orchid of Northeast India of high commercial value. An alternative source of material is needed to satisfy commercial demands if wild populations are to be saved. In the present study, a successful attempt was made to develop an  in vitro  system for the mass propagation of  C. mastersii . This was based on the germination of seeds from a small number of fruit capsules and manipulating their development through primary protocorm production. Each protocorm in turn produced numerous well-rooted plantlets that could be successfully weaned in greenhouse conditions to generate independently growing plants that were indistinguishable from the original parent. The protocol is uncomplicated and will enable commercial production of  C. mastersii , thereby relieving pressure on the surviving natural population. This study is an initial attempt to mass propagate  C. mastersii  and the method we describe could be rendered commercially successful with the application of bioreactor technology.  This work was supported by financial assistance from the  Centre for Advanced Studies in Botany, NEHU, Shillong, India .  All the authors contributed to a similar extent overall and have seen and agreed to the submitted manuscript.  None declared.  The authors acknowledge the Centre for Advanced Studies in Botany, NEHU, Shillong, India, for financial assistance to carry out the research work. 