Growing up or growing out? How soil pH and light affect seedling growth of a relictual rainforest treeEffects of nutrient accumulation by aspen, spruce, and pine on soil propertiesLeaf optical responses to light and soil nutrient availability in temperate deciduous treesGrowth and carbon partitioning in rainforest and eucalypt forest species of south coastal New South Wales, AustraliaSoil phosphate and the delimitation of plant communities in eastern AustraliaVegetation associated with <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> (Araucariaceae)Establishing kauri in a pine stand and in scrubFactors affecting growth and distribution of kauri (<italic>Agathis australis</italic> Salisb.). III. Effect of temperature and soil conditionsThe tortoise and the hare: ecology of angiosperm dominance and gymnosperm persistenceFire-induced dynamics of <italic>Araucaria araucana</italic>—<italic>Nothofagus antartica</italic> forest in the southern AndesDifferent responses to gaps among shade-tolerant tree speciesPhotosynthetic responses of tropical forest plants to contrasting light environmentsPhysiological changes accompanying the induction of salt tolerance in <italic>Eucalyptus microcorys</italic> stems in tissue cultureConverting Australian tropical rainforest to native Araucariaceae plantations alters soil fungal communitiesSoil-related floristic variation in a hyperdiverse dipterocarp forestPatterns of plant species diversity during succession under different disturbance regimesChanging the gap dynamics paradigm: vegetative regeneration control on forest response to disturbanceEcophysiological responses of <italic>Araucaria angustifolia</italic> (Araucariaceae) seedlings to different irradiance levelsAssessing the role of light availability in the regeneration of <italic>Araucaria angustifolia</italic> (Araucariaceae)Biological flora of New Zealand. 8. <italic>Agathis australis</italic>. D.Don. Lindl. (Araucariaceae) KauriFeedback in the plant–soil systemPatterns of species composition, recruitment, and growth within canopy gaps in two New Zealand kauri (<italic>Agathis australis</italic>) forestsDynamics of forests and Araucariaceae in the western PacificThe ecological strategy of <italic>Araucaria araucana</italic>Canopy tree–soil interactions within temperate forests: species effects on pH and cationsAdaptation to sun and shade: a whole-plant perspectiveThe maintenance of species-richness in plant communities: the importance of the regeneration nicheSoil acidity in New-South-Wales—current pH values and estimates of acidification ratesArchitecture of the Wollemi pine (<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic>, Araucariaceae), a unique combination of model and reiterationEvolution of conifer foliage in the southern hemisphereSeedling growth responses to soil resources in the understory of a wet tropical forestPhytochrome-interacting factor 1 is a critical bHLH regulator of chlorophyll biosynthesisFloristic and ecological diversity of the vegetation on ultramafic rocks in New Caledonia. <italic>The Vegetation of Ultramafic (Serpentine) Soils: Proceedings of the First International Conference on Serpentine Ecology</italic><italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic>, a new living Australian genus and species in the AraucariaceaeThe southern conifer family Araucariaceae: history, status, and value for paleoenvironmental reconstructionChanging ratios of phototransformable protochlorophyll and photochlorophyllide of bean seedlings developing in the darkPhotosynthetic responses to light in seedlings of selected Amazonian and Australian rainforest tree speciesWollemi Pine ‘old pollen records for a newly discovered genus of gymnospermMechanisms of adaptation of plants to acid soilsAspects of the natural regeneration of the kauri (<italic>Agathis australis</italic> Salisb.)Spatial heterogeneity of light and woody seedling regeneration in tropical wet forestsPushed to the limit: consequences of climate change for the Araucariaceae: a relictual rain forest familyThe effects of temperature, light and stratification on seed germination of Wollemi pine (<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic>, Araucariaceae)Sexual reproduction and early plant growth of the Wollemi pine (<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic>), a rare and threatened Australian coniferThe late Quaternary history of kauri (<italic>Agathis australis</italic>) in New Zealand and its climatic significanceStudies of the development of wood-land conditions under different trees. I. Soil pHPhotosynthetic and growth responses to different light regimes of the major canopy species of Tasmanian cool temperate rainforestStand structure of the emergent conifer <italic>Araucaria laubenfelsii</italic>, in maquis and rainforest, Mont Do, New CaledoniaInterspecific demographic trade-offs and soil-related habitat associations of tree species along resource gradientsThe biology of kauri (<italic>Agathis australis</italic>) in New Zealand. Production, biomass, carbon storage, and litter fall in four forest remnantsPlant traits and temporal scale: evidence from a 5-year invasion experiment using native speciesTransformations of 2:1 phyllosilicates in 41-year-old soils under oak and pineThe impact of nitrification on soil acidification and cation leaching in a red alder ecosystemThe influence of simulated shadelight and daylight on growth, development and photosynthesis of <italic>Pinus radiata</italic>, <italic>Agathis australis</italic> and <italic>Dacrydium cuperssinum</italic>Soil differences between secondary and old growth <italic>Agathis macrophylla</italic> forest at Nadarivatu, FijiCanopy gaps and the two major groups of forest treesA review of some aspects of tropical rain forest seedling ecology with suggestions for further enquiryEvolutionary implications of the distribution and ecology of the tropical conifer <italic>Agathis</italic>Growth responses of five forest plant species to the soils formed beneath New Zealand kauri (<italic>Agathis australis</italic>)Recruitment bottlenecks in the rare Australian conifer. <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic><bold>Associate Editor:</bold> James F. CahillThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Our aim was to uncover the drivers of seedling growth in a rare rainforest conifer. <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> is limited to canyons, characterized by deeply shaded understories and acid soils. In a glasshouse experiment, we grew seedlings at a range of pH and light levels. Growth increased with increasing light, and was higher at low pH, regardless of light. Number of stems, however, was greatest in lower light. <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> seedlings may vary their architecture - growing up when light is high, and growing out when light is lower. Nevertheless, low light is likely the key limitation of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> growth in the wild.Seedling growth rates can have important long-term effects on forest dynamics. Environmental variables such as light availability and edaphic factors can exert a strong influence on seedling growth. In the wild, seedlings of Wollemi pine (<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic>) grow on very acid soils (pH ∼4.3) in deeply shaded sites (∼3 % full sunlight). To examine the relative influences of these two factors on the growth of young <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings, we conducted a glasshouse experiment growing seedlings at two soil pH levels (4.5 and 6.5) under three light levels: low (5 % full sun), medium (15 %) and high (50 %). Stem length and stem diameter were measured, stem number and branch number were counted, and chlorophyll and carotenoid content were analysed. In general, increased plant growth was associated with increased light, and with low pH irrespective of light treatment, and pigment content was higher at low pH. Maximum stem growth occurred in plants grown in the low pH/high light treatment combination. However, stem number was highest in low pH/medium light. We hypothesize that these differences in stem development of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> among light treatments were due to this species' different recruitment strategies in response to light: greater stem growth at high light and greater investment in multiple stem production at low light. The low light levels in the <italic>W. nobilis</italic> habitat may be a key limitation on stem growth and hence <italic>W. nobilis</italic> recruitment from seedling to adult. Light and soil pH are two key factors in the growth of this threatened relictual rainforest species.Light is a fundamental factor limiting the growth and survival of seedlings in closed forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C13">Chazdon <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C63">Whitmore 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C44">Nicotra <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). Recent work has suggested that soil pH may be of equal or greater importance than light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C33">Holste <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Species-specific growth and survival responses to resources, particularly soil and light, play a key role in determining forest composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C28">Grubb 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C16">Davies <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C33">Holste <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Central to understanding tree species persistence is an understanding of their strategy for recruitment from understorey to canopy. Tree species range from those that are slow growing and shade tolerant, to fast-growing pioneers that typically dominate the post-disturbance environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C17">Denslow 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C62">Whitmore 1989</xref>). It is competition for resources, governed by differences in survival and growth rate, that results in forest changes through time (i.e. stand development).The influence of soil in defining species and plant community distributions is well known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C5">Beadle 1954</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C53">Russo <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Soil pH governs many plant–soil chemical relations, particularly the availability of micronutrients and toxic ions, due to its influence on solubility. At low pH, the availability of essential micronutrients Fe, Mn, Cu and Zn is increased, as is the availability of potentially toxic Al and Mn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C2">Atwell <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Alternatively, the availability of P and Mo decreases. High-pH soils, however, are high in Cr, Co, Ni, Fe and Mg, and deficient in N, P, K and Ca (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C2">Atwell <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Plants with optimal growth and survival below and above pH 5–7 are known as acidophiles and calciphiles, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C22">Ehrenfeld <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>); these plants employ strategies to avoid or tolerate otherwise suboptimal conditions. For example, acidophiles avoid the stresses of nutrient deficiency by conservation of minerals via slow growth, high storage in seeds, high root surface area and relationships with rhizosphere microorganisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C41">Marschner 1991</xref>). Soil pH can also influence plant community dynamics: low pH can prevent invasion of exotic species into native acid-tolerant plant communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C55">Thompson <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>), while some species are apparently restricted to high-pH environments (e.g. ultramafics in New Caledonia; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C35">Jaffré 1992</xref>).Wollemi pine (<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic>, Araucariaceae) is a rare conifer with a highly restricted distribution. Araucariaceae is a family with origins in the early Triassic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C37">Kershaw and Wagstaff 2001</xref>), and the earliest fossil record of <italic>Wollemia</italic> is from 91 million years ago (<italic>Dilwynites</italic> pollen; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C40">Macphail <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>). <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> has unique architecture with only first-order plagiotropic branches and is capable of producing multiple stems without injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C31">Hill 1997</xref>). The plagiotropic branches can grow up to 150 cm long and are shed whole, forming a dense litter layer. Branches are short-lived (&lt;15 years) and have either adult or juvenile leaf types above and below the rainforest canopy, respectively. Wollemi pine grows in several small stands in the Wollemi National Park, part of the Greater Blue Mountains World Heritage area, New South Wales, Australia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C36">Jones <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C45">NSW Department of Environment and Conservation 2006</xref>). Wollemi National Park has predominantly sandstone geology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C36">Jones <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>), which is typically associated with acid soils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C9">Binkley and Fisher 2000</xref>). <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> exists at the base, and on low terraces, of deep narrow canyons within a warm temperate rainforest community with co-dominant <italic>Ceratopetalum apetalum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C6">Benson and Allen 2007</xref>). Recruitment from seed to adult is rare, even though seed production is relatively high (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C45">NSW Department of Environment and Conservation 2006</xref>). Fewer than 100 adult trees have been discovered, and some 300 seedlings have been observed, the majority under 500-mm stem length. Height growth of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings is very slow in the wild (5–20 mm per year; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C66">Zimmer <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The presence of seedlings indicates that <italic>W. nobilis</italic> is capable of producing viable seed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C48">Offord <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). Yet lack of intermediate-sized trees (i.e. 5–20 m) and slow growth indicates that there are other factors limiting their establishment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C64">Whitmore and Page 1980</xref>).The overarching aim of this study was to explore the relative importance of light and soil pH in determining <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedling success. To do this we investigated <italic>W. nobilis</italic> growth in response to the natural light and soil pH conditions where <italic>W. nobilis</italic> grows in the wild, and then to a wider range of light and pH conditions, in a glasshouse experiment.A preliminary study of the soil characteristics associated with the areas in which <italic>W. nobilis</italic> grows indicated that the pH is very acidic (∼pH 4) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C45">NSW Department of Environment and Conservation 2006</xref>). Soil samples (10 × 500 g) were collected adjacent to <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings growing in the wild. Soil pH was measured in water 1 : 2.Photosynthetic photon flux density (PPFD) was measured around 42 <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings with a hand-held Licor quantum light meter around midday on two typical sunny days in summer. These were compared with full-sun light meter readings in nearby areas.<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> seeds collected from multiple trees in the wild were germinated in Petri dishes in growth cabinets set at 24 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C47">Offord and Meagher 2001</xref>). Freshly germinated seedlings were grown in 75-mm (0.44-L) pots containing steam-pasteurized peat and sand (1 : 2 v/v) at pH 4.5 or adjusted to pH 6.5 with lime and dolomite (1 : 1 w/w). When seedlings were 4–5 months of age they were potted in 140-mm (1.5-L) pots containing the same potting mix and pH treatments with the addition of the fertilizer Nutricote Total N<sub>13</sub> (13 : 5.7 : 10.8 N : P : K) 270 day type added to the mix at a rate of 3 g L<sup>−1</sup> prior to steam pasteurization (time zero). Pasteurization was undertaken such that it did not affect fertilizer release rates (temperatures did not exceed 60 °C for &gt;30 min). Plants were fertilized and re-potted after the 12-month assessment. Plants were watered daily or as needed.In a glasshouse at the Australian Botanic Garden, Mount Annan (ABGMA, 34°05′S, 150°47′E), plants were randomly assigned to areas with 5, 15 or 50 % full sunlight (low, medium or high relative light). This was achieved by using different grades of shade cloth with the same wavelength transmission properties, in addition to light attenuated by the glasshouse. The light at plant level relative to ambient was determined using a pyranometer (Environdata P/L). The temperatures within the glasshouse were controlled to a mean of 24 °C (standard error [SE] = 3 °C) during the day and 16 °C (SE = 3 °C) at night. There were 20 replicate potted plants of each light and pH treatment combination (in a full factorial design). Plants were randomly positioned, and randomly re-positioned after each measurement, within each light treatment.Average daily PAR (mol m<sup>−2</sup>) received at the Australian Botanic Garden Mount Annan (5-year average 1998–2002) (error bars = SE).At 24 months four leaf samples taken from the new leaves of three plants per treatment combination were analysed for chlorophyll (chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> and chlorophyll <italic>b</italic>, protochlorophyll) and carotenoids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C14">Chen <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>).Two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was conducted on all variables (SYSTAT; SPSS Inc.). Where there were no significant interactions, <italic>post hoc</italic> tests, specifically least significant difference (LSD), were undertaken. Where significant interactions were found, one-way ANOVAs and/or <italic>t</italic>-tests were conducted on the variables, and these results, and associated LSDs, were reported. Data for stem and branch number were log-transformed to normalize the data for analysis. Untransformed data are presented in the tables.Mean soil pH in the field was 4.32 (SE = 0.12, <italic>n</italic> = 10) in water. Light levels at <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings in the field were highly variable and were as low as 1 % of full sunlight even at the brightest time of the day. Light penetration into the canyon was restricted by its depth, the angle of the sun and the dense canopy of other tree species growing within it. On the canyon floor, PPFD at approximately midday on a sunny day in February averaged 60 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> (SE = 9, <italic>n</italic> = 43), which represents around 3 % of full sunlight measured in adjacent open areas (mean = 2000 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, SE = 163, <italic>n</italic> = 4).Analysis of variance of measured <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedling characters (growth and leaf pigment) according to treatment variables (light and pH). Where there were significant interactions between the treatments, simple main effects are presented (lower table). **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; NS, not significant; <sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic> = 0.050.Growth characteristics of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings grown at low, medium and high light in potting mix at pH 4.5 or 6.5 for 24 months<italic>.</italic> (A) Stem length, (B) stem diameter and (C) stem count means taken across combined light and pH treatments (±SE). (D) Mean branch count is presented separately for (i) light treatments and (ii) pH treatments (±SE). Within each response variable, means sharing the same letter are not significantly different by LSD<sub>5%</sub>. Note: <italic>y</italic>-axis varies.No significant interactions between light and pH were detected for the pigment concentrations (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU011TB1">1</xref>). The concentrations of chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>, chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> + <italic>b</italic> and chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>/<italic>b</italic> were significantly associated with light (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU011TB1">1</xref>). Chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> and chlorophyll <italic>b</italic> were higher in low light. The highest chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> + <italic>b</italic> concentration was in plants under the higher light treatments. The chlorophyll <italic>a</italic>/<italic>b</italic> ratio was also significantly higher at low and medium light.Pigment concentration (μg cm<sup>−2</sup>) or ratio in leaves of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings grown at low, medium and high light in potting mix at pH 4.5 or 6.5 for 24 months (mean ± SE). (A–F) Means for pH and light treatments (means sharing the same letter are not significantly different by LSD<sub>5%</sub>). Note: <italic>y</italic>-axis varies.<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> is an acidophile. Growth of seedlings was maximal at a soil pH considered suboptimal for many species (pH 4.5; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C29">Handreck and Black 2002</xref>). <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> growth also increased with increased light, but this response was moderated by pH—higher pH resulted in growth suppression. Moreover, the chlorophyll content (chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> + <italic>b</italic>) of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> leaves was higher in the low soil pH treatments, indicating increased growth and, perhaps, potential for growth.Acid soils are a feature of natural stands of Araucariaceae, particularly <italic>Agathis australis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C42">Mirams 1957</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C8">Bieleski 1959</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C21">Ecroyd 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C60">Weaver 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C65">Wyse 2012</xref>), and Araucariaceae plantations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C15">Curlevski <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Changes in soil acidity under different plants can be due to differences among species in nutrient accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C1">Alban 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C26">Finzi <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>), nitrogen fixation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C58">van Miegroet and Cole 1984</xref>), litter chemical composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C50">Ovington 1953</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C1">Alban 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C26">Finzi <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>) and the stimulation of mineral weathering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C56">Tice <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>). The source of acid soils associated with Araucariaceae is hypothesized to be litterfall (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C8">Bieleski 1959</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C54">Silvester and Orchard 1999</xref>). Acid soils (pH &lt; 7) are also common in eastern New South Wales, but soils of pH ≤4.5 are much less common (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C30">Helyar <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>). Sandstone-derived soils are also typically acidic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C9">Binkley and Fisher 2000</xref>). Because we did not test the soils beyond the <italic>W. nobilis</italic> stand, we cannot say what effect (if any) <italic>W. nobilis</italic> has on the soil. Instead, our results suggest that low pH, and associated changes in soil nutrients, is likely to be a major factor in enhancing the growth of established <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings. Indeed, low pH may also indirectly benefit <italic>W. nobilis</italic> by reducing competition from other species not adapted to acid soils.<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> seedling growth increased with increasing light availability. Seedling growth was suppressed by low light (5 %), resulting in stem lengths half that attained by the high-light (50 %) treatment at 24 months. Previous studies have demonstrated that rainforest species, including <italic>C. apetalum</italic>, have lower growth at high light, but higher mean biomass accumulation at low light, when compared with eucalypt or ecotone species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C4">Barrett and Ash 1992</xref>). This study revealed that while stem length increased with increased light, the number of stems was highest in medium light. We hypothesize that this species has a low-light strategy of producing more stems and a high-light (i.e. large gap) strategy to invest more in growth of primary stems. However, it appears that multiple stem production in low light increases substantially above a threshold light level, between 5 and 15 %; this threshold is yet to be defined.<italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> seedlings respond to increased light by increasing growth, but they can also grow slowly and survive in low light. In low light, <italic>W. nobilis</italic> can maintain its photosynthetic apparatus in a state in which it can take advantage of changes in light levels, indicated by the chlorophyll pigment concentrations and ratio. However very low light (and associated low growth) in the wild may contribute to seedling mortality by fungal pathogens, herbivory, litterfall and drought, in line with models of increased juvenile risk in slow-growing species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C10">Bond 1989</xref>).Young <italic>W. nobilis</italic> leaves are adapted to shaded understorey conditions, maximizing light interception by arranging leaves in a single plane, while adult foliage is arranged in two ranks to capture light from all around (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C32">Hill and Brodribb 2003</xref>). Moreover, <italic>W. nobilis</italic> juveniles had a high proportion of branches to stems; this is typical of many understorey species, and demonstrates structural flexibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C27">Givnish 1988</xref>). This study indicates that <italic>W. nobilis</italic> has the ability to produce multiple leaders at all light levels, but particularly at medium-light and low-pH soil growth conditions. The difference among light treatments, in the production of multiple stems, was only apparent at the 24-month measurement (compared with the 12-month measurement; data not presented). This is comparable to the growth lag phase, which has been observed previously in <italic>W. nobilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C48">Offord <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). Hence, <italic>W. nobilis</italic> can take advantage of light gaps by extending leaders, in effect seeking light and then producing the branches at a later time to maximize growth in the gap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C27">Givnish 1988</xref>).The maximum light treatment used in our study was 50 %, rather than 100 %, full sun. Previous research has shown that young <italic>Agathis</italic> trees can be damaged by full sunlight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C61">Whitmore 1977</xref>), and along with other temperate rainforest species, <italic>Agathis</italic> have been shown to have lower chlorophyll concentrations in full sunlight compared with trees grown in medium and heavy shade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C39">Langenheim <italic>et al.</italic> 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C51">Read 1985</xref>). Moreover, photoinhibition may occur before obvious leaf damage. <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> is highly susceptible to heat stress (compared with other Araucariaceae species; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C46">Offord 2011</xref>), and anecdotal observations of young <italic>W. nobilis</italic> (&lt;5 years) suggest that the leaves can become chlorotic under full sun. The quality of light in the canopy, especially the ratio of red to far red, may also influence the growth of shade-adapted <italic>Agathis</italic> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C59">Warrington <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>). Although this study has found a positive correlation between light and growth in <italic>W. nobilis</italic> seedlings, this effect is likely to be curtailed at higher light availabilities due to light saturation.The positive effects of light on growth were moderated by pH. Growth of stems (height and diameter), and stem number, was highest in the low-pH treatments, regardless of light. In contrast, in the high-pH treatments, increased light was associated with increased growth. While both pH and light affected pigments, there was no modulating effect detected. Over the range of light availabilities assessed, the chlorophyll content and the <italic>a</italic> to <italic>b</italic> ratio varied little, compared with the variation associated with pH. Protochlorophyll is a precursor to chlorophyll and is readily converted with light exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C38">Lancer <italic>et al.</italic> 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C34">Huq <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Protochlorophyll was significantly higher in the low-pH treatment. The direct effects of pH on protochlorophyll are unknown, but low levels (in the high-pH treatment) suggest that the plants would be less able to take advantage of increases in light. Higher carotenoid-to-chlorophyll ratios in the high-pH treatment may also reflect growth suppression. Soil fertility (influenced by pH) can also affect plants' capacity to capture light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C3">Baltzer and Thomas 2005</xref>). However, the combined effects of light and pH were not significant in defining pigment concentrations in this study.The need for open canopy conditions, with &gt;10 % light (i.e. large canopy gaps), for recruitment of juveniles to canopy trees is evident in a number of Araucariaceae species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C7">Bergin and Kimberley 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C23">Enright <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C25">Fincke and Paulsch 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C52">Rigg <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Furthermore, infrequent large-scale landscape disturbance is required for substantial recruitment of other Araucariaceae species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C49">Ogden <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C11">Burns 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C24">Enright <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). Likewise, very low rates of seedling recruitment are a feature of mature undisturbed Araucariaceae stands (in association with increasing dominance of angiosperm tree species; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C24">Enright <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). The demonstrated increase in <italic>W. nobilis</italic> growth with light availability is consistent with growth responses observed in other Araucariaceae species.Our results imply that canopy gaps may be required for significant increases in stem length and hence recruitment from <italic>W. nobilis</italic> juveniles to canopy trees. How much light required is unknown, but positive responses to 50 % light availability (i.e. large gaps) were recorded in this study. If <italic>W. nobilis</italic> growth and recruitment to larger size classes is dependent on light, this may explain the lack of intermediate-sized <italic>W. nobilis</italic> juveniles in the wild, where <italic>W. nobilis</italic> is competing with rainforest angiosperms (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C24">Enright <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). <italic>Wollemia nobilis</italic> response to increased light availability after long-term suppression in the shade is also unknown. The self-coppicing habit of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> allows it to survive in low light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C27">Givnish 1988</xref>) and may aid recovery from disturbance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C18">Dietze and Clark 2008</xref>). Its architecture may also mean that it can respond quickly (change morphologically) to intercept light (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C12">Canham 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C62">Whitmore 1989</xref>), similar to <italic>A. angustifolia</italic>, which can quickly colonize gaps from both seedling banks and resprouts of damaged trees via plastic growth patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C20">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>).The ability of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> to respond to increased light was strongly moderated by soil pH. Although there is evidence to suggest that Araucariaceae can modify soil pH, we suggest that pH is unlikely to be limiting <italic>W. nobilis</italic> success in the wild as acid soils are widespread in eastern New South Wales; hence the question remains, what factors limit the distribution of <italic>W. nobilis</italic> in the wild? Despite the strong limiting effect of pH on growth demonstrated in this study, light availability (i.e. the presence of large canopy gaps) may be more limiting in the wild.Understanding the climatic and edaphic factors governing plant growth is important for the conservation management of species in the wild, and especially species like <italic>W. nobilis</italic> that have restricted distributions and are under threats such as disease, fire and climate change. Where management of wild stands cannot provide sufficient protection, translocation of threatened species is one complementary conservation measure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C57">Vallee <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Selection of suitable soil types and light regimes provided by topography, aspect and vegetation assemblages is essential to translocation success. Additionally, optimal growth of plants <italic>ex situ</italic>, in gardens or germplasm collections, necessitates knowledge of fundamental growth requirements. This and several other studies partially provide this knowledge for <italic>W. nobilis</italic> (vide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU011C46">Offord 2011</xref>). Importantly, our results indicate that <italic>W. nobilis</italic> recruitment may be light limited in the wild. Our results also suggest that <italic>W. nobilis</italic> translocation efforts should be focused on sites with low-pH soils and outside the deeply shaded conditions of a closed rainforest.Seedling growth responses to varying light regimes suggest that <italic>W. nobilis</italic> is a shade-tolerant, gap-responding species: tolerating low light and increasing growth at higher light. However, this response is strongly moderated by soil pH; <italic>W. nobilis</italic> growth is significantly enhanced on low-pH soils. While these factors clearly influence seedling growth of this species, at least under glasshouse conditions, other factors, such as drought, herbivory and microbial interactions, may also strongly influence the recruitment of this species in the wild.Our work was funded by the Royal Botanic Gardens and Domain Trust, Sydney.C.O. and P.M. were responsible for the experimental design. P.M. conducted the experimental components including data collection. C.O. and H.Z. analysed data and wrote the manuscript.None declared.The authors wish to acknowledge the input of Faye Cairncross, Felicity Keiper, Graeme Errington, Glen Fensom, the Sydney Environment and Soil Laboratory and the staff of the NSW National Parks and Wildlife Service.