The use of haemoglobin concentrations to assess physiological condition in birds: a reviewLittle evidence that condition, stress indicators, sex ratio, or homozygosity are related to landscape or habitat attributes in declining woodland birdsHematological investigations of captive Hill Mynah <italic>Gracula religiosa</italic> in ThailandDevelopment of some aspects of blood oxygen transport in nestling short-tailed shearwatersUsing haematological parameters to infer the health and nutritional status of an endangered black-necked swan populationNew aspects on migratory physiology of trans-Saharan passerine migrantsHabitat and year-to-year variation in haemoglobin concentration in nestling blue tits <italic>Cyanistes caeruleus</italic>Effects of brood size manipulation on physiological condition of nestling Blue Tits <italic>Cyanistes caeruleus</italic>Body condition parameters of nestling Great Tits <italic>Parus major</italic> in relation to experimental food supplementationBlood hemoglobin content and metabolic performance of Arctic Tern chicks <italic>Sterna paradisaea</italic>Reproductive parameters of adult birds and morphophysiological characteristics of chicks in the pied flycatcher (<italic>Ficedula hypoleuca</italic> Pall.) in technogenically polluted habitatsEstrogen-induced apoptosis by inhibition of the erythroid transcription factor GATA-1Haematological changes during development of the noisy miner: implications for oxygen transportHematological responses to hematozoa in North American and neotropical songbirdsSeasonal variation in body mass and blood oxygen carrying capacity of the superb fairy-wren (<italic>Malurus cyaneus</italic>)The external parasites of birds: a reviewHematological and body-mass changes of small passerines overwintering in South-Eastern AustraliaAssessing body condition in birdsEffect of brood size manipulation on offspring physiology: an experiment with passerine birdsCytologyEctoparasites affect hemoglobin and percentages of immature erythrocytes but not hematocrit in nestling eastern bluebirdsSome blood characteristics of White-crowned Sparrows during moltEffect of biologically active plants used as nest material and the derived benefit to starling nestlingsEffect of estrogen on rate of <sup>59</sup>Fe uptake by hematopoietic tissue in Japanese quailIn superb fairy wrens (<italic>Malurus cyaneus</italic>), nuptial males have more blood parasites and higher haemoglobin concentration than eclipsed malesMaking conservation physiology relevant to policy makers and conservation practitionersConservation physiology: perspectives on an increasingly integrated and essential scienceMigratory carryover effects and endocrinological correlates of reproductive decisions and reproductive success in female albatrossesPostmigratory body condition and ovarian steroid production predict breeding decisions by female gray-headed albatrossesVariation during breeding in parameters that influence blood oxygen carrying capacity in shearwatersAre avian hematocrits indicative of condition? American kestrel as a modelEcology of parasitism of nestling American kestrels by <italic>Carnus hemapterus</italic> (Diptera: Carnidae)Changes in the blood and plasma volume of Harris&apos; sparrows during postnuptial moltSeasonal changes in the blood composition of captive and free-living white-crowned sparrowsHematological and blood chemical values of mallard, <italic>Anas p. platyrhynchos</italic>, drakes before, during and after remige moultEffects of the introduced ectoparasite <italic>Philornis downsi</italic> on haemoglobin level and nestling survival in Darwin&apos;s small ground finch (<italic>Geospiza fuliginosa</italic>)Blood parasites, health, reproductive success, and egg volume in female Great Tits <italic>Parus major</italic>Maternal effects of egg size on emu <italic>Dromaius novaehollandiae</italic> egg composition and hatchling phenotypeBiomarkers and fluctuating asymmetry as indicators of pollution-induced stress in two hole-nesting passerinesSources of variation in haematocrit in birdsAn experimental study on the effects of an introduced parasite in Darwin&apos;s finchesSexual differences in blood values of the pigeon, <italic>Columba livia</italic>Alteration in haematocrit values and plasma protein fractions during the breeding cycle of female pigeons, <italic>Columba livia</italic>Ectoparasitic blow flies (<italic>Protocalliphora</italic> sp.) and nestling Eastern Bluebirds (<italic>Sialia sialis</italic>): direct effects and compensatory strategiesReduced immunocompetence and cost of reproduction in common eidersHaematology of wild penguins (Spenisciformes) in the Falkland IslandsOxidative stress of House Sparrow as bioindicator of urban pollutionHaematological characteristics of response to inflammation or traumatic injury in two species of black cockatoos: <italic>Calyptorhynchus magnificus</italic> and <italic>C. funereus</italic>Parasites, morphology, and blood characters in male red jungle fowl during developmentEffects of haematophagous ectoparasites on nestling house wrens, <italic>Troglodytes aedon</italic>: who pays the cost of parasitism?Haematocrit values of breeding red-billed queleas <italic>Quelea quelea</italic> (Aves: Ploceidae) in relation to body condition and thymus activityHaemoglobin concentration and body condition of nestling Great Tits <italic>Parus major</italic>: a comparison of first and second broods in two contrasting seasonsWeak correlation between haemoglobin concentration and haematocrit of nestling Great Tits <italic>Parus major</italic> and Blue Tits <italic>P. caeruleus</italic>Parallel variation in haemoglobin concentration in nestling-rearing Blue Tits <italic>Cyanistes caeruleus</italic> and Great Tits <italic>Parus major</italic>Sex and other sources of variation in the haematological parameters of White Stork <italic>Ciconia ciconia</italic> chicksChanges in hematological parameters in free-living pigeons (<italic>Columba livia</italic> f. <italic>urbana</italic>) during the breeding cyclePrevalence and effect of helminthiasis on haematological parameters in the migratory sparrows (<italic>Alauda arvensis</italic>) and treatment with an antihelmintic, fenbendazoleThe ratio of amount of haemoglobin to total surface area of erythrocytes in birds in relation to body mass, age of nestlings and season of the yearThe ratio of amount of haemoglobin to total surface area of erythrocytes in mammalsThe changes in the values of red blood indices during the nestling development of the House Martin <italic>Delichon urbica</italic>Changes in respiratory function of the blood of nestling Tree Sparrows (<italic>Passer m. montanus</italic> L.) during their developmentChanges of the respiratory function of blood of nestling common sparrows <italic>Passer domesticus</italic> L. during their developmentChanges in the hematological values during the nestling period of the Great Tit (<italic>Parus major</italic> L.)Acute infection of avian malaria impairs concentration of haemoglobin and survival in juvenile altricial birdsBlood parameter changes during stopover in a long-distance migratory shorebird, the bar-tailed godwit <italic>Limosa lapponica taymyrensis</italic>Heinz-body hemolytic anemia from the ingestion of crude oil: a primary toxic effect in marine birdsAre haematocrit and haemoglobin concentration reliable body condition indicators in nestlings: the Welcome Swallows as a case studyAre haematocrit and haemoglobin concentration reliable indicators of body condition in adult Welcome Swallows?Blood chemistry and hematologic values in free-living nestlings of Montagu&apos;s Harriers (<italic>Circus pygargus</italic>) in a natural habitatHematological and parasitological health conditions of the Pale-breasted Thrush (<italic>Turdus leucomelas</italic>) (Passeriformes: Turdidae) in southeastern BrazilFirst report of establishment of <italic>Trypanosoma evansi</italic> infection in pigeon nestlings (<italic>Columba livia</italic>)Hematological and immunological properties of herring gull (<italic>Larus argentatus</italic>) nestlings experimentally infected with <italic>Diphyllobothrium dendriticum</italic> (Cestoda: Pseudophyllidae)Variation in body condition indices of crimson finches by sex, breeding stage, age, time of day, and year.High glucose concentrations are associated with symptoms of mild anaemia in Whiskered Terns: consequences for assessing physiological quality in birdsHemoglobin concentrations in waders vary with their strategies of migration: a comparative analysisLow oxygen-carrying capacity of blood may increase developmental instability of molt in migrating wadersEcological, physiological and morphological correlates of blood hemoglobin concentration in a migratory shorebirdHeterozygosity correlates with body size, nest site quality and productivity in a colonial waterbird, the whiskered tern (<italic>Chlidonias hybrida</italic>, Aves: Sternidae)Opposing selective pressures may act on the colony size in a waterbird speciesDevelopmental stability and fitness: a reviewMaternal energy expenditure does not change with flight costs or food availability for nestlingsActivity-related variation in blood parameters associated with oxygen transport and chronic stress in little penguinsDoes haemosporidian infection affect hematological and biochemical profiles of the endangered Black-fronted piping-guan (<italic>Aburria jacutinga</italic>)?Hematological studies on Antarctic birds. I. Hematological indices in some species of the birds studied during Australian summerBlood parameters as consistent predictors of nestling performance in great tits (<italic>Parus major</italic>) in the wildNutritional and feeding ecology in Cory&apos;s shearwater <italic>Calonectris diomedea</italic> during breedingHealth and nutritional status of a perturbed Black-necked Swan (<italic>Cygnus melanocoryphus</italic>) population: diet qualityDo ticks and <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> s.l. constitute a burden to birds?Assessing the effects of haematophagous ectoparasites on the health of nestling birds: haematocrit vs haemoglobin levels in House Wrens parasitized by blow fly larvaeDifferential rates of offspring provisioning in Gould&apos;s petrels: are better feeders better breedersAge, sexual and seasonal differences of haematological values and antibody status to <italic>Chlamydophila</italic> sp. in feral and racing pigeons (<italic>Columba livia</italic> forma <italic>domestica</italic>) from an urban environment (Zagreb, Croatia)Build-up of red blood cells in refuelling bar-tailed godwits in relation to individual migratory qualityDevelopment of diving capacity in Emperor PenguinsEnvironmental and genetic variation in the haematocrit of fledgling pied flycatchersBody condition and chronic stress in urban and rural Noisy MinersEffects of the haematophagous mite <italic>Ornithonyssus bursa</italic> on nestling starlings in New ZealandBlood oxygen transport properties during migration to higher altitude of wild quail, <italic>Coturnix coturnix coturnix</italic>The influence of moulting on blood parameters in the Starling <italic>Sturnus vulgaris</italic>Age-correlation of blood values in the rock pigeon (<italic>Columba livia</italic>)Socially mediated trade-offs between aggression and parental effort in competing color morphsMothers adjust offspring sex to match the quality of the rearing environmentContext-dependent sex allocation: constraints on the expression and evolution of maternal effectsCovariation in life-history traits: differential effects of diet on condition, hormones, behavior, and reproduction in genetic finch morphsHematology and plasma chemistry of house sparrows (<italic>Passer domesticus</italic>) along the summer months and after testosterone treatmentBody water dynamics at the onset of egg-laying in the zebra finch <italic>Taeniopygia guttata</italic>Effects of a dipteran ectoparasite on immune response and growth trade-offs in barn swallow, <italic>Hirundo rustica</italic>, nestlingsVitellogenin dynamics during egg-laying: daily variation, repeatability and relationship with egg sizeAge-related hematology and plasma chemistry changes in captive Masai ostriches (<italic>Struthio camelus massaicus</italic>)Recent advances in avian respirationInfluence of biological and ecological factors on hematological values in wild Little Penguins, <italic>Eudyptula minor</italic>A hematologic survey of captive waterfowlDevelopment of parameters influencing blood oxygen carrying capacity in the welcome swallow and fairy martinPhysiological ecology of Mediterranean blue tits: effects of ectoparasites (<italic>Protocalliphora</italic> spp.) and food abundance on metabolic capacity of nestlingsEffects of experimental reduction in nest micro-parasite and macro-parasite loads on nestling hemoglobin level in blue tits <italic>Parus caeruleus</italic>Use of portable blood physiology point-of-care devices for basic and applied research on vertebrates: a review.Seasonal variation of vascular oxygen transport in the Dark-eyed JuncoDensity-dependent processes in the population dynamics of a bird ectoparasite <italic>Ceratophyllus gallinae</italic>Relationship of hemoglobin concentration to packed cell volume in avian blood samplesHaematological parameters, mass and moult status in dunlins <italic>Calidris alpina</italic> preparing for spring migrationPhysiological condition and reproductive consequences in Ad&eacute;lie penguinsHematological changes associated with egg production: estrogen dependence and repeatabilityHematological changes associated with egg production: direct evidence for changes in erythropoiesis but a lack of resource dependence?Nonvertebrate hemoglobins: functions and molecular adaptationsPathogenicity of larval <italic>Protocalliphora</italic> (Diptera: Calliphoridae) parasitizing nestling birdsWhat causes the decrease in haematocrit during egg production?Laying-sequence-specific variation in yolk oestrogen levels, and relationship to plasma oestrogen in female zebra finches (<italic>Taeniopygia guttata</italic>)Female zebra finches (<italic>Taeniopygia guttata</italic>) are chronically but not cumulatively &lsquo;anemic&rsquo; during repeated egg laying in response to experimental nest predationWhat is individual quality? An evolutionary perspectiveErythropoietin depletion and anaemia in diabetes mellitus<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Total blood hemoglobin concentration is increasingly often used to assess physiological condition in wild birds, although its robustness has not been explicitly evaluated over a wide range of avian taxa. This review summarizes how reliable is hemoglobin concentration in assessing physiological condition and how it is related to various components of fitness and individual quality in birds.Total blood haemoglobin concentration is increasingly being used to assess physiological condition in wild birds, although it has not been explicitly recognized how reliably this parameter reflects different components of individual quality. Thus, I reviewed over 120 published studies linking variation in haemoglobin concentrations to different measures of condition and other phenotypic or ecological traits. In most of the studied avian species, haemoglobin concentrations were positively correlated with other commonly used indices of condition, such as body mass and fat loads, as well as with quality of the diet. Also, chick haemoglobin concentrations reliably reflected the intensity of nest infestation by parasitic arthropods, and haemoglobin was suggested to reflect parasitism by haematophagous ectoparasites much more precisely than haematocrit. There was also some evidence for the negative effect of helminths on haemoglobin levels in adult birds. Finally, haemoglobin concentrations were found to correlate with such fitness-related traits as timing of arrival at breeding grounds, timing of breeding, egg size, developmental stability and habitat quality, although these relationships were not always consistent between species. In consequence, I recommend the total blood haemoglobin concentration as a relatively robust indicator of physiological condition in birds, although this parameter is also strongly affected by age, season and the process of moult. Thus, researchers are advised to control fully for these confounding effects while using haemoglobin concentrations as a proxy of physiological condition in both experimental and field studies on birds.Although animal physiologists have long relied on different blood markers to assess animal&ndash;environment interactions, the measurement of physiological parameters of blood is now increasingly being adopted to explain ecological and evolutionary processes occurring within vertebrate populations. The wide application of physiological approaches in basic ecology provided a tool that became of key importance in solving conservation problems, which laid the foundation for a new discipline called conservation physiology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C25">Cooke and O&apos;Connor, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C26">Cooke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). One of the most common applications of physiological methods in ecological studies and wildlife surveillance is to assess different components of individual condition and health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C114">Stoot <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). While many blood physiological parameters have been proposed to serve as proxies of condition in birds (e.g. plasma concentrations of different metabolites, reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C17">Brown, 1996</xref>), there is little consensus on which markers are sufficiently robust to reflect varying physiological condition reliably across different avian taxa. Among others, total blood haemoglobin concentration (usually expressed as the mass of haemoglobin per unit of blood) was suggested to be a condition-dependent trait that may be related to fitness in birds (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C88">O&apos;Brien <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C6">Ba&nacute;bura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), but the generality of this pattern has not been evaluated explicitly.Haemoglobin is encountered in all five kingdoms of organisms, ranging from single-chain globins in bacteria, algae, protozoa and plants to large, multisubunit and multidomain molecules in some invertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C122">Weber and Vinogradov, 2001</xref>). In the animal kingdom, haemoglobin occurs widely but sporadically in non-vertebrate species, being found in some 33&percnt; of presently known animal classes. In vertebrates, total blood haemoglobin concentration is considered to be the most important determinant of oxygen-carrying capacity. Although in mammals the amount of oxygen supplied to the tissues per unit time (measured by the amount of haemoglobin per total surface area of erythrocytes) is of greater physiological importance than the oxygen-carrying capacity of the blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C58">Kostelecka-Myrcha, 2002</xref>), the opposite situation is found in birds. The amount of haemoglobin per total surface area of erythrocytes remains constant among all avian species, even in differing physiological and environmental situations, as the changes in the number and size of erythrocytes always proceed in proportion to the changes in haemoglobin concentration. Such an adaptation seems to be optimal for the process of blood oxygen saturation in the lungs of birds, which is maintained at a relatively constant rate via the presence of air sacs and the cross-current exchange of gas between the air and the blood in the pulmonary capillaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C108">Schmidt-Nielsen, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C57">Kostelecka-Myrcha, 1997</xref>). Taking all this into account, the total blood haemoglobin concentration most appropriately reflects the potential of an avian organism to satisfy its oxygen requirements.In consequence, high concentrations of haemoglobin improve aerobic capacity, whereas low concentrations are associated with the poor states of regenerative or non-regenerative anaemias. In birds, regenerative anaemias are usually caused by haemorrhage and haemolysis, most commonly attributed to parasitism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C15">Boyd, 1951</xref>), injuries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C47">Jaensch and Clark, 2004</xref>) and intoxication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C65">Leighton <italic>et al.</italic>, 1983</xref>). In this kind of anaemia, the reductions in blood oxygen-carrying capacity typically result in increased erythropoiesis, resulting in the rapid production of large quantities of immature red blood cells (reticulocytes). In contrast, non-regenerative anaemias (with no response of bone marrow to the increased need for erythrocytes) are caused by chronic diseases, but also from nutritional deficiencies or starvation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C44">Harrison and Harrison, 1986</xref>). For these reasons, haemoglobin concentration has been proposed as a robust indicator of physiological condition in birds (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C6">Ba&nacute;bura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and is increasingly being used to assess individual quality (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C129">Wilson and Nussey, 2010</xref>) in this group of vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C101">Pryke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C28">Crossin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C78">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015b</xref>).The physiological condition of birds has also been commonly assessed using haematocrit (packed cell volume), which is the percentage of blood volume occupied by erythrocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C44">Harrison and Harrison, 1986</xref>). However, reliability of haematocrit as a general measure of condition has recently been questioned. It has been acknowledged that haematocrit may not accurately reflect the concentration of erythrocytes in the blood, because it depends largely on the size of erythrocytes, and thus, it may not represent well the physiological condition of birds and other vertebrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C39">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). In fact, haematocrit was shown not to be condition dependent in some of the studied avian species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C30">Dawson and Bortolotti, 1997a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C43">Hanssen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C37">Dzialowski and Sotherland, 2004</xref>). Consequently, alternative haematological parameters, including total blood haemoglobin concentration, have been proposed as potentially more reliable indicators of physiological condition and health in birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C88">O&apos;Brien <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Although haematocrit and haemoglobin concentrations are expected to be correlated in birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C117">Velguth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), the strength of this correlation may be weak, because both parameters show different sensitivity to ecological factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C52">Kali&nacute;ski, <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). In fact, haematocrit and haemoglobin concentration are based on different biological principles (blood cytology and blood biochemistry, respectively), and consequently, they may be indicative of different environmental and physiological processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C6">Ba&nacute;bura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).The aim of this review was to evaluate whether total blood haemoglobin concentration may be used reliably as an indicator of physiological condition in birds. The second objective of the study was to identify phenotypic and ecological factors that could affect haemoglobin concentrations, potentially reducing its applicability as a proxy of individual quality. For these purposes, I reviewed over 120 published studies linking variation in haemoglobin concentrations to age, sex, season, moult, nutritional state/condition, parasitism and other fitness-related traits.Data on the changes in haemoglobin concentration throughout the post-hatching development of chicks were collected for 20 avian species (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cov007/-/DC1">Supplementary material Table S1</ext-link>), mainly passerines (10 species) and seabirds (five species). All the studies that covered the entire period of chick development showed increases in haemoglobin concentration from hatching to fledging. Such patterns result from the process of haematopoiesis (production of blood cellular components) taking place in the liver, spleen and bone marrow, which starts at the embryonic stage of development and continues after hatching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C19">Campbell, 1994</xref>). There was, however, considerable variation in developmental patterns of blood oxygen-carrying capacity between species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C111">Simmons and Lill, 2006</xref>). In most altricial species, haemoglobin concentration tends to increase in a linear manner throughout nestling development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C60">Kostelecka-Myrcha <italic>et al.</italic>, 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C61">1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C62">1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C12">Bolton <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). In some other altricial species (e.g. in Hirundininae) and some precocial species, haemoglobin concentration changes in a non-linear manner, because it increases rapidly during first days after hatching and thereafter the rate of change gradually slows down (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C59">Kostelecka-Myrcha and Jaroszewicz, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C111">Simmons and Lill, 2006</xref>). In these species, peak values of haemoglobin concentrations may be attained well before fledging and, afterwards, they decrease slightly to reach the adult level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C111">Simmons and Lill, 2006</xref>). In contrast, the haemoglobin concentration in Procellariiformes shows an initial decrease, which is followed by relative stability during the most intensive growth period, and it starts to increase rapidly during mass recession, i.e. the period of body mass loss before fledging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C3">Arnold <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C89">O&apos;Dwyer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Similar patterns were also recorded in other seabirds, e.g. a slight decrease in haemoglobin concentration was found in Arctic tern (<italic>Sterna paradisea</italic>) chicks during the first days after hatching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C9">Bech and Klaassen, 1996</xref>).It seems that in many species the haemoglobin concentration attained at the time of fledgling increases gradually until adulthood. In most of the analysed species (72.2&percnt;), adult individuals were reported to have a significantly higher haemoglobin concentration in comparison to juveniles. Only one study on captive Masai ostriches (<italic>Struthio camelus</italic>) investigated changes in haemoglobin concentration throughout the entire first year of life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C107">Samour <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The authors demonstrated that the haemoglobin concentration initially decreased slightly, but from the third month of life it started to increase at a constant rate until the age of at least 1&emsp14;year, with the total increase being &sim;40&percnt; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C107">Samour <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Such patterns of changes may be characteristic for long-lived species with a long period of development. In fact, the only two studies on short-lived passerines found no differences in haemoglobin concentration between juveniles and adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C103">Puerta <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C2">Archawaranon, 2005</xref>). There is little empirical data on the changes in haemoglobin concentration during the period of adulthood in birds. While three of four studied species showed no clear patterns of changes in haemoglobin concentrations throughout adulthood (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV007TB1">1</xref>), the study on feral pigeons (<italic>Columba livia</italic> f. <italic>domestica</italic>) demonstrated a significant decrease in haemoglobin concentration after the ninth year of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C98">Prinzinger and Misovic, 2010</xref>). In conclusion, more data are needed to establish the patterns of haemoglobin changes with age.<table-wrap id="COV007TB1" position="float"><label>Table 1:</label><caption><p>Seasonal changes of haemoglobin concentrations in birdsAbbreviations: ANS, Anseriformes; CHA, Charadriiformes; COL, Columbiformes; PAS, Passeriformes; PRO, Procellariiformes. Studies conducted in captivity are marked with an asterisk. Results valid for females only are marked with an &lsquo;F&rsquo;. <sup>a</sup>Brown thornbill (<italic>Acanthiza pusilla</italic>), red-browed firetail (<italic>Emblema temporalis</italic>), eastern yellow robin (<italic>Eopsaltria australis</italic>) and superb fairywren (<italic>Malurus cyaneus</italic>).Data on differences in haemoglobin concentration between sexes in adult birds were available for 36 species (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cov007/-/DC1">Supplementary material Table S2</ext-link>), mainly Charadriiformes (nine species) and Passeriformes (six species). In the large majority of species (86.1&percnt;), there was no significant difference between the sexes in the haemoglobin concentration of adult individuals, and this conclusion is consistent with the general patterns recorded for haematocrit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C39">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). In species where between-sex differences in haemoglobin concentration were found, females tended to have higher levels of haemoglobin, as found in two passerine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C53">Kali&nacute;ski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) and one procellariiform species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C83">Myrcha and Kostelecka-Myrcha, 1980</xref>). A higher haemoglobin concentration in males compared with females was found in only one study on feral pigeons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C41">Gayathri and Hegde, 1994</xref>), but two other studies on this species did not confirm the observation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C90">Pavlak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C55">Kasprzak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).Thus, it seems that any observed differences in haemoglobin concentrations between sexes may result primarily from temporal physiological processes associated with reproduction or moulting. In fact, a study on the crimson finch (<italic>Neochmia phaeton</italic>) indicated that such differences may appear only during specific reproductive stages, such as egg laying or incubation, although in general males and females have similar haemoglobin concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C72">Milenkaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Between-sex differences in haemoglobin concentration were found relatively often in nestlings, but it seems likely that these patterns could result largely from the different ages of male and female chicks sampled for the analyses.Decreasing haemoglobin concentrations during egg laying were recorded in females of at least two bird species (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV007TB1">1</xref>). Similar symptoms of anaemia during egg production, indicated by reduced haematocrit, have been documented in a wider range of avian taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C33">DeGraw <italic>et al.</italic>, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C50">Jones, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C128">Gayathri and Hegde, 2006</xref>). The exact mechanisms responsible for these changes have not been explicitly recognized, and a few non-exclusive explanations have been proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C124">Williams, 2004</xref>). A reduction in haemoglobin concentration during egg laying was hypothesized to result from transient suppression of erythropoiesis, so that energy for red blood cell production could be redirected to meet the elevated metabolic demands of the reproductive organs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C50">Jones, 1983</xref>) and because components normally allocated to erythropoiesis could be required for egg production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C128">Gayathri and Hegde, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C55">Kasprzak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Decreased haemoglobin concentration during egg laying may also be caused by the production of yolk precursors and concurrent osmoregulatory adjustments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C106">Salvante and Williams, 2002</xref>), which trigger an increase in plasma volume (haemodilution) due to osmotic movement of water from extracellular spaces into the blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C104">Reynolds and Waldron, 1999</xref>). In such circumstances, the haematocrit and blood haemoglobin concentration would be decreased, although the number of red blood cells would remain constant. Finally, anaemia during egg production may develop as a consequence of elevated levels of oestrogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C125">Williams <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C120">Wagner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008a</xref>), which suppress haematopoiesis by inhibiting proliferation and survival of blood cell precursors in bone marrow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C23">Clermont and Schrar, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C11">Blobel and Orkin, 1996</xref>). In spite of these predictions, one of the studies on female feral pigeons showed an increased haemoglobin concentration during the period of egg laying, but this pattern was attributed to dehydration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C55">Kasprzak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Likewise, there was no pronounced decrease in haemoglobin concentrations of two procellariiform species during the egg-laying phase when compared with the pre-laying period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C29">Davey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C85">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). In these species, levels of haemoglobin increased at a constant rate from the pre-laying to the chick-rearing period, which was attributed to the high costs of the very long foraging trips undertaken by parents when feeding nestlings and the preparation for migration that is undertaken soon after the conclusion of reproductive activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C29">Davey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>).Migratory behaviour was, indeed, found to have a strong effect on haemoglobin concentration in birds. For example, haemoglobin concentrations increased considerably over the migratory period in two studied wader species, which was associated with increasing fat loads necessary for long-distance flights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C91">Piersma <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C76">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). In other avian taxa, a requirement for improved oxygen-carrying capacity during migration was suggested by elevated haematocrit levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C5">Bairlein and Totzke, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C96">Prats <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>). In contrast, changes in haemoglobin concentration during the autumn period proceeded in a different manner in non-migratory species. In the superb fairywren (<italic>Malurus cyaneus</italic>), haemoglobin concentration was found to decrease from summer to winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C14">Box <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), although the other study on this species found no changes over autumn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C16">Breuer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). In other non-migratory passerine species, there were no changes in haemoglobin levels between seasons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C16">Breuer <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). There is also little empirical support for increased haemoglobin concentrations during winter. It has been hypothesized that birds should have the highest oxygen-carrying capacity of blood during winter period, because oxygen uptake should be elevated during increased thermogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C115">Swanson, 1990</xref>). The only evidence for such relationships comes from free-living feral pigeons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C90">Pavlak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and noisy miners (<italic>Manorina melanocephala</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C94">Powell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), as well as from captive waterfowl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C110">Shave and Howard, 1976</xref>).Changes of haemoglobin concentrations in response to moult in birdsAbbreviations: ANS, Anseriformes; CHA, Charadriiformes; COL, Columbiformes; PAS, Passeriformes; SPH, Spenisciformes. Studies conducted in captivity are marked with an asterisk.Decreased haemoglobin levels at the beginning of moult were recorded for young (partial post-juvenile moult) and adult (complete post-breeding moult) common snipe (<italic>Gallinago gallinago</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C76">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). However, post-breeding moult in this species was associated with much greater change in haemoglobin concentration. Adult snipe had 12&percnt; higher haemoglobin concentrations after moult compared with birds at the beginning of moult. In contrast, the haemoglobin concentration of juvenile snipe decreased by only 2&percnt; at the beginning of post-juvenile moult (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C76">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).Despite the fact that most of the studies indicated lower haemoglobin concentrations during moult, some exceptions to this general pattern were also observed. In two species, no moult-related changes in haemoglobin concentration were recorded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C45">Hawkey <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C97">Prinzinger and Hakimi, 1997</xref>). In bar-tailed godwits (<italic>Limosa lapponica</italic>), individuals moulting breast feathers at a spring stopover site had a higher haemoglobin concentration in comparison to non-moulting individuals; however, early moult of body feathers was associated with high individual quality, so this relationship could be purely correlative in nature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C91">Piersma <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>).Relationships of haemoglobin concentrations with different measures of nutritional state and condition in birdsAbbreviations: Ad., adult; CHA, Charadriiformes; CHOL, cholesterol; GL, glucose; Juv., juvenile; PAS, Passeriformes; PRO, Procellariiformes; Pull., pullus; SPH, Sphenisciformes; TG, triglycerides; TP, total protein; UA, uric acid; UR, urea. Studies conducted in captivity are marked with an asterisk. Note: &lsquo;&plus;&rsquo; indicates a positive relationship; &lsquo;&minus;&rsquo; indicates a negative relationship; and &lsquo;(&minus;)&rsquo; indicates no relationship. <sup>a</sup>Common sandpiper (<italic>Actitis hypoleucos</italic>), dunlin (<italic>Calidris alpina</italic>), common snipe (<italic>Gallinago gallinago</italic>), ruff (<italic>Philomachus pugnax</italic>), spotted redshank (<italic>Tringa erythropus</italic>) and green sandpiper (<italic>Tringa ochropus</italic>).Strong support for the reliability of haemoglobin concentrations as a predictor of condition comes from experimental studies on captive passerines, where haemoglobin concentration was positively affected by the quality of diet in both nestlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C101">Pryke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C100">Pryke and Rollins, 2012</xref>) and adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C102">Pryke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In contrast, the only one study on captive zebra finches (<italic>Taeniopygia guttata</italic>) showed no effect of diet on haemoglobin concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C121">Wagner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008b</xref>). No effect of food supplementation on haemoglobin concentration was also found for a free-living population of great tits (<italic>Parus major</italic>), although it was probably due to non-restrictive abundance of natural food resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C8">Ba&nacute;bura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). It must be acknowledged, however, that haemoglobin concentration may not provide a good indication of body condition during serious dehydration of an organism, as was shown for fasting Ad&eacute;lie penguins (<italic>Pygoscelis adeliae</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C119">Vleck and Vleck, 2002</xref>).Much less consistent are relationships between the concentrations of haemoglobin and different plasma metabolites. The only reported positive correlations were found for the common snipe, where haemoglobin concentration was correlated with the plasma concentration of total proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C76">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). No significant relationships were found in other species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C85">Navarro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C72">Milenkaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), and in the whiskered tern (<italic>Chlidonias hybrida</italic>) a negative correlation between haemoglobin concentration and plasma glucose level was recorded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C73">Minias, 2014</xref>); this pattern was attributed to the oxidative stress associated with hyperglycaemia, which may reduce synthesis of erythropoietin, a hormone responsible for red blood cell production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C127">Winkler, <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>).Changes of haemoglobin concentrations in response to parasite pressure in birdsAbbreviations: Ad., adult; CHA, Charadriiformes; COL, Columbiformes; GAL, Galliformes; Juv., juvenile; PAS, Passeriformes; Pull., pullus; SPH, Sphenisciformes. Studies conducted in captivity are marked with an asterisk. Note: &lsquo;&minus;&rsquo; indicates a decrease in haemoglobin concentration; and &lsquo;(&minus;)&rsquo; indicates no change in haemoglobin concentration.In contrast, the response of nestling haematocrit to the parasitism by nest arthropods follows no clear pattern (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C39">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Although some of the studies indicated a negative impact of parasitic burden on chick haematocrit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C80">Moreno <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C93">Potti <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C112">Simon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), a relatively large number of the studied species did not show any significant relationships. It has been reported that parasitism by <italic>Carnus haemapterus</italic> (Diptera: Carnidae) had no effect on haematocrit of American kestrel (<italic>Falco sparverius</italic>) chicks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C31">Dawson and Bortolotti, 1997b</xref>), the presence of the hen flea (<italic>Ceratophyllus gallinae</italic>; Ceratophyllidae) did not reduce haematocrit in blue tits (<italic>Cyanistes caeruleus</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C116">Tripet and Richner, 1999</xref>), and experimental infestation of nestling barn swallows (<italic>Hirundo rustica</italic>) with hippoboscid louse flies (<italic>Ornithomyia biloba</italic>; Diptera: Hippoboscidae) also had no impact on this parameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C105">Saino <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>). Taking all these findings into account, it may be concluded that haemoglobin concentration seems to reflect parasitism by haematophagous ectoparasites much more precisely than haematocrit. This hypothesis was first put forward by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C88">O&apos;Brien <italic>et al.</italic> (2001)</xref>, who demonstrated that house wren (<italic>Troglodytes aedon</italic>) nestlings heavily parasitized by larvae of the blow fly (<italic>Protocalliphora parorum</italic>) showed no reduction in haematocrit, but a significant 28&percnt; reduction in haemoglobin level. This confirmed the earlier observations of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C49">Johnson and Albrecht (1993)</xref>, who found that heavily parasitized house wren nestlings retained normal haematocrits. These observations suggested that haemoglobin concentration and haematocrit may respond in a different manner to blood loss. In fact, blood loss in birds is immediately followed by production of immature blood cells, reticulocytes, which rapidly complement haematocrit. However, the quantity of haemoglobin synthesized in reticulocytes does not exceed 20&percnt; of the level found in the mature red blood cells, so blood haemoglobin concentration is complemented with a substantial delay. The higher sensitivity of haemoglobin concentration to infestation by ectoparasites clearly indicates that it should be preferred over haematocrit in studies investigating the health consequences of parasitic pressure in birds.Only two studies investigated the impact of helminths on blood haemoglobin concentration in birds, and both demonstrated reduced haemoglobin levels in response to parasitic infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C56">Khan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C71">Mazur <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Detrimental effects of intestinal nematodes <italic>Ascaridia galli</italic> on the haematological condition of birds were confirmed by reduced haematocrits in experimentally infected young male red jungle fowl (<italic>Gallus gallus</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C48">Johnsen and Zuk, 1998</xref>). In contrast, there is little support for the effects of haematozoan infections on blood haemoglobin concentrations in birds (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COV007TB4">4</xref>). A robust study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C13">Booth and Elliott (2002)</xref> found no within-family and within-species relationships between infections by haematozoa and blood haemoglobin concentrations in 688 Neotropical passerines from over 100 species during spring migration. Likewise, no negative effect of haematozoa on haemoglobin concentrations was found in breeding great tits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C36">Dufva, 1996</xref>) and superb fairywrens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C24">Colombelli-N&eacute;grel and Kleindorfer, 2008</xref>). In contrast, reduced haemoglobin concentration was found in nestling great tits infected with haematozoa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C63">Krams, <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), and a similar effect was found in captive feral pigeon nestlings infected with <italic>Trypanosoma evansi</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C70">Mandal <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Thus, the possibility cannot be excluded that haematozoan infections have more detrimental consequences for nestlings, when compared with adult birds, but more empirical studies are needed to confirm this hypothesis. There is much more information on the impact of haematozoa on haematocrit in free-living birds; nevertheless, the results are also inconsistent among the studied taxa (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C39">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). It also remains unclear whether anaemic states are caused directly by haematozoan infections or indirectly by the blood loss caused by their vectors.There is little and inconsistent information on whether haemoglobin concentration correlates with reproductive performance of adult birds. There is some evidence that individuals with higher haemoglobin concentrations return earlier from wintering quarters to breeding grounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C28">Crossin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) and initiate breeding earlier in the season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C73">Minias, 2014</xref>); however, in some other species no such relationships were found (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C27">Crossin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Likewise, breeding grey-headed albatrosses (<italic>Thalassarche chrysostoma</italic>) had higher haemoglobin concentrations in comparison to non-breeders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C28">Crossin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), but there was no such association in the black-browed albatross (<italic>Thalassarche melanophris</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C27">Crossin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). It was also found that adult whiskered terns with higher haemoglobin concentrations had clutches with larger eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C73">Minias, 2014</xref>). Surprisingly, there are no data on whether the physiological condition of adult birds as assessed by blood haemoglobin concentration is correlated with such basic reproductive parameters as clutch size, hatching success or breeding output.Relationships of haemoglobin concentrations with different fitness-related traits in birdsAbbreviations: ACC, Accipitriformes; Ad., adult; ANS, Anseriformes; CHA, Charadriiformes; CIC, Ciconiiformes; Juv., juvenile; PAS, Passeriformes; PRO, Procellariiformes; Pull., pullus. Studies conducted in captivity are marked with an asterisk. Note: &lsquo;&plus;&rsquo; indicates a positive relationship; &lsquo;&minus;&rsquo; indicates a negative relationship; and &lsquo;(&minus;)&rsquo; indicates no relationship. <sup>a</sup>Buff-rumped thornbill (<italic>Acanthiza reguloides</italic>), dusky woodswallow (<italic>Artamus cyanopterus</italic>), brown treecreeper (<italic>Climacteris picumnus</italic>), grey shrikethrush (<italic>Colluricincla harmonica</italic>), eastern yellow robin (<italic>Eopsaltria australis</italic>), fuscous honeyeater (<italic>Lichenostomus fuscus</italic>), yellow-tufted honeyeater (<italic>Lichenostomus melanops</italic>), white-plumed honeyeater (<italic>Lichenostomus penicillatus</italic>), superb fairywren (<italic>Malurus cyaneus</italic>), brown-headed honeyeater (<italic>Melithreptus brevirostris</italic>), spotted pardalote (<italic>Pardalotus punctatus</italic>), striated pardalote (<italic>Pardalotus striatus</italic>) and weebill (<italic>Smicrornis brevirostris</italic>).Some empirical evidence has been presented for habitat-related differences in haemoglobin concentrations within passerine populations. Nestlings of two tit species were found to have higher haemoglobin concentrations in woodland in comparison to parkland, and these differences were suggested to reflect variation in food availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C6">Ba&nacute;bura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C51">Kali&nacute;ski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). In two other passerines, adults from rural populations had higher blood haemoglobin concentrations in comparison to urban birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C46">Herrera-Due&ntilde;as <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C94">Powell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Given that haemoglobin is considered a reliable oxidative stress marker, these patterns were explained by differences in pollution between rural and urban areas. In contrast, no evidence for a relationship between haemoglobin concentrations and habitat fragmentation were found for 13 woodland passerines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C1">Amos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).Only two studies investigated the effects of different social environments on haemoglobin concentrations in birds. A cross-fostering experiment conducted on a colonial waterbird species demonstrated that offspring raised in larger nesting aggregations had lower haemoglobin concentrations, probably due to increased social stress, although the effects of increased parasitism could not be excluded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C78">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015b</xref>). The second study, on Gouldian finches (<italic>Erythrura gouldiae</italic>), showed that offspring raised in experimentally manipulated highly competitive environments had lower haemoglobin concentrations in comparison to offspring whose parents were subject to reduced levels of competition and aggression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C99">Pryke and Griffith, 2009</xref>).Blood haemoglobin levels were also found to covary with developmental stability (defined as the ability of individuals to undergo stable development of their phenotype in a range of environmental conditions, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C79">M&oslash;ller, 1997</xref>), although the evidence for such a relationship came only from studies on common snipe. It was demonstrated in young snipe that a low haemoglobin concentration had a negative effect on post-juvenile moult symmetry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C75">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013b</xref>). This relationship was speculated to be causal, because low oxygen-carrying capacity of the blood may cause organismal hypoxia during long migratory flights, leading to disruptions in developmental homeostasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C75">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013b</xref>). In contrast, in adult snipe the haemoglobin concentration was associated with symmetry in the wing shape, but this relationship was suggested purely to be correlative, indicating lower genetic and phenotypic quality of birds with lower levels of developmental stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C76">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Relationships between other measures of genetic quality, such as heterozygosity, and haemoglobin concentrations were investigated only in the whiskered tern, but no significant correlation has been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COV007C77">Minias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015a</xref>).On the basis of the reviewed literature, it seems safe to conclude that the total blood haemoglobin concentration may be used as a relatively robust indicator of physiological condition in birds. In most of the studied taxa, the concentration of haemoglobin was correlated with other commonly used indices of condition, such as body mass (corrected and uncorrected for size) and fat loads. Haemoglobin concentrations were also found to increase with a high-quality diet, suggesting that they may directly reflect the nutritional state of individuals. Haemoglobin concentrations reliably reflected parasitic pressure from haematophagous ectoparasites and they correlated with a number of fitness-related traits, although these relationships were not always consistent between species. In spite of this, there are additional sources of variation in haemoglobin levels, which have to be taken into account while using this parameter as a proxy of physiological condition. Due to increasing erythropoiesis, haemoglobin concentrations were found to increase rapidly with age, especially at the nestling stage and possibly also during the post-fledging period. Although in general there was no difference in haemoglobin concentration between sexes, some intersexual variation may appear during specific reproductive stages, such as egg laying or incubation. In fact, anaemic states associated with egg production are primarily responsible for seasonal patterns in haemoglobin concentrations. In contrast, the requirement for improved oxygen-carrying capacity in migrating birds is responsible for increased haemoglobin concentrations often recorded during the spring and autumn periods. Haemoglobin concentrations were also found to be affected by the process of feather replacement, usually decreasing at the beginning of moult and then gradually increasing to the pre-moult level. In conclusion, factors such as age, season and moult are recommended to be controlled for fully, if haemoglobin concentrations are expected to reflect variation in the physiological condition of birds reliably. It remains to be established whether and how strongly condition assessed by haemoglobin concentration may affect direct fitness components, i.e. reproductive output and survival, in natural bird populations and whether it is related to the genetic quality of individuals.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://conphys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/conphys/cov007/-/DC1">Supplementary material is available at <italic>Conservation Physiology</italic> online</ext-link>.I thank the anonymous reviewers whose thoughtful comments helped to improve the manuscript.