Assessment of hybridization among wild and cultivated <italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> subspecies revealed by arbitrarily primed polymerase chain reaction analysisAssessment of genetic diversity in cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> L. Walp.) germplasm from Ghana using simple sequence repeat markersGenetic diversity in cowpea [<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> (L.) <italic>Walp</italic>.] as revealed by RAPD markersGenetic diversity of a <italic>Capsicum</italic> germplasm collection from Nepal as determined by randomly amplified polymorphic DNA markersAssessing genetic diversity and population structure in a citrus germplasm collection utilizing simple sequence repeat markers (SSRs)Genetic diversity in <italic>Vigna</italic>Molecular analysis of phylogenetic relationships among myrmecophytic <italic>Macaranga</italic> species (<italic>Euphorbiaceae</italic>)Arbitrarily amplified DNA markers as characters for phylogenetic inferenceEvaluation of genetic diversity and genome-wide linkage disequilibrium among U.S. wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) germplasm representing different market classesDo outbreaks affect genetic population structure? A worldwide survey in <italic>Locusta migratoria</italic>, a pest plagued by microsatellite null allelesAFLP analysis of the phenetic organization and genetic diversity of <italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> L. Walp. reveals extensive gene flow between wild and cultivated typesUsing AFLP to resolve phylogenetic relationships in a morphologically diversified plant species complex when nuclear and chloroplast sequences fail to reveal variabilityGenetic differentiation of <italic>Vigna</italic> species by RAPD, URP and SSR markersConfidence limits of phylogenies: an approach using bootstrapMolecular heterogeneity of cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic>, Fabaceae) seed storage proteinsThe molecular genetics of <italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> (L.) Walp: the physical organization of 18S-5.8S-25S rRNA genes, 5S rRNA genes, telomere-like sequences and family of centromeric repetitive DNA sequencesIsozyme diversity in <italic>Vigna vexillata</italic> (L.) A. Rich (Fabaceae) complexThe colonization history of <italic>Olea europaea</italic> L. in Macaronesia based on internal transcribed spacer 1 (ITS-1) sequences, randomly amplified polymorphic DNAs (RAPD), and intersimple sequence repeats (ISSR)Species relationship in the subgenus <italic>Ceratotropis</italic> (genus <italic>Vigna</italic>) as revealed by RAPD analysisRandom amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD) analysis in Indian mungbean (<italic>Vigna radiata</italic> (L.) Wilczek) cultivarsDetermining genetic similarities and relationships among cowpea breeding lines and cultivars by microsatellite markersThe domestications and improvement of cowpeas (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> (L.)Walp.)Mathematical model for studying genetic variation in terms of restriction endonucleasesGenetic structure of <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> populations in Mediterranean basinGenetic relationships within <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> (L.) Walp. based on isozymes analysisCultivated cowpea <italic>(Vigna unguiculata)</italic> evolutionMorphological study of cultivated cowpea <italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> (L) Walp: importance of ovule number and definition of cv. gr. <italic>Melanophthalmus</italic>Genetic relationships among subspecies of <italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> (L.) Walp based on allozyme variationAllozyme diversity of cultivated cowpea <italic>V</italic>. <italic>unguiculata</italic> (L.) WalpGenetic relationships among <italic>Rehmannia glutinosa</italic> cultivars and varietiesGenetic relatedness (diversity) and cultivar identification by randomly amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD) markers in teasle gourd (<italic>Momordica dioica</italic> Roxb.)Molecular characterization of <italic>Vigna radiata</italic> (L.) Wilczek genotypes based on nuclear ribosomal DNA and RAPD polymorphismAnalysis of population substructure, genetic differentiation and phylogenetic relationships among selected Asiatic <italic>Vigna</italic> speciesRibosomal RNA gene diversity within and between mungbean and other Asiatic <italic>Vigna</italic> speciesMolecular evolution of 5S rDNA region in <italic>Vigna</italic> subgenus <italic>Ceratotropis</italic> and its phylogenetic implicationsEvaluation of long primers for APPCR analysis of mungbean [<italic>Vigna radiata</italic> (L.) Wilczek]: genetic relationship and fingerprinting of some genotypesIntra-individual and intra-species heterogeneity in nuclear rDNA ITS region of <italic>Vigna</italic> species from subgenus <italic>Ceratotropis</italic>Genetic diversity in mungbean germplasm revealed by RAPD analysisCowpea, a multifunctional legumeIsozyme diversity in the cowpea species complexTREECON for Windows: a software package for the construction and drawing of evolutionary trees for the Microsoft Windows environmentPhylogenetic analysis of subgenus <italic>Vigna</italic> species using ribosomal RNA ITS: evidence of hybridization among <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspeciesMolecular characterization of intergenic spacer region of 5S ribosomal RNA genes in subgenus <italic>Vigna</italic>: extensive hybridization among <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspeciesRAPD and internal transcribed spacer sequence analyses reveal <italic>Zea nicaraguensis</italic> as a Section <italic>Luxuriantes</italic> species close to <italic>Zea luxurians</italic>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.This paper show that inter-subspecies hybridization among certain <italic>Vigna unguiculata subspecies</italic>, occurred during the course of evolution. This has affected several regions of the genome and is interfering with the dependable assessment of sub-species relationships using single (rRNA regions) or multilocus markers.Intra-species hybridization and incompletely homogenized ribosomal RNA repeat units have earlier been reported in 21 accessions of <italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> from six subspecies using internal transcribed spacer (ITS) and 5S intergenic spacer (IGS) analyses. However, the relationships among these accessions were not clear from these analyses. We therefore assessed intra-species hybridization in the same set of accessions.Arbitrarily primed polymerase chain reaction (AP-PCR) analysis was carried out using 12 primers. The PCR products were resolved on agarose gels and the DNA fragments were scored manually. Genetic relationships were inferred by TREECON software using unweighted paired group method with arithmetic averages (UPGMA) cluster analysis evaluated by bootstrapping and compared with previous analyses based on ITS and 5S IGS.A total of 202 (86 %) fragments were found to be polymorphic and used for generating a genetic distance matrix. Twenty-one <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> accessions were grouped into three main clusters. The cultivated subspecies (var. <italic>unguiculata</italic>) and most of its wild progenitors (var. <italic>spontanea</italic>) were placed in cluster I along with ssp. <italic>pubescens</italic> and ssp. <italic>stenophylla.</italic> Whereas var. <italic>spontanea</italic> were grouped with ssp. <italic>alba</italic> and ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> accessions in cluster II, ssp. <italic>alba</italic> and ssp. <italic>baoulensis</italic> were included in cluster III. Close affinities of ssp. <italic>unguiculata,</italic> ssp. <italic>alba</italic> and ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> suggested inter-subspecies hybridization.Multi-locus AP-PCR analysis reveals that intra-species hybridization is prevalent among <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies and suggests that grouping of accessions from two different subspecies is not solely due to the similarity in the ITS and 5S IGS regions but also due to other regions of the genome.<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> is an important legume crop belonging to section <italic>Catiang</italic> in the subgenus <italic>Vigna. Vigna</italic> comprises a heterogeneous assemblage of 39 species of African origin that are divided into six sections, viz. <italic>Vigna</italic>, <italic>Comosae</italic>, <italic>Macrodontae</italic>, <italic>Reticulatae</italic>, <italic>Liebrechtsia</italic> and <italic>Catiang</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C23">Maxted <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Disagreement still exists over the primary centres of domestication of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic>; however, based on the studies, different centres have been proposed such as Northeast Africa, West Africa, Ethiopia, Asia, etc. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C4">Baudoin and Maréchal 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C29">Pasquet 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C31">1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C17">Garba and Pasquet 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C11">Coulibaly <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C3">Ba <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C44">Timko and Singh 2008</xref>). These include both wild and cultivated taxa of perennial and annual species, having high variation in their morphological characterization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C31">Pasquet 1999</xref>). Cultivated species differ from wild species in having non-dehiscent pods, larger pods and non-dormant larger seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C22">Lush and Evans 1981</xref>). Apart from these characters associated with domestication, some traits such as rhomboid leaves and anthocyanin pigmentation of the internodes, the length of the floral peduncle, photosensitivity and morphology of the seeds and pods are the principal variations in the cultivated forms.<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic> has 11 subspecies that differ from one another with respect to various morphological characteristics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C31">Pasquet 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C23">Maxted <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>). Five of the subspecies, viz. <italic>baoulensis</italic>, <italic>burundiensis</italic>, <italic>letouzeyi</italic>, <italic>aduensis</italic> and <italic>pawekiae</italic>, are perennial, allogamously adapted to humid environments and are mainly recognized by their floral characteristics. Five other subspecies, viz. <italic>alba</italic>, <italic>pubescens</italic>, <italic>tenuis</italic>, <italic>stenophylla</italic> and <italic>dekindtiana,</italic> are wild, perennial, autogamous and are recognized by their vegetative traits showing their adaptation to drier and coastal environments. Only one subspecies is annual (ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic>), comprising wild (var. <italic>spontanea</italic>) and cultivated (var. <italic>unguiculata</italic>) forms. The var. <italic>spontanea</italic> is a savanna taxon and often grows as a weed in and around cultivated fields. The cultivated forms of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> are classified into five cultivar groups (cv.-gr.): <italic>Unguiculata</italic>, <italic>Biflora, Sesquipedalis, Textilis</italic> and <italic>Melanophthalmus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C30">Pasquet 1998</xref>).The relationship between the subspecies from subgenus <italic>Vigna</italic> has been analysed in the recent past by using different parameters, including morphological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C27">Padulosi 1993</xref>) and biochemical parameters (seed storage proteins: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C15">Fotso <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>; isozymes: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C28">Panella and Gepts 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C45">Vaillancourt <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C31">Pasquet 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C32">2000</xref>). Molecular marker techniques, viz. AFLP (amplified fragment length polymorphism; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C11">Coulibaly <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>), RAPD (randomly amplified polymorphic DNA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C3">Ba <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>), SSR (simple sequence repeat; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C2">Asare <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) and nrRNA (nuclear ribosomal RNA) spacer sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C38">Saini 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C41">Saini <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C39">Saini and Jawali 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">2011</xref>), have also been used to help understand relationships among the wild and cultivated accessions of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic>. Relationships among subspecies of most of the <italic>Vigna</italic> species could be analysed with the exception of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic>. The relationships among taxa belonging to <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies inferred by 18S-5.8S-26S rRNA ITS (internal transcribed spacer) did not show subspecies-specific clustering, but an intragenomic ITS variant was detected in an accession belonging to <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> ssp<italic>. tenuis</italic> (NI 1637; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>)<italic>.</italic> In addition, some accessions of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> have very intriguing relationships among the 5S IGS (intergenic spacer) variants in relation to subspecies. This indicates extensive hybridization among the <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies, which is generally uncommon in rRNA gene units (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).Arbitrarily amplified DNA markers are used extensively for reconstructing relationships among various species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C8">Bussel <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). Randomly amplified polymorphic DNA has the ability to amplify DNA from dispersed polymorphic loci from the genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C5">Baral and Bosland 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C35">Rasul <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C49">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and has been used to assess genetic diversity among and between species/subspecies/cultivars of <italic>Vigna</italic> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C19">Kaga <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C43">Santalla <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C20">Lakhanpaul <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C3">Ba <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C40">Saini <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C36">Raturi <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). There are several studies where the same set of taxa has been analysed by single-locus sequence analysis as well as multi-locus techniques such as RAPD to get more insight into relationships at population, subspecies and species levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C18">Hess <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C26">Ortíz-Dorda <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C34">Qi <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C49">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).The objective of the present study was to assess the genetic relationships among wild and cultivated <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> germplasm using a multi-locus marker technique, AP-PCR (arbitrarily primed polymerase chain reaction).<italic>Vgna unguiculata</italic> accessions along with their country of origin and germplasm accession numbers.NA, information not available.Hashes indicate <italic>Vigna</italic> accessions harbouring single 5S IGS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">Vijaykumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).An asterisk indicates <italic>Vigna</italic> accession harbouring intra-genomic ITS variant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).<sup>a</sup>List of <italic>Vigna</italic> accessions used. ssp., subspecies; <italic>ung.</italic>, <italic>unguiculata</italic>; var., variety; cv.-gr., cultivar-group.<sup>b</sup>Accession numbers of the National Botanic Garden, Meise, Belgium.<sup>c</sup>DR Congo, Democratic Republic of Congo.Characteristics of primers used for AP-PCR analysis along with the number of total and polymorphic bands obtained.The AP-PCR was carried out twice and profiles were analysed manually; the amplified products were scored as present (1) or absent (0) for each primer–accession combination. Molecular data were used to compute genetic distances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C25">Nei and Li 1979</xref>) within and between <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies using TREECON (version 1.3b; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C46">Van de Peer and De Watcher 1994</xref>; http://bioc-www.uia.ac.be/u/yvdp/treeconw.html) and a dendrogram was generated using the unweighted paired group method with arithmetic averages (UPGMA). Statistical analysis was carried out by the bootstrap method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C14">Felsenstein 1985</xref>).<bold>AP-PCR profiles of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> genotypes obtained with primers SS9.1 (A) and SS5.1 (B).</bold> Lane 1: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> cv.-gr. <italic>Unguiculata</italic> (NI 479); Lane 2: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> cv.-gr. <italic>Sesquipedalis</italic> (NI 269); Lane 3: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1405); Lane 4: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> cv.-gr. <italic>Textilis</italic> (NI 816); Lane 5: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1639); Lane 6: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1668); Lane 7: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1687); Lane 8: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1475); Lane 9: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1384); Lane 10: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 945); Lane 11: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 319); Lane 12: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1507); Lane 13: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> (NI 1712); Lane 14: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> (NI 1636); Lane 15: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> (NI 1637); Lane 16: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>alba</italic> (NI 1652); Lane 17: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>alba</italic> (NI 1388); Lane 18: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>baoulensis</italic> (NI 1651); Lane 19: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>stenophylla</italic> (NI 1478); Lane 20: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>pubescens</italic> (NI 856); Lane 21: <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>pubescens</italic> (NI 989); Lane M contains a mixture of ϕX174 DNA (HaeIII digest) and λ (HindIII digest).<bold>UPGMA cluster analysis of 21 <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> genotypes based on the AP-PCR marker data.</bold> Numbers at nodes indicate bootstrap values (in %) for a 1000-replicate analysis. An asterisk indicates the <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> accession that showed intra-genomic ITS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) and hashes indicate the <italic>V. u.</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> accessions that showed single type 5S IGS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).Cluster II comprised seven taxa belonging to three subspecies, viz. <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata, V. unguiculata</italic> ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> ssp. <italic>baoulensis</italic>. Three <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> accessions from South African countries, viz. NI 1507 (Zimbabwe), NI 1639 (Namibia) and NI 1384 (Botswana), in cluster II were found to be divergent from the six <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> accessions placed in cluster I (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS012F2">2</xref>). Cluster III included only two accessions belonging to two different subspecies: ssp. <italic>alba</italic> (NI 1652, Angola) and ssp. <italic>baoulensis</italic> (NI 1651, Ivory Coast).Multi-locus marker techniques such as RAPD, AP-PCR, inter simple sequence repeat, AFLP, etc. have been extensively used for a variety of genetic analyses, including investigating genetic relationships; they can also provide valuable information on phylogenetics and systematics, if used appropriately (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C8">Bussell <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). These multi-locus markers have also been extensively used for analysis of species of Asian and African origin from the genus <italic>Vigna</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C21">Li <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C11">Coulibaly <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C3">Ba <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C13">Dikshit <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C37">Ruchi <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C36">Raturi <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). In the present study, the AP-PCR profiles of 21 taxa belonging to different subspecies of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> showed moderate divergence and were used to determine their genetic relationships. The same set of taxa was previously analysed using ITS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) and 5S IGS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) regions. Hence, the phylogenetic trees obtained from these analyses were compared to understand how some of the taxa have evolved.In general, the analyses of species/subspecies using multi-locus genome-wide marker analyses show clustering at the species as well subspecies level. On the contrary, the dendrogram obtained from the AP-PCR analyses of the taxa belonging to <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> did not show clear-cut grouping of taxa at the subspecies level. Out of the 12 taxa belonging to <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> ssp<italic>. unguiculata</italic>, nine were placed in cluster 1A, and the other three were grouped with other subspecies, albeit at low bootstrap values. Among the other subspecies (ssp. <italic>pubescens</italic>, ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and ssp. <italic>alba</italic>) where more than one taxa was analysed, two accessions of ssp. <italic>pubescens</italic> were placed together (in subcluster IB) along with ssp. <italic>stenophylla</italic>. Accessions of both ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and ssp. <italic>alba</italic> also showed divergence and did not cluster together. Accession NI 1388 of ssp. <italic>alba</italic> was placed in cluster II along with <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic>, while NI 1652 was placed in cluster III with ssp. <italic>baoulensis</italic>. The three accessions (NI 1636, NI 1637 and NI 1712) of ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic>, though placed in cluster II, were highly divergent. Accession NI 1637, which harboured intra-genomic ITS variant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) was placed in cluster II and showed more affinity towards ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1384) compared with the other two ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> accessions (NI 1637, NI 1712) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS012F2">2</xref>). Our results are also in agreement with previous reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C31">Pasquet 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C32">2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C11">Coulibaly <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>).The present AP-PCR analysis clearly delineated cultivated <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> accessions from wild types. The present analyses placed the majority of the ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> accessions with the cultivated <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> in cluster I. However, three ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> accessions, viz., NI 1384, NI 1507 and NI 1639, were highly divergent and grouped with ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and ssp. <italic>alba</italic> in cluster II. Two of these accessions, i.e. NI 1384 and NI 1639 (=SP 160), were part of the var. <italic>spontanea</italic> BWA group (includes accessions from Botswana) in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C31">Pasquet (1999)</xref>; however, NI 1507 (=MT 76) was not, which reinforces the hybridization origin of this group of var. <italic>spontanea</italic> accessions from southern Africa. A close relationship between NI1639 and NI 1384 was also observed based on the ITS analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). The clustering of var. <italic>spontanea</italic> with ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and ssp. <italic>alba</italic> may be the result of hybridization between these taxa. These results confirm that, in general, the genomes of ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic>, ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and ssp. <italic>alba</italic> have indeed undergone hybridization, and this has led to their convergence with accessions of other subspecies. Accession NI 1637 of ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> was grouped with two other accessions of ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> (NI 1712, NI 1636); however, this accession harboured intra-individual ITS and 5S IGS variants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">2011</xref>)<italic>.</italic> In the case of ITS analysis, the two variants were found to have originated as a result of hybridization between ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and ssp. <italic>pubescens</italic>. However, AP-PCR analysis revealed that the major proportion of the genome of the NI 1637 accession is close to ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic>. This indicates that although rRNA genes (18S-5.8S-26S rRNA and 5S rRNA) have not been homogenized subsequent to subspecies hybridization in NI 1637 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">2011</xref>), the genome is homogenized towards ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic>. The present analysis grouped one accession each from ssp. <italic>baoulensis</italic> (NI 1651) and ssp. <italic>alba</italic> (NI 1652) in cluster III (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS012F2">2</xref>). However, this accession of ssp. <italic>alba</italic>, based on ITS, was found to be close to ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> (NI 1384 and NI 1639). This is in accordance with previous studies based on AFLP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C11">Coulibaly <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>) and isozymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C31">Pasquet 1999</xref>). The three ssp<italic>. unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic> accessions, viz. NI 1384, NI 1507 and NI 1639, also appear to be a product of hybridization between ssp<italic>. unguiculata</italic> and ssp<italic>. tenuis</italic>.The accession NI 1478 belonging to ssp. <italic>stenophylla</italic> showed close affinity to NI 1475 from ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> on the basis of rRNA gene analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">2011</xref>). Under the present investigation it grouped with ssp. <italic>pubescens</italic>, suggesting that NI1478 may have undergone hybridization with ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> and ssp. <italic>pubescens,</italic> during the course of evolution<italic>.</italic> However, more detailed studies would be required to prove these aspects, as perfect assessment of positions of distant accessions may not be possible solely on the basis of AP-PCR marker analysis.In general, different taxa of the same species/genus are analysed by different approaches and the results inferred from such studies are often not directly comparable. If done appropriately, studies on the same set of taxa using a multiple marker system help in understanding the genetic relationships at subspecies/population level, along with evolutionary/phylogenetic relationships at species level, and also allow us to decipher how different <italic>loci vis-á-vis</italic> genome have evolved. Furthermore, multi-locus markers are also useful when single-locus regions fail to resolve phylogenetic/genetic relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C12">Després <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>). Despite these advantages, studies on the same set of taxa using multiple markers are not often carried out and only a few molecular phylogenetic studies have been reported where the rRNA gene sequences and multi-locus marker analysis have been performed using the same set of taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C7">Blattner <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>). Arbitrarily primed-PCR techniques have also been explored to study the genetic relationships among species in combination with sequence-based analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C18">Hess <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; Jorgensen <italic>et al.</italic> 2003; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C26">Ortíz-Dorda <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C34">Qi <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C49">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). The same set of accessions has been used for assessment of phylogenetic relationships using both multi-locus and single-locus markers in different species such as <italic>Olea europaea</italic> complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C18">Hess <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>), <italic>Trollius</italic> species complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C12">Després <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>), <italic>Atriplex halimus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C26">Ortíz-Dorda <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>), genus <italic>Rehmannia</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C34">Qi <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), genus <italic>Zea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C49">Wang <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and <italic>Vigna</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C36">Raturi <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).In the present investigation we have used the same set of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> accessions and the results were very useful in understanding the evolution of some of the species/taxa analysed. Our previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">2011</xref>) suggest that intra-species hybridization has affected the rRNA gene loci during the course of evolution. Consequently, it was difficult to infer phylogenetic relationships among certain <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies. Hence, the present analysis was carried out to infer the relationships among the same set of taxa using information generated from multi-locus markers that can analyse many regions of the genome. The results presented in this study suggest that regions of the <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> genome other than ITS and 5S IGS also show evidence of inter-subspecies hybridization.Our previous study on the analysis of <italic>Vigna</italic> species from subgenus <italic>Vigna</italic> (African <italic>Vigna</italic>) using the 18S-5.8S-26S nrDNA ITS region gave evidence of hybridization and slow molecular drive of the repeat units. An accession of ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> harboured an additional ITS variant (more similar to ssp. <italic>pubescens</italic>); however, it was not active transcriptionally. Furthermore, certain accessions of ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic>, ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic> and ssp. <italic>alba</italic> showed close relationships with other subspecies. This suggested that these accessions have also undergone hybridization but subsequently the ITS sequences have homogenized towards the other subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C47">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). Analysis of the same set of taxa by 5S IGS region also suggested hybridization among several <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). The 5S IGS sequences were homogenized to a much lower extent as compared with the ITS sequences, although the number of 5S loci in <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> were reported to be lower than 18S-5.8S-25S genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C16">Galasso <italic>et al</italic>. 1995</xref>).The evidence for inter-subspecies hybridization among the <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> accessions came from the fact that despite using a large number of markers, relationships among accessions of certain subspecies (ssp. <italic>unguiculata</italic> var. <italic>spontanea</italic>, ssp. <italic>alba</italic> and ssp. <italic>tenuis</italic>) in cluster II were not supported by high bootstrap values. The low bootstrap values have been attributed to very frequent intercrossing among the taxa analysed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C6">Barkley <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C9">Chao <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C10">Chapuis <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Our results show that subspecies relationships within <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> cannot be inferred and this could be due to intra-subspecies hybridization. Similar findings were recorded in our previous studies using rRNA gene analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS012C48">Vijaykumar <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).The results from the present analyses confirm that the <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies have undergone inter-subspecies hybridization and introgression, with most taxa maintaining the variant 5S IGS sequences while very few maintain variant ITS sequences. Hence, irrespective of the actual multi-locus marker analysis, the relationships among the subspecies could not be clearly inferred.The present analysis of <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies using AP-PCR markers clearly shows that extensive hybridization has occurred among certain subspecies. The same set of taxa when previously analysed by ITS and 5S IGS sequences had shown evidence of hybridization and incomplete homogenization of rRNA repeat units. The present study based on multi-locus analysis further substantiates the previous findings on intra-subspecies hybridization events among certain <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies. The present study thus advocates further in-depth analysis of such interactions among the <italic>V. unguiculata</italic> subspecies, along with eco-geographical parameters.The project was conceived and planned by N.J. The major experimental part of the study was carried out by A.V. as part of her PhD thesis. Some parts of the experiments and data analysis were done by A.S.None declared.We thank Dr Thierry Vanderborght, Seed Bank Manager, National Botanic Garden, Belgium, for providing plant materials used in this study. We thank Dr S. K. Apte, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai, India, for encouragement and support.