Molecular marker-based characterization in candidate plus trees of <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic>, a potential biodiesel legumeOptimizing parental selection for genetic linkage mapsDNA fingerprinting of India cashew (<italic>Anacardium occidentale</italic> L.) varieties using RAPD and ISSR techniquesMicrosatellite marker diversity in common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L.)Studies on <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> (L.) Pierre leaves: understanding the mechanism(s) of action in infectious diarrheaThe distribution of random amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD) diversity among populations of <italic>Isotoma petraea</italic> (Lobeliaceae)Measures of the amount of ecological association between speciesAFLP variation in four blue gram seed sourcesIsozymes and analyses of genetic structure of plant populationsThe genetic structure of tropical tree population: associations with reproductive biologyGenetic structure of <italic>Buxus sinica</italic> var. parvifolia, a rare and endangered plantIdentification of <italic>Hedysarum</italic> varieties using amplified fragment length polymorphism on a capillary electrophoresis systemGenetic variability and association studies in pod and seed traits of <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> (L.) Pierre in Haryana, IndiaEvaluation of soybean RFLP marker diversity in adapted germplasmSystematic characterization and seed oil analysis in candidate plus trees of biodiesel plant, <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> (L.)PCR amplification of the genomic DNA from the seeds of Ceylon Ironwood, Jatropha and PongamiaPhysico-chemical characterization and microbial assay from seed oil of <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic>, potential biofuel cropRAPD and morphological diversity among four populations of the tropical tree species <italic>Paramichelia baillonii</italic> (Pierre) Hu in ChinaGenetic distance estimators based on molecular data for plant registration and protection: a reviewRAPD and ISSR molecular markers in <italic>Olea europaea</italic> L.: Genetic variability and molecular cultivar identificationThe detection of disease clustering and generalized regression approachesGene flow in plant pathosystemsDNA extraction from dry seeds for RAPD analysis in varietal identification studiesA review of the chemistry and biological activity of <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic>Almost forgotten or latest practice? AFLP applications, analyses and advancesVariability assessment in <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> (L.) Pierre germplasm for biodiesel traitsAnalysis of gene diversity in subdivided populations5th R&amp;D report on tree borne oilseedsGenetic relationships among South-East Turkey wild barley populations and sampling strategies of <italic>Hordeum spontaneum</italic>Molecular characterization and identification of markers for toxic and non-toxic varieties of <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> L. using RAPD, AFLP and SSR markersThe unity of RFLP, RAPD, AFLP and SSR (microsatellite) markers for germplasm analysisThe analysis of genetic diversity of <italic>Salix viminalis</italic> genotypes as a potential source of biomass by RAPD markersInter simple sequence repeat (ISSR) polymorphism and its application in plant breeding. Version 2.231Inter and intra-population variability of <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic>: a bioenergy legume treeA comprehensive analysis of fuel properties of biodiesel from koroch seed oilComparative study of the discriminating capacity and effectiveness of AFLP, STMS and EST markers in assessing genetic relationships among evergreen azales<italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic>: an untapped resource for the biofuels: industry of the futureAssessment of genetic diversity of biodiesel species <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> accessions using AFLP and three endonuclease-AFLPA penalty of using anonymous dominant markers (AFLPs, ISSRs, and RAPDs) for phylogenetic inferenceA comparison of three indirect methods for estimating average levels of gene flowThe description and assessment of distances between inbred lines of maize. II. The utility of morphological, biochemical and genetic descriptors and a scheme for testing of distinctiveness between inbred linesAmplified fragment length polymorphism as a tool for molecular characterization of almond germplasm: genetic diversity among cultivated genotypes and related wild species of almond, and its relationships with agronomic traitsA comparative analysis of genetic diversity in blackgram genotypes using RAPD and ISSR markersIdentification of <italic>Hedysarum</italic> varieties using amplified fragment length polymorphism on a capillary electrophoresis systemGenetic diversity among varieties and wild species accessions of pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.) based on molecular markers, and morphological and physiological charactersAFLP-based molecular characterization of an elite germplasm collection of <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> L., a biofuel plantAFLP: a new technique for DNA fingerprintingDNA polymorphisms amplified by arbitrary primers are useful as genetic markersRAPD variation within and among natural populations of trembling aspen (<italic>Populus tremuloides</italic> Michx.) from AlbertaSelective restriction fragment amplification: a general method for DNA fingerprintingGenome fingerprinting by simple sequence repeat (SSR)-anchored polymerase chain reaction amplificationThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Molecular marker studies provide valid guidelines for collection, characterization and selective cultivation of elite <italic>Pongamia</italic> germplasm that can be exploited further for its improvement through breeding and marker assisted selection for improved characters and oil yield towards biodiesel production.<italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic>, a legume tree, has many traditional uses and is a potential biodiesel plant. Despite its importance and the availability of appropriate molecular genetic tools, the full potential of <italic>Pongamia</italic> is yet to be realized. The objective of this study was to assess genetic diversity among 10 systematically characterized candidate plus trees (CPTs) of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> from North Guwahati.The application and informativeness of polymerase chain reaction-based molecular markers [random amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD), inter-simple sequence repeat (ISSR) and amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP)] to assess the genetic variability and relatedness among 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> were investigated.Polymorphism rates of 10.48, 10.08 and 100 % were achieved using 18 RAPD, 12 ISSR and 4 AFLP primer combinations, respectively. Polymorphic information content (PIC) varied in the range 0.33–0.49, 0.18–0.49 and 0.26–0.34 for RAPD, ISSR and AFLP markers, respectively, whereas the corresponding average marker index (MI) values for the above markers were 7.48, 6.69 and 30.75. Based on Nei's gene diversity and Shannon's information index, inter-population diversity (<italic>h</italic><sub>sp</sub>) was highest when compared with intra-population diversity (<italic>h</italic><sub>pop</sub>) and the gene flow (<italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub>) ranged from a moderate value of 0.607 to a high value of 6.287 for the three DNA markers. Clustering of individuals was not similar when RAPD- and ISSR-derived dendrogram analyses were compared with that of AFLP. The Mantel test cophenetic correlation coefficient was higher for AFLP (<italic>r</italic> = 0.98) than for ISSR (<italic>r</italic> = 0.73) and RAPD (<italic>r</italic> = 0.84). Molecular markers discriminated the individuals efficiently and generated a high similarity in dendrogram topologies derived using unweighted pair-group arithmetic average, although some differences were observed. The three-dimensional scaling by principal coordinate analysis supported the result of clustering.Comparing the results obtained with the three DNA markers, AFLP indicated higher efficiency for estimating the levels of genetic diversity and proved to be reliable for fingerprinting, mapping and diversity studies in <italic>Pongamia</italic> in view of their suitability for energy production purposes.<italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> also referred to as Pongam, is a biodiesel tree legume well adapted to arid zones and has many traditional uses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C23">Meera <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C4">Brijesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C37">Scott <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C25">Mukta <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The pongam tree has the rare property of producing seeds with high oil content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C35">Sarma <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C16">Kesari <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Despite the importance of this versatile plant and the availability of appropriate molecular genetic tools, the full potential of <italic>Pongamia</italic> is far from being realized. The natural constraints that limit its large-scale production and availability, to meet the demand for biodiesel production, are its long gestation period (4–7 years), plant height, seed storage behaviour, insect pests, and the seed oil yield and quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C27">NOVOD 2010</xref>). Until recently, the identification of elite individuals of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> was mainly described in terms of morphological and agronomic traits which are known to be deeply influenced by environmental factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C12">Kaushik <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C14">Kesari <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The cross-pollinating nature of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> contributes to its wide germplasm biodiversity. Thus, it becomes an important step to examine the genetic variations among naturally growing elite individuals of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> at inter- and intra-population levels, and to prepare strategies for its specific exploitation by plant breeders in promoting it as a versatile biodiesel plant.With the large array of molecular analytical techniques available, it has become possible to provide an accurate and unambiguous tool for the evaluation of genetic diversity and identification of germplasm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C24">Meudt and Clarke 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C39">Simmons <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C17">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). In the last decade, several polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based DNA marker classes, viz. random amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD), inter-simple sequence repeat (ISSR) and amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP), contributed to this goal, and may extend and complement the assessment of genetic variation within the species based on morphological and polypeptide descriptions, providing more speed, accurate and detailed information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C49">Williams <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C52">Zabeau and Vos 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C53">Zietkiewicz <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C45">Surekha and Larson 2005</xref>). In addition, it is independent of the growth, stage, season, location and agronomic practices, which gives them a high value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C18">Lombard <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). RAPD markers have been widely used in plant research for phylogenetic studies, genome mapping and genetic variation analysis both at intra- and inter-population levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C17">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The technique has several advantages including simplicity, low cost, speed and lack of requirement for DNA sequence information (Williams <italic>et al.</italic> 1990; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C19">Lopes <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). However, RAPD technology has several limitations including dominance, uncertain locus homology, sensitivity and reliability. Inter-simple sequence repeat represents the marker of choice for varietal identification studies as they are transferable, hypervariable, highly polymorphic, multiallelic dominant markers, relatively simple to interpret and show high information content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C44">Souframanien and Gopalkrishna 2004</xref>). The AFLP technique has been used for DNA fingerprinting in a number of tree species such as almond (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C43">Sorkheh <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), cashew (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C2">Archak <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>) and <italic>Jatropha</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C47">Tatikonda <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The choice of primer pairs used in AFLP amplification is critical for obtaining high levels of polymorphism. Therefore, it would be useful if few informative primers are identified such that they amplify markers with high levels of polymorphism, which are representative of the whole genome.There is a strong need to assess and document the extent of genetic diversity in naturally growing, systematically characterized <italic>P. pinnata</italic> populations to expedite its use in different germplasm-related studies and breeding programmes. In continuation of our studies on candidate plus trees (CPTs), the present study was undertaken with the objective of screening the untapped genetic variability or relatedness among the 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> tagged from North Guwahati, Assam, at the inter- and intra-population levels using PCR-based DNA markers (RAPD, ISSR and AFLP). Candidate plus trees are individual trees of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> possessing superior morphological and reproductive characters compared with other individuals of the same species identified on the basis of morphometric markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C14">Kesari <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The study further involves comparing the informativeness of RAPD, ISSR and AFLP assays employed at the level of populations and individuals in order to analyse the variability studies in the <italic>P. pinnata</italic> genome. So far, this is the first study that deals with the systematic characterization of elite individuals for further genetic improvement of important biodiesel tree species.The germplasm used in this study for genetic diversity studies were young seeds, collected during the month of September 2007 from 10 different tagged CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> [North Guwahati <italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> (NGPP) 26–30 and NGPP 46–50]. The 10 CPTs identified, based on morphometric traits, belong to two different naturally growing populations, viz. 6 and 10 occurring at Sila Forest Range, North Guwahati, Assam (latitude 26°14′6″N and longitude 91°41′28″E) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C14">Kesari <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). All the seed samples were appropriately stored at −20 °C for further analysis.Genomic DNA extraction for genetic diversity studies was performed by modified sodium dodecyl sulphate method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C15">Kesari <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The quality and quantity of the extracted DNA were confirmed to be consistent both spectrophotometrically and by running the extracted DNA in a 0.8 % agarose gel stained with ethidium bromide (0.5 μg mL<sup>−1</sup>). At least two independent DNA preparations for each individual were made, and the quantity and quality of DNA samples were estimated.For RAPD fingerprinting, PCR amplification of the genomic DNA was carried out using 20 arbitrary decamer oligonucleotide primers (Operon Tech, USA). The primer sequence information is provided in the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/plq017/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Additional information, Table 1</ext-link>. Each 20 µL of reaction mixture contained 50 ng µL<sup>−1</sup> template DNA, 1× assay buffer (100 mM Tris sulfonic acid, pH 8.8, 15 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 500 mM KCl and 0.1 % gelatin), 0.2 mM each deoxyribonucleotide triphosphate (B'LGenei, India), 5 pM each primer and 0.5 U of <italic>Taq</italic> polymerase (B'LGenei, India). The reaction was performed in 0.2-mL microfuge tubes (Dialabs, UK). PCR amplification was carried out in a Mini Thermal Cycler (Applied Biosystems 9700) programmed for 35 cycles. The first amplification cycle consisted of an initial denaturation step of 5 min at 94 °C, followed by 34 cycles of 45 s at 94 °C, annealing temperature of 1 min at 32 °C, and extension at 72 °C for 1 min 30 s. An additional cycle of 5 min at 72 °C was used for primer extension. The amplification products were electrophoresed on 1.5 % agarose gels in 0.5× Tris borate EDTA (10× stocks contained 0.8 M Tris, 0.8 M boric acid, 0.5 M EDTA). A 1 kb DNA ladder (Life Technologies, USA) was included as a size marker, and the amplified products were detected with ethidium bromide staining (0.5 μg mL<sup>−1</sup>). The gels were photographed under a UV transilluminator.PCR amplification was carried out for 20 ISSR primers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/plq017/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Additional information, Table 1</ext-link>), using a similar method to that used for RAPD analysis with the final volume of the reaction mixture being 20 µL. The steps of temperature cycling were as follows: 94 °C for 4 min, followed by 35 cycles of 45 s at 94 °C, 1 min with varied temperatures as per the melting temperature of the ISSR primers used, 1 min 30 s at 72 °C and 10 min final extension step at 72 °C. The amplified products were visualized in a 1.5 % agarose gel containing ethidium bromide and photographed for further analysis.Reagents from the Applied Biosystems plant mapping kit consisting of the ligation/preselective amplification module and selective primer kits were used, and assay performed as per the manufacturer's protocol followed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C48">Vos <italic>et al</italic>. (1995)</xref> with minor modifications. DNA (500 ng) was double-digested with restriction endonucleases <italic>Eco</italic>RI/<italic>Mse</italic>I (New England Biolabs) for 2 h at 37 °C and ligated to adapters using T4 DNA ligase (New England Biolabs). The digested DNA mixture was diluted (10-fold) and used for pre-selective amplification with pre-selective primer pair. The pre-selective amplification was performed at 72 °C for 2 min followed by 20 cycles of denaturation (at 94 °C for 20 s), primer annealing (at 56 °C for 30 s) and primer extension (at 72 °C for 2 min). The reaction mixture was finally maintained at 60 °C for 30 min. An aliquot of the pre-selective PCR product was electrophoresed on a 1.5 % agarose gel and checked for amplification. It was then diluted (1:20) with DNase-free water and used as a template for the selective amplification.The selective amplification was performed using primers from the AFLP selective primer kit. The selective amplification involved the following thermal cycling conditions: denaturation at 94 °C for 2 min followed by 11 cycles of 94 °C for 20 s, 66 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 2 min. The annealing temperature was reduced by 1 °C every cycle till it reached 56 °C. This was followed by another 20 cycles of amplification at 94 °C for 20 s, 56 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 2 min, with a final extension at 60 °C for 30 min.Selectively amplified product (1 μL) was mixed with 0.5 µL of the GeneScan 500 ROX internal size standard (Applied Biosystems P/N 402985) and 8.5 µL of Hi-Di Formamide (Applied Biosystems P/N 4311320). The mixture was then denatured prior to separation by capillary gel electrophoresis on an automated DNA sequencer (ABI 3130; Applied Biosystems). The electropherograms generated by the sequencer were interpreted with GeneScan<sup>®</sup> analysis software (PE Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Genotyper<sup>®</sup> analysis software (PE Applied Biosystems) was then used to create a list of fragments detected in each lane by fragment size. Fragments sized from 50 to 500 bp with a peak height &gt;50 bp in the electropherogram were retained for subsequent analysis.For all three types of marker system, duplicate samples from each individual were tested, and only clear, unambiguous and reproducible bands amplified in both cases were considered for scoring the data. The number of polymorphic and monomorphic amplification products was determined for each primer for 10 individuals. To avoid taxonomic weighing, the intensity of bands was not taken into consideration, and only the presence of band was taken as an indicative. To compare the efficiency of primers, polymorphic information content (PIC), as a marker discrimination power, was computed using the formula <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="plq017ileq1" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>, where <italic>p<sub>i</sub></italic> is the frequency of the <italic>i</italic>th allele at a given locus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C1">Anderson <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>). The PIC values are commonly used in genetics as a measure of polymorphism for a marker locus using linkage analysis. Marker index (MI) defined as the product of the polymorphism percentage and PIC is used to estimate the overall utility of each marker system and was calculated according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C43">Sorkheh <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>.The basic parameters for genetic diversity were calculated in the POPGENE application (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C51">Yeh <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). The polymorphism of amplification products (<italic>P</italic>), the number of observed alleles (<italic>n</italic><sub>a</sub>), the mean number of effective alleles (<italic>n</italic><sub>e</sub>), the mean Nei's gene diversity index (<italic>h</italic>), the Shannon index (<italic>I</italic>) and the level of gene flow (<italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C40">Slatkin and Barton 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C21">McDermott and McDonald 1993</xref>) were determined. Within-population diversity (<italic>h</italic><sub>pop</sub>), total gene diversity (<italic>h</italic><sub>sp</sub>) and inter-population differentiation (<italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C26">Nei 1973</xref>) were calculated using the POPGENE software.Level of similarity among individuals was established as a percentage of polymorphic bands, and a matrix of genetic similarity compiled using Dice's coefficient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C6">Dice 1945</xref>). By applying the unweighted pair-group arithmetic average (UPGMA) method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C42">Sneath and Sokal 1973</xref>) using the SHAN subroutine through the NTSYS-pc version 2.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C33">Rohlf 2002</xref>), dendrograms representing the genetic relationship among the 10 CPTs of <italic>Pongamia</italic> were generated. The correlation between the original similarity indices and cophenetic values was calculated, and Mantel's test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C20">Mantel 1967</xref>) was performed using 250 permutations to check the goodness of fit of the CPTs to a specific cluster in the UPGMA similarity matrix. Further, principal coordinate analysis (PCA) was undertaken for the families with modules STAND, CORR and EIGEN of NTSYS-pc (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C33">Rohlf 2002</xref>) using the Euclidean distances derived from the standardized values using the NTSYS software.Degree of polymorphism and PIC for RAPD and ISSR primers in 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic>POL, polymorphism; M, monomorphic marker; PIC, average polymorphic information content for polymorphic bands; MI, marker index = POL (%) × PIC.<bold>RAPD and ISSR polymorphic profiles for 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> belonging to populations 6 and 10.</bold> Lane M, 1 kb DNA ladder; lanes 1–5, NGPP 26–NGPP 30; lanes 6–10, NGPP 46–NGPP 50. (A) RAPD (OPAH 13); (B) ISSR (825).Amplification of ISSR markers was performed using 20 primers, of which 12 primers gave reproducible and good quality banding patterns. The 12 ISSR primers produced a total of 129 fragments with size ranging from 0.2 to 0.85 kb. Out of 129 ISSR loci, 14 bands were polymorphic among 10 CPTs as revealed by six primers (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ017TB1">1</xref>), whereas the other six primers (HB 14, HB 15, P 6, P 8, 809 and 824) produced monomorphic fragments. The percentage of ISSR polymorphism for these 10 CPTs is thus a maximum of 10.08. The average number of bands per primer was 10.75. A survey of different ISSR primers used (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ017TB1">1</xref>) indicated that for each primer, the number of visible bands ranged from 6 to 17 (obtained by primer 824 and HB 12, respectively). Primers 825 (ACACACACACACACACT) and 826 (ACACACACACACACACC) exhibited the highest level of variability, and the polymorphism rate was 25 % in both cases. Typical polymorphic ISSR fingerprint using the primer 825 is shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ017F1">1</xref>B. The PIC values for polymorphic ISSR primers ranged from 0.18 (818) to 0.50 (CAG)<sub>5</sub> with an average of 0.39, whereas MI ranged from 2.25 (818) to 12.33 (825).Degree of polymorphism and PIC for AFLP primers applied to 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic>POL, polymorphism; PIC, average polymorphic information content for polymorphic bands;MI, marker index = POL (%) × PIC.Mean genetic data of two populations having a total of 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic><italic>n</italic><sub>a</sub>, observed number of alleles; <italic>n</italic><sub>e</sub>, effective number of alleles; <italic>h</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C26">Nei's (1973)</xref> gene diversity; <italic>I</italic>, Shannon's information index; <italic>P</italic>, number of polymorphic bands; POL (%), percentage polymorphism.Genetic population structure and estimate of gene flow within the populations of CPT of <italic>P. pinnata</italic><italic>H</italic><sub>sp</sub>, total variability; <italic>H</italic><sub>pop</sub>, variability within population; <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub>, inter-population differentiation; <italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub>, estimate of gene flow from <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C40">Slatkin and Barton 1989</xref>). <italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub> = 0.5(1 − <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub>)/<italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub>  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C21">McDermott and McDonald 1993</xref>).<bold>Dendrograms representing the genetic variability among 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> belonging to populations 6 and 10 as revealed by the UPGMA cluster analysis.</bold> The genetic distances were from the Dice similarity coefficient. (A) RAPD; (B) ISSR; (C) AFLP.The relationship among individual CPTs belonging to two populations was also visualized in the UPGMA dendrogram generated from AFLP analysis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ017F2">2</xref>C). Five distinct clusters were formed. The data obtained based on AFLP analysis in the present study discriminated most individuals and grouped them together, though belonging to two different populations (such as NGPP 26, 48; NGPP 28, 46 and NGPP 49, 30 more closely related), hinting that inter-population differences were more significant compared with intra-population ones (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ017F2">2</xref>C). The PCA analysis supported the results of clustering (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/plq017/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Additional information, Fig. 1A–C</ext-link>). The Mantel method used to compare the similarity matrices produced correlation coefficients that were statistically significant for each of the three marker systems used independently, viz. RAPD, ISSR and AFLP. The cophenetic correlation coefficient between the dendrogram and the original similarity matrix was large and significant for RAPD (<italic>r</italic> = 0.84), ISSR (<italic>r</italic> = 0.73) and AFLP (<italic>r</italic> = 0.98), giving a good degree of confidence in the association obtained for the CPTs.For the effective genetic improvement programme of <italic>P. pinnata</italic>, maintenance of high genetic diversity is one of the most important issues as the species have immense multipurpose importance, yet genetically uncharacterized. A wide range of variability exists in <italic>Pongamia</italic> with respect to seed and oil traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C12">Kaushik <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C14">Kesari <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C25">Mukta <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Morphological markers for identifying the individuals are limited in number and they do not often reflect genetic relationships because of interaction with the environment, epistasis and the largely unknown genetic control of the traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C41">Smith and Smith 1989</xref>). In contrast, DNA markers are found in abundance and are not influenced by the environment or developmental stage of a plant, making them an ideal tool for genetic relationship studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C32">Reddy <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). In the case of <italic>Pongamia</italic>, a few recent studies have been conducted to assess molecular diversity in the germplasm collection using a PCR-based approach. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C34">Sahoo <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> utilized ISSR markers to assess the extent of genetic structure in a representative set of 226 individuals of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> encompassing 7 populations from different eco-geographical regions of Orissa. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C38">Sharma <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> assessed 20 random individuals of the <italic>P. pinnata</italic> using 2 dominant molecular markers, AFLP and 3 endonuclease (TE)-AFLP. In the present study, genetic variability for 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> from North Guwahati, Assam, was assessed by DNA marker-based analysis.The use of seeds instead of leaves as a starting material for genetic variability studies is time saving and less expensive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C22">McDonald <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>). The plants do not have to be individually grown, and DNA can be extracted directly from seeds with the technical precautions of eliminating polysaccharides by supplementary DNA precipitation. The use of RAPD markers from seeds in a stable manner for varietal identification and genetic diversity evaluation has already been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C22">McDonald <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C7">Fu <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). The present study constitutes the first successful attempt at assessment of genetic variability by DNA-based molecular characterization using seeds of <italic>Pongamia</italic> CPTs.The amplification profiles of the three marker systems resulted in differences in the detected banding patterns. The level of polymorphism for each of the three marker systems was quite variable. AFLP analysis revealed a high level of genetic diversity (100 %) in natural populations of <italic>P. pinnata</italic>, whereas only a small amount of variation (approx. 10 %) was detected based on both RAPD and ISSR markers in CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C12">Kaushik <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> also reported that the distribution of genetic variability is limited in <italic>P. pinnata</italic> on the basis of their morphological characteristics such as pod and seed traits. However, higher level of polymorphism (94.3 %) was reported in seven populations of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> using few ISSR markers, but the samplings were done from three different eco-geographical regions of Orissa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C34">Sahoo <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Other woody perennial species such as <italic>Populus tremuloides</italic> and <italic>Isotoma petraea</italic> display lower levels of genetic variation detected with the same RAPD methodology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C50">Yeh <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C5">Bussell 1999</xref>).PIC analysis can be used to evaluate markers so that the most appropriate marker can be selected for genetic mapping and phylogenetic analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C1">Anderson <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C30">Powell <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>). Higher PIC value for the AFLP marker obtained would make its MI much higher than that of the other two dominant makers used in the present study.  MI together with PIC value has been used to assess the informativeness of the markers earlier in another biofuel crop <italic>Jatropha</italic> (PIC = 0.26, MI = 25.15; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C47">Tatikonda <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).From the heterogeneity data obtained it was observed that the total variability (<italic>h</italic><sub>sp</sub>) was highest when compared with average intra-population diversity (<italic>h</italic><sub>pop</sub>) based on all three molecular markers used in the current study. Similar trends have been observed in other crop species such as wild species of almond (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C3">Blair <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C43">Sorkheh <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). AFLP revealed high levels of genetic diversity at the population as well as the species level based on the value of the Shannon index. The estimate of mean <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub> revealed that <italic>P. pinnata</italic> tends to be mainly an outcrossing mating system. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C8">Hamrick (1989)</xref>, the tree populations distributed continuously having a longer life span with anemophily or cross-pollinating in nature possess higher genetic diversity, but lower genetic differentiation. Higher <italic>N</italic><sub>m</sub> value (6.287) based on AFLP reflects ample gene flow among and within populations that might be attributed primarily to the long-distance dispersal of pollen by strong winds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C10">Huang <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The results of the current study for <italic>P. pinnata</italic> are, in general, in accordance with what is expected for tropical trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C17">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C31">Przyborowski and Sulima 2010</xref>).The wide variation in genetic similarity among the 10 CPTs by the three DNA-based markers used in the study reflects a high level of polymorphism at the DNA level. RAPD and ISSR markers showed a high degree of similarity in dendrogram topologies, although with some differences, in the positioning of few individuals. Both markers aim to amplify a different region of the genome, and thus it is reasonable that there are some fine differences between the two dendrograms based on an individual data set. Relationships inferred from a neighbour-joining tree were similar to the ones obtained from morphology, but somewhat better resolutions were achieved. The similar structure of the dendrogram also suggests that both techniques are suitable for genetic polymorphism research on <italic>Pongamia</italic>. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C9">Hamrick and Loveless (1989)</xref>, the breeding system of a species is an important determinant of variability at both the species and population levels. The morphological, RAPD and ISSR data led to similar representations of the individual relationships. However, AFLP results revealed that the genetic variability was not according to the population distribution.In the current study, four AFLP primer combinations were sufficient to disclose a proper number of polymorphic DNA fragments in support of all comparisons and of their statistical evaluation. Amplified fragment length polymorphism detected polymorphism more efficiently due to a greater number of loci detected/assay reactions. Based on the marker index value obtained, AFLP is found to be more efficient in detecting diversity among 10 CPTs. Genotype identification should be possible even with few AFLP primer combinations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C11">Karudapuram and Larson 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C28">Ozkan <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). However, to assess the genetic diversity and the genetic structure, a higher number of genotypes and localities are necessary. In this sense, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C28">Ozkan <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C11">Karudapuram and Larson (2005)</xref> analysed 76 genotypes from 10 ecologically and geographically different locations. Among the three marker systems used, the highest similarity and cophenetic correlations were obtained for AFLP followed by RAPD and ISSR. The reason could be associated with the different nature of the three markers and different types of polymorphism detected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C36">Scariot <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Principal coordinate analysis is used to show multiple dimensions of the distribution of the genotypes in a scatter-plot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C13">Keim <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>). Separation of individuals to their respective clusters as evident from the UPGMA dendrogram as well as PCA was observed for all the three markers with the exception of a few rearrangements. This multivariate approach was used to complement the information obtained from the cluster analysis because it is more informative regarding distances among major groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C46">Taran <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>).The advantages of using three different marker systems are that they may have different applications in studies of <italic>P. pinnata</italic>, specific to their characteristics, but are unlikely to be similar because of convergent evolution and they can generate information at many different loci. In fact, the ISSR markers target regions between microsatellite loci distributed across the genome, while the RAPD and AFLP markers scan the entire genome and, hence, genome-wide genetic variation could be detected by the use of three DNA-based marker systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ017C29">Pamidimarri <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).In summary, in this genomic era, the present study is the first attempt at molecular characterization in systematically identified locally grown CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> with multiple molecular markers. The observations demonstrate the usefulness, limitations and resolution power of several types of molecular markers in comparison to classical morphological descriptors for analysing the <italic>P. pinnata</italic> genome, for which no prior genome sequence information is available. The results presented herein reveal that 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> belonging to two different populations exhibit large proportions of genetic variation as confirmed by fingerprinting profiles. Amplified fragment length polymorphisms outperform RAPDs and ISSRs in determining genetic variability among CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> due to their high reproducibility, robustness, informativeness and fewer reported reaction artefacts. The other two markers, RAPD and ISSR, showed less variability and showed congruent results in determining the genetic relationship among elite individuals of the study material. This study has provided a larger number of reliable and reproducible fingerprinting profiles for sustainable management, linkage mapping, developing single-locus sequence-characterized amplified region markers and genetic improvement of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> through conventional breeding methodologies as well as molecular breeding approaches such as marker-assisted selection.The following additional information is available in the online version of this article.Figure S1. Principal co-ordinate map for the first, second and third principal coordinates estimated for RAPD, ISSR and AFLP markers for 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> belonging to populations 6 and 10. (A) RAPD; (B) ISSR; (C) AFLP.Table S1. Sequence information of RAPD and ISSR oligonucleotide primers used for amplification and polymorphism study among 10 CPTs of <italic>P. pinnata</italic> belonging to populations 6 and 10.V.K. thanks <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Council of Industrial Research</grant-sponsor> (CSIR), <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Government of India for Senior Research Fellowship</grant-sponsor> (SRF). L.R. acknowledges <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Department of Science and Technology-Science and Engineering Research Council</grant-sponsor> (DST-SERC), <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Government of India,</grant-sponsor> for funding the research.All the authors contributed to a similar extent overall and all authors have seen and agreed to the submitted manuscript.None declared.Authors are thankful to the Forest Department officials of Sila Forest, North Guwahati, for kind supply of study material.