Dominant plant taxa predict plant productivity responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment across precipitation and soil gradientsWhat have we learned from 15 years of free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (FACE)? A meta-analytic review of the responses of photosynthesis, canopy properties and plant production to rising CO<sub>2</sub>Biota growth factor β: stimulation of terrestrial ecosystem net primary production by elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>Maintenance of C sinks sustains enhanced C assimilation during long-term exposure to elevated [CO<sub>2</sub>] in Mojave Desert shrubsEcosystem assembly and terrestrial carbon balance under elevated CO<sub>2</sub>Productivity responses to altered rainfall patterns in a C<sub>4</sub>-dominated grasslandPrimary productivity and water balance of grassland vegetation on three soils in a continuous CO<sub>2</sub> gradient: Initial results from the Lysimeter CO<sub>2</sub> Gradient ExperimentRelative effects of precipitation variability and warming on tallgrass prairie ecosystem functionSoil-mediated effects of subambient to increased carbon dioxide on grassland productivityCommunity shifts under climate change: Mechanisms at multiple scalesIncreasing precipitation event size increases aboveground net primary productivity in a semi-arid grasslandEffects of biodiversity on ecosystem functioning: a consensus of current knowledgeIncreases in desert shrub productivity under elevated carbon dioxide vary with water availabilitySeasonal not annual rainfall determines grassland biomass response to carbon dioxideElongated chambers for field studies across atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> gradientsBiotic, abiotic and performance aspects of the Nevada Desert Free-Air CO<sub>2</sub> Enrichment (FACE) facilityPlant CO<sub>2</sub> responses: an issue of definition, time and resource supplyElevated CO<sub>2</sub> enhances water relations and productivity and affects gas exchange in C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> grasses of the Colorado shortgrass steppeCO<sub>2</sub> enhances productivity, alters species composition, and reduces digestibility of shortgrass steppe vegetationWater relations in grassland and desert ecosystems exposed to elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>C<sub>4</sub> grasses prosper as carbon dioxide eliminates desiccation in warmed semi-arid grasslandPhotosynthetic responses of Mojave Desert shrubs to free air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment are greatest during wet yearsElevated CO<sub>2</sub> increases soil moisture and enhances plant water relations in a long-term field study in semi-arid shortgrass steppe of ColoradoNo cumulative effect of 10 years of elevated [CO<sub>2</sub>] on perennial plant biomass components in the Mojave DesertDoes a decade of elevated [CO<sub>2</sub>] affect a desert perennial plant community?Leaf conductance decreased under free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (FACE) for three perennials in the Nevada desertElevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> does not conserve soil water in the Mojave DesertFunctional responses of plants to elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>—do photosynthetic and productivity data from FACE experiments support early predictions?Ecosystem-level responses of tallgrass prairie to elevated CO<sub>2</sub>Projected ecosystem impact of the Prairie heating and CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment experimentCross-scale interactions, nonlinearities, and forecasting catastrophic eventsSoil- and plant-water dynamics in a C<sub>3</sub>/C<sub>4</sub> grassland exposed to a subambient to superambient CO<sub>2</sub> gradientIncreasing CO<sub>2</sub> from subambient to superambient concentrations alters species composition and increases above-ground biomass in a C<sub>3</sub>/C<sub>4</sub> grasslandInitial response of evapotranspiration from tallgrass prairie vegetation to CO<sub>2</sub> at subambient to elevated concentrationsApplication of a conceptual framework to interpret variability in rangeland responses to atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> enrichmentCO<sub>2</sub>-caused change in plant species composition rivals the shift in vegetation between mid-grass and tallgrass prairiesFeedback from plant species change amplifies CO<sub>2</sub> enhancement of grassland productivityDifferential sensitivities of grassland structural components to changes in precipitation mediate productivity response in a desert ecosystemDominant species maintain ecosystem function with non-random species lossA framework for assessing ecosystem dynamics in response to chronic resource alterations induced by global changeElevated CO<sub>2</sub> increases productivity and invasive species success in an arid ecosystemLong-term response of a Mojave Desert winter annual plant community to a whole-ecosystem atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> manipulation (FACE)<bold>Guest Editor:</bold> Elise S. GornishContinued increases in atmospheric carbon dioxide will increase the productivity of rangelands partly by plant community change. Soil moisture increases may contribute more in arid systems or on coarser-textured soils, but not in deserts. Surprisingly, community change explained virtually all of yearly productivity increases in semi-arid grassland and up to 80% in mesic grassland, but only on some soil types, and a xeric shrubland exhibited no productivity, soil moisture or community change responses. Thus, community change dominated the productivity response to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in grasslands, and the contribution of yearly soil moisture responses requires further research.The Earth's atmosphere will continue to be enriched with carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) over the coming century. Carbon dioxide enrichment often reduces leaf transpiration, which in water-limited ecosystems may increase soil water content, change species abundances and increase the productivity of plant communities. The effect of increased soil water on community productivity and community change may be greater in ecosystems with lower precipitation, or on coarser-textured soils, but responses are likely absent in deserts. We tested correlations among yearly increases in soil water content, community change and community plant productivity responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in experiments in a mesic grassland with fine- to coarse-textured soils, a semi-arid grassland and a xeric shrubland. We found no correlation between CO<sub>2</sub>-caused changes in soil water content and changes in biomass of dominant plant taxa or total community aboveground biomass in either grassland type or on any soil in the mesic grassland (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.60). Instead, increases in dominant taxa biomass explained up to 85 % of the increases in total community biomass under CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment. The effect of community change on community productivity was stronger in the semi-arid grassland than in the mesic grassland, where community biomass change on one soil was not correlated with the change in either the soil water content or the dominant taxa. No sustained increases in soil water content or community productivity and no change in dominant plant taxa occurred in the xeric shrubland. Thus, community change was a crucial driver of community productivity responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in the grasslands, but effects of soil water change on productivity were not evident in yearly responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment. Future research is necessary to isolate and clarify the mechanisms controlling the temporal and spatial variations in the linkages among soil water, community change and plant productivity responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment.Continued enrichment of the Earth's atmosphere with carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) is certain through the coming century and is expected to alter climate and terrestrial ecosystem structure and function. In water-limited ecosystems, one major mechanism by which CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment may cause ecosystem change is by increasing soil water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C20">Morgan <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C27">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>a</italic></xref>). CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment can increase soil water by reducing stomatal conductance and leaf- and canopy-scale transpiration in both C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C28">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C1">Ainsworth and Long 2005</xref>). Lower stomatal conductance and plant transpiration under CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in turn decreases soil water depletion, which results in higher soil water and potentially reduced water limitation of ecosystem processes compared with ambient CO<sub>2</sub>.Increased soil water with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment generally increases the productivity of water-limited plant communities. Greater productivity increases often occur with lower precipitation across precipitation levels typical of grassland ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C29">Owensby <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C20">Morgan <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C28">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C16">Körner 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C35">Polley <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), because the increased soil water under CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment is more likely to relieve water limitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C28">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>b</italic></xref>). However, in severely water-limited systems such as deserts, CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment may not increase productivity if reduced leaf transpiration is offset by increased leaf area because soil water may not increase. In addition, slow growth rates in drought-adapted desert plants limit the potential to increase community productivity in the short-term (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C28">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C24">Newingham <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>).Model by which increased soil water resulting from atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment may increase plant community productivity in water-limited ecosystems. The increase in soil water may predict the increase in community productivity, or the effect of soil water increase may be mediated by change in the abundance of dominant plant taxa, which in turn predicts in the increase in community productivity.The contributions of increased soil water and community change to increased community productivity with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment are also expected to differ with soil texture. At precipitation levels typical of grasslands, soil water will be lower on coarse-textured than fine-textured soils, increasing water limitation of community productivity, and thus the importance of soil water increases in regulating productivity. For example, over 4 years of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment, the increase in plant aboveground biomass was best predicted by soil water on a coarse-textured soil, but increases in biomass were best predicted by the abundance of a dominant grass species on a fine-textured soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C8">Fay <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>), which accounted for up to 60 % of the effect of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C37">Polley <italic>et al</italic>. 2012<italic>b</italic></xref>).To investigate how water-limited plant communities respond to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment across varying precipitation amounts and soils, we examined soil water, plant community change and plant productivity responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in five multi-year CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment experiments from mesic and semi-arid grasslands and in a xeric shrubland in the central and western USA. The experiments span a 6-fold range of mean annual precipitation (MAP), which provides a test of variation in CO<sub>2</sub> responses with precipitation. The mesic grassland experiment contained fine and coarse-textured soils, providing a test of texture effects on CO<sub>2</sub> responses. Interannual variability in precipitation is often high in water-limited systems, and so yearly community productivity increases from CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment were correlated with increases in soil water and community change.Location, climate and CO<sub>2</sub> treatments for the four experiments. MAP, mean annual precipitation; MAT, mean annual temperature.CO<sub>2</sub> manipulation experiments included in the study. (A) Carbon dioxide gradient chambers used in PCG and LYCOG experiments in mesic grassland (Photo: P. Fay, USDA-ARS). (B) Open-top chambers used in short-grass steppe experiment (Photo: S. Cox, USDA-ARS). (C) Free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment technology used in mixed-grass prairie PHACE experiment (Photo: S. Cox, USDA-ARS). (D) FACE plot used in xeric shrubland experiment (L. Fenstermaker, Desert Research Institute).The Lysimeter CO<sub>2</sub> Gradient (LYCOG) experiment was the successor to the PCG experiment and adapted the PCG chambers to enclose 60 intact soil monoliths (1.5 m<sup>3</sup>) from a silty clay, a sandy loam and a heavy clay soil, arranged in a stratified random design along the two chambers (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F2">2</xref>A; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C34">Polley <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C6">Fay <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). The monoliths supported well-established, constructed communities of native prairie. The C<sub>4</sub> grasses <italic>Sorghastrum nutans</italic>, <italic>Bouteloua curtipendula</italic>, <italic>Schizachyrium scoparium</italic> and <italic>Tridens albescens</italic> accounted for 80 % of total aboveground biomass. The remainder was C<sub>3</sub> forbs (<italic>Solidago canadensis</italic>, <italic>Salvia azurea</italic>) and one legume (<italic>Desmanthus illinoensis</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C8">Fay <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C36">Polley <italic>et al</italic>. 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>). Other species were regularly removed by hand or selective glyphosate application. Air temperature and vapour pressure deficit were controlled as for PCG; CO<sub>2</sub> concentration was maintained at 500–380 and 380–250 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> during 2006–10. In both experiments, irrigation regimes were representative of average growing season precipitation for the site.Two CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment experiments were conducted in a cold semi-arid steppe region of northeastern Colorado and southeastern Wyoming, characterized by cooler summers than the other sites (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV027TB1">1</xref>). Semi-arid grasslands are more water-limited than mesic grasslands, are dominated by a different, more drought tolerant assemblage of species and are predicted to be more responsive in plant productivity to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment than mesic grasslands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C20">Morgan <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>b</italic></xref>). An open-top chamber (OTC, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F2">2</xref>B) experiment was conducted during 1996–2001 in short-grass steppe near Fort Collins, Colorado. Basal cover of the vegetation was ∼25 %. Two perennial C<sub>3</sub> grasses <italic>Pascopyrum smithii</italic> and <italic>Hesperostipa comata</italic> accounted for 60 % of aboveground biomass, accompanied by a C<sub>4</sub> grass, <italic>Bouteloua gracilis</italic>, and forbs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C18">Morgan <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C19">2004<italic>a</italic></xref>). Six circular plots of 15.5 m<sup>2</sup> were fitted with OTCs which were randomly assigned to maintain an ambient CO<sub>2</sub> level of 360 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> or an elevated CO<sub>2</sub> level of 720 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> during the growing season.The Prairie Heating and CO<sub>2</sub> Experiment (PHACE, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F2">2</xref>C) was conducted in a northern mixed prairie near Cheyenne, Wyoming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C30">Parton <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). Cool-season C<sub>3</sub> grasses, mostly <italic>P. smithii</italic> and <italic>H. comata</italic>, account for 75 % of aboveground biomass. C<sub>4</sub> grasses, almost exclusively <italic>B. gracilis</italic>, and sedges, forbs and small shrubs account for the rest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C21">Morgan <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). PHACE treatments were factorial combinations of two levels of CO<sub>2</sub>; ambient = 385 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> and elevated = 600 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> achieved using Free-Air CO<sub>2</sub> Enrichment (FACE) technology, and ambient or warmed temperature regimes (+1.5/3.0 day/night), with five replications each. Treatments were randomly assigned to twenty 3.3 m diameter circular plots. Here we consider data from 2006 to 2009 from ambient temperature treatments.The Nevada Desert FACE Facility (NDFF, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F2">2</xref>D) was located in the Mojave Desert in southern Nevada, USA, on the Nevada National Security Site, formerly the Nevada Test Site. The climate is mid-latitude desert with the lowest annual precipitation of the sites (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV027TB1">1</xref>) and was thus predicted to be the least responsive to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment due to severe water limitation. Most precipitation occurs during the winter. The NDFF used the FACE technology with three ambient plots averaging 375 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup>, three elevated plots averaging 550 µmol mol<sup>−1</sup> CO<sub>2</sub> and three non-blower control plots without FACE infrastructure; all plots were 23 m in diameter. The NDFF experiment was conducted from April 1997 to June 2007. Experimental plots were in a <italic>Larrea tridentata</italic>—<italic>Ambrosia dumosa</italic> desert scrub community, which consisted of C<sub>3</sub> shrubs, forbs, annuals and a C<sub>4</sub> bunchgrass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C15">Jordan <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>).We used previously published data on soil water content, and dominant taxa and total community aboveground biomass to estimate soil water change, community change and community productivity change in each year of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment. All sites measured vertical profiles of volumetric soil water content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C23">Nelson <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C27">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C30">Parton <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C6">Fay <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). In LYCOG soil water potential was calculated from soil water content using soil water characteristic curves for each soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C8">Fay <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). At the grassland sites, dominant taxa and community biomass were estimated annually from the dry mass of current-year standing aboveground biomass. Aboveground biomass in the xeric shrubland experiment was determined by a single harvest of standing aboveground biomass after 10 years of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C24">Newingham <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>), and responses of dominant species were determined as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C25">Newingham <italic>et al</italic>. (2014)</xref>.The calculation of <italic>β</italic> standardizes the responses for different levels of CO<sub>2</sub> used among the experiments.Soil water content <italic>β</italic> was calculated for the soil depth that best predicted aboveground biomass: 0–135 cm (PCG), 0–40 cm (LYCOG), 70–100 cm (OTC) and 5–25 cm (PHACE). We calculated <italic>β</italic> in the mesic grassland CO<sub>2</sub> gradients from values of biomass and soil water content at 500 and 390 µL L<sup>−1</sup> CO<sub>2.</sub> These values were estimated from linear regressions of biomass and soil water content against CO<sub>2</sub> for each year. In LYCOG, regressions were fit across all three soils and for each soil separately. The <italic>β</italic> values were not calculated for the xeric shrubland because there were no responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in growing season soil water content and no on-going responses in total or dominant taxa aboveground biomass. Correlations among the <italic>β</italic> for community biomass, soil water content and dominant taxa were tested with linear regression analysis. The magnitude of community biomass <italic>β</italic> with no community change was estimated from the <italic>y</italic>-intercept of community biomass <italic>β</italic>/dominant taxa <italic>β</italic> regressions.Relationships among community aboveground biomass, MAP, dominant plant taxa biomass and soil water content (SWC) responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in xeric shrubland, mesic grassland and semi-arid grassland CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment experiments. (A) Community biomass <italic>β</italic>, mean ± SE across all years of CO<sub>2</sub> manipulation for each experiment, plotted by site MAP. Inset is the corresponding mean ± SE soil water content <italic>β</italic>. (B) Relationship between annual values of <italic>β</italic> for community biomass and dominant plant taxa, with linear regressions fit separately to mesic grassland and semi-arid grassland experiments. (C and D) Relationships of community biomass <italic>β</italic> and dominant plant taxa <italic>β</italic> to soil water content <italic>β</italic>.Carbon dioxide enrichment altered the abundance of dominant grasses in both mesic grassland CO<sub>2</sub> experiments. In LYCOG, C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>β</italic> ranged from −0.9 to 1.2. In PCG, C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>β</italic> ranged from −0.23 to 1.0 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F3">3</xref>B), corresponding to −20 to 90 % changes in C<sub>4</sub> grass biomass. Across both experiments, community biomass <italic>β</italic> increased with the C<sub>4</sub> grass β (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.43, <italic>P</italic> = 0.03, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F3">3</xref>B). The community biomass <italic>β</italic> at the <italic>y</italic>-intercept was 0.6, equating to a 15 % increase in community biomass with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in the absence of change in C<sub>4</sub> grass biomass. The values of <italic>β</italic> for community and C<sub>4</sub> grass biomass were not correlated with soil water content <italic>β</italic> (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.69, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F3">3</xref>C and D).Mean community biomass <italic>β</italic> was 0.51 in OTC and 0.73 in PHACE (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F3">3</xref>A), corresponding to 31 and 35 % increases, respectively, in community biomass under CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment. Mean soil water content <italic>β</italic> averaged 0.26 for OTC and 0.39 for PHACE (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F3">3</xref>A, inset), corresponding to 17–18 % increases in soil water content.Summary of correlations among changes in soil water, abundance of dominant plant taxa and plant community biomass increases with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in mesic grassland, semi-arid grassland and xeric shrubland. Solid arrows denote positive correlations among variables, and thicker lines denote stronger relationships. Grey boxes indicate no significant CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment effects, and grey lines indicate no correlations.The xeric shrubland responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment were a dramatic departure from those of the mesic and semi-arid grasslands. Carbon dioxide enrichment at the NDFF had no effect on soil water content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C27">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>a</italic></xref>) or on cumulative total aboveground and belowground biomass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C24">Newingham <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) and productivity of dominant annual plant taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C42">Smith <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F4">4</xref>) following 10 years of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment. Thus, there was no basis for testing correlations among <italic>β</italic> values for soil water content, dominant taxa and aboveground biomass in this system.Relationships among community aboveground biomass, dominant plant taxa biomass and soil water content responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in the three soils in the LYCOG experiment in mesic grassland. (A) Community biomass β, mean ± SE across all years of CO<sub>2</sub> manipulation in relation to soil water content <italic>β</italic>. Large symbols denote means ± SEs across years for each soil. Inset is the corresponding mean ± SE soil water potential for each soil type. (B) Community biomass <italic>β</italic> relationship to C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>β</italic>, with linear regressions fit to silty clay and sandy loam soils. (C) C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>β</italic> relationship to soil water content <italic>β</italic>.Summary of correlations among changes in soil water, abundance of dominant plant taxa and plant community biomass increases with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment on three soils in mesic grassland. Solid arrows denote positive correlations among variables, and thicker lines denote stronger relationships. Grey boxes indicate no significant CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment effects, and grey lines indicate no correlations.The value of <italic>β</italic> for C<sub>4</sub> grasses ranged from −1.0 to 2.0 across all soils (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F5">5</xref>B), corresponding to −41 to 130 % changes in C<sub>4</sub> biomass with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment. The community biomass <italic>β</italic> increased with C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>β</italic> on the silty clay and sandy loam soils (slope = 0.52, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.90, <italic>P</italic> = &lt;0.0001). The community biomass <italic>β</italic> on these two soils was 0.9 at the <italic>y</italic>-intercept for C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>β</italic>, equating to a 2 % increase in community biomass with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in the absence of change in C<sub>4</sub> grass biomass. Community biomass <italic>β</italic> was not correlated with C<sub>4</sub> grass <italic>β</italic> on the clay soil (<italic>P</italic> = 0.31, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F5">5</xref>B). Dominant grass <italic>β</italic> was not correlated with soil water content <italic>β</italic> for any soil (0.28 &lt; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.58; Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F5">5</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F6">6</xref>).Carbon dioxide enrichment can increase the productivity of communities solely by increasing soil water or by mediating community change. Soil water increases were expected to cause larger community productivity responses with lower precipitation and on coarser-textured soils in the grasslands, but responses were expected to decline sharply in the extreme aridity of the xeric shrubland. Our findings indicate that in the grasslands, yearly soil water content increases never predicted community change or community productivity. Instead, community change caused a larger community productivity response in semi-arid than that in mesic grasslands, and the predicted sharp decline in responsiveness to CO<sub>2</sub> was supported in the xeric shrubland.The absence of cumulative increases in community productivity with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in the xeric shrubland may be explained by the absence of increased soil water and community change. There was no sustained increase in soil water content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C27">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2004<italic>a</italic></xref>) because CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment only increased photosynthesis and water-use efficiency and decreased stomatal conductance in occasional wet years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C26">Nowak <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C22">Naumburg <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C12">Housman <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C3">Aranjuelo <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). There was also no sustained community change because the dominant perennial species were unaffected by CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C25">Newingham <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>), and responses were confined to native and exotic annuals which transiently increased with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment only during high rainfall years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C41">Smith <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C42">2014</xref>). Thus, the mechanisms proposed as the fundamental drivers of productivity increases with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in water-limited ecosystems were largely absent in this arid ecosystem.In the grasslands, the absent correlations between soil water content change, community change and community productivity increases suggests that effects of increased soil water on plant productivity were not well represented by the growing season mean soil moisture response. Increased soil water content may not always translate into greater plant growth because plant growth exhibits a threshold response to soil water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C17">Lambers <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Soil water variability, such as an increased duration or severity of soil water deficit, in current or previous years may lower community productivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C32">Polley <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C5">Fay <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C7">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C10">Heisler-White <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C13">Hovenden <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C38">Reichmann and Sala 2014</xref>), and the CO<sub>2</sub> effect on soil water during drought periods may be a better predictor of productivity responses than the mean response in soil water over the growing season.The lack of correlation between yearly soil water change and community responses differs from previous findings. Averaged over multiple years of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment, increased community productivity occurred in part because of increased soil water in these grassland experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C33">Polley <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C23">Nelson <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C21">Morgan <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C8">Fay <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). The importance of soil water increases averaged over multiple years but not in any given year suggests that predictors of community change or productivity responses at one temporal scale may not apply at other scales in these grasslands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C31">Peters <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>).Community change was a stronger predictor of community productivity increases in the drier semi-arid grassland compared with the mesic grassland. The weaker relationship to community change in mesic grassland stemmed from 2 years when CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment increased plant productivity but decreased the dominant taxa (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV027F3">3</xref>B), indicating that productivity of other species in these mesic grassland communities increased with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment enough to offset decreases in the dominants. In contrast, the dominant taxa never decreased in the semi-arid grassland. Offsetting responses within communities may dampen the productivity response to CO<sub>2</sub> in mesic grassland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C11">Hooper <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>), and both dominant and sub-dominant taxa can contribute to community productivity responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment.Two other factors may have contributed to the stronger community change effect on community productivity increases in the semi-arid grassland. First, lower MAP and higher mean soil water content increases with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment may have resulted in release from water limitation for all community members in the semi-arid grassland compared with the mesic grassland. Second, in the mesic grassland, there was no community change effect on community productivity on the clay soil. The strong community change/productivity responses occurred on the two soils with high mean soil water potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C8">Fay <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>), suggesting that the overall availability of soil water, not the increase in soil water content, determines community and productivity responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment.In the semi-arid grassland during years with no community change, there was no increase in community biomass, suggesting that yearly increases in community productivity were almost completely explained by community change. Although community change was a weaker predictor of community productivity change in mesic grassland, it still predicted ∼80 % of the productivity response. These results suggest that, in years with no community change, community productivity increased by 15–22 % from other potential causes, such as direct effects of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment on carbon gain or plant water status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV027C1">Ainsworth and Long 2005</xref>).Community change predicted most of the changes in community productivity in the grasslands and better predicted community productivity responses in the drier grassland and on soils with higher plant availability of soil water in the mesic grassland. The xeric shrubland makes clear that in the absence of increased soil water or community change, increased community productivity is unlikely. The linkage of community change and productivity to yearly changes in soil water with CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment remains unclear, but it may depend more on the temporal variability in soil water than on the size of the increase. Future research needs to isolate and clarify the temporal and spatial mechanisms controlling the linkages among soil water, community change and plant productivity responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment.<italic>Mesic grassland experiments</italic>: USDA-ARS Climate Change, Soils &amp; Emissions and Pasture, Forage and Rangeland Systems Programs. <italic>Semi-arid grassland experiments</italic>: NSF-TECO (IBN-9524068), NSF (DEB-9708596, 1021559), the NSF LTER (DEB-9350273), USDA-ARS Climate Change, Soils &amp; Emissions Program, USDA-CSREES (2008-35107-18655), the US DOE NICCR (DE-SC0006973). <italic>Xeric shrubland experiments</italic>: US DOE (DE-FG02-03ER63651), NSF (DEB-0212812) and the Nevada Agricultural Experiment Station. Opinions, findings and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation. USDA is an Equal Opportunity Employer.P.A.F. and B.A.N. conceived the manuscript and led the writing, P.A.F. analysed the data and the remaining authors contributed data, edited the manuscript and approved the submission.None declared.The authors thank the many technicians, students and collaborators whose fieldwork made these data available and whose preceding research provided the foundation for this paper.