When Michaelis and Menten met Holling: towards a mechanistic theory of plant nutrient foraging behaviourImplications of flexible foraging for interspecific interactions: lessons from simple modelsQuantitative descriptions of resource choice in ecological modelsKinetics of nutrient uptake by roots: responses to global changePatch use as an indicator of habitat preference, predation risk, and competitionThe behavioral ecology of nutrient foraging by plantsA comparative-study of plant responsiveness to the duration of episodes of mineral nutrient enrichmentA trade-off between scale and precision in resource foragingOptimal foraging, marginal value theoremLinking aboveground and belowground diversityMorphological plasticity in clonal plants—the foraging concept reconsideredNutrient supply and growth of seminal root system in Barley. II. Localized, compensatory increases in lateral root growth and rates of nitrate uptake when nitrate supply is restricted to only part of root systemKin recognition in an annual plantNutrient foraging traits in 10 co-occurring plant species of contrasting life formsA kinetic study of the absorption of alkali cations by barley rootsLong-term disadvantages of selective root placement: root proliferation and shoot biomass of two perennial grass species in a 2-year experimentOn territorial behavior and other factors influencing habitat distribution in birdsTragedy of the commons as a result of root competitionRoot proliferation and marginal patch valueThe plastic plant: root responses to heterogeneous supplies of nutrientsRoot decisionsThe components of predation as revealed by a study of small mammal predation of the European pine sawflyForaging in plants—the role of morphological plasticity in resource acquisitionToward understanding the consequences of soil heterogeneity for plant populations and communitiesThe scale of nutrient heterogeneity around individual plants and its quantification with geostatisticsRoot plasticity of native and invasive Great Basin species in response to soil nitrogen heterogeneityThe original Michaelis constant: translation of the 1913 Michaelis–Menten paperPlant behaviour and communicationPlant foraging—a marginal value model and coiling response in <italic>Cuscuta subinclusa</italic>Resource choice in <italic>Cuscuta europaea</italic>Plant phenotypic plasticity belowground: a phylogenetic perspective on root foraging trade-offsImproving the scale and precision of hypotheses to explain root foraging abilityPicante: R tools for integrating phylogenies and ecologyPatch-background contrast and patch density have limited effects on root proliferation and plant performance in <italic>Abutilon theophrasti</italic>Preferential expression of an ammonium transporter and of two putative nitrate transporters in root hairs of tomatoThe determination of enzyme dissociation constantsAn ideal free distribution explains the root production of plants that do not engage in a tragedy of the commons gamePlant root growth and the marginal value theoremGame theory and plant ecologyFocusing the metaphor: plant foraging behaviourEcological implications of single and mixed nitrogen nutrition in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Die Kinetik der InvertinwirkungState dependent behavior and the marginal value theoremRoot foraging for patchy resources in eight herbaceous plant speciesKinetics of functional responseThe responses of plants to nonuniform supplies of nutrientsResource capture by localized root proliferation: why do plants bother?The effects of nutrient dynamics on root patch choiceA framework for plant behaviorOptimal foraging when regulating intake of multiple nutrientsThe foraging tactics of plantsRoot resource foraging: does it matter?Trade-offs and coexistence in consumer-resource models: it all depends on what and where you eatPhylomatic: tree assembly for applied phylogenetics<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> James F. CahillThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.To the untrained eye plants might appear to be more like an inanimate object than the type of organism that exhibits behaviour. However, if you know where to look, you will find that plants are remarkably good at assessing and responding to environmental conditions in ways that are best described using behavioural models. Here we show that botanists and zoologists have been using rearranged forms of an identical equation to explain resource intake. By rearranging this equation, botanists may preserve existing knowledge on uptake physiology, while simultaneously gaining access to a rich literature on foraging theory.Plants are adept at assessing and responding to nutrients in soil, and generally proliferate roots into nutrient-rich patches. An analogy between this growth response and animal foraging movement is often drawn, but because of differences between plants and animals it has not always been clear how to directly apply existing foraging theory to plants. Here we suggest one way to unite pre-existing ideas in plant nutrient uptake with foraging theory. First, we show that the Michaelis–Menten equation used by botanists and the Holling disc equation used by zoologists are actually just rearrangements of the same functional response. This mathematical unity permits the translation of existing knowledge about the nutrient uptake physiology of plants into the language of foraging behaviour, and as a result gives botanists direct access to foraging theory. Second, we developed a model of root foraging precision based on the Holling disc equation and the marginal value theorem, and parameterize it from the literature. The model predicts (i) generally plants should invest in higher quality patches compared to lower quality patches, and as patch background–contrast increases; (ii) low encounter rates between roots and nutrients result in high root foraging precision; and (iii) low handling times for nutrients should result in high root foraging precision. The available data qualitatively support these predictions. Third, to parameterize the model above we undertook a review of the literature. From that review we obtained parameter estimates for nitrate and/or ammonium uptake for 45 plant species from 38 studies. We observe that the parameters ranged over six orders of magnitude, there was no trade-off in foraging ability for nitrate versus ammonium: plants that were efficient foragers for one form of nitrogen were efficient foragers for the other, and there was also no phylogenetic signal in the parameter estimates.Nutrients are typically distributed heterogeneously throughout the soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C24">Jackson and Caldwell 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C22">Hutchings and de Kroon 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C19">Hodge 2004</xref>) and plants are adept at assessing and responding to this nutrient heterogeneity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C46">Robinson 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C10">de Kroon and Hutchings 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C19">Hodge 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C30">Kembel and Cahill 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C5">Cahill and McNickle 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C54">Tian and Doerner 2013</xref>). Generally, plants respond to nutrient-rich patches by preferentially proliferating roots into those patches. This growth response results in an increased absorptive surface area inside nutrient-rich patches relative to lower quality regions of the average background soil and is generally considered to be an adaptive response. Increasingly, there has been a trend towards viewing this plasticity in root growth with respect to nutrients through a lens of behavioural ecology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C53">Sutherland and Stillman 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C49">Silvertown and Gordon 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C29">Kelly 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C22">Hutchings and de Kroon 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C10">de Kroon and Hutchings 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C17">Gersani <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C12">Dudley and File 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C20">Hodge 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C27">Karban 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C39">McNickle <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C5">Cahill and McNickle 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C54">Tian and Doerner 2013</xref>). This gradual shift in perspectives on how plants acquire nutrients has been driven by data demonstrating that plants are not passively following pre-determined growth trajectories, but instead plant growth is based on actively assessing and responding to cues from the soil nutrient environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C49">Silvertown and Gordon 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C22">Hutchings and de Kroon 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C20">Hodge 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C27">Karban 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C5">Cahill and McNickle 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C54">Tian and Doerner 2013</xref>).However, despite substantial gains in our knowledge of the range of plant nutrient foraging behaviours, we are still a long way from incorporating plant foraging behaviour as a united sub-field of behavioural ecology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C39">McNickle <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C5">Cahill and McNickle 2011</xref>). Indeed, many questions remain about plant root foraging behaviour. For example, the average plant appears to strongly proliferate roots into nutrient-rich patches; however, some species do not strongly proliferate roots into patches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C19">Hodge 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C30">Kembel and Cahill 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C31">Kembel <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C5">Cahill and McNickle 2011</xref>). Additionally, some species of plants appear to discriminate among patches of varying quality by proliferating higher root mass into more nutrient-rich patches, while other species show little discrimination among patches that differ in nutrient availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C18">Gleeson and Fry 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C23">Hutchings <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C37">McNickle and Cahill 2009</xref>). There are also unresolved questions about how plants should invest in patches based on the contrast between nutrient availability in rich patches versus poorer background soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C33">Lamb <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Logically, we would expect all plant species to benefit from nutrient-rich patches (when they are nutrient limited) and so we lack a first principles explanation that can permit an understanding of why species differ so much in their foraging responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C31">Kembel <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C37">McNickle and Cahill 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C39">McNickle <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).In a perfect world plant foraging theory would not reinvent the wheel, but integrate existing ideas about plant ecology, plant nutrient uptake physiology and behavioural ecology. Here, we attempt such a synthesis by exploring the previously recognized fact that the Holling disc equation used by foraging ecologists to model resource intake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C21">Holling 1959</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C51">Stephens and Krebs 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C55">Vincent <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C52">Stephens <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) and the Michaelis–Menten equation used by plant physiologists to model nutrient uptake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C41">Michaelis and Menten 1913</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C35">Lineweaver and Burk 1934</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C14">Epstein and Hagen 1951</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C26">Johnson and Goody 2011</xref>) are actually rearranged forms of the same functional response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C45">Real 1977</xref>). As we show, this identity in functional response permits the translation of plant nutrient uptake physiology into the language of foraging behaviour. We have three main objectives: first, we compare the models used by biologists to describe resource capture to show that the models used by plant physiologists and animal behaviourists are mathematically identical. Second, we derive a simple example model to predict the root foraging precision of plants that is based on the well-described functional response of plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C14">Epstein and Hagen 1951</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C3">Bassirirad 2000</xref>) and the marginal value theorem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C8">Charnov 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C37">McNickle and Cahill 2009</xref>). Third, we parameterize the foraging model with a realistic range of plant foraging traits obtained from a literature review of existing studies of plant uptake kinetics for nitrate and ammonium and recast these results from ‘enzyme-kinetics’ into ‘foraging kinetics’. We also present a summary of these data with three sub-objectives: (i) we describe the range and central tendency within the observed patterns of nutrient uptake traits; (ii) we ask whether there is any relationship in the ability of plants to capture the substitutable resources of nitrate and ammonium and (iii) we ask whether there is any phylogenetic signal in these uptake parameters. We conclude with a discussion of the value of rethinking plant uptake of nutrients as a process of enzyme kinetics to a process of foraging behaviour.Graphical comparison of (A) the Michaelis–Menten equation that relates resource harvest rates to resource abundance and (B) the Holling disc equation that relates resource harvest to resource abundance. The parameters of the Michaelis–Menten equation describe the shape of the curve where <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> is the maximum resource harvest rate and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> is the concentration of nutrients that produces half of the maximum resource harvest rate (A). The parameters of the Holling disc equation describe traits of the organisms, and though they produce the same curve, these parameters cannot be placed in the figure.As above, <italic>dH/</italic><italic>dt</italic> is the harvest rate (units of resource per time per individual forager); <italic>N</italic> is the concentration of prey in the environment (more typically referred to as prey abundance, but abundance per area or volume is mathematically identical to the concept of nutrient concentration); <italic>a</italic> is the rate that prey are encountered by the forager (here in units of per time per individual forager, often called search efficiency) and <italic>h</italic> is the time required by the forager to handle each encountered prey item (units of individual forager × time per prey). Note here that instead of describing the shape of the functional response, the parameters <italic>a</italic> and <italic>h</italic> describe activities relevant to the process of foraging.In the root foraging form of the Holling disc equation, a unit of root (<italic>r</italic>, units of mass or length) substitutes for the individual forager, and the plant can effectively be many foragers at once by proliferating many units of root into a volume of soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C39">McNickle <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).Comparison of the parameters of the Michaelis–Menten equation, and the Holling disc equation. The two models are built from an equation of the same general form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C45">Real 1977</xref>) and the two equations model identical processes in plants and animals. This produces interchangeable parameters, where the units of measurement also perfectly translate.From the Holling equation, where parameters map directly to functional behavioural traits, many aspects of foraging behaviour can be intuitively derived as a direct consequence of search and handling (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C52">Stephens <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Here we advance a simple nutrient foraging model for plants which is based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C8">Charnov's (1976)</xref> marginal value theorem and the Holling disc equation as one example of the value of translating Michaelis–Menten kinetics into Holling's foraging kinetics. The marginal value theorem hypothesizes that foragers should invest effort (here effort is root biomass) into patches until the nutrient uptake rate inside the patch balances the rate in the background soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C8">Charnov 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C18">Gleeson and Fry 1997</xref>), and several species of plants have been shown to follow this prediction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C28">Kelly 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C29">Kelly 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C37">McNickle and Cahill 2009</xref>). For plants that can place foraging roots in multiple locations, this prediction is also similar to the ideal free distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C16">Fretwell and Lucas 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C36">McNickle and Brown 2014</xref>). However, plant foraging is sufficiently different from animal foraging that one further modification is necessary.Plant foraging is often measured as root foraging precision, which compares the investment of root biomass or root length inside a patch with other locations in the soil. This plant foraging behaviour differs from animal foraging where questions are typically about understanding time investment or energy requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C39">McNickle <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Thus, the model we develop predicts root foraging precision, which we define as the ratio of root production inside a nutrient-rich patch of some volume to the root production in the poorer quality background soil of equal volume (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C43">Rajaniemi and Reynolds 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C25">James <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C37">McNickle and Cahill 2009</xref>). It is important to note that many other definitions of root foraging precision have been used by empiricists. However, all of these definitions of precision are conceptually similar in that they attempt to estimate the relative investment of root biomass inside a nutrient-rich patch relative to the investment in average background habitat quality. These other definitions are not easily predicted from the functional response without more complicated treatments of root : shoot growth or spatial dimensions of soil. For example, some authors defined precision as the mass of roots inside a patch as a fraction of total body mass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C7">Campbell <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>) but a model for this type of foraging precision would require significantly more complex treatments of root growth relative to nutrients and shoot growth relative to photosynthetically active radiation that are beyond the scope of this manuscript. Other authors have defined precision as the relative proportion of total root system inside a patch (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C30">Kembel and Cahill 2005</xref>) or the relative root mass difference between patch and background as a fraction of total root biomass (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C13">Einsmann <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). These are also difficult to solve without complex and explicit treatments of space at the scale of the entire root system that are beyond the goals of this manuscript.Equation (5b) thus represents a simple approximation of foraging precision in plants based on plant nutrient uptake physiology and foraging theory. A key assumption of this model is that plants are nitrogen limited and not limited by other resources, particularly carbon. When plants are carbon limited they may shift allocation away from roots and towards shoot production. Additionally, this model assumes that the roots are the sole source of nitrogen uptake. For example, root production may not be as important for nitrogen acquisition in nitrogen-fixing plants or mycorrhizal species. These assumptions can be easily met in controlled manipulative experiments and by choosing appropriate model species, but may not apply to all species and contexts.To estimate the range of behavioural foraging traits in plants and parameterize our model, we broadly searched the literature for estimates of <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> for nitrate and ammonium and translated the reported <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> into encounter rates and handling times (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB1">1</xref>). In February 2011, we searched the ISI Web of Science for the topic ‘root uptake kinetics’ which returned 870 papers. To make search results more manageable, we filtered the results to the Web of Science Category ‘<italic>Plant Sciences</italic>’. This produced 509 papers. We then inspected titles and abstracts to reduce the search to only papers that reported parameters for nitrate and/or ammonium. From the remaining 219 papers we read each manuscript to collect parameter estimates. We limited our data collection to papers that estimated parameters based on either fresh or dry weight of roots and that estimated both <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> using the Michaelis–Menten equation. Despite the fact that all plant papers we reviewed used the two-parameter Michaelis–Menten equation to fit their data, a surprisingly large number of papers only reported <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>, while failing to report the second parameter, <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub><italic>.</italic> We excluded these papers. Additionally, we limited the data to only plant species with areal shoots so that nutrient capture was achieved exclusively through roots. Fully aquatic plants and algae were therefore excluded, but wetland plants were included. A small number of studies (&lt;10) were not in English, were unavailable after an exhaustive physical and online search or did not report the units of measurement, and these were excluded. When different studies reported estimates of <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> for the same species, we report these as separate data points [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu066/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>see Supporting Information</bold></ext-link>]. When multiple treatments were employed we used only the control treatment or the equivalent ‘no manipulation’ treatment. These search criteria resulted in a final set of 38 studies, with parameter estimates for nitrate and/or ammonium for 45 distinct plant species, and three species that had been studied more than once [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu066/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>see Supporting Information]</bold></ext-link>.Parameter estimates were adjusted uniformly to µmol g<sup>−1</sup> min<sup>−1</sup> for <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> and µM for <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>. Parameter estimates from fresh weight and dry weight of roots were plotted and interpreted separately. We used linear regressions to compare foraging ability for nitrate and ammonium (R Statistical environment, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C44">R Development Core Team 2009</xref>). To summarize the taxonomic diversity and patterns in these parameter estimates, we performed a phylogenetic analysis. The hypothesized phylogenetic relationships among species were constructed using the online phylogenetic database and assembly tool, Phylomatic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C56">Webb and Donoghue 2005</xref>), with Phylomatic tree version R20120829 as the backbone for our phylogenetic hypotheses. The Phylomatic tree is well resolved up to the level of family, but the tool places all genera as polytomies within family and all species as polytomies within genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C30">Kembel and Cahill 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C56">Webb and Donoghue 2005</xref>). We tested for a phylogenetic signal in the foraging trait data (a and h) by calculating a <italic>K</italic> statistic using the R library ‘Picante’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C32">Kembel <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The <italic>K</italic> statistic compares the observed phylogenetic signal in the trait with the signal that would be expected under the Brownian motion model of trait evolution. <italic>K</italic> values &gt;1 imply a strong phylogenetic signal, <italic>K</italic> values equal to 1 imply the Brownian motion model and <italic>K</italic> values &lt;1 imply a random or convergent pattern of evolution. Traits were mapped onto the phylogeny for visualization using the ‘plotBranchbyTrait’ tool in the R library ‘phytools’. For several species there were multiple independent estimates of traits. In these cases, we took the average trait value. Traits were ln(<italic>x</italic> + 1) transformed for normality and to control for differences between fresh and dry weight estimates. There was considerable variation in the methods used among studies to estimate nitrogen foraging parameters [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu066/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>see Supporting Information</bold></ext-link>]. Thus, we envision the phylogenies as a way of summarizing the data with respect to taxonomy, but urge caution in interpreting the phylogenetic signal from these data.Summary of observed parameter estimates from the literature review for plant uptake of nitrate and ammonium. Authors sometimes calculated based on dry or fresh weight of roots, these are summarized independently. Note that <italic>a</italic> and <italic>h</italic> were calculated from <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> according to Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB1">1</xref>.Scatter plots and linear regressions of the observed relationship between (A) the search time for nitrate and ammonium (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,26</sub> = 100.4, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.79), (B) the handling time for nitrate and ammonium (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,26</sub> = 31.2, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.53), (C) <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> for nitrate and ammonium (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,26</sub> = 31.2, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.53) and (D) <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> for nitrate and ammonium (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,26</sub> = 43.2, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.61). Fresh (fw) and dry (dw) weights are plotted separately, but the patterns were qualitatively similar and so they were pooled for regression fits. Data were ln(<italic>x</italic> + 1) transformed.For <italic>handling time</italic> the maximum and mean estimates were generally larger for nitrate compared with ammonium, while other statistics were relatively similar, or showed no clear pattern (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB2">2</xref>). Again the pattern was retained whether the estimates were based on fresh or dry tissue. The range of parameter values suggests that nitrate may be more difficult or costly to transport across root membranes compared with ammonium given the higher average handling costs. It also suggests that at the extreme, the number of encounters which turn into effective encounters (i.e. uptake) may be lower for nitrate.We also present the range of estimates of parameters for the Michaelis–Menten equation. The parameter <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> is simply the inverse of handling time, and so the patterns in <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> were the same as for <italic>h</italic> above, but inverted. That is, where handling times were larger for nitrate compared with ammonium, maximum influx rates (<italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>) tended to be lower for nitrate compared with ammonium. For the half saturation constant, <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>, there seemed to be no obvious differences between ammonium and nitrate (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB2">2</xref>). If nutrient uptake in plants is a foraging process, then this may not be surprising since <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> is actually a combination of search and handling time, and the patterns described above for each of these are cancelled by confounding them within this parameter (i.e. <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> = 1/<italic>ah</italic>).We also explored the relationships in nutrient uptake ability for nitrate and ammonium within a species to examine whether plants might specialize in one type of nitrogen over the other (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F2">2</xref>). Here, all four parameters (<italic>a</italic>, <italic>h</italic>, <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>) tell a similar story: plants that are efficient foragers for nitrate are also efficient foragers for ammonium. Interestingly, this suggests that there are no general trade-offs in foraging ability for these two common forms of nitrogen, and instead species are either efficient or inefficient foragers. However, note that it is not possible to be simultaneously good at searching and handling because of the way that these parameters are conceptualized (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB1">1</xref>).Phylogeny of species for which we have foraging parameters for nitrate (A and B) or ammonium (C and D). Species come from three major clades including conifers, monocots and eudicots. Colour on the branch tips represent ln(<italic>x</italic> + 1) transformed trait values for search efficiency (A and C) and handling time (B and D). The species lists for nitrate and ammonium foraging parameters were not identical and so the upper and lower phylogenies are not identical.Predicted root foraging precision over the observed range of search efficiency (A), handling time (B), maximum uptake rate (C) and half saturation constant (D) among plants. In each case the value of the background soil was <italic>N</italic><sub>b</sub> = 0.2 µmol L<sup>−1</sup>, and the value of the patch associated with each curve is shown in the figure legend (0.5 µmol L<sup>−1</sup> &lt; <italic>N</italic><sub>p</sub> &lt; 2 µmol L<sup>−1</sup>). In each panel, the <italic>x</italic>-axis parameter was varied, while the second parameter was held constant at the mean observed value for nitrate calculated from dry weight (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB2">2</xref>). In each panel, the mean (open triangle) and median (closed triangle) observed values of parameters are indicated by dotted vertical lines.Within the range of <italic>a<sub>j</sub></italic> observed for plants (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB2">2</xref>), the marginal value theorem hypothesizes that plants possessing the ability to encounter nitrogen at a high rate should discriminate less among patches of differing quality compared with plants with low encounter rates. Theoretically this occurs because encounter rate acts like a scaling parameter for the effectiveness of each unit of root produced. Plants with high encounter rates between uptake sites and nutrient ions will be able to gather more resources, with a low investment in root surface area compared with plants with low encounter rates that require high amounts of surface area to effectively encounter nutrients. We observe from our examination of the literature that the mean and median plant species in our dataset of 45 species possess relatively low values of this parameter compared with the maximum range that is observed in the literature (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB2">2</xref>, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>A). Thus, based on our literature review parameterized model the marginal value theorem would predict that the average plant should have relatively high root foraging precision, and should discriminate among patches of different quality by putting more roots in higher quality patches. However, the literature review also reveals that species exist with extremely efficient encounter rates, and these species are predicted to exhibit low root foraging precision in any patch and exhibit similar root foraging precision regardless of patch quality.In the context of handling time (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>B), plants with low handling times have low time lags associated with nutrient uptake, meaning that within a prescribed amount of time spent foraging for nutrients (e.g. the duration of a foraging experiment), plants with low handling times are able to actually acquire more of the available nitrogen compared with plants with high handling time. Logically, plants with low handling times for nitrogen are hypothesized to have high nutrient foraging precision because plants with low handling times are able to capitalize on high quality patches more than plants with high handling costs. As above, we observe from our literature review that the mean and median plant species in our dataset of 45 species possess relatively low handling time compared with the range observed in the literature (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB2">2</xref>). This means that as above, the average plant in our dataset of 45 species has relatively high foraging precision, and discriminates a great deal among patches of differing quality. However, the observed range for handling time is large, suggesting that some species are hypothesized to have relatively low foraging precision, and not discriminate among patches of variable quality (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>B).Finally, in the context of either parameter of the Michaelis–Menten equation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>C and D), only the lowest values of <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> or <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> lead to much discrimination among species with respect to root foraging precision. For either parameter, we see that a plateau is reached quite quickly, and then root foraging precision changes only slightly. Mathematically, this happens because <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> is the inverse of handling time, and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> is the inverse and the product of both search and handling. Roughly, this reverses the patterns observed for the Holling parameters. Biologically, it suggests that the concepts of maximum uptake rate (<italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>) and the half saturation constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>) are simply not concepts that are particularly informative about processes important for root proliferation and nutrient foraging. Instead, as we have shown, ecologists interested in nutrient foraging behaviour of plants will be able to discriminate more clearly among the behaviours and traits of plants by translating the Michaelis–Menten parameters into Holling parameters (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB1">1</xref>).We had three major objectives in this paper: First, we showed that the Michaelis–Menten and Holling equations are mathematically identical, and how to translate parameter estimates for each model back and forth (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB1">1</xref>). The most important insight from this exercise is that under a foraging interpretation of nutrient uptake, the parameter <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> turns out to be a confounded mixture of search and handling that is not particularly useful for predicting plant foraging behaviour (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>). The equality of the Michaelis–Menten and Holling equations is mathematically straightforward, and we do not discuss this further.The analysis of the parameter estimates themselves yielded interesting insights. Interestingly, within species, their ability to capture ammonium and nitrate was positively correlated for all parameters (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F2">2</xref>). This means that there are no trade-offs in the ability of species to capture these two important nitrogen types; instead there are ‘super-foragers’ where some species are extremely efficient either encountering or handling both nitrate and ammonium simultaneously, while other species are extremely inefficient. Given that these parameters ranged over six orders of magnitude, this ‘super-forager’ effect is very large indeed (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB2">2</xref>). However, it should be noted that there is a trade-off (not shown) between encounter rate and handling time. We do not show this because it is a necessary mathematical condition on the way <italic>a</italic> and <italic>h</italic> are calculated (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU066TB1">1</xref>). But it is important to note that while plants can be simultaneously efficient at either encountering or handling nitrate and ammonium, they cannot be simultaneously efficient at both encountering and handling. Thus, species must specialize on one or the other of these foraging processes, and ‘super-foragers’ should actually be unpacked into ‘super-encounterers’ versus ‘super-handlers’ where species cannot be both. It remains unclear what forces cause this specialization, and our phylogenetic analysis did not shed any light on this problem.We analysed the parameter data in the context of historical phylogenetic relationships among species, and the results of the phylogenetic analysis were consistent with random or convergent evolution on foraging traits. However, we suggest that convergent evolution is unlikely since the parameter values varied over six orders of magnitude instead of converging on a single value. We are reluctant to draw too many conclusions about this result because of the large differences in methods among studies from which we obtained parameter estimates. Currently we are inclined to suspect that the observed lack of phylogenetic signal may simply reflect this diversity of methods. We suggest caution in interpreting this result at this time, but this is certainly a pattern that demands further investigation using a common set of methods and a large taxonomic sample.The foraging model generated three predictions: (i) on average, plants should invest more root biomass into higher quality patches relative to lower quality patches but not all species should be expected to discriminate among patches of differing quality depending on their foraging traits (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>); (ii) root foraging precision, and discrimination among patches of variable quality, should be lowest in species with high encounter rates between nutrients and active uptake sites (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>A); and (iii) root foraging precision and discrimination among patches of variable quality should be lowest in plants with the highest handling times for nutrients (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>B).Empirically testing these hypotheses will require studies that include a large number of taxonomically diverse plant species and produce paired estimates of physiological uptake parameters and root foraging precision (e.g. to generate an empirically derived version of Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C30">Kembel and Cahill (2005)</xref> assembled a dataset of root foraging precision for ∼120 species. Unfortunately, there are only five species in common between the precision dataset from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C30">Kembel and Cahill (2005)</xref> and the assembled dataset of uptake parameters presented here. A second problem is that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C30">Kembel and Cahill (2005)</xref> defined precision as the percentage of total roots inside a patch which is not predicted from the model presented here. Thus, currently there are not enough data available to quantitatively test the foraging model. However, we note that, qualitatively, the available data support the model. For example, the model predicts based on data we assembled from the literature that the average plant should have relatively high root foraging precision, and indeed high root foraging precision appears to be the behaviour of the average plant species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C22">Hutchings and de Kroon 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C19">Hodge 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C30">Kembel and Cahill 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C5">Cahill and McNickle 2011</xref>). Further, the prediction that some species should strongly discriminate among patches of variable quality while others should not discriminate among patches is also supported by the available data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C15">Fransen and de Kroon 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C23">Hutchings <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C33">Lamb <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C37">McNickle and Cahill 2009</xref>).There has been no clear explanation for why some plants should exhibit high root foraging precision while others should not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C46">Robinson 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C47">Robinson 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C31">Kembel <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), or why some species discriminate among patches of variable quality while others do not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C37">McNickle and Cahill 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C39">McNickle <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Indeed, some authors have even gone so far as to suggest that the large range of behaviour of root proliferation is illogical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C46">Robinson 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C47">1996</xref>) or that certain results suggest the behaviour might even be maladaptive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C15">Fransen and de Kroon 2001</xref>) when explained using previous conceptual frameworks. We suggest that recasting enzyme kinetics as a foraging process of search and handling provides one clear first principles hypothesis for why so many plant species exhibit high root foraging precision (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>). Low encounter rates and low handling times intuitively lead to high root foraging precision by virtue of the marginal value theorem (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>). However, there is a theoretical trade-off between search and handling: foragers cannot do both simultaneously leading to differences in adaptation and ultimately foraging behaviour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C21">Holling 1959</xref>).Switching from the Michaelis–Menten enzyme kinetics view of nutrient uptake to Holling’s functional response view of nutrient uptake as foraging behaviour will require integration of some new concepts into our understanding of plant nutrient foraging. Since handling time is just the inverse of the maximum uptake rate (<italic>h</italic> = 1/<italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>) then handling time, as a concept, is already in common use by plant biologists. Plants with high influx rates necessarily have low handling times. However, as we have shown, switching to the inverse of <italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub> allows a more subtle discrimination between the foraging behaviour of different species with differing uptake abilities (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>B versus C) and as a result is a more ecologically valuable parameter.The concept of encounter rate, which can also be thought of as search efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C52">Stephens <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), is a relatively new idea for plant ecologists that was confounded, along with handling time, inside the half saturation constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> = 1/<italic>ah</italic>). The concept of encounter rates is critically important in the foraging literature, and is important for understanding the patch-use behaviour of foragers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C55">Vincent <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C52">Stephens <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Just as the inverse of influx rate is a more informative parameter for root foraging behaviour, unpacking encounter rate from within <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> provides better insights into root foraging behaviour of plants that was obscured inside of <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU066F4">4</xref>A versus D). Encounters will be influenced by any factor that influences the rate at which nutrient ions are encountered by active uptake sites on a plant root and can include behavioural responses of the plant such as changing the number of active uptake sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C34">Lauter <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C39">McNickle <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), or by changing total root biomass/length and therefore the number of active uptake sites per volume of soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C22">Hutchings and de Kroon 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C5">Cahill and McNickle 2011</xref>). Encounter rate will also be influenced by physical properties of the soil and physical properties of the nutrient molecules that might limit ion movement in soil solution. For example, most uptake studies are conducted in nutrient solutions within laboratories, which likely have quite high mobility of ions leading to artificially high encounter rates. However, physical factors that limit diffusion rates in field soil will also limit the rate at which plants can encounter nutrients and should have an influence on plant foraging behaviour. An experimental test of the root foraging precision model could manipulate encounter rates by manipulating properties of the soil environment. For example, soils with high clay content have lower mobility of cations, and this would limit the ability of plants to encounter positively charged ions such as nitrate.With any model there are caveats around the assumptions made. We assumed that nitrogen was the only limiting resource. This is unlikely to be true in many contexts, but can and has been achieved in controlled experiments (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C11">Drew and Saker 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C40">McNickle <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Mathematically, the model could be extended to include foraging for multiple essential resources by the use of a minimum function, where foraging decisions were based on Liebig's law of the minimum. This would require a more complex model, but foraging theory exists for this problem (See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C55">Vincent <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C50">Simpson <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Additionally, we assumed that nitrogen levels were not depleted over the course of the experiment. Again, controlled manipulative experiments can and have met this assumption (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C6">Campbell and Grime 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C48">Shemesh <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). This assumption could be relaxed by allowing nutrients to have their own dynamics in the model (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C55">Vincent <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>). Relaxing both of these assumptions would change the quantitative predictions of our model, but we do not believe they would change the qualitative predictions. Specifically, that encounter rates and handling times are important predictors of foraging precision. The assumptions that plants are limited by nitrogen more than carbon can be more easily met by ensuring adequate light supplies. Similarly, the assumption that uptake is achieved through roots alone can be met by the selection of model species, or by sterilizing soil prior to experimentation. Finally, this model assumes that foraging is all that matters to plants. There are many other problems such as mutualisms, enemy attack and competition that plants must solve (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C9">De Deyn and Van der Putten 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C38">McNickle and Dybzinski 2013</xref>), and trade-offs required to solve these problems may cause undermatching in foraging behaviour as plants direct resources away from nutrient foraging and towards solving these other problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C4">Brown 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C42">Nonacs 2001</xref>).The model of root foraging precision presented here is just one example of how the application of a Holling functional response to plant nutrient uptake could enhance our understanding of plant nutrient foraging behaviour, and we hope this work will lead to further advances. For example, much of the existing foraging theory in the animal literature is based upon the Holling disc equation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C45">Real 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C51">Stephens and Krebs 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C55">Vincent <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C52">Stephens <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C1">Abrams 2010<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C2">2010<italic>b</italic></xref>) and a diversity of models can be derived from this functional response. We suggest that interested plant ecologists can now begin to take full advantage of the existing foraging literature by using the Holling equation to interpret nutrient uptake instead of the Michaelis–Menten equation. It is beyond the scope of this manuscript to review the existing animal models (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C51">Stephens and Krebs 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU066C52">Stephens <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), but we believe that there is considerable room for enhanced linkages between processes of interest to plant ecologists and plant physiologists mediated through pre-existing understanding of foraging ecology.We have argued that a switch from the phenomenological view of plants as passive <italic>enzyme-like</italic> entities that are largely governed by chemical fluxes to a more mechanistic view of plants as active foragers that assess and respond to their environment fits with the trend towards viewing plant plasticity as a behavioural process. We believe that the ability to translate existing plant physiological data into information relevant to foraging behaviour and theory will be valuable for plant ecologists. Our model has the potential to generate improved ecological understanding by uniting traditionally separate fields of ecology, while still preserving our existing knowledge and understanding.Our work was funded by a Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council (Canada) Post-Doctoral Fellowship and a Banting Post-Doctoral Fellowship to G.G.M.G.G.M. and J.S.B. conceived the study and developed the theoretical approach. J.S.B. developed the comparison between the Holling and Michaelis–Menten equations. G.G.M. developed the root foraging model, performed the literature review and analysed the models. Both authors contributed to the writing of the manuscript.None declared.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu066/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">The following Supporting Information is available in the online version of this article –</ext-link><bold>File S1.</bold> Text with two figures. The Holling disc equation and Michaelis–Menton equation were fit to the same randomly generated data to demonstrate that they are mathematically identical.<bold>File S2.</bold> Supporting data. The Michaelis–Menten parameter estimates collected from the literature for (i) nitrate, (ii) ammonium including (iii) metadata, and (iv) reference list.The authors thank R. Julia Kilgour, Paul Orlando and Christopher J. Whelan for their helpful discussion during the development of these ideas. They thank Steve W. Kembel for advice on phylogenetic analysis and Liam Revell for his blog (<uri xlink:href="http://blog.phytools.org" xlink:type="simple">http://blog.phytools.org</uri>) containing detailed advice about how to use the ‘phytools’ library in R.