 Moving from a regional to a continental perspective of  Phragmites australis  invasion in North America  Mechanisms of marsh habitat alteration due to  Phragmites : response of young-of-the-year mummichog ( Fundulus heteroclitus ) to treatment for  Phragmites  removal  Clonal integration and the expansion of  Phragmites australis   Seed banks of  Phragmites australis -dominated brackish wetlands: relationships to seed viability, inundation, and land cover  Environmental determinants of  Phragmites australis  expansion in a New Jersey salt marsh: an experimental approach  Spatial dynamics and morphological plasticity of common reed ( Phragmites australis ) and cattails ( Typha  sp.) in freshwater marshes and roadside ditches  Seeds contribute strongly to the spread of the invasive genotype of the common reed ( Phragmites australis )  Evidence of sexual reproduction in the invasive common reed ( Phragmites australis  subsp.  australis ; Poaceae) in eastern Canada: a possible consequence of global warming  Roadside as invasion pathway for common reed ( Phragmites australis )  Plant functional group identity and diversity determine biotic resistance to invasion by an exotic grass  Effects of salinity and sulfide on the distribution of  Phragmites australis  and  Spartina alterniflora  in a tidal saltmarsh  Common reed  Phragmites australis  occurrence and adjacent land use along estuarine shoreline in Chesapeake Bay  Louisiana estuarine and coastal fisheries and habitats: perspectives from a fish's eye view  Species at Risk Act: Annual report for 2009  Species composition and inter-annual dynamics of a freshwater tidal plant community following removal of the invasive grass,  Phragmites australis   Invasiveness in wetland plants in temperate North America   Phragmites australis : an analysis of reproductive differences in two adjacent populations in the Mississippi River delta   Phragmites australis  in Quebec: geographical distribution, chromosome number, and reproduction  Wetland inventories: wetland loss along the United States coast  Genetic variation in the common reed,  Phragmites australis , in the Mississippi River delta marshes: evidence for multiple introductions  Rapid growth of a Eurasian haplotype of  Phragmites australis  in a restored brackish marsh in Louisiana, USA  Hydrological factors controlling the spread of common reed ( Phragmites australis ) in the St. Lawrence River (Quebec, Canada)  Changements dans les milieux humides du fleuve Saint-Laurent de 1970–2002 [Changes in the wetlands of the St. Lawrence River, 1970–2002]  Highways as corridors and habitats for the invasive common reed  Phragmites australis  in Quebec, Canada  Plant diversity in  Lythrum ,  Phragmites , and  Typha  marshes, Massachusetts, U.S.A  Genetic diversity, reproductive mode, and dispersal differ between the cryptic invader,  Phragmites australis , and its native conspecific  Seed viability and seed dormancy of non-native  Phragmites australis  in suburbanized and forested watersheds of the Chesapeake Bay, USA   Phragmites australis  (common reed) invasion in the Rhode River subestuary of the Chesapeake Bay: disentangling the effects of foliar nutrients, genetic diversity, patch size, and seed viability  Mechanisms of  Phragmites australis  invasion: feedbacks among genetic diversity, nutrients, and sexual reproduction   Phragmites  invasion and control in the Great Salt Lake watershed: 2012 land manager survey  Threshold effects of coastal urbanization on  Phragmites australis  (common reed) abundance and foliar nitrogen in Chesapeake Bay  Long-distance dispersal and high genetic diversity are implicated in the invasive spread of the common reed,  Phragmites australis  (Poaceae), in northeastern North America  Nonnative  Phragmites australis  invasion into Utah wetlands  Tracing the origin of Gulf Coast  Phragmites  (Poaceae): a story of long-distance dispersal and hybridization  Exotic plant species of the St Lawrence River wetlands: a spatial and historical analysis  Le roseau envahisseur: la dynamique, l'impact et le contrôle d'une invasion d'envergure  Expansion pathways of the exotic common reed ( Phragmites australis ): a historical and genetic analysis  Biological invasions: recommendations for U.S. policy and management  Assessing invasive alien species across multiple spatial scales: working globally and locally  Mapping the invasive species  Phragmites australis  in linear wetland corridors  Landscape ecology of  Phragmites australis  invasion in networks of linear wetlands   Phragmites australis  ( Phragmites communis ): threats, management, and monitoring  Extent and reproductive mechanisms of  Phragmites australis  spread in brackish wetlands in Chesapeake Bay, Maryland (USA)  Spread of invasive  Phragmites australis  in estuaries with differing degrees of development: genetic patterns, Allee effects and interpretation  Distribution of native and introduced  Phragmites australis  in freshwater and oligohaline tidal marshes of the Delmarva peninsula and southern New Jersey  Wetlands in Maryland  The effects of  Phragmites  removal on nutrient pools in a freshwater tidal marsh ecosystem  A tale of three lineages: expansion of common reed ( Phragmites australis ) in the U.S. Southwest and Gulf Coast  Hybridization of common reed in North America? The answer is blowing in the wind  Disturbance-mediated competition and the spread of  Phragmites australis  in a coastal marsh  Mechanisms of exclusion of native coastal marsh plants by an invasive grass  Tracing plant introduction and spread: genetic evidence from  Bromus tectorum  (cheatgrass)   Phragmites  control plan  Isozyme variation among populations of the clonal species,  Phragmites australis  (Cav.) Trin. ex Steudel  Colonization and expansion of  Phragmites australis  in upper Chesapeake Bay tidal marshes  Cryptic invasion by a non-native genotype of the common reed,  Phragmites australis , into North America  Recognition of  Phragmites australis  subsp.  americanus  (Poaceae: Arundinoideae) in North America: evidence from morphological and genetic analyses  Shoreline development drives invasion of  Phragmites australis  and the loss of plant diversity on New England salt marshes  Coexistence of introduced and native common reed ( Phragmites australis ) in freshwater wetlands  Modification of sediments and macrofauna by an invasive marsh plant  Effect of oxygen availability and salinity on early life history stages of salt marsh plants. I. Different germination strategies of  Spartina alterniflora  and  Phragmites australis  (Poaceae)  Effect of oxygen availability and salinity on early life history stages of salt marsh plants. II. Early seedling development advantage of  Spartina alterniflora  over  Phragmites australis  (Poaceae)  Historical distribution and abundance of  Phragmites australis  at Long Point, Lake Erie, Ontario  Net impact of a plant invasion on nitrogen-cycling processes within a brackish tidal marsh  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited  Here we describe the results of a regional comparison of introduced  Phragmites australis  and two other  P. australis  lineages found in North America. The regional similarities and differences in introduced  P. australis  invasion highlight the importance of continental-scale studies for decoding plant invasions.  We use a regional comparison of  Phragmites australis  (common reed) subsp.  americanus ,  P. australis  subsp.  berlandieri  and introduced  P. australis  (possibly five sublineages) in the Chesapeake Bay, the St Lawrence River, Utah and the Gulf Coast to inform a North American perspective on  P. australis  invasion patterns, drivers, impacts and research needs.  Our regional assessments reveal substantial diversity within and between the three main lineages of  P. australis  in terms of mode of reproduction and the types of environment occupied. For introduced  P. australis , the timing of introduction also differed between the regions. Nevertheless, a common finding in these regions reinforces the notion that introduced  P. australis  is opportunistic and thrives in disturbed habitats. Thus, we expect to see substantial expansion of introduced  P. australis  with increasing anthropogenic disturbances in each of these regions. Although there have been some studies documenting the negative impacts of introduced  P. australis , it also plays a beneficial role in some regions, and in some cases, the purported negative impacts are unproven. There is also a broader need to clarify the genetic and ecological relationships between the different introduced sublineages observed in North America, and their relative competitive ability and potential for admixture. This may be done through regional studies that use similar methodologies and share results to uncover common patterns and processes. To our knowledge, such studies have not been performed on  P. australis  in spite of the broad attention given to this species. Such research could advance theoretical knowledge on biological invasion by helping to determine the extent to which the patterns observed can be generalized or are sublineage specific or region specific.  Given what appears to be sometimes idiosyncratic invasion patterns when interpreted in isolation in the regions that we analysed, it may be time to consider initiatives on a continental (if not intercontinental) scale to tackle unresolved issues about  P. australis .  Understanding the patterns, drivers and impacts of plant invasions requires a perspective that is both detailed and broad as well as coordinated efforts to collect, store and access data ( Lodge  et al.  2006 ;  Mack  et al.  2007 ). However, for many species we lack these different levels of research and assessment to allow for synthesis and consensus on what makes invasive species successful and on their real impacts on ecosystems. To advance our understanding of the invasion process, we suggest that an effective approach is to focus on model species that are intensively studied at multiple scales in an attempt to synthesize knowledge (e.g.  Bromus tectorum ;  Novak and Mack 2001 ).  We can apply such an approach to the invasion of  Phragmites australis  (common reed) in North America.  Phragmites australis  is a globally distributed species consisting of a number of described subspecies, lineages and sublineages. It is emerging as a model system for studying invasive plants in North America, in part because of the phenotypic and ecological diversity within and between the lineages. For the reader to better appreciate the invasion of  P. australis , it is best to begin with the terminology and taxonomy that is used in this review and explain how it relates to recent literature, all the while realizing that the taxonomy is in flux as more genetic and biogeographic data are accumulated.  Lineages, sublineages and haplotypes of  P. australis .   a For a summary of possible origins and North American ranges of these lineages, see  Meyerson  et al.  (2012) .   b In two situations, multiple names were given to the same sublineage by independently operating research groups.   c  Saltonstall (2002) .   d  Saltonstall  et al.  (2004) .   e  Meadows and Saltonstall (2007) .   f  Hauber  et al.  (2011) .   g  Lambertini  et al.  (2012) .   h  Pellegrin and Hauber (1999) .  Among the introduced sublineages, much of the current understanding of the genetic relationships comes from two recent studies of introduced  P. australis  populations in the Mississippi River Balize delta on the US Gulf Coast ( Hauber  et al.  2011 ;  Lambertini  et al.  2012 ). Based mostly on microsatellite analysis in conjunction with haplotype sequencing, most introduced populations along the east coast of North America and the Great Lakes region align with the Short B sublineage ( Hauber  et al.  2011 ; a.k.a. EU,  Lambertini  et al.  2012 ). Interestingly, the Balize delta is dominated by a unique sublineage, Delta ( Hauber  et al.  2011 ;  Lambertini  et al.  2012 ), while Short B is relatively uncommon there. The other introduced sublineages listed in Table  1  have all been found in the Balize delta but are also relatively uncommon ( Lambertini  et al.  2012 ). Greeny 2 and 3 have not been found elsewhere in North America, and Short A (Greeny 1) is rare outside of the Balize delta ( Lambertini  et al.  2012 ). Further details of the Balize delta sublineages are found in the discussion on the Gulf Coast region later in this review. Whereas the haplotype diversity of the native  P. australis  subsp.  americanus  had been known for a while, it is only recently that studies have reported on the considerable genetic and phenotypic diversity in the introduced lineage.  So far, most ecological studies on  P. australis  in North America, including the ones reviewed here, have been conducted at the landscape or regional scale and have compared ecological patterns at the broad lineage level (i.e. native vs. introduced type). As knowledge continues to improve on the genetic composition of lineages and sublineages of  P. australis , it is important that researchers compare ecological and genetic patterns across regions to highlight similarities and differences. Such a continental perspective can also help identify biases in research focus, locate gaps in knowledge and provide direction for future research initiatives.  The locations of the four study regions in North America and more detailed images of (A) the Chesapeake Bay, (B) the Gulf Coast, (C) Utah and (D) the St Lawrence River.  The research questions addressed and summarized findings regarding the three  Phragmites  lineages in the four study regions.  We begin with a synopsis of native and introduced  P. australis  in the Chesapeake Bay, since many of the ideas that have influenced the study of  P. australis  invasion in North America come from the eastern seaboard of the USA (e.g.  Wijte and Gallagher 1996 a  ,   b  ;  Chambers  et al.  1998 ;  Farnsworth and Meyerson 1999 ;  Meyerson  et al.  1999 ;  Amsberry  et al.  2000 ;  Bart and Hartman 2000 ). The Chesapeake Bay is the largest estuary in North America, with a 26 000-ha watershed spanning six states and the District of Columbia. The climate is temperate, with hot and humid summers and relatively mild winters ( Alliance for the Chesapeake Bay 2004 ). The wetlands of the Chesapeake Bay provide critical habitat—as a nursery, for feeding, and for cover—for the ∼200 species of fish that occur in the Bay ( Metzgar 1973 ;  Tiner and Burke 1995 ). In addition, the wetlands of the Chesapeake Bay are extremely important to migratory birds on the Atlantic Flyway; one-third of these birds actually winter in the Bay ( Tiner and Burke 1995 ). The Chesapeake Bay is also world renowned for its blue crab ( Callinectes sapidus ), the Bay's most valuable fishery (  http://chesapeakebay.noaa.gov/fish-facts/blue-crab  ). Blue crabs use most aquatic habitats of the Bay, including intertidal wetlands where  P. australis  often dominates, at some point during their life cycle.  The consequences of  P. australis  invasion and wholesale conversion of multi-species wetlands to monocultures of  P. australis  is an active area of research. In the Chesapeake Bay, introduced  P. australis  is typically considered undesirable because of its aggressive spread, and because of known negative effects of  P. australis  on diversity and ecosystem processes. In fact, a recent study in the Rhode River subestuary of the Chesapeake Bay documents that brackish tidal wetlands that have become dominated by introduced  P. australis  support few native plant species (M. Sievers, Smithsonian Environmental Research Center, unpubl. data). However, in some cases  P. australis -dominated tidal wetlands might provide valuable services by acting as a sediment trap and thus buffering wetlands from sea-level rise ( Rice  et al.  2000 ). Although in other regions introduced  P. australis  may serve an important role in nutrient removal, there has been little research on such beneficial effects in nutrient-rich Chesapeake Bay wetlands.   The two  P. australis  lineages—subspecies  americanus  and introduced—in the Chesapeake Bay . Photographs (A), (C) and (D) by K. Kettenring, and (B) by D. F. Whigham.  The only information concerning the initial invasion of introduced  P. australis  in the Chesapeake Bay is that it was present in the early 1900s at Chesapeake Beach, MD ( Saltonstall 2002 ;  Saltonstall  et al.  2004 ). More recently, a detailed study by  McCormick  et al . (2010 a  ) of introduced  P. australis  spread in the Rhode River subestuary of the Chesapeake Bay found that over a 40-year period (1970–2007), the number of  P. australis  patches increased from 5 to 212 and the area occupied by  P. australis  increased from 0.73 to 18 ha. Another study documented high intrinsic rates of increase of  P. australis  patches in the Chesapeake Bay (0.06–0.19 year −1  in more recently colonized brackish wetlands), but it is not clear as to whether patches that were followed were native or introduced ( Rice  et al.  2000 ). While there is no direct evidence for multiple introductions of  P. australis  in Chesapeake Bay wetlands,  McCormick  et al . (2010 a  ,   b  ) found substantial genetic diversity in  P. australis  populations, supporting the notion that there have been multiple introductions.  Genetic analyses of introduced  P. australis  populations across nine subestuaries of the Chesapeake Bay and detailed study of all  P. australis  patches within the Rhode River subestuary indicate that seeds are the predominant means of movement within and between subestuaries ( McCormick  et al.  2010 a  ,   b  ), while spread within patches appears to be a mixture of clonal and seed propagation. The ability of introduced  P. australis  patches to spread by seed can vary because: (i) seed viability differs greatly between patches, due to the availability of out-crossed pollen, (ii)  P. australis  seed densities in seed banks reflect patch-level viable seed production, and (iii) floret and inflorescence production is driven strongly by nutrient levels ( Kettenring and Whigham 2009 ;  Baldwin  et al.  2010 ;  Kettenring  et al.  2010 ,  2011 ). Each of these factors drives variability in reproductive output and potential spread by seed between introduced  P. australis  patches. How these mechanisms of spread compare to native  P. australis  is not known.  Introduced  P. australis  has colonized both tidal freshwater and brackish wetlands in the Chesapeake Bay, over a wide range of salinities. In Maryland tidal wetlands,  P. australis  appears to be able to invade all plant communities, eventually displacing species such as  Iva frutescens ,  Spartina patens ,  Spartina cynosuroides ,  Schoenoplectus americanus ,  Distichlis spicata  and  Typha angustifolia  (D. Whigham, Smithsonian Environmental Research Center, pers. comm.). However, sometimes these species and others (e.g.  Smilax rotundifolia ,  Apios americana  and  Acer rubrum  on the forest border; M. Sievers, unpubl. data) are able to persist in the leading edges of developing  P. australis  patches. It is likely that there is some replacement of native  P. australis  by introduced  P. australis  in the habitats where they co-occur, but there have not been systematic studies to document this phenomenon.   The two  P. australis  lineages—subspecies  americanus  and introduced—in the St Lawrence River region . Photographs by J. Brisson.  The St Lawrence River drains the world's largest system of freshwater lakes and is the third-largest drainage basin in North America. The climate is continental, with hot, humid summers and cold, snowy winters. The freshwater wetlands along its major fluvial lakes and banks harbour a large proportion of Canada's at-risk species ( Environment Canada 2010 ), and several of the basin's national wildlife areas and migratory bird sanctuaries are recognized as internationally significant. Whereas the rate of wetland loss has declined in recent years along parts of the fluvial corridor ( Jean and Létourneau 2011 ), scientists believe that most of the original wetlands of the St Lawrence valley may have already disappeared. Over 50 exotic plant species have colonized the remaining wetlands, with introduced  P. australis  being among the most conspicuous. The proportion of plant cover occupied by exotic species tends to be higher in the densely populated fluvial sectors of the St Lawrence than in the estuarine portions ( Lavoie  et al.  2003 ).  Three situations in particular have contributed to rising concerns over the environmental impact of introduced  P. australis.  First, the construction of new transport infrastructures and the drainage of lowlands for agriculture in the St Lawrence valley in the 1960s and 1970s were followed by the rapid and very conspicuous  P. australis  invasion of linear wetlands associated with these infrastructures (roadside and agricultural drainage ditches) ( Maheu-Giroux and de Blois 2005 ,  2007 ;  Jodoin  et al.  2008 ). The proliferation of a well-connected invasion network can lead to increased  P. australis  propagule pressure on natural wetlands ( Taddeo and de Blois 2012 ), but in an agricultural context with heavy nutrient loading  P. australis  may also be beneficial as an effective barrier that filters water and traps sediment. Second, episodes of low water levels in the St Lawrence River system as a result of climatic fluctuations led to the massive invasion of shores by introduced  P. australis  ( Hudon  et al.  2005 ), raising concerns over its impacts on fish spawning sites and waterfowl. Finally, numerous wetland restoration sites have become dominated by introduced  P. australis , with potential loss of quality habitat for the species these wetlands were intended to protect (A. Michaud, Ducks Unlimited, pers. comm.). In all these cases, the invasion of  P. australis  is viewed as a consequence of management practices that resulted in ideal conditions for this opportunistic species.  Evidently, introduced  P. australis  is highly competitive on disturbed sites and new anthropogenic habitats, and this is nowhere better exemplified than in roadside habitats of the St Lawrence valley. Genetic analyses of &gt;260 leaf samples obtained from an intensive survey along 1359 1-km highway sections in Quebec showed that they were overwhelmingly introduced  P. australis . The native lineage, on the other hand ,  is mostly found along the last remaining large freshwater wetlands of the St Lawrence River (Lake Saint-François, Lake Saint-Louis, Lake Saint-Pierre;  Jodoin  et al.  2008 ). A detailed study of  P. australis— in one of these large remaining freshwater wetlands where the two types co-occur—shows that the introduced and native lineages are associated with distinct land uses and land covers ( Taddeo and de Blois 2012 ). Native  P. australis  is mostly found in low marshes and areas with fewer human impacts, whereas introduced  P. australis  is associated with roads (or other disturbances) and drier areas. These patterns are similar to those found at the regional scale for introduced and native  P. australis  and suggest that co-existence is possible, at least for some time.  To reconstruct the historical spatial distribution of  P. australis  at the regional scale,  Lelong  et al . (2007)  mapped the location of herbarium specimens from Quebec through time and conducted genetic analyses on the specimens in historical collections. The oldest native specimen was collected on the shore of a river in the far east of the study area in 1882, whereas the oldest available introduced specimen was collected in 1916 along the St Lawrence River southeast of Quebec City. Introduced  P. australis  has thus been present for at least 96 years in this region and may have been introduced by boats through exchanges with Europe well before that. Multiple introductions are likely, given the high level of genetic diversity among populations of introduced  P. australis  ( Belzile  et al.  2010 ;  Kirk  et al.  2011 ).  In herbarium collections, most of the specimens collected prior to the 1970s are of native  P. australis ; the vast majority of the specimens collected or sampled after that point are of the introduced lineage. The 1960s and 1970s were a period of historically low water levels in the St Lawrence River, and coincided with the expansion of the Quebec highway system and agricultural intensification. Focusing on linear wetlands (roadside and agricultural ditches, riparian habitats),  Maheu-Giroux and de Blois (2005)  used aerial photographs to reconstruct the spread from the 1980s to 2002 of introduced  P. australis  in peri-urban landscapes. Very high rates of increase were observed, with populations more than doubling in spatial extent each year. Interestingly, riparian habitats, being less disturbed, were also less invaded. New populations established on average 27–77 m away from alreadyestablished patches, although rare longer-distance dispersal events also occurred. Densification of the patches was facilitated by nutrient-rich agricultural run-off in a time of rapid intensification of agricultural activities.  Given that clonal propagation is usually vigorous, the contribution of sexual reproduction to the spread of introduced  P. australis  has been somewhat overlooked until recently. Three lines of evidence have been used to assess invasion mechanisms. First, the numerous colonization events and dispersal patterns observed by  Maheu-Giroux and de Blois (2007)  within and between linear habitats suggested a more important role of seed dispersal than previously acknowledged. Low seed germination rates are compensated for, to some extent, by very high seed production rates. Second,  Brisson  et al . (2008)  directly observed seedling establishment and survival over two growing seasons in roadside ditches. They suggested that warming in recent years may have contributed to increased seed production and seedling survival for the introduced lineage, a hypothesis that is currently being investigated. Finally, genetic studies have reported high rates of genetic diversity among populations of introduced  P. australis  at both the landscape ( Belzile  et al.  2010 ) and regional scale ( Kirk  et al.  2011 ), with both long-distance and short-distance dispersal events determining population structure ( Maheu-Giroux and de Blois 2007 ;  Kirk  et al.  2011 ). It is possible that the contribution of sexual reproduction has increased with time with increased density of populations and the availability of out-cross pollen ( Kettenring  et al.  2010 ,  2011 ).  Unlike the introduced lineage, the native lineage is not known to progress regionally by colonizing previously unoccupied wetland sites. In sites where the introduced and native lineages co-occur, however, populations of both types can expand locally mostly by clonal propagation, with a non-significant trend towards faster densification of the introduced lineage (S. de Blois, unpubl. data). Direct pre- and post-invasion surveys at the edge of an invasion front would be needed to evaluate the effect of the spread of the introduced lineage on resident plant communities. This would help clarify whether low plant diversity patterns reported in invaded systems result from the competitive effect of  P. australis  on resident plants or the fact that already species-poor disturbed habitats were invaded. Disturbed habitats are easily invaded, but if seeds of  P. australis  reach a resident plant community, that community will offer resistance to  P. australis  seedling establishment, and the level of invasion resistance will depend on the plant functional groups present ( Byun  et al.  2013 ).  At the regional scale, historical herbarium records suggested that native  P. australis  were being replaced by the introduced lineage over time ( Lelong  et al.  2007 ). S. de Blois and colleagues (unpubl. data) monitored five locations with native and introduced populations, for periods ranging up to 5 years, to verify the displacement hypothesis. They found that competitive outcomes can vary with site conditions, but native  P. australis  resisted invasion better than expected. Landscape distribution patterns also show that native  P. australis  occupies less-disturbed habitats, where it may manage to escape competition ( Taddeo and de Blois 2012 ).  In the freshwater and brackish portions of the St Lawrence River, introduced  P. australis  has been associated with habitats supporting species such as  Typha  spp.,  Carex lacustris ,  Sparganium eurycarpum  and  Calamagrostis canadensis , as well as with other introduced species such as  Lythrum salicaria  and  Phalaris arundinacea . Introduced  P. australis  has been shown to outcompete  Typha  spp. for space in roadside habitats and wetlands ( Bellavance and Brisson 2010 ), but as yet there is no direct report of the replacement of other vegetation types by introduced  P. australis . Comparisons of fish, bird and amphibian populations in invaded and non-invaded wetland habitats have found limited support for negative impacts of introduced  P. australis  on fauna ( Le Groupe Phragmites 2012 ).  The introduction of  P. australis  in Utah appears to be the most recent invasion relative to the other regions of North America reported here, but given its progression in wetlands and other habitats, it is likely to become as significant a factor as in the other regions if left unchecked. Most wetlands in Utah are found in the northern part of the state in the Great Salt Lake watershed, which includes the wetlands around Bear Lake and Utah Lake, and riparian and other wetlands throughout the watershed (Fig.  1 ). Salt Lake City, the major metropolitan area in the Wasatch Front, the area east of the Great Salt Lake, has a semi-arid climate characterized by warm, dry summers and cold, snowy winters. Most wetlands in northern Utah are fed largely by snow melt and are critical habitat for wildlife including migratory waterfowl and shorebirds on the Pacific and Central Flyways ( Evans and Martinson 2008 ). In fact, the Great Salt Lake and its 160 000 ha of wetlands have been designated a Western Hemisphere Shorebird Reserve Network site with a ‘hemispheric rank’ ( Western Hemisphere Shorebird Reserve Network 2009 ). Perhaps the most important wetlands on the Great Salt Lake are found in the Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge, where the 1000 km Bear River terminates on the northeast arm of the Great Salt Lake. These 29 000 ha of wetlands, playas and mudflats are used by &gt;260 species of birds, including 33 species of shorebirds ( Olson  et al.  2004 ;  Denton 2007 ). During the fall migration as many as 500 000 ducks and 200 000 shorebirds visit the Refuge ( Olson  et al.  2004 ).  The invasion of introduced  P. australis  (presumably Short B; see analysis in  Hauber  et al.  2011 ) into wetlands in Utah, particularly in the Great Salt Lake watershed, is perceived as one of the biggest threats to the state's native wetland plant diversity and wildlife habitat quality ( Olson 2007 ;  Kettenring and Mock 2012 ). For that reason, there are major efforts on the part of private, state and federal land managers to control  P. australis  in Utah's wetlands. Documentation of the impacts of  P. australis  invasion, however, is lacking in this region.   The two  P. australis  lineages—subspecies  americanus  and introduced—in Utah . Photographs by K. Kettenring.  Many wetland managers think  P. australis  began to spread rapidly after major floods of the Great Salt Lake in the 1980s ( Kettenring  et al.  2012 ). (Such floods occur periodically as natural fluctuations on a decadal scale.) When the floodwaters receded through the latter part of the decade and into the 1990s, they left vast areas of mudflats. Interestingly, these anecdotes about the timing of rapid  P. australis  invasion are confirmed by recent analyses which show that the earliest recorded herbarium specimen of introduced  P. australis  was from 1993, from near Camp Williams (between the Great Salt Lake and Utah Lake, ∼40 km south of Salt Lake City;  Kulmatiski  et al.  2011 ). The rates of expansion have not been calculated for introduced  P. australis , but clearly it has spread rapidly in &lt;20 years to become a dominant feature in northern Utah wetlands. The extent to which human dispersal plays a role in  P. australis  invasion has not been determined, although it appears that the major corridor of invasion has been along Interstate 15 in the northern part of the state.  A recent study by  Kettenring and Mock (2012)  suggests that spread by seed is much more important for introduced  P. australis  than for subsp.  americanus  at the landscape scale in Utah. Within patches, introduced  P. australis  spreads both by clonal propagation and by seeds, depending on the site, while for subsp.  americanus , most spread is clonal. The substantial amount of genetic variation  Kettenring and Mock (2012)  found in introduced  P. australis  suggests that multiple introductions have occurred, but this hypothesis has not been explicitly tested.  There is no evidence that introduced  P. australis  has yet widely displaced subsp.  americanus .  Kettenring and Mock (2012)  were able to identify native  P. australis  in many of the historic herbarium collection locations described in  Kulmatiski  et al . (2011) . Still, there are a number of places where introduced  P. australis  and subsp.  americanus  co-occur that should be closely monitored. These include sites on Utah Lake, in Cutler Marsh in Cache Valley (which is between Bear Lake and Great Salt Lake), on the north side of Bear Lake, and on the north side of the Great Salt Lake (Fig.  1 ; K. M. Kettenring, pers. observ.). Although there have not been detailed studies of the type of vegetation that introduced  P. australis  is replacing, field observations indicate that it takes over areas occupied by other emergent wetland plants such as  Schoenoplectus maritimus ,  S. acutus ,  Typha  spp., and mudflat species such as  Distichlis spicata  ( Olson 2007 ; K. M. Kettenring, pers. observ.).   The two  P. australis  lineages—subspecies  berlandieri  and introduced—and three of the introduced sublineages in the Gulf Coast . Photographs by C. S. Hood.  The northern Gulf of Mexico coastline has a subtropical climate, with hot, humid summers and mild winters (  www.worldclimate.com  ). Wetlands are the dominant habitats in this region. Louisiana alone contains 40–45 % of the wetlands of the continental US, and most occur as coastal marshes (as defined by  Keddy 2000 ). The northern Gulf of Mexico contains 58 % of coastal marshes of the continental US ( Alexander  et al.  1986 ), most of which are the result of deltaic deposits of the meandering mouth of the Mississippi River over the past 4000 years ( Gosselink and Baumann 1980 ). The northern US Gulf Coast marshes serve as nurseries supporting the production of &gt;30 % of domestic seafood in the Gulf of Mexico ( Chabreck 1988 ;  Chesney  et al.  2000 ). The quality habitat required by these fisheries is jeopardized by wetland loss caused by anthropogenic factors, subsidence, coastal erosion and sea-level rise.  In the diverse interior marshes of the Balize delta, introduced  P. australis  is seen as having both negative and positive impacts. It decreases the foraging habitat for migratory birds on the Mississippi Flyway, which do not feed on  P. australis . In these interior marshes,  Schoenoplectus deltarum ,  Sagittaria latifolia  and  Sagittaria platyphylla  are being replaced by both  Typha  spp. and introduced  P. australis  (D. A. White, pers. observ.). On the other hand, in the outer delta marshes where introduced  P. australis  is by far the dominant emergent plant species, wetland managers see it as a benefit due to its capacity to trap sediment, allowing for stabilization from subsidence. It also serves to buffer and protect the diverse interior marshes, particularly during tropical storm events. Introduced  P. australis  is salt tolerant. It also tolerates other disturbances: following the British Petroleum oil spill in 2010, though the oil-covered  P. australis  culms died off, many of the stands appeared to be producing new shoots from perennial growth below the waterline (D. A. White, pers. comm.), thus buffering interior marshes from the effects of the spill.  It has been estimated (as described in  Hauber  et al.  2011 ) that the initial introduction of the Delta sublineage in the Balize delta was ∼90 years ago, based on historical accounts and the fact that the main river distributaries in the Balize delta have experienced over 200 years of international passages along with periodically spilled cargo and dumped ballast water. Over time, periodic tropical storm events and anthropogenic impacts via canal construction and channel dredging are believed to have accelerated subsidence and likely provided greater opportunity for introduced  P. australis  to spread. The Delta sublineage's ancestral origin appears to be from a Mediterranean/African population ( Hauber  et al.  2011 ;  Lambertini  et al.  2012 ). The other four introduced sublineages appear to be very recent, likely occurring within the past 20 years ( Hauber  et al.  2011 ).  The other lineage of  P. australis  found in this region, subsp.  berlandieri , is likely the resident taxon on the Gulf Coast and possibly has dispersed there naturally from populations in Central and South America, which are more diverse ( Lambertini  et al.  2012 ; D. P. Hauber, unpubl. data). Based on observations from field studies along the Gulf Coast over the past 25 years, subsp.  berlandieri  lacks aggressive growth (D. P. Hauber and D. A. White, pers. observ.). It commonly occurs on roadsides, lowlands and wet soils in general, but usually not in standing water (Fig.  5 ). In the Balize delta, it occurs sporadically on spoil banks and elevated splays (D. P. Hauber, D. A. White and C. S. Hood, pers. observ.).  The different  P. australis  lineages and sublineages along the Gulf Coast do seem to vary in their primary mechanism of propagation. Subspecies  berlandieri  (6× ploidy;  Gaudreault  et al.  1989 ;  Hauber  et al.  2011 ) appears to spread entirely clonally given its low genetic diversity based on microsatellite analysis and lack of viable seed based on germination trials (D. P. Hauber, unpubl. data). Delta, Short B and Greeny 2 have displayed inter-population genetic variation and/or viable seed production, indicating that sexual propagation is playing at least a minor role in their spread. However, over half of the Delta sublineage populations sampled shared the same multilocus allele (nuclear) phenotype, and similarly for the Short A sublineage, so undoubtedly clonal spread is the primary mechanism for most of the introduced sublineages ( Hauber  et al.  2011 ). Preliminary data from growth rate studies of select clones in the Balize delta show that all introduced sublineages seem to exhibit rapid clonal spread (D. A. White, D. P. Hauber and C. S. Hood, unpubl. data).  Without archived material older than 30 years, it is not possible to say if replacement of the ‘resident’ subsp.  berlandieri  by Delta has occurred in introduced  P. australis -dominated exterior marshes of the Balize delta. It is clear that in those locations subsp.  berlandieri  is infrequent, and colonies exhibit slow clonal spread (D. A. White, D. P. Hauber and C. S. Hood, unpubl. data). In the past 10 years, introduced  P. australis  along with  Typha  spp. have successfully invaded some interior marshes, converting large portions of the diverse vegetation from a dominant  Schoenoplectus deltarum  and  Sagittaria  spp. marsh to mostly introduced  P. australis  and  Typha  spp. (D. A. White, pers. comm.). Also, competition studies conducted in the Barataria marshes of Louisiana indicate that the introduced  P. australis  lineage easily outcompetes subsp.  berlandieri  as well as  Schoenoplectus  spp. and  Distichlis spicata  ( Howard  et al.  2008 ).  Our regional assessments reveal substantial ecological diversity between and within the lineages of  P. australis . These observations are supported by recent genetic advances. We now see that the variation within the species reflects more complexity than previously considered. The introduced lineage alone occurs in diverse climates, in wetland types with widely varying environmental conditions and disturbance regimes, and exhibits differing reproductive strategies. It must still be determined whether these variations reflect inherent differences in ecological requirements, or are evidence for extreme plasticity within a species and adaptations to local conditions; or if these different sublineages are representative of a cryptic species complex within introduced  P. australis , as demonstrated by recent studies in the Balize delta. As researchers discover more sublineages of introduced  P. australis , collaboration at the continental level will be important in identifying patterns of genetic diversity that may be associated with different invasion patterns. At a broad level, comparisons between the introduced and native lineages have clearly shown ecological and phenological differences, but more research is required to identify the contribution of genetic diversity to ecological differences within the introduced lineage, or the native lineage for that matter. In regions other than the Gulf Coast, Short B appears to be the predominant invasive sublineage, but as Delta or other introduced sublineages spread more widely, careful identification will be important.  Comparing the four regions, we found interesting and surprising differences within the introduced lineage in terms of the timing of introduction, the habitat occupied and mode of reproduction. In Utah and the Chesapeake Bay, introduced  P. australis  is found in a diversity of wetlands and newly created habitats, while in the St Lawrence and Gulf Coast, the preferred habitat is narrower. Also, although sexual reproduction is common for introduced  P. australis  in Utah, the Chesapeake Bay and the St Lawrence River, in the Gulf Coast there is substantial variation in mode of reproduction in the introduced sublineages. Mode of reproduction and adaptation to different environments can drive the timing and pattern of invasion in  P. australis  ( Kettenring and Mock 2012 ), thus gaining a better understanding of what is driving these differences is critical.  Despite differences within the introduced lineage, we do see an omnipresent characteristic in  P. australis  invasion across North America: this lineage is highly opportunistic. It has been shown to invade disturbed or newly created habitats in the four study regions, areas where there is little to no competition from other vegetation types and likely high resource availability. Similar findings have been found in other regions of North America as well (e.g.  Minchinton and Bertness 2003 ;  Silliman and Bertness 2004 ). These initial disturbances seem to be important for establishment especially by seeds and may indicate ways of limiting the species in targeted locations. Once established,  P. australis  can quickly proliferate, even in pristine wetlands.  Looking to the future, it is important to consider what other opportunities humans may be providing for  P. australis  invasion. For instance, currently in the St Lawrence River watershed, large sections of the highway system, which are over 40 years old, are being rebuilt, with the resulting widespread disturbance of roadsides. Water levels are also at record lows, exposing suitable shoreline habitats. In Utah, human movement of propagules and human-caused disturbances may trigger the invasive lineage to become more widespread in the remote places where native  P. australis  is still dominant. In the Gulf Coast, introduced  P. australis  may become a dominant feature of interior marshes of the Balize delta, while in the Chesapeake Bay we may see further expansion into forested watersheds where the species is currently uncommon ( King  et al.  2007 ) as anthropogenic development increases. Even if the introduced lineage has been present for a long time in North America, conditions that favour the continental expansion of  P. australis  have increased in recent times, suggesting continued expansion in all regions.  In spite of some research on the biological impacts of introduced  P. australis  on wetland ecosystems (e.g.  Meyerson  et al.  1999 ;  Keller 2000 ;  Talley and Levin 2001 ;  Able  et al.  2003 ;  Windham and Ehrenfeld 2003 ;  Minchinton  et al.  2006 ), a continental perspective highlights that there is insufficient or conflicting evidence regarding impacts on the flora and fauna. In the St Lawrence River, researchers have found more plant diversity in native vs. introduced stands of  P. australis  (S. de Blois, unpubl. data), but additional studies are required to determine if this is a result of an invasion effect or other factors such as differences in environmental conditions. At the current level of invasion, researchers have also observed no significant difference in the use by birds, fish or amphibians of introduced  P. australis  stands compared with adjacent non-invaded vegetation types ( Le Groupe Phragmites 2012 ) but some habitat thresholds may have to be reached at the landscape scale before impacts on the fauna can be identified. Similarly, researchers following the invasion front of introduced  P. australis  into native  P. australis  stands have found limited evidence to indicate that native stands are being replaced rapidly by introduced  P. australis  (S. de Blois, unpubl. data). All these findings highlight the need for long-term monitoring that takes into account vegetation patterns and habitat diversity at the landscape scale, in order to better predict the competitive outcomes and impacts on biodiversity; and monitoring across regions using similar approaches to facilitate generalization.  Given that introduced  P. australis  is here to stay, it is important to reflect on both the positive and negative impacts of the sublineages. In the Mississippi River delta, introduced  P. australis  may be protecting inner natural marshes from storms and oil spills. If it invades interior marshes as well, however, it may negatively impact important wildlife habitat. In the St Lawrence, introduced  P. australis  may fill a role in new habitats along agricultural fields by processing the nutrient-rich run-off, but it may conflict with biodiversity conservation in adjacent species-rich wetlands or even with production on agricultural land. So, although  P. australis  has been widely perceived as a threat to wetland ecosystems, evidence of its impacts on biodiversity and ecosystem services still needs to be better documented. It should be recognized that the nature of these impacts is likely to change with time since invasion.  Our comparison highlights important research priorities that can drive further efforts to inform a continental perspective. There is a definite need to better clarify the genetic and ecological relationships between the different introduced sublineages observed in North America, and their relative competitive ability and potential for admixture. This may be done through regional studies that use similar methodologies and share results to uncover common patterns and processes. To our knowledge, such studies have not been performed on  P. australis  in spite of the broad attention given to this species. A continental perspective can help untangle the relationships between the introduced sublineages, reproductive strategy and environmental changes such as nutrient enrichment or disturbances. Such research could advance theoretical knowledge on biological invasion by helping to determine the extent to which the patterns observed can be generalized or are sublineage specific or region specific. Controlled experiments, long-term monitoring and perhaps a functional approach across different ecological settings could be used to improve knowledge. When the regions are analysed in isolation from each other, invasion patterns sometimes appear idiosyncratic and resist generalization. It may be time to consider initiatives at the continental (if not intercontinental) scale to tackle unresolved issues.  K.K. acknowledges the  UT Agricultural Experiment Station , the Gardner Junior Faculty travel award, and the  UT State University Center  for Women and Gender for funding. S.d.B. acknowledges Les Fonds de Recherche du Québec—Nature et technologies, and The  Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada  for funding. D.H. thanks Loyola University Grants and Leaves Committee Research Grant, Faculty Development Grant, and Sabbatical Leave; Rev. J.H. Mullahy Fund; the Coastal Restoration and Enhancement through Science and Technology program; and the  LA Board of Regents  grant  LEQSF(2007-12)-ENH-PKSFI-PES-03  to Frank Jordan.  All authors jointly wrote the manuscript.  None declared.  We thank Diane Menuz for making the map. SdB acknowledges the  Phragmites  Group ( phragmites.crad.ulaval.ca/en/)  and D.H. acknowledges the US Fish and Wildlife Service for access to the Delta National Wildlife Refuge and D.A. White and C.S. Hood for valuable technical support. Dennis Whigham, Tom Mozdzer and two anonymous reviewers provided helpful comments on earlier versions of this manuscript. 