 The influence of water temperature and accelerometer-determined fight intensity on physiological stress and reflex impairment of angled largemouth bass  Energy partitioning in largemouth bass under conditions of seasonally fluctuating prey availability  Understanding the complexity of catch-and-release in recreational fishing: an integrative synthesis of global knowledge from historical, ethical, social, and biological perspectives  Effects of handling and electrofishing on plasma glucose and whole blood lactate of  Leuciscus cephalus   Observing the unwatchable through acceleration logging of animal behavior  Recovery bags reduce post-release impairments in locomotory activity and behavior of bonefish ( Albula  spp.) following exposure to angling-related stressors  Fishing-related stressors inhibit refuge-seeking behavior in released subadult Great Barracuda  Animal welfare perspectives on recreational angling  Do we need species-specific guidelines for catch-and-release recreational angling to effectively conserve diverse fishery resources?  Physiological impacts of catch-and-release angling practices on largemouth bass and smallmouth bass  Effects of different capture techniques on the physiological condition of bonefish  Albula vulpes  evaluated using field diagnostic tools  Recreational fisheries  Simulated fishing experiments for predicting delayed mortality rates using reflex impairment in restrained fish  Fish stress and mortality can be predicted using reflex impairment  Wounding and reflex impairment may be predictors for mortality in discarded or escaped fish  Cortisol and glucose responses in juvenile brown trout subjected to a fluctuating flow regime in an artificial stream  Physiological response of largemouth bass to angling stress  Life history and biology of the largemouth bass  Effects of stress on growth, cortisol and glucose levels in non-domesticated Eurasian perch ( Perca fluviatilis ) and domesticated rainbow trout ( Oncorhynchus mykiss )  Competitive fishing in freshwaters of North America: a survey of Canadian and US jurisdictions  Limits to exhaustive exercise in fish  Physiology and organismal performance of centrarchids  Effects of catch-and-release angling on nesting male smallmouth bass  Physiological response of wild rainbow trout to angling: impact of angling duration, fish size, body condition, and temperature  Do catch-and-release guidelines from state and provincial fisheries agencies in North America conform to scientifically based best practices?  The impact of catch-and-release angling on the reproductive success of smallmouth bass and largemouth bass  Trends in regulatory and voluntary catch-and-release fishing  Centrarchid fisheries  Validation of reflex indicators for measuring vitality and predicting the delayed mortality of wild coho salmon bycatch released from fishing gears  R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing  The status of competitive sport fishing in North America  A review of the effects of catch-and-release angling on black bass,  Micropterus  spp.: implications for conservation and management of populations  Use of portable blood physiology point-of-care devices for basic and applied research on vertebrates: a review  The effect of catch-and-release angling on the parental care behavior of male smallmouth bass  Physiological disturbance and recovery dynamics of bonefish ( Albula vulpes ), a tropical marine fish, in response to variable exercise and exposure to air  Physiology, behaviour, and survival of angled and air-exposed largemouth bass  Effects of hook and release on Atlantic salmon in the River Alta, northern Norway  Centrarchid identification and natural history  Behavioral and physiological responses of the congeneric largemouth ( Micropterus salmoides ) and smallmouth bass ( M. dolomieu ) to various exercise and air exposure durations   Editor:  Craig Franklin  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  We examined the influence of fight intensity on physiological stress and reflex impairment in largemouth bass during angling events using rod-mounted accelerometers across two temperatures (12 and 22°C). Temperature was the strongest predictor of physiological stress response, while fight intensity was not a strong predictor.  Release of fish captured by recreational anglers is a common practice due to angler conservation ethics or compliance with fisheries regulations. As such, there is a need to understand the factors that influence mortality and sub-lethal impairments to ensure that catch-and-release angling is a sustainable practice. Longer angling times generally contribute to increased stress and mortality in fish such that reducing these times putatively reduces stress and improves survival. However, the relative importance of fight intensity (rather than simply duration) on fish condition is poorly understood. The objective of this research was to examine the effects of fight intensity on physiological stress and reflex impairment of largemouth bass ( Micropterus salmoides ). The largemouth bass were angled using conventional recreational fishing gear in May (water temperature ∼12°C) and June (∼22°C) of 2014 in Lake Opinicon, Ontario, Canada. Fight intensity was quantified using tri-axial accelerometer loggers mounted on the tips of fishing rods. Upon capture, reflex impairment measures were assessed, and fish were held for 1 h prior to blood sampling for measurement of physiological stress (blood glucose and lactate concentrations and pH). Physiological stress values showed a negative trend with fight duration and total fight intensity, but a positive trend with average fight intensity. Water temperature emerged as the most important predictor of the stress response in largemouth bass, while fight duration and intensity were not strong predictors. Reflex impairment was minimal, but higher reflex impairment scores were associated with elevated blood glucose. Overall, the findings of this study suggest that angling for largemouth bass at colder temperatures (&lt;15°C) causes greater physiological stress than at warmer temperatures (&gt;20°C). Based on our findings, we conclude that fight intensity is likely not to be a major driver of physiological stress in this species using typical largemouth bass angling gear, owing to the relatively short fight times (i.e. &lt;2 min).  Catch-and-release angling is growing in popularity worldwide as a management and conservation strategy ( Cowx 2002 ;  Arlinghaus  et al ., 2007 ). For example, in Canada, release rates among recreational anglers are approaching 60% nationwide ( Brownscombe  et al . 2014 ). While catch-and-release angling can be an effective conservation strategy, stressors associated with angling (i.e. hooking, fighting, handling and air exposure) can have negative impacts on fish fitness that may lead to population-level effects (reviewed by  Cooke and Suski, 2005 ;  Arlinghaus  et al ., 2007 ). The fate of angled and released fish is primarily determined by angler behaviour (including gear choice) and environmental conditions ( Cooke and Sneddon, 2007 ), so employing certain angling practices can minimize impacts ( Pelletier  et al ., 2007 ). For example, the minimization of angling times and air exposure and the avoidance of angling at extreme temperatures can reduce physiological stress, behavioural impairment and mortality ( Cooke and Suski, 2005 ).  The largemouth bass ( Micropterus salmoides ) is a warm-water fish in the Centrarchidae family, indigenous to eastern North America ( Heidinger, 1975 ;  Warren, 2009 ) and, due to their popularity with recreational anglers, are now widely distributed in warm freshwater systems worldwide ( Quinn and Paukert, 2009 ). Largemouth bass support massive recreational fisheries, including large competitive fishing industries ( Schramm  et al ., 1991 ;  Kerr and Kamke, 2003 ), and given its popularity for sportfishing, release rates are especially high ( Quinn, 1996 ;  Brownscombe  et al ., 2014 ). The potential impacts of angling on this species are well studied (reviewed by  Siepker  et al. , 2007 ) and can include physiological stress, behavioural impairment (reduced foraging abilities or nest guarding during reproductive period in the spring) and mortality ( Philipp  et al ., 1997 ;  Cooke  et al ., 2002 ;  Suski  et al ., 2003 ;  Thompson  et al ., 2008 ;  White  et al ., 2008 ). Given the ecological, economic and social importance of largemouth bass, understanding and minimizing the impacts of catch-and-release angling on this species is particularly important.  The duration of angling (between hooking and landing when fish resist capture) is often a significant aspect of angling events (e.g.  Meka and McCormick, 2004 ;  Thompson  et al ., 2008 ) because fish typically fight themselves into exhaustion, which involves the depletion of energy reserves and anaerobic respiration ( Kieffer, 2000) . Indeed, fight duration has been correlated with stress in a number of fish species, including largemouth bass ( Gustaveson  et al ., 1991 ;  Kieffer  et al ., 1995 ;  Thorstad  et al ., 2003 ). For this reason, reducing fight times is generally thought to minimize stress and fitness consequences ( Cooke and Suski, 2005 ). However, no studies have ever reduced the fight duration experimentally in order to confirm its putative value or examined the effects of fight intensity (the amount that the fish resists capture) on fish stress, impairment or mortality. The objective of the present research, therefore, was to examine the influence of fight intensity on physiological stress and reflex impairment in largemouth bass. We predicted that, while physiological stress and reflex impairment would correlate with fight duration, fight intensity would be a stronger predictor of these stress responses. More specifically, we predicted that the stress response would be equal between shorter, more intense fights and longer, less intense fights. To accomplish this, we used fishing rod-mounted tri-axial accelerometer loggers to quantify fight intensity during capture at two temperatures.  Fishing rod with tri-axial accelerometer attached for measurement of angling fight intensity.  When a largemouth bass strike was detected, the angler set the hook into the fish's mouth as per typical angling events and noted the timing of the hook set. Anglers maintained the position of the rod as consistently as possible to isolate the influence of the pull upon the rod by the fish as the main source of acceleration. Upon landing with a rubberized fishing net, the time was noted, and fish were air exposed for a standardized 30 s period, during which time the hook was removed. After the air exposure period, fish were placed in a 90 litre cooler, which was regularly flushed with ambient lake water.  Once placed in the holding containers, fish were assessed for reflex impairment using methods developed under the codification of reflex action mortality predictors (RAMP;  Davis, 2010 ). Five RAMP parameters were assessed, as follows: equilibrium, tail grab, head complex, vestibular–ocular response (VOR) and body flex. Equilibrium was assessed by flipping the fish upside down in water; a positive response was indicated by the fish righting itself within 3 s. Tail grab was measured by grabbing the fish's caudal peduncle while in water; a positive response was indicated by an attempt to escape from the handler. Head complex was assessed by observing the fish's opercula; regular opercular beats indicated a positive response. The VOR was measured by rolling the fish side to side in the longitudinal axis; a positive response was indicated by the fish's eyes moving back and forth, tracking level. Body flex was assessed by lifting the fish into the air by the centre of the body; a positive response was indicated by the flexing or movement of the body. These predictors were used because they are consistent indicators of vitality in teleost fishes ( Davis, 2010 ;  Raby  et al ., 2012 ;  Brownscombe  et al. , 2013 ,  2014 ). Each indicator was scored as 1 = impaired and 0 = unimpaired, and overall RAMP scores were calculated as the proportion of indicators impaired.  Fish were retained in holding containers for 1 h prior to phlebotomy because physiological stress typically peaks ∼1 h post-stressor in most teleost fishes ( Flodmark  et al. , 2002 ;  Bracewell  et al ., 2003 ;  Jentoft  et al. , 2005 ;  Suski  et al ., 2007 ). After the 1 h period, fish were transported to a sloped trough filled with freshwater for drawing of ∼1 ml of blood via caudal venipuncture using an 18-gauge syringe and 3 ml Vacutainer ®  (lithium heparin). Blood was analysed immediately using point-of-care devices calibrated for fish (see  Cooke  et al. , 2008 ;  Stoot  et al. , 2014 ) for blood-plasma lactate (in millimoles per litre; Lactate Pro LT-1710; Akray Inc., Kyoto, Japan), glucose (in millimoles per litre; Accu-Chek Compact Plus; Roche Diagnostics, Basel, Switzerland) and pH (HI-99161; Hanna Instruments, Woonsocket, RI, USA).  Tri-axial accelerometers recorded total acceleration ( g ) at 25 Hz in three axes ( x ,  y  and  z ), where  g  was the sum of both dynamic (fishing rod) and static (gravity) acceleration, with maximal values of ± 8  g . Acceleration sum vectors (SV;  g ) were calculated as SV = √( x  2  +  y  2  +  z  2 ) for the duration of each angling event to quantify total and average fight intensities ( g ).  Initially, Pearson's  r  correlations were calculated between angling fight metrics (fight duration, average fight intensity and total fight intensity) and fish metrics (length, blood glucose, blood lactate and blood pH). The above metrics were compared between angling temperatures (12°C in May and 22°C in June) using Welch's  t -tests. To examine the relationships between RAMP scores and fight metrics, fight duration, total fight intensity and average fight intensity, as well as blood glucose, lactate and pH were compared between unimpaired fish (RAMP = 0) and impaired fish (RAMP ≥ 0.2) with Welch's  t -tests. To determine significant predictors of physiological stress responses in largemouth bass, linear mixed effects models were generated for blood lactate and glucose concentrations, as well as blood pH. Fixed effects included fight time, mean fight intensity, temperature and the interactions between mean fight intensity × temperature and fight time × mean fight intensity, with fishing rod (angler) as a random effect. Candidate linear models were generated using all combinations of predictors and compared using second-order Akaike information criterion (AICc). The level of significance was set at  P  ≤ 0.05, and all analyses were conducted using RStudio (version 0.97.314). All data are presented as means ± SD ( R Core Team, 2013 ).  Angling metrics for largemouth bass  Accelerometric signature (sum vector;  g ) of a largemouth bass angling event.  Pearson's  r  correlation coefficients (bottom left) and corresponding  P -values (italics; upper right) of largemouth bass angling metrics  Asterisks indicate significant correlations at 84 degrees of freedom.  Relationship between fight duration (seconds) and ( A ) total fight intensity ( g ), and ( B ) average fight intensity ( g ) during angling events.  Relationship between average fight intensity and ( A ) blood glucose (mmol/l), ( B ) blood lactate (mmol/l), and ( C ) blood pH at 12°C (black dots) and 22°C (grey triangles) 1 h after angling events.  Final linear mixed effects models of largemouth bass blood glucose and lactate concentrations and blood pH 1 h after angling events  It is well established that longer angling, air exposure and handling times can cause greater physiological and ­behavioural impairment in largemouth bass ( Gustaveson  et al ., 1991 ;  Thompson  et al ., 2008 ;  White  et al ., 2008 ). Here, we attempted to isolate and quantify the effects of fighting intensity on physiological stress and reflex impairment in largemouth bass using novel fishing rod-mounted accelerometers at two water temperatures. Interestingly, fight duration and total fight intensity were not correlated with any measured physiological stress responses (blood glucose and lactate concentrations and pH) or reflex impairment scores in angled largemouth bass. However, longer fights had lower average fight intensities, while average fight intensity did correlate positively with blood glucose and lactate concentrations and negatively with blood pH (Table  1 ). Blood glucose concentrations were significantly higher at colder water temperatures, when average fight intensities were also higher. Furthermore, larger fish had higher average fight intensities, larger fish on average were caught at colder ­temperatures, and blood glucose concentrations were positively correlated with fish size. While it is difficult to isolate the relative contributions of these factors to the blood glucose response of largemouth bass, temperature emerged as the only significant predictor of blood glucose 1 h after angling events, while there were no significant predictors measured here of blood lactate or pH.  While stress responses have been well studied in largemouth bass, no studies have examined their response at temperatures as cold as those included in the present study (mean 12°C during May sampling). In fact, blood glucose concentrations were significantly higher at these colder temperatures than at 22°C.  Thompson  et al . (2008)  also found that stress responses, including glucose concentrations, were significantly higher at cooler temperatures (∼15 compared with ∼21°C). This could be because largemouth bass are further from their metabolic optima (see  Kieffer and Cooke, 2009 ) and experience greater anaerobic respiration at lower temperatures ( Thompson  et al ., 2008 ). However, when comparing stress responses at different times of the year, other factors, such as prey availability, gut fullness or reproductive status, may also vary. Indeed, at the lower temperatures in the present study largemouth bass are typically preparing for reproduction and more readily mobilize endogenous energy reserves or have higher gut fullness ( Adams  et al ., 1982 ). In eastern Ontario, where the present study was conducted, targeting largemouth bass during this season is prohibited by law; however, largemouth may be caught frequently while targeting other species with open seasons, such as bluegill sunfish ( Lepomis macrochirus ) or walleye ( Sander vitreus ). Furthermore, in some areas of Canada and the USA, largemouth bass angling is legal during seasons when temperatures are lower. During these time periods, catch-and-release angling of largemouth bass may be inherently more stressful than at warmer temperatures after the spawning period.  Cooke and Suski, 2005  called for additional research on the physiological consequences of catch-and-release angling at low water temperatures, which seems merited given our findings.  Angling fights with higher mean intensity did trend towards greater physiological stress responses in largemouth bass, while temperature and mean fight intensity comprised the best model for blood glucose concentrations. However, neither fight intensity nor duration were significant predictors of the stress responses measured here 1 h after landing. While it is intuitive that more intense fighting responses entail greater anaerobic exercise, resulting in a greater stress response, our findings did not strongly support this prediction. It is also surprising that blood lactate and pH, which are also typically reflective of anaerobic exercise, were not related to any fight metrics or environmental variables measured here.  White  et al . (2008)  found that exercising largemouth bass for 180 s caused significantly higher blood lactate concentrations and haematocrit than at 20 s, but found no significant differences in blood glucose concentrations.  Meka and McCormick (2004)  also found that rainbow trout ( Oncorhynchus mykiss ) with longer fight times (&gt;2 min) had significantly higher blood lactate and cortisol concentrations; however, larger fish also had longer fight times. Indeed, it is difficult to disentangle the effects of fish size and fighting metrics on fish stress response using ‘natural’ angling events because these metrics are so commonly correlated. Perhaps, if we had collected blood samples at a different time (e.g. 30 min post-stressor, while peaking, or 2 h post-stressor, when recovery would typically be underway), we might have detected such a relationship. The results of the present study may simply reflect the fact that fight duration and intensity are not major factors contributing to the stress response of largemouth bass with typical gear and conditions (all fight times in the present study were &lt;2 min with 6.8 kg break-strength line and medium-strength rods).  Greater durations of air exposure have shown to increase stress responses ( Cooke  et al ., 2002 ;  Thompson  et al. , 2008 ), and collectively, research on largemouth bass suggests that using typical bass fishing gear and minimizing or eliminating air exposure results in relatively low stress, few reflex impairments and high survival (reviewed by  Siepker  et al. , 2007 ). Here, we used a standardized duration of air exposure (30 s) to examine the relationship between fight intensity, stress and reflex impairment. There may also be an interaction between fight intensity while on the line and subsequent air exposure duration in real angling scenarios. For example, fish that fight more vigorously may be more exhausted and less active during handling, reducing air exposure times. Future studies should aim to examine how various aspects of angling practices interact and influence fish condition upon release.  The ability to assess fish condition prior to release has important applications for fish conservation. For example, anglers can make educated decisions about whether to release a fish immediately, retain it for a short recovery period or harvest it for consumption. It may also serve as a practical proxy for fish survival for fisheries managers to incorporate post-release mortality into management strategies. In the present study, all largemouth bass exhibited relatively low reflex impairment with limited (30 s) amounts of air ­exposure and &lt;2 min fight times. However, over 50% of fish lacked a body flex response when removed from water, and these fish had significantly higher blood glucose concentrations 1 h post-angling than fish showing no impairment. Reflex impairment measures, e.g. RAMP ( Davis, 2010 ), are consistent indicators of behavioural impairment and mortality across fish species (e.g.  Davis and Ottmar, 2006 ;  Davis, 2007 ;  Raby  et al ., 2012 ;  Brownscombe  et al. , 2013 ); however, the connection of RAMP with physiological stress is more tenuous. Here we found that impaired fish did have significantly higher blood glucose, but there was no relationship with RAMP and any other physiological stress measure. Future work should aim to test the applicability of reflex tests further in predicting stress, behavioural impairment and mortality for this species to contribute to its conservation.  In conclusion, angling for largemouth bass at cold temperatures prior to the spawning period caused greater physiological disturbance in blood glucose concentrations than at warmer temperatures, which may be related to temperature and/or seasonal changes in the physiological status of the fish prior to angling. Our findings suggest that the fight, where fish resist capture prior to landing, has limited influence on physiological and behavioural impairment of largemouth bass when fight times are relatively low, using typical largemouth bass angling gear. Reflex impairment measures reflect underlying physiological stress in this species and may have further applications for assessing the condition of largemouth bass prior to release. Future research should aim to understand how fight duration and intensity mechanistically contribute to fish stress in species that typically exhibit greater fight times (e.g. rainbow trout, bonefish,  Albula  spp .  or billfish) to determine whether minimization of fight times is effective at reducing physiological stress and negative fitness consequences.  This work was supported by the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada. The research vessel used for this research was funded by the Canada Foundation for Innovation and the Ontario Research Fund.  J.W.B. is supported by the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC). S.J.C. is supported by the Canada Research Chairs program and NSERC. We thank the staff of Queen's Biology Station for logistical support. We thank the Ontario Ministry of Natural Resources for providing a scientific collection permit. All work and training described within was in accordance with the guidelines of the Canadian Council of Animal Care. 