Carbon dioxide stimulation of photosynthesis in <italic>Liquidambar styraciflua</italic> is not sustained during a 12-year field experimentWhat have we learned from 15 years of free air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (FACE)? A meta-analytic review of the responses of photosynthesis, canopy properties and plant production to rising CO<sub>2</sub>The response of photosynthesis and stomatal conductance to rising [CO<sub>2</sub>]: mechanisms and environmental interactionsSustained enhancement of photosynthesis in mature deciduous forest trees after 8 years of free air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichmentPhotosynthesis and stomatal conductance responses of poplars to free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (PopFACE) during the first growth cycle and immediately following coppiceIncreased nitrogen-use efficiency of a short-rotation poplar plantation in elevated CO<sub>2</sub> concentrationRubisco activation state decreases with increasing nitrogen content in apple leavesLong-term response of nutrient-limited forests to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment; equilibrium behavior of plant–soil modelsCanopy position affects photosynthetic adjustments to long-term elevated CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (FACE) in aging needles in a mature <italic>Pinus taeda</italic> forestElevated CO<sub>2</sub> concentration affects leaf photosynthesis–nitrogen relationships in <italic>Pinus taeda</italic> over nine years in FACEA meta-analysis of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> effects on woody plant mass, form, and physiologyWill photosynthetic capacity of aspen trees acclimate after long-term exposure to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub>?Forest water use and water use efficiency at elevated CO<sub>2</sub>: a model-data intercomparison at two contrasting temperate forest FACE sitesOptimal function explains forest responses to global changeMore efficient plants: a consequence of rising atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>?Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> affects photosynthetic responses in canopy pine and subcanopy deciduous trees over 10 years: a synthesis from Duke FACEEffects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> concentration on leaf characteristics and photosynthetic capacity of beech (<italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic>) during the growing seasonDirect and indirect effects of elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> on net ecosystem production in a Chesapeake Bay tidal wetlandMoving beyond photosynthesis: from carbon source to sink-driven vegetation modelingProgressive nitrogen limitation of ecosystem processes under elevated CO<sub>2</sub> in a warm-temperate forestIncreases in nitrogen uptake rather than nitrogen-use efficiency support higher rates of temperate forest productivity under elevated CO<sub>2</sub>Litterfall <sup>15</sup>N abundance indicates declining soil nitrogen availability in a free air CO<sub>2</sub>-enrichment experimentPhotosynthetic responses of two eucalypts to industrial-age changes in atmospheric [CO<sub>2</sub>] and temperaturePhotosynthetic acclimation in trees to rising atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>: a broader perspectiveFoliar gas exchange responses of two deciduous hardwoods during 3 years of growth in elevated CO<sub>2</sub>: no loss of photosynthetic enhancementEnvironmental and stomatal control of photosynthetic enhancement in the canopy of a sweetgum (<italic>Liquidambar styraciflua</italic> L) plantation during three years of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichmentA free-air enrichment system for exposing tall forest vegetation to elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>Effects of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment on the photosynthetic light response of sun and shade leaves of canopy sweetgum trees (<italic>Liquidambar styraciflua</italic>) in a forest ecosystemNo photosynthetic down-regulation in sweetgum trees (<italic>Liquidambar styraciflua</italic> L.) after three years of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment at the Duke Forest FACE experimentLeaf senescence and late-season net photosynthesis of sun and shade leaves of overstory sweetgum (<italic>Liquidambar styraciflua</italic>) grown in elevated and ambient carbon dioxide concentrationsModelling optimal temperature acclimation of the photosynthetic apparatus in C-3 plants with respect to nitrogen usePseudoreplication and the design of ecological field experimentsExtinction coefficients of chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic> in <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylformamide and 80 % acetoneClimate change 2013: the physical science basisNitrogen limitation in a sweetgum plantation: implications for carbon allocation and storageNet mineralization of N at deeper soil depths as a potential mechanism for sustained forest production under elevated [CO<sub>2</sub>]Photosynthetic acclimation of overstory <italic>Populus tremuloides</italic> and understory <italic>Acer saccharum</italic> to elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration: interactions with shade and soil nitrogenSeasonal response of photosynthesis to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> in loblolly pine (<italic>Pinus taeda</italic> L.) over two growing seasonsPhotosynthetic stimulation under long-term CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment and fertilization is sustained across a closed <italic>Populus</italic> canopy profile (EUROFACE)Progressive nitrogen limitation of ecosystem responses to rising atmospheric carbon dioxideForest responses to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment and climate warmingEffects of growth temperature on the responses of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase, electron transport components, and sucrose synthesis enzymes to leaf nitrogen in rice, and their relationships to photosynthesisResponse of photosynthetic carbon assimilation of Norway spruce exposed to long-term elevation of CO<sub>2</sub> concentrationThe optimal allocation of nitrogen within the C<sub>3</sub> photosynthetic system at elevated CO<sub>2</sub>Effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> on photosynthesis in European forest species: a meta-analysis of model parametersTemperature response of parameters of a biochemically based model of photosynthesis. II. A review of experimental dataReconciling the optimal and empirical approaches to modelling stomatal conductanceDevelopment of a standardized methodology for quantifying total chlorophyll and carotenoids from foliage of hardwood and conifer tree speciesIsoprene emission from terrestrial ecosystems in response to global change: minding the gap between models and observationsElevated CO<sub>2</sub> response of photosynthesis depends on ozone concentration in aspenTree responses to rising CO<sub>2</sub>: implications for the future forestAllometric determination of tree growth in a CO<sub>2</sub>-enriched sweetgum standFine-root production dominates response of a deciduous forest to atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> enrichmentForest response to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> is conserved across a broad range of productivityCO<sub>2</sub> enhancement of forest productivity constrained by limited nitrogen availabilityTransient nature of CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization in Arctic tundraOn the complementary relationship between marginal nitrogen and water use efficiencies among <italic>Pinus taeda</italic> leaves grown under ambient and enriched CO<sub>2</sub> environmentsCarbon metabolite feedback regulation of leaf photosynthesis and developmentThe photosynthesis–leaf nitrogen relationship at ambient and elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide: a meta-analysisRelationships between nutrient supply, nitrogen partitioning and growth in young Sitka spruce (<italic>Picea sitchensis</italic>)Long-term photosynthetic acclimation to increased atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in young birch (<italic>Betula pendula</italic>) treesPhotosynthetic acclimation of <italic>Pinus taeda</italic> (loblolly pine) to long-term growth in elevated <italic>p</italic>CO<sub>2</sub> (FACE)Growth and nutrition response of young sweetgum plantations to repeated nitrogen fertilization on two site typesPersistent stimulation of photosynthesis by elevated CO<sub>2</sub> in a sweetgum (<italic>Liquidambar styraciflua</italic> L.) forest standPlant respiration and photosynthesis in global-scale vegetation models: incorporating acclimation to temperature and CO<sub>2</sub>Relationships between net photosynthesis and foliar nitrogen concentrations in a loblolly pine forest ecosystem grown in elevated atmospheric carbon dioxideThe interaction between elevated carbon dioxide and nitrogen nutrition: the physiological and molecular backgroundPhysiological and growth response of <italic>Eriophorum vaginatum</italic> to field elevated CO<sub>2</sub> and temperature in the Alaskan tussock tundraLong-term effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> and nutrients on photosynthesis and Rubisco in loblolly pine seedlingsAtmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment increases growth and photosynthesis of <italic>Pinus taeda</italic>: a 4 year experiment in the fieldLeaf respiration at different canopy positions in sweetgum <italic>(Liquidambar styraciflua</italic>) grown in ambient and elevated concentrations of carbon dioxide in the fieldComprehensive ecosystem model-data synthesis using multiple data sets at two temperate forest free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment experiments: model performance at ambient CO<sub>2</sub> concentrationEvergreen trees do not maximize instantaneous photosynthesisEcohydrologic impact of reduced stomatal conductance in forests exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub>Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> enhances premature leaf senescence during extreme climatic events in a temperate forestGrowth and photosynthetic response of nine tropical species with long-term exposure to elevated carbon dioxide<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Jeffrey S. DukesThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Atmospheric carbon dioxide levels have increased by∼25% over the last 50 years. While more carbon dioxide can initially stimulate plant photosynthesis, we found that long-term (12 years) exposure of sweetgum trees to elevated carbon dioxide resulted in no stimulation of photosynthesis. The loss of initial increases in photosynthesis was due to low leaf nitrogen levels, which suggests other limiting resources may moderate future impacts of elevated carbon dioxide on photosynthesis.Elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> (eCO<sub>2</sub>) often increases photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation (<italic>A</italic>) in field studies of temperate tree species. However, there is evidence that <italic>A</italic> may decline through time due to biochemical and morphological acclimation, and environmental constraints. Indeed, at the free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (FACE) study in Oak Ridge, Tennessee, <italic>A</italic> was increased in 12-year-old sweetgum trees following 2 years of ∼40 % enhancement of CO<sub>2</sub>. <italic>A</italic> was re-assessed a decade later to determine if the initial enhancement of photosynthesis by eCO<sub>2</sub> was sustained through time. Measurements were conducted at prevailing CO<sub>2</sub> and temperature on detached, re-hydrated branches using a portable gas exchange system. Photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> response curves (<italic>A</italic> versus the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the intercellular air space (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>); or <italic>A</italic>–<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub> curves) were contrasted with earlier measurements using leaf photosynthesis model equations. Relationships between light-saturated photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>), maximum electron transport rate (<italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>), maximum Rubisco activity (<italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub>), chlorophyll content and foliar nitrogen (N) were assessed. In 1999, <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> for eCO<sub>2</sub> treatments was 15.4 ± 0.8 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, 22 % higher than aCO<sub>2</sub> treatments (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). By 2009, <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> declined to &lt;50 % of 1999 values, and there was no longer a significant effect of eCO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> = 6.9 or 5.7 ± 0.7 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> for eCO<sub>2</sub> or aCO<sub>2</sub>, respectively). In 1999, there was no treatment effect on area-based foliar N; however, by 2008, N content in eCO<sub>2</sub> foliage was 17 % less than that in aCO<sub>2</sub> foliage. Photosynthetic N-use efficiency (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> : N) was greater in eCO<sub>2</sub> in 1999 resulting in greater <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> despite similar N content, but the enhanced efficiency in eCO<sub>2</sub> trees was lost as foliar N declined to sub-optimal levels. There was no treatment difference in the declining linear relationships between <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> or <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> with declining N, or in the ratio of <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> : <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> through time. Results suggest that the initial enhancement of photosynthesis to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> will not be sustained through time if N becomes limited.In 2013, annual atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration exceeded 396 ppm at Mauna Loa, 2.6 ppm greater than in 2012 and 25 % greater than the initial measurements in 1959 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C33">Keeling <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Global atmospheric model simulations estimate that this trajectory will continue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C30">IPCC 2013</xref>), and thus terrestrial plant communities will remain exposed to increasing CO<sub>2</sub> for the foreseeable future. Atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> is a potent climate-forcing agent contributing to increased atmospheric temperatures, and ecosystem balance between plant CO<sub>2</sub> uptake through photosynthesis and release through respiratory activity remains a key uncertainty in mechanistic Earth system models that project ecosystem feedbacks to the atmosphere. To address ecosystem response to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> (eCO<sub>2</sub>), various plant species have been exposed to air enriched with CO<sub>2</sub> in short-term open- or closed-topped field chambers. Results suggested substantial eCO<sub>2</sub> stimulation of photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C39">Luxmoore <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C20">Gunderson and Wullschleger 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C42">Medlyn <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C47">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>) across various woody species (e.g. in oak, yellow poplar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C21">Gunderson <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>), pine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C67">Tissue <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>), eucalypts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C74">Ghannoum <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and tropical seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C75">Ziska <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>)). In other studies, eCO<sub>2</sub> induced significant down-regulation and loss of photosynthetic capacity (e.g. in Arctic tundra grasses and shrubs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C65">Tissue and Oechel 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C76">Oechel <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>), beech (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C77">Epron <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>) and spruce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C78">Marek <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>)), indicating that interaction with soil resources, longer term feedbacks and progressive plant acclimation remained a key uncertainty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C79">Curtis and Wang 1998</xref>). New, larger experiments using free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (FACE) technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C48">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>) have allowed field crops, grasses and, in particular, woody forest vegetation to be exposed to eCO<sub>2</sub> over many years. Such studies allow distinction of long-term responses from transient responses due to leaf plasticity, stand development or inter-annual environmental variability.Similar to the response of plants in chambers, an initial increase in net photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic>) and net primary productivity is common across woody plant species exposed to FACE eCO<sub>2</sub> treatments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C50">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C2">Ainsworth and Rogers 2007</xref>), including in <italic>Liquidambar styraciflua</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>), <italic>Pinus taeda</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C8">Crous and Ellsworth 2004</xref>), <italic>Populus × euramericana</italic>, <italic>Populus alba</italic>, <italic>P. nigra</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C4">Bernacchi <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C37">Liberloo <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), <italic>P. tremuloides</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C46">Noormets <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), <italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic>, <italic>Quercus petraea</italic>, <italic>Carpinus betulus</italic>, <italic>Acer campestre</italic> and <italic>Tilia platyphyllos</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C3">Bader <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). However, longer term eCO<sub>2</sub> field results are mixed, with some experiments reporting feedbacks such as acclimation and photosynthetic down-regulation through time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C56">Rey and Jarvis 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C42">Medlyn <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C35">Kubiske <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C4">Bernacchi <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C9">Crous <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) and others not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C3">Bader <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C10">Darbah <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).Leaves typically adjust their Rubisco activity or content to the prevailing CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, i.e. down-regulation by elevated CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C66">Tissue <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C13">Drake <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C64">Stitt and Krapp 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C58">Rogers and Ellsworth 2002</xref>). Since eCO<sub>2</sub> increases the efficiency of Rubisco, <italic>A</italic> can be maintained or enhanced despite reductions in enzyme content, activity or maximum photosynthetic capacity. This implies greater photosynthetic N-use efficiency (PNUE) as displayed across C3 woody plant species exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C54">Peterson <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C5">Calfapietra <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).Sweetgum (<italic>L. styraciflua</italic>) is a common temperate North American tree species, and is the dominant canopy species at the ORNL-FACE site in TN, USA, and the primary mid-canopy species at the Duke-FACE site in NC, USA. Prior results from these sites indicate a strong and consistent enhancement of light-saturated photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) by elevated CO<sub>2</sub>; the ∼40 % increase in atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> resulted in 45 % enhancement of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> at the ORNL-FACE site after 3 years of treatments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C22">Gunderson <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) and consistently &gt;50 % enhancement of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> at the Duke-FACE site through 6 years of treatments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C24">Herrick and Thomas 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C26">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C63">Springer <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). After 3 years of treatment at ORNL-FACE there was no change in maximum photosynthetic capacity (<italic>A</italic><sub>max</sub>), maximum electron transport rate (<italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>) or maximum carboxylation rate (<italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub>) when foliage from both treatments was measured at the same CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> did reduce foliar N content and increase soluble carbohydrates and leaf mass per area (LMA, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C26">Herrick and Thomas 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>)—results consistent across time for sweetgum in both FACE studies. After 6 years of eCO<sub>2</sub> treatment at ORNL-FACE, there was still no significant difference in <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> when both treatments were measured at 400 ppm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C45">Monson <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), indicating little eCO<sub>2</sub> down-regulation of photosynthesis.After 12 years of eCO<sub>2</sub> treatment at the ORNL-FACE research study, we re-assessed photosynthetic capacity of the dominant sweetgum trees to determine if the early enhancement of photosynthesis during the years 1–3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C22">Gunderson <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) was sustained after an additional 9–10 years of treatment.Over the 12-year study, the canopy spread upward and there was expansion of the stand diameter distribution as dominant individual trees maintained growth, while suppressed individuals stagnated and began to die. In addition, soil N availability decreased across the site, with the greatest rates of decline in the eCO<sub>2</sub> plots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C19">Garten <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Decreased site nutrient availability was reflected by persistent inter-annual reductions in foliar N content and net primary production (NPP) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C51">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), and a shift in carbon (C) allocation belowground to roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C49">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). The reductions in NPP through time were greatest for eCO<sub>2</sub> plots despite treatment-specific increases or decreases in canopy leaf area in response to inter-annual variability such as drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C72">Warren <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>), or the substantial reduction in eCO<sub>2</sub> site water use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C71">Warren <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C72"><italic>b</italic></xref>). In addition to increased soil moisture availability in eCO<sub>2</sub> plots, the increase in root production should lead to an enhanced capacity for soil nutrient extraction. Yet canopy N content continued to decline through time at a greater rate for eCO<sub>2</sub> plots than for aCO<sub>2</sub> plots, which correlated with a greater reduction in NPP for eCO<sub>2</sub> plots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C51">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).The main goal of this project was to determine if the initial enhancement of photosynthesis by eCO<sub>2</sub> was sustained through time, and if responses were linked to the progressive decline in site resource availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C19">Garten <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), foliar N content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C51">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and shift in internal plant C allocation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C49">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). In 2008–09, we re-measured gas exchange in sweetgum leaves and compared the results with data from previous gas exchange campaigns conducted across seasons from 1998 to 2000 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C22">Gunderson <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>); specifically the mid-summer 1999 dataset was used as it was the most comprehensive dataset and overlapped with the same period sampled in 2008–09 (from late July to early August). We hypothesized that (i) declining N availability would be reflected in reduced photosynthetic capacity through time and (ii) when photosynthesis is N-limited, eCO<sub>2</sub> leaves maintain greater RuBP-regeneration capacity, at lower Rubisco carboxylation rates, compared with aCO<sub>2</sub> leaves (e.g. the slope of <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> : <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> is steeper in aCO<sub>2</sub> leaves). Finally, we evaluated treatment effects on coupling between stomatal conductance and C-assimilation.The study site was a 20-year-old sweetgum (<italic>L. styraciflua</italic> L.) plantation forest in Oak Ridge National Environmental Research Park in eastern TN, USA (35°54′N; 84°20′W). The soil was an Aquic Hapludult with a silty clay-loam texture. A free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C23">Hendrey <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>) was installed at the site in four 25-m-diameter plots in 1996. The FACE system regulated the release of CO<sub>2</sub> from vertical PVC pipes located in a ring around each plot based on wind speed, wind direction and in-situ measurements of current CO<sub>2</sub> concentration within the canopy. From 1998 to 2009, CO<sub>2</sub> was released into two FACE rings during each growing season to a target [CO<sub>2</sub>] of 560 ppm. Two FACE rings received ambient [CO<sub>2</sub>] and one additional ring, without FACE infrastructure, was established to serve as a third control plot. Actual CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment varied through time as ambient concentrations rose incrementally and through modifications in the release regime, which resulted in a mean 40 % increase over ambient CO<sub>2</sub>. In 2008, tree height ranged from 10 to 24 m (mean = 18.2 ± 3.4 m (±1 SD)), median tree diameter was 14.6 ± 4.1 cm (±1 SD) and peak leaf area index (mid-July) was 4.1 ± 0.2. Mean growing season (April–October) temperature was 19.6 °C in 2008 and 19.1 °C in 2009, and growing season precipitation was 440 mm in 2008 and 511 mm in 2009 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C57">Riggs <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The site, experimental design and FACE apparatus have been previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C48">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C72">Warren <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>) and results including micrometeorological data have been archived for public use: <uri xlink:href="http://cdiac.ornl.gov/ftp/FACE/ornldata" xlink:type="simple">http://cdiac.ornl.gov/ftp/FACE/ornldata</uri>.For each measurement campaign (2008–09), branches were collected early in the morning from mid-canopy (2009) and fully exposed upper canopy (2008, 2009) dominant or co-dominant trees within each treatment plot. Canopy access was achieved via the FACE infrastructure towers, which provided access to trees within ∼8 m from the towers. Trees were selected primarily from within the treatment plots (i.e. &gt;2.5 m from the ring edge); however, in ambient plots, several buffer trees were also sampled. On measurement days, 1–2 m long branches were cut from the mid- and upper canopy of selected trees with a pole pruner and quickly placed into plastic bags with wet paper towels to minimize desiccation. Branches were re-cut under water to remove potential embolism induced during removal from the trees. Most <italic>L. styraciflua</italic> vessel length is &lt;0.3 m, therefore &gt;0.5 m of the branch was removed. Prior measurements of gas exchange on severed or attached branches at the site found no differences in measurements over a 2-h period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C68">Tissue <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C45">Monson <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Gas exchange was measured using four portable photosynthesis systems (LI-6400XT, LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA) during late July 2008 and early August 2009. Measurements were conducted outside under ambient conditions on one or two leaves per branch (total samples <italic>n</italic> = 16–23 (2008); <italic>n</italic> = 29–31 (2009)). Conditions in the gas exchange cuvette were set to approximate ambient outside temperature: relative humidity was ∼50–80 %, photosynthetically active radiation was 1800 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration was initially set at 400 ppm prior to the <italic>A</italic><italic>–C</italic><sub>i</sub> curve measurements (see below). Foliage was retained for the analysis of N, chlorophyll and LMA. Similar raw datasets were available from previous work performed at the site in late July–August 1999 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C22">Gunderson <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). At that time, photosynthesis was measured in situ using vertical man lifts. Upper canopy photosynthetic and biochemical datasets were combined across years (1999, 2008, 2009) to investigate shifts in response through time.In addition to measurement of the light-saturated photosynthetic rate (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) at the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in which the trees were growing, response curves of assimilation versus the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration within the intercellular spaces of the leaf (<italic>C</italic><sub>i</sub>), or <italic>A–C</italic><sub>i</sub> curves, were measured in all years. These response curves were used to estimate maximum electron transport rate, <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>, and maximum Rubisco activity, <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub>, using a consistent set of leaf photosynthesis model equations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C43">Medlyn <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). In 2008 and 2009, curves were conducted through an initially declining, then increasing, reference CO<sub>2</sub> regime (400, 300, 200, 100, 50, 400, 550, 700, 900, 1200, 1600 ppm). This contrasts slightly with curves conducted in 1999 using a declining CO<sub>2</sub> regime (1500, 1200, 960, 760, 560, 360, 250, 175, 100, 50, 0 ppm). To contrast gas exchange responses at growth CO<sub>2</sub>, results were assessed at 400 or 550 ppm for aCO<sub>2</sub> or eCO<sub>2</sub>, respectively. Since those CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations were not part of the 1999 campaigns, values at 400 or 550 ppm were interpolated from the linear portion of each response curve (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &gt; 0.99) for comparison. Atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> varied between 1998 and 2008 due to incremental ambient CO<sub>2</sub> increases and FACE performance and management; range (384–405 or 528–560 ppm CO<sub>2</sub>) for aCO<sub>2</sub> or eCO<sub>2</sub>, respectively. Relationships between <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>, <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub>, stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>), foliar N, chlorophyll content and CO<sub>2</sub> treatments were assessed.To assess foliar chlorophyll and N concentrations, and LMA, nine leaf discs (9 mm diameter) were collected from the same area of each leaf (avoiding midrib) used for gas exchange measurements (2008–09). For chlorophyll analysis, two leaf discs were immediately placed in scintillation vials containing 5 mL of <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylformamide (DMF) and extracted at 4 °C in the dark until analysis. Following extraction total chlorophyll, chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> and chlorophyll <italic>b</italic> were determined based on spectroscopy at 647 and 665 nm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C29">Inskeep and Bloom 1985</xref>), and results contrasted with previous chlorophyll analysis in 1999 using an ethanol extraction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). The two extraction solvents have been shown to provide comparable estimates of total chlorophyll in 9 of 11 tree species studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C44">Minocha <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). However, paired comparisons at our lab with sweetgum found that while DMF was able to fully extract chlorophyll within 1 day, 95 % ethanol at room temperature took up to 7 days for full extraction, and even then yielded only 80 % of the total chlorophyll yielded by DMF. Chlorophyll was thus likely underestimated in the earlier studies, and results are discussed in this context. Foliar N concentration was assessed for oven-dry (70 °C) discs using an elemental analyser (Costech Analytical Technologies, Inc., Valencia, CA, USA). In 1999, N content was measured on whole leaves, but not leaf discs, as used in 2008–09. Thus, comparison of N content across years required an LMA adjustment from whole leaf to leaf disc (LMA<sub>disk</sub> = 0.9635(LMA<sub>total</sub>) + 0.7013 (mg cm<sup>−2</sup>); <italic>n</italic> = 28; <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.66; based on 2008 foliage). All N content is provided on a disc basis.Regression slopes and treatment differences in photosynthesis, chlorophyll content, <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> and <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> were analysed using <italic>t</italic>-tests and analysis of variance techniques. There were no significant plot (ring) effects on chlorophyll, N, <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> or <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> measured in 1999 or later years (0.1 &lt; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.9). As such, individual leaves were considered as the (pseudo-replicated) experimental unit (df = 37–60 per treatment per year) as opposed to use of treatment rings (df = 1–2). This is common for analyses of these large, expensive studies where true replication is limited, and results should be considered in this context; i.e. there is a greater chance to detect <italic>spurious</italic> treatment effects (Type I errors) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C28">Hurlbert 1984</xref>). Data manipulation and statistical procedures were completed using SAS statistical software (ver. 9.1.3, SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) and SigmaPlot (ver. 11.1, Systat Software, Inc., San Jose, CA). Relative differences between treatments and significance levels (<italic>P</italic> values) are presented; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 indicates statistical significance.(A) Light-saturated photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>) at growth CO<sub>2</sub> (400 or 550 ppm for ambient (aCO<sub>2</sub>) and elevated (eCO<sub>2</sub>) CO<sub>2</sub> treatments, respectively) for mature upper canopy sweetgum foliage in mid-summer 1999, 2008 and 2009 as derived from <italic>A–C</italic><sub>i</sub> curves. (B) <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> for aCO<sub>2</sub> and eCO<sub>2</sub> foliage at 400 and 550 ppm CO<sub>2</sub>. (C) Foliar N content expressed on a mass (%) or (D) leaf area (mg cm<sup>−2</sup>) basis through time.Tracking the temporal pattern of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>, foliar N concentration declined by ∼50 % from 1999 to 2009 across both treatments, with values as low as 6.9 or 8.5 mg g<sup>−1</sup> for eCO<sub>2</sub> or aCO<sub>2</sub>, respectively, which was not much higher than the seasonal senescent foliar litter (5.8 mg g<sup>−1</sup>). Mass-based foliar N content in eCO<sub>2</sub> leaves was significantly lower than for aCO<sub>2</sub> in 2008 and 2009 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), but not in 1999 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.22) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU074F1">1</xref>C). Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> area-based N content was significantly lower than for aCO<sub>2</sub> in 2008 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), but not in 2009 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.08) or in 1999 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.47) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU074F1">1</xref>D).(A) Total foliar chlorophyll (chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> + <italic>b</italic>) for ambient (aCO<sub>2</sub>—solid line) and elevated (eCO<sub>2</sub>—dashed line) treatments in mid-summer 1999, 2008 and 2009 in relation to foliar N content, expressed on a leaf-area basis. Regressions were significant for <italic>N</italic> &lt; 0.2 mg cm<sup>−2</sup> (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.26 or 0.54; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), and there was a significant treatment effect on slope (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; <italic>F</italic> = 4.09; df = 107), but little trend was apparent in 1999 when <italic>N</italic> &gt; 0.2 (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.02 or 0.08; <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05). (B) Light-saturated photosynthesis at growth CO<sub>2</sub> (400 or 550 ppm) in mid-summer across years (1999, 2008, 2009) in relation to foliar N content, expressed on an area basis.Nitrogen content also had a significant impact on <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub>, particularly at lower values of N. Values of <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> plateaued as N content increased (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU074F2">2</xref>B). The linear regression slope between <italic>A</italic><sub>sat</sub> and N for 1999–2009 was slightly steeper for eCO<sub>2</sub> than for aCO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>P</italic> = 0.055) slopes and coincided at 0.057 mg cm<sup>−2</sup>, which is approximately the N content of senescent tissue (regression not shown).(A) Maximum electron transport rate (<italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>) and (B) carboxylation rate (<italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub>) at 25 °C for ambient (aCO<sub>2</sub>) and elevated (eCO<sub>2</sub>) CO<sub>2</sub> treatments by year or (C) across all years in relation to foliar N content on an area basis (as leaf discs). Linear regressions by treatment were generally significant in 2008 and 2009 (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.14–0.80; <italic>P</italic> = 0.07–0.003) when <italic>N</italic> &lt; 0.2 mg cm<sup>−2</sup>, but not significant in 1999 (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0–0.08; <italic>P</italic> = 0.98–0.1). There were no significant treatment effects on the relationships within or across years (<italic>P</italic> = 0.22–0.75). Regression equations are given for combined data across treatments.Relationships between maximum carboxylation rate (<italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub>) and electron transport rate (<italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>) standardized to 25 °C for ambient (aCO<sub>2</sub>—solid lines) and elevated (eCO<sub>2</sub>—dashed lines) CO<sub>2</sub> treatments through time. Regressions were significant for all treatments and years (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.45–0.77), but there were no treatment effects on the relationships (in 2009, aCO<sub>2</sub> had a slightly steeper slope, <italic>P</italic> = 0.067).Light-saturated photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic>) in relation to stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>) for mature upper canopy foliage exposed to elevated (eCO<sub>2</sub>; dashed line) or ambient (aCO<sub>2</sub>; solid line) CO<sub>2</sub> (400 or 550 ppm, respectively) in mid-summer 2008 and 2009. Dotted regression lines represent results of similar measurements conducted across seasons from 1998 to 2000 based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C22">Gunderson <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref>.Photosynthesis was down-regulated after long-term eCO<sub>2</sub> treatments at the ORNL-FACE research site due to a reduction in foliar N content, a symptom indicative of progressive N limitation as the stand developed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C51">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Net photosynthesis (<italic>A</italic>) and photosynthetic capacity of sweetgum trees declined through time as the stand matured; these responses were correlated with increased nutrient (N, Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup>) sequestration in long-term biomass or soil organic matter and reduced availability and uptake of N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C17">Finzi <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C51">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C32">Iversen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; K. Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, unpubl. data). Consistent with our first hypothesis, we found a significant reduction in overall photosynthetic capacity across treatments as leaf N content declined. However, in contrast to our second hypothesis, the reduction in foliar N was so acute that the benefit of eCO<sub>2</sub> in generating enhanced photosynthetic efficiency was lost. As such, the initial CO<sub>2</sub> stimulation (∼45 % greater) of net photosynthesis observed after 3 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C22">Gunderson <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C61">Sholtis <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) was not sustained after 12 years.There was no relationship between foliar N and <italic>A</italic> in 1999, suggesting that foliar N content of upper canopy leaves (2.0–2.1 %) was in excess of photosynthetic requirements during the early years of the experiment. Total canopy N content in aCO<sub>2</sub> plots declined from ∼1.8 % prior to the experiment in 1996 to 1.6 % by 2004 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C51">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Earlier work in younger 6-year-old sweetgum stands indicated that a leaf N threshold for maximum biomass production was ∼1.9 % (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C59">Scott <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). In March 2004, part of our sweetgum stand was fertilized (200 kg ha<sup>−1</sup> urea), which boosted upper canopy leaf N concentrations from ∼1.65 % (control) to 2.04 % (fertilized) by late July, and substantially increased canopy leaf area and stem growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C31">Iversen and Norby 2008</xref>). The sweetgum trees at the Duke-FACE site indicated no down-regulation of photosynthesis and no change in tissue N content of upper canopy leaves from 1997 to 2004 (N content &gt;1.5 %) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C24">Herrick and Thomas 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C68">Tissue <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C63">Springer <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C14">Ellsworth <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Together, these prior studies support our conclusion that upper canopy photosynthesis at ORNL-FACE was not N limited in 1999, but strongly limited by the end of the experiment when the foliar N content had dropped to 1.03 % (eCO<sub>2</sub>) and 1.16 % (aCO<sub>2</sub>), which was significantly lower for the eCO<sub>2</sub> treatment.There was also no relationship between foliar N and chlorophyll in 1999, suggesting that the chlorophyll content was in excess of photosynthetic requirements during the early years of the experiment. However, the chlorophyll values reported for the site in 1999 appear to be too low, suggesting a poor extraction yield occurred with the ethanol solvent as described earlier in the Methods section: ‘Foliar biochemistry and leaf mass per area’. Chlorophyll values ranged from ∼0.020 to 0.043 mg cm<sup>−2</sup> in 1999, similar to the values in 2008–09 (0.014–0.041 mg cm<sup>−2</sup>), despite much lower N content. Actual chlorophyll levels at the ORNL-FACE site in 1999 were thus likely significantly higher than indicated here. Indeed, chlorophyll extracted from similar aged sweetgum trees at the Duke-FACE site that were not N limited indicated late season values from 0.047 to 0.071 mg cm<sup>−2</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C25">Herrick and Thomas 2001</xref>).The lack of relationship between foliar N content and chlorophyll, <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> or <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> in 1999 suggests that the photosynthetic apparatus in sweetgum was N saturated above ∼0.2 mg cm<sup>−2</sup> and that N had accumulated in excess to meet other N requirements (e.g. growth and storage). A similar pattern of N saturation of <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> has been suggested for pine at the Duke-FACE site, with saturation of the carboxylation rate at tissue contents &gt;1.4 % N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C52">Palmroth <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Nitrogen is most often stored as free amino acids or proteins, especially Rubisco, or as inorganic N within the vacuole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C55">Proe and Millard 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C70">Warren and Adams 2004</xref>). It is likely that reductions in enzyme activation state in eCO<sub>2</sub> foliage can partially uncouple photosynthetic response from foliar N content, as N is shifted into non-active ‘storage’ components. For example, the activation state of Rubisco has been shown to decline linearly with increasing leaf N in apple (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C6">Cheng and Fuchigami 2000</xref>). Given that <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> are often modelled based on N content of the leaf, not on the proportion of N actively used in photosynthesis this may lead to increased uncertainty in estimates of GPP at higher N contents.While the initial foliar N content of the stand was adequate for photosynthesis, N became progressively more limiting, restricting light harvesting, rates of Rubisco and the electron transport chain. N content for several of the measured leaves in 2008–09 dropped to values as low as 0.075 mg cm<sup>−2</sup>, which was not much higher than senescent foliage (0.057 mg cm<sup>−2</sup>). At lower foliar levels of N (0.075–0.2 mg cm<sup>−2</sup>), eCO<sub>2</sub> leaves utilized N more efficiently (greater PNUE) compared with aCO<sub>2</sub> leaves (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU074F2">2</xref>B). For leaves operating at greater PNUE, the theoretical photosynthetic N requirement is lower. In our study, this would entail a lower photosynthetic N threshold in eCO<sub>2</sub> leaves. Our results could not determine this threshold, as <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> became similarly N-restricted below ∼0.2 mg cm<sup>−2</sup>, independent of CO<sub>2</sub> availability.In mature leaves, the optimum N distribution between RuBP carboxylation/regeneration and electron transport may shift as a result of environmental changes (e.g. CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, nutrient availability or thermal acclimation) such that the processes are co-limiting (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C40">Makino <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C41">Medlyn 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C27">Hikosaka 1997</xref>). Theory predicts that the <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> : <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> ratio should increase under eCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C41">Medlyn 1996</xref>), and simulations with pine seedlings suggest that this optimization may vary seasonally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C36">Lewis <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>). We found no evidence of a treatment-dependent shift through time (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU074F4">4</xref>). Similar work at the Duke-FACE site with <italic>P. taeda</italic> also found that there was no change in the slope of <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> : <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> due to eCO<sub>2</sub> treatments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C9">Crous <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Other observations have found that <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> : <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> can increase slightly (∼5 %) with eCO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C42">Medlyn <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C1">Ainsworth and Long 2007</xref>), although this change is generally smaller than predicted by theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C41">Medlyn 1996</xref>).After long-term eCO<sub>2</sub> treatment at the Duke-FACE site, there was a decline in the slope of <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>–N and <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub>–N in pine, indicating eCO<sub>2</sub> down-regulation of overall photosynthetic capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C9">Crous <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). In contrast, at the ORNL-FACE site, there was no treatment effect on the relationships between <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub>–N and <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub>–N in sweetgum. Rather, the declining slope of <italic>J</italic><sub>max</sub> : <italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> through time for all treatments suggests a gradual reallocation of N as plants acclimated to reductions in soil N availability.The decline in photosynthetic capacity and resultant reduction in eCO<sub>2</sub> enhancement of NPP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C51">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), coupled with the demonstrated reduction in N availability for eCO<sub>2</sub> plots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C19">Garten <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), is consistent with the progressive N limitation hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C7">Comins and McMurtrie 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C38">Luo <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). New root production was stimulated in eCO<sub>2</sub> plots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C49">Norby <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) likely as a result of increased internal plant nutrient demand and chemical signalling, including the buildup and translocation of newly fixed sugars. Enhanced root production and exploration at deeper soil depths increased N availability and uptake for eCO<sub>2</sub> trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C18">Finzi <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C32">Iversen <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), but N uptake rates were unable to meet demand and resulted in progressive reductions in photosynthesis. Limitation by other elements could also dampen photosynthetic activity, e.g. Mg, which is the central element in chlorophyll and a key cofactor for Rubisco activation. However, base cation uptake (including Mg and Ca) increased through time in eCO<sub>2</sub> trees based on wood composition (K. Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, unpubl. data), likely as a consequence of the enhanced root exploration. Foliar content of other essential mineral nutrients such as P and K did not decline through time in litter collected from 1998 to 2002, nor in wood tissue collected in 2009.The measurement of gas exchange under fully rehydrated conditions was useful for resolving maximum rates of photosynthesis. Under these hydrated conditions, stomatal conductance remained lower for eCO<sub>2</sub> foliage than for aCO<sub>2</sub> foliage; eCO<sub>2</sub> : aCO<sub>2</sub> <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> ranged from 0.75 to 0.81. Similarly, under dry field conditions, whole canopy conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>c</sub>) based on sap flow remained lower for eCO<sub>2</sub> foliage; eCO<sub>2</sub> : aCO<sub>2</sub> <italic>g</italic><sub>c</sub> was ∼0.7 and declined to ∼0.4 as stomatal aperture declined during extreme drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C72">Warren <italic>et al.</italic> 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). The relationship between <italic>A</italic> and <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> did not change much through time for aCO<sub>2</sub> foliage, but was significantly reduced for eCO<sub>2</sub> foliage (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU074F5">5</xref>). This suggests that the eCO<sub>2</sub> stimulation of photosynthetic WUE declined through time with increasing N limitation. Even so, WUE remained greater for eCO<sub>2</sub> sweetgum trees, and the relationship between stomatal conductance and assimilation was in agreement with predictions of the optimal stomatal model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C80">Medlyn <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), independent of leaf N content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C11">De Kauwe <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). At the Duke-FACE site, partitioning N either to ‘photosynthetically active’ or ‘storage components’ based on the <italic>N</italic>–<italic>V</italic><sub>cmax</sub> threshold allowed for linkage of eCO<sub>2</sub>-stimulated WUE to marginal N-use efficiency within the context of optimality theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C52">Palmroth <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Results from these studies allow predictive capacity of ecosystem level responses to changes in site resources such as CO<sub>2</sub>, water and nutrients.While shorter-term environmental (e.g. solar radiation, T, CO<sub>2</sub> concentration) regulation of photosynthesis has been studied in detail, knowledge of longer-term shifts in the photosynthetic apparatus in response to eCO<sub>2</sub> has been generally limited to observations at the FACE studies and a few long-term open-top chamber studies (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C15">Erickson <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Long-term dynamics of soil water or nutrient availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C17">Finzi <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C52">Palmroth <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and growth sink demands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C53">Paul and Pellny 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C16">Fatichi <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) provide additional regulation of photosynthetic feedback mechanisms and capacity of C uptake in some ecosystems. These processes are not always well represented in global models that depend on scaling mechanistic photosynthetic responses to the land surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C62">Smith and Dukes 2013</xref>). However, it is encouraging that some optimization models do successfully predict biochemical (e.g. reduced foliar N) and mechanistic (e.g. reduced stomatal conductance) process response to eCO<sub>2</sub> and shifts in resource availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C12">Dewar <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Data from the FACE studies, including this one, are being used in a multi-model comparison to assess land surface model structure and variation in predictive capacity, which will result in future model improvement (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C11">De Kauwe <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU074C69">Walker <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).Photosynthesis is the predominant mechanism that removes CO<sub>2</sub> from the atmosphere. Therefore, accurate projections of CO<sub>2</sub> feedbacks to climate forcing rely on the correct mechanistic representation of plant photosynthetic C assimilation capacity. At the ORNL-FACE site, the initial stimulation of carbon assimilation by sweetgum trees exposed to eCO<sub>2</sub> was lost over the 12-year study. The loss of stimulation was due to the declining foliar N content, which has been related to lower soil N availability and uptake. Sweetgum foliar N content below a threshold value (∼0.2 mg N cm<sup>−2</sup> leaf area) restricted carbon assimilation due to photosynthetic biochemical limitations. This study indicates that atmospheric enrichment of CO<sub>2</sub> may result in an initial ‘fertilization’ effect, directly increasing photosynthesis and productivity, but this may later be offset by the declining soil N availability, which could completely eliminate the initial positive effects of eCO<sub>2</sub>. Overall, we suggest caution in extrapolating shorter-term eCO<sub>2</sub> responses to longer-term ecosystem processes, which are confounded by other controlling factors such as soil nutrient availability, water availability or air temperature that can change through time.This article is based upon work supported by the <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">US Department of Energy, Office of Science, Office of Biological and Environmental Research</grant-sponsor>, under contract <grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">DE-AC05-00OR22725</grant-num>.J.M.W. designed and conducted the experiment. A.M.J. performed laboratory work. B.E.M. analysed the data. All authors contributed to the writing and editing of the manuscript.None declared.The authors appreciate fieldwork and facility maintenance from Joanne Childs (arbornaut), Cassandra Bruno, Jeff Riggs and Danny Sluss, and data from Colleen Iversen and Carla Gunderson. This manuscript has been authored by UT-Battelle, LLC under Contract No. DE-AC05-00OR22725 with the US Department of Energy. The United States Government retains and the publisher, by accepting the article for publication, acknowledges that the United States Government retains a non-exclusive, paid-up, irrevocable, world-wide license to publish or reproduce the published form of this manuscript, or allow others to do so, for United States Government purposes. The Department of Energy will provide public access to these results of federally sponsored research in accordance with the DOE Public Access Plan (http://energy.gov/downloads/doe-public-access-plan).