 Wheat production in Bangladesh: its future in the light of global warming  Sowing dates mediated heat stress affects the leaf growth and dry matter partitioning in some spring wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.) cultivars  Development of climate scenarios with general circulation models  Evaluation of seedling praline content of wheat genotypes in relation to heat tolerance  Effect of seeding time and spacing on yield of wheat under irrigated and non irrigated conditions  Stability of different physiological characters, yield and yield components under high temperature stress in tolerant and susceptible wheat genotypes  Effects of zinc deficiency and drought on grain yield of field-grown wheat cultivars in Central Anatolia  Effect of water stress on protein content of some Calvin cycle enzymes in different wheat genotypes  Supply and demand situations for major crops and food items in Bangladesh  Morphological and physiological attributes associated to drought tolerance of Ethiopian durum wheat genotypes under water deficit condition  Multi-location testing as a tool to identify plant response to global climate change  Wheat seed germination under the influence of temperature regimes  Molecular and agro-physiological approaches for parental selection before intercrossing in salt tolerance breeding programs of durum wheat  Impact of temperature on phenology and pollen sterility of wheat varieties  Evaluation of yield, dry matter accumulation and leaf area index in WGs as affected by terminal drought stress  Drought-induced leaf protein alternations in sensitive and tolerant wheat varieties  Identification and functional validation of expressed sequence tags (ESTs) preferentially expressed in response to drought stress in durum wheat  Heat stress in  Triticum : kinetics of Fe and Mn accumulation  Molecular and biochemical studies on some bread WGs in relation to water stress tolerance  Food, fibre and forest products  Evaluation of drought tolerance in bread wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.) using  in vivo  and  in vitro  techniques  Trends of wheat production in the warmer areas: major issues and economic considerations  Yield, protein and starch content of 20 wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.) genotypes exposed to high temperature under late sowing conditions  Damage and management of cyclone  Sidr -affected homestead tree plantations: a case study from Patuakhali, Bangladesh  Identification of cultivable heat tolerant wheat genotypes suitable for Patuakhali district in Bangladesh  Kernel growth physiology of wheat under late planting heat stress  Effect of late planting heat stress on membrane thermostability, proline content and heat susceptibillity index of different wheat cultivars  Evaluating genetic diversity for heat tolerance traits in Mexican wheat landraces  Phenology, growth and yield of three wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.) varieties as affected by high temperature stress  Effect of sowing dates on yield of wheat varieties and lines developed since 1998  Effect of temperature on yield and some agronomic characters of spring wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.) genotypes  Effect of soil and climatic conditions on yield-related components performance of spring wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.) varieties in the northern Bangladesh  Effect of soil and climatic conditions on phenology of spring wheat varieties in the northern Bangladesh  The effect of high temperature stress on the phenology, growth and yield of five wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.) genotypes  High temperature combined with drought affect rainfed spring wheat and barley in South-Eastern Russia: I. Phenology and growth  High temperature combined with drought affect rainfed spring wheat and barley in south-eastern Russia: yield, relative performance and heat susceptibility index  Influence of sowing dates and seed rate on two varieties of wheat  Effect of seeding dates on the yield and maturity of spring wheat  Effect of dates of sowing and rate of fertilizers on yield of wheat under irrigated conditions  Membrane thermostability, grain growth and contribution of pre-anthesis stem reserves to grain weight of wheat under late seeded conditions  Research report-106  Impact of few important climatic parameters on aman rice production in Mymensingh District  Uncertainty in climate carbon-cycle projections associated with the sensitivity of soil respiration to temperature  Variation and inheritance of leaf angle and its relationship with resistance to spot blotch in wheat ( Triticum aestivum )  Leaf tip necrosis: a phenotypic marker associated with resistance to spot blotch disease in wheat  Inheritance of resistance to spot blotch caused by  Bipolaris sorokiniana  in spring wheat  Wheat improvement in India: present status, emerging challenges and future prospects  Stay green trait: variation, inheritance and its association with spot blotch resistance in spring wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.)  Associations of environments in South Asia based on spot blotch disease of wheat caused by  Cochliobolus sativus   Stability analysis of wheat for grain yield affected by different environment  Acid, cold and drought tolerance in cereal  Climate models—projection of future climate  Photosynthetic basis for wheat crop improvement: genetic modification of photosynthesis  Drought tolerance screening of wheat varieties by inducing water stress conditions  Asia  Soil organic matter: Brazilian perspectives  Supporting online materials for: Prioritizing climate change adaptation needs for food security in 2030  Drought stress tolerance of two WGs  Acclimatization of soil respiration to warming in a tall grass prairie  Resistance to rusts in Bangladeshi wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.)  Transient responses of a coupled ocean atmosphere model to gradual changes of atmospheric CO 2 . Part I: annual mean response  Effect of seeding dates on the performance of wheat varieties in Rangpur region  Infection effects of  Septoria  leaf blotch on grain yield and its components of three bread wheat genotypes ( Triticum aestivum  L.)  Mechanistic insight of water stress-induced aggregation in wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.) quality: the protein + paradigm shift  Environment Directorate Development Co-operation Directorate  Sources of inoculum and reappearance of spot blotch of wheat in rice–wheat cropping system in eastern India  Farmers’ preference and informal seed dissemination of first Ug99 tolerant wheat variety in Bangladesh  Physical constraints to cropping in Southern Bangladesh  Growth and yield components of wheat genotypes exposed to high temperature stress under control environment  Performance of wheat genotypes under optimum and late sowing condition  Heat stress environments and impact on wheat productivity in India: guestimate of losses  Building yield in Bangladesh wheat crops: experience from traditional wheat-producing regions  Wheat breeding strategies in the rice farming system of Bangladesh  Yield and yield components parameters of bread wheat genotypes as affected by sowing dates  Modeling temporal and large-scale spatial variability of soil respiration from soil water availability, temperature and vegetation productivity indices  Metabolomics: creating new potentials for unraveling mechanisms in response to salt and drought stress and for biotechnological improvement of xero-halophytes  A critical review on improvement of photosynthetic carbon assimilation in C 3  plants using genetic engineering  Leaf blight diseases and associated soil borne fungal pathogens of wheat in south and south-east Asia  World distribution in relation to economic losses  Spikelets sterility of wheat in farmer's field in northwest Bangladesh  Water logging tolerance  Application of eddy covariance measurements to the temperature dependence of soil organic matter mean residence time  Performance of some modern cultivars of wheat under different dates of planting  Selection of some suitable drought tolerant wheat genotypes using carbon isotopes discrimination (CID) technique  Drought stress effect on photosynthesis rate and leaf gas exchange of wheat  Drought stress effects on water relation of wheat  Accumulated heat unit and phenology of wheat cultivars as influenced by late sowing heat stress condition  Evaluation of heat tolerance of wheat cultivars through physiological approaches  Heat tolerance and relative performance of wheat varieties under late seeded conditions  The wheat rusts  Contribution of pre-anthesis reserves of wheat cultivars differing in membrane thermo-stability under heat stress environment  Grain weight and grain number responsiveness to pre-anthesis temperature in wheat, barley and triticale  Heat tolerance in plants: an overview  Interaction between drought and chronic high temperature during kernel filling in wheat in a controlled environment  Yield performance of spring wheat improved by regulated deficit irrigation in an arid area  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Global warming has already seen a radical change in temperature regimes in Bangladesh. This review provides the first up-to-date perspective and detailed analysis of wheat research in Bangladesh and the impact that global warming will have on its agriculture, especially wheat farming.  The most fundamental activity of the people of Bangladesh is agriculture. Modelling projections for Bangladesh indicate that warmer temperatures linked to climate change will severely reduce the growth of various winter crops (wheat, boro rice, potato and winter vegetables) in the north and central parts. In summer, crops in south-eastern parts of the country are at risk from increased flooding as sea levels increase.  Wheat is one of the most important winter crops and is temperature sensitive and the second most important grain crop after rice. In this review, we provide an up-to-date and detailed account of wheat research of Bangladesh and the impact that global warming may have on agriculture, especially wheat production. Although flooding is not of major importance or consequence to the wheat crop at present, some perspectives are provided on this stress since wheat is flood sensitive and the incidence of flooding is likely to increase.  This information and projections will allow wheat breeders to devise new breeding programmes to attempt to mitigate future global warming. We discuss what this implies for food security in the broader context of South Asia.   Yearly import (1000 MT) and growth rate (%) of wheat from 1971 to 2011 in Bangladesh.  Growth rate (%) was calculated relative to the previous year's value (data source:  Index Mundi 2012 b  ).   Domestic consumption (1000 MT) and growth rate (%) of wheat from 1960 to 2011 in Bangladesh.  Growth rate (%) was calculated relative to the previous year's value (data source:  Index Mundi 2012 b  ).   Yearly production (1000 MT) and growth rate (%) of wheat from 1960 to 2011 in Bangladesh.  Growth rate (%) was calculated relative to the previous year's value (data source:  Index Mundi 2012 b  ).   Area cultivated (1000 ha) and growth rate (%) of wheat from 1960 to 2011 in Bangladesh.  Growth rate (%) was calculated relative to the previous year's value (data source:  Index Mundi 2012 b  ).  Characteristics of existing wheat varieties of Bangladesh developed since 1998 ( BARI 2012 a  ).   Year of release and average yield (tons ha −1 ) of Bangladesh wheat varieties developed since 1974 up until 2012 . Figures in the centre of the bars indicate the year of release, while those above the bars indicate average yield (tons ha −1 ). Bars in white indicate existing Bangladesh wheat varieties (i.e. bred in BARI) (data source:  BARI 2012 a  ).   Beginning stock (▴ 1000 MT) for future security and growth rate (%) of wheat over the last 10 years (2002–2011) in Bangladesh.  Bars indicate years from 2002 to 2011. The percentage values (±) in the bars indicate the growth rate relative to the previous year (data source:  Index Mundi 2012 b  ).  In the initial stages of wheat growing in Bangladesh, several Mexican varieties, especially ‘Sonora 64’ and ‘Kalyansona’, were successfully introduced in collaboration with the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT). However, the release of ‘Sonalika’ in 1972 created a true breakthrough in wheat production. This fast maturing and high-yielding variety (yield = 2 tons ha −1 ) became very popular among wheat growers and adapted well to different production environments, and was adopted in 80 % of the wheat area by the early 1980s ( WRC 2009 ). In 1983, the Wheat Research Centre (WRC), Bangladesh Agricultural Research Institute (BARI), released four more high-yielding (yield = 2–3 tons ha −1 ) varieties (‘Ananda’, ‘Kanchan’, ‘Barkat’ and ‘Akbar’). Among these, ‘Kanchan’ proved particularly adaptable and gradually replaced ‘Sonalika’ to become the predominant variety in Bangladesh by the early 1990s. Two other high-yielding varieties, ‘Aghrani’ and ‘Protiva’, were recommended by the Bangladesh National Seed Board in 1987 and 1993, respectively. These varieties were more responsive to a wider range of weather conditions as well as crop management practices such as fertilizers, irrigation and intercultural operations. Therefore, by the mid-1990s, adoption of high-yielding varieties was almost 100 %, thereby increasing wheat productivity substantially. The year of release and average yield of the new wheat varieties developed in Bangladesh from 1974 to 2012 are presented in Fig.  5 .  However, breeding efforts to develop high-yielding varieties still continued. Several more high-yielding varieties were developed. These included ‘BARI Gom 19’ (‘Sourav’) and ‘BARI Gom 20’ (‘Gourab’) released in 1998; ‘BARI Gom 21’ (‘Shatabdi’) in 2000; ‘BARI Gom 22’ (‘Sufi’), ‘BARI Gom 23’ (‘Bijoy’) and ‘BARI Gom 24’ (‘Prodip’) in 2005 ( Pandit  et al . 2011 ); and ‘BARI Gom 25’ and ‘BARI Gom 26’ released in 2010 ( BARI 2012 b  ). In 2012, two more varieties, ‘BARI Gom 27’ and ‘BARI Gom 28’, were released. Some general characteristics of the existing elite wheat varieties of Bangladesh are presented in Table  1 . Thanks largely to the new varieties, total production increased between 1970 and 2002, but thereafter production decreased as the production area also fell (based on 52 years of data from  Index Mundi (2012 b ) ; Figs  3  and  5 ). The decrease in area was due to competition from other rabi-grown crops such as boro rice, potato and maize ( WRC 2009 ), even though the yield of existing wheat varieties increased through intensive research (Table  1 ; Fig.  5 ).  The CIMMYT has worked closely with the Bangladesh wheat programmes and has played a vital role in popularizing wheat cultivation in Bangladesh from the start. The CIMMYT provided an enormous elite wheat germplasm from which promising types could be selected to suit the Bangladesh environment. Many wheat scientists attended in-service training at CIMMYT on issues such as wheat improvement, production agronomy, wheat quality and station management ( Pandit  et al . 2011 ). Some Bangladesh Agricultural Development Corporation (BADC) personnel were also trained on seed production by CIMMYT. Such training programmes were initiated in 1969 and still continue. The CIMMYT wheat scientists visit research stations and farmers' fields. This collaboration was a key factor in quickly turning Bangladesh into a wheat-growing country. In addition to collaboration with CIMMYT, the Canadian International Development Agency (CIDA), Australian Government Overseas Aid Program (Aus-AID), United States Agency for International Development (USAID) and the Ford Foundation provided grants for facility improvement and manpower development of the WRC, BARI, in Bangladesh ( Pandit  et al . 2011 ).  Global and regional wheat production and consumption statistics in wheat-producing countries ( FAOSTAT 2012 ).  The CIMMYT has recently examined the potential impact of climate change on wheat production. For the purposes of crop technology development, CIMMYT classifies world production in terms of ‘mega-environments’  (Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) 2009) . These are broad, often non-contiguous or even transcontinental areas showing similar crop production conditions. Focusing on South Asia's Indo-Gangetic Plain, which produces ∼90 million tons of wheat grain year −1  (or nearly 15 % of total production worldwide), CIMMYT researchers examined how climate change might affect the current classification of two wheat mega-environments ( CGIAR 2009 ). While both are irrigated, one is favourable for wheat production, while the other is not because of heat stress early and late in the growing season. Under the climatic conditions expected to prevail by 2050, researchers project that the favourable wheat mega-environment will shrink by just over half, mainly because of increased heat stress ( CGIAR 2009 ). This will most probably lead to a major reduction in wheat harvests, threatening the food security of ∼200 million people ( CGIAR 2009 ).  Regarding agriculture and food security overall, crop yields of wheat, maize and rice are predicted to decrease in South Asia by up to 30 % by the end of this century (compared with an increase of up to 20 % in East and South East Asia) ( Anonymous 2012 ). In cereal production alone, the most conservative climate change projections suggest a minimum decline across South Asia of between 4 and 10 %. In Bangladesh, rice production could fall by 8 % and wheat production by 32 % as early as 2050 ( Anonymous 2012 ). Substantial losses in rain-fed wheat are also anticipated. Studies in India suggest that a 0.5 °C rise in winter temperature would reduce wheat yield by 0.45 tons ha −1 . Similarly, a rise in temperature beyond 2.5 °C would reduce non-irrigated wheat and rice farm revenue by 9–25 % ( Anonymous 2012 ).  In response to the predicted problems for wheat production summarized above, researchers in numerous countries are trying to develop heat-tolerant wheat varieties or improve management practices to mitigate the effects of future global warming. Representative research findings related to high temperature, drought stress and their effect on different wheat cultivars in different countries around the world are presented in Table  4 .  General circulation model estimates of temperature and precipitation changes (source:  OECD 2003 ).  Figures in parenthesis indicate standard deviation.  DJE, December, January and February; JJA, June, July and August.  Bangladesh is a deltaic land of ∼144 000 km 2  bordered by the Himalayas to the north and the Bay of Bengal to the south. Its South Asian position extends from 20°45′N to 26°40′N and from 88°05′E to 92°40′E. Fifty per cent of the country's land elevation is within 5 m of sea level. About 68 % of the country is vulnerable to flooding while 20–25 % of the area is inundated during normal flooding. It has a complex coastline of ∼710 km and a long continental shelf with a shallow bathymetry. The Bay of Bengal forms a funnel shape towards the Meghna estuary. Because of this, its storm surge is the highest in the world ( A. S. Islam 2009 ;  C. M. A. Islam 2009 ). Water-stressed wheat, in response to flooding, suffers considerable changes in its metabolic profile, particularly proteins ( Noorka and Teixeira da Silva 2012 ). Flooding can therefore alter the nutritional profile of this crop.  Existing vulnerability to flooding, caused by upstream deforestation, will be aggravated by the effects of climate change. Climate change is anticipated to bring increased sedimentation and an increase in extreme rainfall events, both of which will increase flood risk beyond its current high levels, as witnessed by Cyclone Sidr in 2007, the most devastating cyclone to have struck Bangladesh ( Haq  et al . 2012 ). All coastal areas in Asia are currently facing increasing stress with threats to human and environmental resilience. However, rising sea levels will have a further, major impact on coastal and low-lying communities in South Asia. The most conservative climate change scenarios predict a rise in sea level of 40 cm by the end of this century, which will increase the annual number of people affected by flooding in Asia from 12 million to 94 million, with almost 60 % of these people living in South Asia (including the coastlines of Pakistan, Sri Lanka and Bangladesh). Modelling suggests that 1 million people will be directly affected by a rise in sea level in 2050 in the region of the Bangladesh Ganges–Brahmaputra–Meghna mega-delta. Moreover, Bangladesh's coastal areas will continue to suffer from saline water intrusion, coastal land degradation, storm surges and drainage congestion due to high water flow and sedimentation in the flood plain ( Rahman 2011 ;  Practical Action 2012 ).  Major basic food in the Bangladeshi diet comprises rice, wheat, pulses, potato, vegetables and fish. These foods contribute almost 85 % of the total calorie and protein intake ( Begum and Luc D'Haese 2010 ). Rice and wheat alone contribute 71 and 53 % of the total per capita calorie and protein intake, respectively ( Anonymous 2008 ). It was projected that in the years up to 2021, annual demand for food exceeds supply. The shortfall was −0.28 % for rice and −1.76 % for wheat. This implies that demand is greater than supply for both crops ( Begum and Luc D'Haese 2010 ).  Pressure for increased crop production is generated mostly by rapid population growth. This constitutes a most serious challenge to political and social strategists. Agriculture is also a major employer (44 % of the total workforce) and contributes ∼12 % of Bangladesh's GDP ( IUCN 2012 ). For these reasons, the government has given topmost priority to the agriculture sector. This is directly related to the relief of rural poverty since agriculture benefits the livelihood of rural poor people who account for the majority of the population. The agriculture sector is therefore the primary income contributor and employment generator in Bangladesh ( Planning Commission 2009 ). Between 2000 and 2005, the prevalence of poverty in Bangladesh diminished from 49 % to 40 % (56 million). However, by mid-2008, an additional 8.5 % (i.e. 12 million) were feared to have slid below the poverty line due to rises in food prices in the world market. The prevalence of poverty is now ∼48.5 %, as reported by the CPD ( Centre for Policy Dialogue 2012 ). Bangladesh is one of the most climate-vulnerable countries in the world. Located between the Himalayas and the Bay of Bengal, the country is very prone to natural disasters ( World Bank 2009 ). Climate change accelerates the intensity and frequency of these through increasing salinity, storms, drought, irregular rainfall, high temperature, flash floods, etc., which are presumed to be the results of global warming.  Every crop has an optimal temperature range for vegetative and reproductive growth. When the temperature falls below this range or exceeds the upper limit, then that crop production faces constraints.  Islam  et al . (2008)  found that a 10 °C increase in maximum temperature at vegetative, reproductive and ripening stages caused a decrease in aman rice production by 2.94, 53.06 and 17.28 tons, respectively. With a change in average temperature of 2–4 °C, the prospect of growing wheat and potato would be severely impaired and production loss may exceed 60 % of the achievable yields ( Karim 1993 ). On the other hand, the response of soil organic matter (SOM) decomposition to increasing temperature is a critical aspect of an ecosystem's responses to global change. The temperature sensitivity of soil carbon decomposition is a key factor determining the response of the terrestrial carbon balance to climatic change, as most recently shown in coupled global carbon climate–vegetation model studies (e.g.  Jones  et al . 2003 ). Consequently, the temperature sensitivity of soil respiration and SOM decomposition has received much attention (e.g.  Luo  et al . 2001 ;  Reichstein  et al . 2003 ;  Sandermann  et al . 2003 ;  Leite and Madari 2011 ).  An increase in winter temperature can reduce the environmental suitability for wheat, potato and other temperate crops grown in rabi in the north and central parts of the country ( A. S. Islam 2009 ;  C. M. A. Islam 2009 ).  Braun  et al . (2010)  reported that while accounting for a fifth of human food consumption, wheat is second only to rice as a source of calories in developing countries such as Bangladesh, and is first as a source of protein. With over 35 % of Bangladeshis suffering from malnourishment ( Lal  et al . 2001 ), the threat of increased hunger from a reduction in agricultural production would suggest agriculture as one of the major vulnerabilities facing the country.  Climate change is already thought to be increasing the incidence and intensity of droughts: there were only five devastating droughts in the 100 years from 1800 to 1900, yet, since 1981, four major droughts have occurred in the last 25 years, mostly in north-western Bangladesh ( Selvaraju  et al . 2006 ). The area affected is also expected to grow. For example, the area severely affected by rabi droughts could increase from 4000 to 12 000 km as global warming increases ( Huq 2006 ). Devastating and regular droughts caused by a lack or a late/early arrival of rainfall are common in many parts of Bangladesh. The impact of drought, associated with late or premature monsoon rains or even complete failure of monsoon, spreads over a much larger geographical area than areas affected by other natural hazards. Bangladesh experienced major droughts in 1973, 1978–79, 1981–82, 1989, 1992 and 1994–95. Food grain production lost in the 1978–79 drought was probably 50–100 % more than that lost in the great flood of 1974, directly affecting 42 % of cultivated land. This shows that drought can be as devastating as major floods or cyclones. Rice, jute and other crops were greatly affected, and livestock also suffered from the severe water shortage. More recently, the droughts of 1994–95 in the north-western districts of Bangladesh led to a 3.5-million-ton shortfall of rice and wheat production, while the 1997 drought caused an ∼1-million-ton shortfall of food grain, of which ∼0.6 million tons was transplanted with aman rice valued at around US$500 million ( Selvaraju  et al . 2006 ).  Bangladesh ranks sixth among the countries in the world most vulnerable to floods. Owing to its topography and position, the country is experiencing flooding in 30–50 % of the area and almost every year. These extreme weather events cause heavy losses to agricultural production, particularly to broad acre crops. Flooding has become severe in the past 4–5 years with severe flooding inundating roughly 60 % of the country. The effect was especially severe on crop agriculture and thus on the livelihood of most Bangladeshi people ( Rahman 2011 ). The reductions in yields of staple crops such as rice and wheat caused by flooding are anticipated to be very great. By 2050, rice yield could drop by 8 % and wheat yields by 32 % ( Practical Action 2012 ). Beyond these values and predictions, there are no further statistics to help manage wheat cropping under flooded conditions. Furthermore, no flooding-tolerant varieties have yet been developed by Bangladeshi scientists, although a start has been made recently. Less attention is given to the effect of flooding on wheat compared with rice since wheat is cultivated mostly in the highlands in the north.  Recent studies related to heat, drought and low-temperature stress in different countries around the world (chronological order).  Research findings related to the effect of temperature on wheat ( T. aestivum  L.) of Bangladesh studied by different scientists.  Research related to membrane thermostability, heat susceptibility, relative performance and stress stability study to identify heat-tolerant cultivars.  Problems of salinity and water logging, heavy erosion of soils and riverbanks all accelerate soil degradation. Estimates of areas affected by nutrient depletion and other forms of soil degradation are ∼5.6 million ha in Bangladesh with ∼0.83 million ha of land being affected by various degrees of salinity. With climate change, saline water may extend to currently non-saline land, ultimately affecting (negatively) crop production ( Rahman 2011 ). The Bangladeshi Ministry of Agriculture has also initiated a number of agricultural programmes, such as the development and distribution of drought- and saline-resistant crop varieties to enhance year-round production. Several projects are focused on improving the infrastructural facilities for varietal development to combat these impacts of climate change. For example, the Wheat Research Centre in Bangladesh has so far released 28 wheat varieties. Of these, BARI Gom 23 (‘Bijoy’) and BARI Gom 24 (‘Prodip’) released in 2005, BARI Gom 25 and BARI Gom 26 released in 2010, and BARI Gom 27 and BARI Gom 28 released in 2012 are recommended for commercial cultivation (Fig.  5 ). All these varieties are high yielding and heat tolerant, resistant to leaf rust and tolerant of bipolaris leaf blight. Of these varieties, BARI Gom 25 tolerates a moderate level of salinity while BARI Gom 26 and BARI Gom 27 are moderately resistant to the Ug99 race of stem rust. Moreover, BARI Gom 28 matures very early and is highly tolerant of terminal heat stress ( BARI 2012 b  ). The major stress faced by wheat in South Asia is high temperature, mainly terminal heat stress ( Joshi  et al . 2007 a  ), which was defined by  Fischer and Byerlee (1991) , due to mean daily temperature above 17.5 °C in the coolest month. Both the proximity to the equator and popular cropping systems, which involve the late sowing of wheat, are the major causes of exposure of wheat in Bangladesh and other neighbouring countries to high temperatures during grain filling ( Rane  et al . 2000 ). Therefore, breeding for high-temperature tolerance in wheat is another major objective of wheat improvement programmes in South Asian countries, including Bangladesh, India and Nepal. Besides the development of varieties and production initiatives, CIMMYT and WRC will strengthen their breeder seed production capacity in the next 5 years to meet the increased demand of climate-vulnerable areas.  The two major characteristics of the eastern part of South Asia are high temperatures and humidity ( Joshi  et al . 2007 c  ). This leads to two important stresses: heat, and spot blotch disease caused by  Bipolaris sorokiniana  (Sacc.) shoem syn.  Drechslera sorokiniana  (Sacc.) Subrm and Jain (syn.  Helminthosporium sativum , teleomorph  Cochliobolus sativus ) ( Joshi  et al . 2004 a  ,   b  ;  Pandey  et al . 2005 ;  Malaker and Reza 2011 ).  Septoria  leaf blotch can also severely damage yield ( Mbarek and Teixeira da Silva 2011 ).  Saari (1998)  reported that the average yield losses due to leaf blight in the Indian subcontinent were as much as 17.5 %. It is generally believed that the level of resistance in high-yielding wheat genotypes is still unsatisfactory and needs to be improved significantly in warmer humid regions of South Asia ( Joshi  et al . 2007 a  ,   b  ,   c  ). Consequently, an integrated approach, with host resistance as a major component, is generally considered best for controlling the disease ( Joshi and Chand 2002 ). In this context, CIMMYT is working with different research institutes in South Asia to develop cultivars that are suitable for these regions.  In Bangladesh, mean temperature in winter (rabi) has risen by 0.66 °C since 1990 and a further warming of 2.13 °C by 2050 is predicted ( Poulton and Rawson 2011 ). A rise in temperature can be expected to increase the severity of  Bipolaris  leaf blight and other wheat diseases in the future because a warm and humid climate favours the development and spread of the pathogen. Changes in the virulence pattern of this pathogen rendering increased susceptibility of wheat varieties are also not unlikely. Increasing temperature might also favour the development and adaptation of wheat stem rust, which can tolerate higher temperatures than other rusts. Although it has not been critically investigated or ascertained, a global rise in temperature could promote mutation and the development of new virulent races of rust pathogens.  Postulated rust resistance genes in the released wheat varieties of Bangladesh (source:  Malaker and Reza 2011) .  R, resistant; APR, adult plant resistance.   a Resistant to all Indian pathotypes of stem rust.   b Genes were not postulated.   c Leaf tip necrosis gene  Lr34 .   d Rust resistance genes present in these two varieties have not yet been identified (may have been detected in the source countries, but we do not have the information); presence of  Sr2  (adult plant slow rusting stem rust resistance gene) in BARI Gom 27 is to be confirmed.  The danger posed by the Ug99 strain of stem rust to global wheat production is widely recognized, including in Bangladesh. The release, in 2010, of the first Ug99-resistant wheat variety (BARI Gom 26—previously known as BAW, and popularly called Hashi) was a major step to countering the threat of this disease in Bangladesh. Subsequently, the variety Francolin (also known as BARI Gom 27 or BAW 1120) was released in March 2012. Originating from CIMMYT-Mexico, Francolin possesses good resistance to all variants of Ug99 along with impressive agronomic performance, yielding ∼10 % more than the most popular variety Shatabdi in 3 years of multi-location testing in Bangladesh ( CIMMYT 2012 ).  About 80 % of people in Bangladesh depend directly on agriculture for their food and livelihood, with wheat being the second most important crop after rice. However, climate change leading to global warming has already produced a radical change in temperature regimes in Bangladesh. This will impact strongly on wheat production. The present review provides the first up-to-date perspective and detailed analysis of wheat research in Bangladesh, and the impact that global warming will have on its agriculture, especially wheat farming. This will allow wheat breeders to plan to mitigate the effects of further global warming. This will have direct implications for food security in Bangladesh as well as South Asia. The development of stress-tolerant wheat within the wider context of a breeding programme, particularly with respect to drought and flooding, needs to be supported by  in vitro  protocols ( Farshadfar  et al . 2012 ) as well as molecular techniques ( Chaabane  et al . 2012 ;  Diab  et al . 2012 ), while genetic modification of crops to increase photosynthesis or metabolomics needs greater focus in wheat improvement programmes ( Kershanskaya and Teixeira da Silva 2010 ;  Ruan and Teixeira da Silva 2011 ;  Ruan  et al . 2012 ).  Both authors have contributed equally to this manuscript.  None declared.  We thank all the employees of the Wheat Research Center, Bangladesh, especially Dr. P. K. Malaker, Chief Scientific Officer, and Dr M. A. Z. Sarker, Principal Scientific Officer, for their encouragement, suggestions and information, which have allowed us to include more precise information within this review. 