Differences in responses to flooding by germinating seeds of two contrasting rice cultivars and two species of economically important grass weedsQTLs associated with tolerance of anaerobic conditions during germination in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye bindingCan knowledge in seed ecology contribute to improved weed management in direct-seeded rice?Ecological studies on <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> and the implications for weed management in direct-seeded riceCompensatory growth of <italic>ludwigia</italic> (<italic>Ludwigia hyssopifolia</italic>) in response to interference of direct-seeded ricePhysiological mechanisms in flooding tolerance of rice: transient complete submergence and prolonged standing waterStrategies of gene action in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> during hypoxiaThe assimilation and degradation of carbohydrates by yeast and cellsIdentification and gene expression of anaerobically induced enolase in <italic>Echinochloa phyllopogon</italic> and <italic>Echinochloa crus-pavonis</italic>Morphological and physiological responses of lowland purple nutsedge (<italic>Cyperus rotundus</italic> L.) to floodingGenetic and biochemical analysis of anaerobically induced enzymes during seed germination of <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> varieties tolerant and intolerant of anoxiaEffect of anoxia on carbohydrate metabolism in rice seedlings<italic>Echinochloa</italic> competition in rice: a comparison of studies from direct-seeded and transplanted flooded rice<italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> (L.) BeauvMechanisms associated with tolerance to flooding during germination and early seedling growth in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>)Adaptation to flooding during emergence and seedling growth in rice and weeds, and implications for crop establishmentAnoxia tolerance and α-amylase activity in four rice cultivarsGermination and seedling growth under anaerobic conditions in <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> (barnyard grass)Germination and seedling development of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) and <italic>echinochloa</italic>Modeling-dependent protein characterization of the rice aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH) superfamily reveals distinct functional and structural featuresColorimetric methods with glucose oxidase and peroxidaseCleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4Rice germination and seedling growth in the absence of oxygenInvolvement of aldehyde dehydrogenase in alleviation of post-anoxic injury in riceTolerance of anaerobic conditions caused by flooding during germination and early growth in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)Constitutive and inducible aerobic and anaerobic stress proteins in the <italic>Echinochloa</italic> complex and riceEnzymic mechanism of starch breakdown in germinating rice seeds. I. An analytical studyExpression of a gene encoding mitochondrial aldehyde dehydrogenase in rice increases under submerged conditionsEnzymic mechanism of starch breakdown in germinating rice seeds. I. Scutellum as the site of sucrose synthesisComparison of growth responses of barnyard grass <italic>(Echinochloa oryzoides)</italic> and rice <italic>(Oryza sativa)</italic> to submergence, ethylene, carbon dioxide and oxygen shortageThe effects of oxygen, carbon dioxide and ethylene on ethylene biosynthesis in relation to shoot extension in seedlings of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) and barnyard grass (<italic>Echinochloa oryzoides</italic>)Adaptation to flooding in upland and lowland ecotypes of <italic>Cyperus rotundus</italic>, a troublesome sedge weed of rice: tuber morphology and carbohydrate metabolismAnaerobic carbohydrate metabolism in wheat and barley, two anoxia-intolerant cereal seedsMobilization of endosperm reserves in cereal seeds under anoxiaEnhancement of submergence tolerance in transgenic rice overproducing pyruvate decarboxylaseWeed management in direct-seeded riceAnaerobic metabolism in germinating seeds of <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> (barnyard grass): metabolite and enzyme studiesAnaerobiosis in <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> (barnyardgrass) seedlings: intermediary metabolism and ethanol toleranceActivity of the pentose phosphate and glycolytic pathways during anaerobic germination of <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> (barnyardgrass) seedsProteomic identification of differentially expressed proteins in the anoxic rice coleoptileAlcohol dehydrogenase in maize: genetic basis for multiple isozymesOrgan-specific expression and chromosomal locations of two mitochondrial aldehyde dehydrogenase genes from rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) <italic>ALDH2a</italic> and <italic>ALDH2b</italic>Induction of mitochondrial aldehyde dehydrogenase by submergence facilitates oxidation of acetaldehyde during re-aeration in riceThe importance of ethanol fermentation to anoxia tolerance during submergence in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>)Germination and seedling growth in <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> var <italic>oryzicola</italic> under anoxic conditions: structural aspectsFunctional electron microscopy in studies of plant response and adaptation to anaerobic stressRegulation of respiration and fermentation to control the plant internal oxygen concentrationEffect of aerobic priming on the response of <italic>Echinochloa crus-pavonis</italic> to anaerobic stress<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Michael B. JacksonThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Barnyard grasses are serious weeds in direct seeded rice. We assessed the effectiveness of using controlled flooding for its control using two rice cultivars and two barnyard grasses contrasting in flood tolerance during germination. Flooding with 100 mm water after seeding suppressed barnyard grasses; but delaying flooding by 2-4 days was ineffective. Flooding increased the activity of alcohol dehydrogenase and pyruvate decarboxylase; the increase was higher in the tolerant rice cultivar but similar in both barnyard grasses. Aldehyde dehydrogenase activity increased only in flood-tolerant types of rice and weeds, but not in flood-sensitive types<italic>,</italic> implying potential role in tolerance.Crop productivity is largely affected by abiotic factors such as flooding and by biotic factors such as weeds. Although flooding after direct seeding of rice helps suppress weeds, it also can adversely affects germination and growth of rice, resulting in poor crop establishment. Barnyard grasses (<italic>Echinochloa</italic> spp.) are among the most widespread weeds affecting rice, especially under direct seeding. The present work aimed to establish effective management options to control these weeds. We assessed the effects of variable depths and time of submergence on germination, seedling growth and carbohydrate metabolism of (i) two cultivars of rice known to differ in their tolerance to flooding during germination and (ii) two barnyard grasses (<italic>Echinochloa colona</italic> and <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>) that commonly infest rice fields. Flooding barnyard grasses with 100-mm-deep water immediately after seeding was effective in suppressing germination and growth. <italic>Echinochloa colona</italic> showed greater reductions in emergence, shoot and root growth than <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>. Delaying flooding for 2 or 4 days was less injurious to both species. <italic>Echinochloa colona</italic> was also more susceptible to flooding than the flood-sensitive rice cultivar ‘IR42’. The activity of alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) and pyruvate decarboxylase (PDC) in rice seedlings was increased by flooding after sowing but with greater increases in ‘Khao Hlan On’ compared with ‘IR42’. The activity of ADH and PDC was enhanced to a similar extent in both barnyard grasses. Under aerobic conditions, the activity of ADH and PDC in the two barnyard grasses was downregulated, which might contribute to their inherently faster growth compared with rice. Aldehyde dehydrogenase activity was significantly enhanced in flood-tolerant ‘Khao Hlan On’ and <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, but did not increase in flood-sensitive <italic>E. colona</italic> and ‘IR42’, implying a greater ability of the flood-tolerant types to detoxify acetaldehyde generated during anaerobic fermentation. Confirmation of this hypothesis is now being sought.Abiotic stresses such as flooding and biotic factors such as weed infestation cause considerable reductions in crop productivity worldwide. Flooding the soil during crop establishment can help control most weeds and reduce production cost. But this is practical only if the crop can tolerate flooding during germination and early growth. The present paper examines the physiological aspects of this approach for controlling weeds in the rice crop. In response to water and labour shortages and for other benefits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C16">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) Asia's rice farmers are progressively shifting from transplanting to direct seeding. However, weed competition in direct-seeded fields can be intense since both weeds and rice germinate together. Consequently, yield losses due to weed competition have been reported to be 3-fold greater in direct-seeded rice than in transplanted rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C13">Hill <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>).In direct-seeded rice, controlled flooding of the field is usually delayed until rice seedlings have emerged. Unfortunately, this also brings about the simultaneous emergence of certain grass weeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C36">Rao <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). It is therefore highly desirable to develop rice lines with greater tolerance to early flooding compared with the weeds. This would allow farmers to flood earlier, thereby selectively suppressing early weed growth while permitting rice seedlings to become established. Such an approach would also reduce the risk of crop losses from uncontrolled flooding events and, in some cases, poor land levelling. Previous studies have shown that rice cultivars have varied responses to flooding during germination and that certain genotypes are more tolerant of the hypoxic soil of flooded fields (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C12">Guglielminetti <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C1">Angaji <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Some of the most important and widespread weeds cohabiting with rice are <italic>Echinochloa</italic> spp. (barnyard grass). Various studies showed that species such as <italic>Echinochloa oryzoides, E. phyllopogon</italic>, <italic>E. crus-pavonis</italic> and <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> can germinate and grow in oxygen-deficient conditions that characterize flooded soils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C30">Pearce and Jackson 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C31">Pearce <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C49">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C9">Fox <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C11">Fukao <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C4">Chauhan and Johnson 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C16">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). This ability makes weed control by imposing early flooding less effective. Moreover, some echinochloa species such as <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> are more tolerant of flooding than others such as <italic>E. colona</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C14">Holm <italic>et al.</italic> 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C26">Mujer <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>).Germinating rice seeds perform various growth and metabolic processes that enhance their chances of surviving oxygen deficiency. These include shifting from aerobic to anaerobic respiration. This generates less energy but the amount remains sufficient to sustain growth by the shoot of the germinating embryo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C38">Rumpho and Kennedy 1983<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C12">Guglielminetti <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C25">Miro and Ismail 2013</xref>). This implies that seeds germinating under water are able to degrade starch into soluble sugar substrates used for anaerobic respiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C18">Kennedy <italic>et al.</italic> 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C33">Perata <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C16">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Key enzymes in anaerobic fermentation are pyruvate decarboxylase (PDC; E.C. 4.1.1.1), alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH; E.C. 1.1.1.1) and aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH, E.C. 1.2.3.1). Increases in activities of these enzymes have been linked to higher energy production, which allows faster coleoptile elongation and seedling survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C28">Nakazono <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C42">Stryer <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C44">Tsuji <italic>et al.</italic> 2003<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C24">Meguro <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>).Understanding the growth responses to flooding in rice and weed species at early growth stages may help formulate water management strategies that exploit differential effects of flooding on rice and barnyard grasses to selectively suppress weed growth without affecting rice crop establishment. Furthermore, a better understanding of biochemical processes associated with differential sensitivity to flooding may assist in developing rice cultivars with greater tolerance of submergence during germination and early growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C16">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). This would improve weed control and reduce the risk of poor crop establishment caused by uncontrolled floods early in the season. To date, most studies have been made of the adaptive features and responses to flooding by rice and rice weeds individually but less information is available on their comparative responses. Some earlier studies have reported contrasting responses in rice and <italic>E. oryzoides</italic> to poorly aerated conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C30">Pearce and Jackson 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C31">Pearce <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>), where shoot elongation was enhanced in germinating rice but slowed in <italic>E. oryzicola</italic>.This study aims to assess differential growth and metabolic responses in rice and barnyard grass to help develop effective management practices to control the weeds in favour of rice. We evaluated two contrasting rice cultivars and two ‘barnyard grasses’. The rice cultivar ‘IR42’ is normally high yielding but sensitive to flooding at all growth stages, while ‘Khao Hlan On’ is a traditional rice landrace with high tolerance to flooding during germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C1">Angaji <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C16">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). <italic>Echinochloa crus-galli</italic> and <italic>E. colona</italic> are two of the most economically important grass weeds of rice with the former known to be the more tolerant of flooding in the field. We evaluated and compared germination and seedling growth and development under different flooding depths and timings in both rice and barnyard grass to assist with the development of an optimal weed management strategy through managing the timing and depth of flooding. We also evaluated changes in fermentative metabolism to help understand the response mechanisms for flooding during germination of the four genotypes.Seeds (caryopses) of rice cultivars ‘Khao Hlan On’ and ‘IR42’ were from the International Rice Research Institute, Philippines. Seeds of <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and <italic>E. colona</italic> were collected from rice fields in Laguna Province, Philippines and multiplied from single panicles to provide common stocks. To break dormancy before sowing, seeds were incubated at 45–50 °C for up to 5 days for rice and for 5 h for barnyard grasses.Experimental details including location, water depth, start of flooding, flooding duration, sampling time and the traits recorded in each experiment. Experiments were conducted across the years between 2007 and 2013.% GerminationShoot and root length% GerminationShoot and root lengthCarbohydrate assaysEnzyme activities% GerminationShoot and root lengthPercent germination was calculated as the ratio of germinated seeds per genotype and the number of total seeds sown. Germinated seeds were those with emerging radicle or coleoptile visible to the naked eye. Shoot and root length were measured on a glass plate (50 × 30 cm) mounted on crushed ice. Shoots included all aerial parts and roots included all below-ground material excluding seeds. At 10 DAS or less, only the coleoptile was visible in submerged seedlings. At 14 DAS and thereafter, all seedlings showed about one to three true leaves and various degrees of root development. Length measurements were recorded on the longest leaf and the longest root.Germinating seeds were carefully washed; seeds were then detached from the seedlings, frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80 °C until freeze-dried and kept in a desiccator at room temperature for analysis. Dry seeds (not sown) were also analysed at Day 0 for both aerobic and flooded treatments.Soluble sugar concentration was determined using the anthrone method as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C8">Fales (1951)</xref>. Soluble sugars were extracted twice from 100 mg of freeze-dried tissue powder in 80 % v/v ethanol. Sugar concentration in each extract was determined colorimetrically at 620 nm using a Beckman Coulter DU 800 spectrophotometer (Brea, USA). Glucose was used as a calibration standard.Starch concentration was determined as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C21">Kunst <italic>et al.</italic> (1988)</xref>. Starch in the residue from the soluble sugar extraction was dried at 70 °C for 24 h, gelled with acetate buffer, boiled and then converted to glucose with amyloglucosidase by incubating at 37 °C for 24 h. The resulting free glucose was measured with glucose oxidase by mixing the sample with peroxidase–glucose oxidase enzyme and <italic>o</italic>-dianisidine dihydrochloride solution. Absorbance was measured at 450 nm.Seedlings were sampled every day until 10 DAS, immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80 °C until assayed. Dry seeds (ungerminated) were used at Day 0 in both control and flooded treatments.About 500 mg of seeds or seedlings were ground to powder in liquid nitrogen and added to cold buffer composed of 100 mM HEPES, pH 7.4, 1 mM EDTA, 5 mM DTT, 0.1 % v/v, Triton X-100 and 10 % glycerol. The homogenate was centrifuged at 12 000 <italic>g</italic> at 4 °C for 20 min. Protein concentration was determined using Bradford reagent (Sigma B 6916) with bovine serum albumin as the standard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C2">Bradford 1976</xref>).Total ADH activity was assayed as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>. Diluted crude extract (100 µL) was added to a reaction mixture of 51.8 mM N-[Tris(hydroxymethyl)methyl]-2-aminoethanesulfonic acid (TES), pH 7.0 and 0.17 mM NADH. Acetaldehyde (20 mM) was added to start the reaction towards ethanol synthesis and ADH activity was monitored by oxidation of NADH. Samples were read at 340 nm under ambient conditions (25 °C) for 180 s.Total PDC activity was analysed using the procedures described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C35">Quimio <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref>. Crude extract was added to a mixture containing 1 % bovine serum albumin, 41.67 mM 2-(N-Morpholino)ethanesulfonic acid (MES) and 0.5 mM thiamine pyrophosphate (TPP) and then centrifuged at 10 000 <italic>g</italic> at 4 °C for 3 min. TES buffer pH 8.0 was added to the supernatant to a final concentration of 446 mM and incubated at 25 °C for 1 h. For the activity assay, the resulting solution (100 µL) was added to a reaction mixture containing 62.5 mM MES, 0.5 mM TPP, 50 mM oxamate, 10 U ADH and 0.17 mM NADH. Sodium pyruvate (10 mM) was added to initiate the reaction, wherein acetaldehyde produced through the action of PDC was concomitantly reduced by ADH. Simultaneous oxidation of NADH was used to monitor PDC activity. Total volume for each of the reaction mixtures was 1000 µL. Samples were spectrophotometrically read at 340 nm under ambient conditions.Aldehyde dehydrogenase activity was assayed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C11">Fukao <italic>et al.</italic> (2003)</xref>. Crude protein extract (100 µL) was added to a reaction mixture containing 100 mM sodium pyrophosphate (pH 9.5) and 1.5 mM NAD<sup>+</sup>. Acetaldehyde (0.34 mM) was added to start the reaction towards its oxidation and the accompanying reduction of NAD<sup>+</sup> was used to monitor the activity of ALDH. Total volume of the reaction mixture was 1000 µL. Samples were read at 340 nm under ambient conditions.Thirty micrograms of total protein was loaded per sample in 8 % sodium dodecyl sulphate–polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and subjected to electrophoresis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C22">Laemmli 1970</xref>) prior to in-gel detection. The antibody (courtesy of Dr M. Nakazono) was a rabbit monoclonal antibody against ALDH2 synthesized from <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> peptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C28">Nakazono <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>), detecting both ALDH2a and ALDH2b. The signal was developed by chemiluminescence following manufacturer's instructions (Novex ECL HRP kit, Invitrogen, USA).Experiments in the greenhouse were replicated four times, while those in the incubator were replicated three times. Treatments in all studies were arranged in a randomized split-plot design with flooding depth as the main plot and timing of flooding as the subplot. Analyses of variance were performed using CropStat for Windows (Version 6.1, 2007) and treatment means were compared using LSD (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Three flooding regimes were used to assess differential responses of rice and barnyard grass during germination under submergence, as well as to evaluate the effectiveness of flooding as a weed control measure under different direct-seeding scenarios. The first two experiments compared different water depths. The first experiment imposed shallow flooding (5, 10 or 20 mm deep) applied at 0, 2 and 4 DAS. The second involved deeper flooding (100 mm) applied at seeding. The third experiment investigated the effect of late flooding (starting 3 DAS) compared with the early flooding (starting 0 DAS).Percent germination of <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, <italic>E. colona</italic>, ‘Khao Hlan On’ and ‘IR42’ submerged in 0, 5, 10 and 20 mm of water immediately after seeding. Vertical bars indicate l.s.d. at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Comparative lengths of the shoots (mm) of <italic>E. colona</italic>, <italic>E. crus</italic>-galli, ‘Khao Hlan On’ and ‘IR42’ at different flooding depths and timing. Seeds were sown in soil and flooded to depths of 5, 10 and 20 mm. Controls were sown under aerobic conditions (0 mm). Flooding was started at 0, 2 or 4 DAS and finished 7, 14 or 21 DAS. Bold numbers with (*) indicate values are significantly different from the control at LSD<sub>0.05</sub>.Comparative lengths of roots (mm) of <italic>E. colona</italic>, <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and rice cultivars ‘Khao Hlan On’ and ‘IR42’ at different flooding depths and timing. Seeds were sown in soil and flooded to depths of 5, 10 and 20 mm. Controls were sown under aerobic conditions (0 mm). Flooding was started 0, 2 or 4 DAS and terminated 7, 14 or 21 DAS. Bold numbers with (*) indicate values are significantly different from the control at LSD<sub>0.05</sub>.Percent germination of <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, <italic>E. colona</italic>, ‘Khao Hlan On’ and ‘IR42’ submerged in 0 and 100 mm of water immediately after seeding. Vertical bars indicate l.s.d. at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Shoot length (A) and root length (B) of <italic>E. colona</italic>, <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, ‘IR42’ and ‘Khao Hlan On’ germinated under 100 mm of water. Controls were kept aerobic (0 mm flooding). Data were taken at 7 DAS and vertical bars indicate l.s.d. at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Shoot length (A) and root length (B) of <italic>E. colona</italic>, <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, ‘IR42’ and ‘Khao Hlan On’ germinated under aerobic conditions for 3 days followed by flooding under 100 mm of water. Controls were kept aerobic (0 mm flooding). Data were taken at 7 DAS and vertical bars indicate l.s.d. at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Starch concentration (% DW) of (A) ‘Khao Hlan On’ and ‘IR42’ and (B) <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and <italic>E. colona</italic> from 0 to 14 days after sowing under aerobic and submerged (100 mm) conditions. Vertical bars indicate l.s.d. at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Soluble sugar concentration (% DW) of (A) ‘Khao Hlan On’ and ‘R42’ and (B) <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and <italic>E. colona</italic> from 0 to 14 days after sowing under aerobic (0 mm) and flooded (100 mm) conditions. Vertical bars indicate l.s.d. at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Activities of PDC (A), ADH (B) and ALDH (C) enzymes during germination under aerobic (0 mm) and flooded (100 mm) conditions. The graphs on the left represent activities in ‘Khao Hlan On’ and ‘IR42’ and the graphs on the right represent <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and <italic>E. colona</italic>. Vertical bars indicate l.s.d. at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Activities of ADH followed more or less similar patterns to PDC under both aerobic and flooded conditions in both species (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F7">7</xref>B). Under flooded conditions, ADH activity in ‘Khao Hlan On’ increased at a much higher rate, rising from 1 to 30 U mg<sup>−1</sup> total protein, which is ∼3-fold higher than that of the sensitive ‘IR42’. Barnyard grass germinated in aerobic soil had low ADH activities (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F7">7</xref>B). The activity slightly increased during the first 2 DAS, then decreased to close to 0 from 3 to 10 DAS. When flooded with 100 mm of water, ADH activity increased gradually but similarly slowly in the two barnyard grasses.Activity of ALDH slowly increased; from close to 0 to 0.2 U mg<sup>−1</sup> total protein in rice germinated in aerobic conditions for the 10-day period following sowing (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F7">7</xref>C). However, the enzyme activity did not follow the same trend as PDC and ADH when rice was flooded with 100 mm of water. Activity of ALDH in ‘Khao Hlan On’ increased faster and reached a peak at ∼6 DAS (0.8 U mg<sup>−1</sup> total protein); then declined progressively until 10 DAS, while that of ‘IR42’ remained similar to that under aerobic conditions. The trend was similar in barnyard grass; ALDH remaining steady at ∼0.05 U mg<sup>−1</sup> total protein both under aerobic conditions and also in the sensitive <italic>E. colona</italic> when flooded. However, ALDH activity in <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> increased significantly under flooding, though the increase was less marked than in ‘Khao Hlan On’. Clearly, ALDH activities increased substantially only in the tolerant genotypes of rice (Khao Hlan On) and barnyard grass (<italic>E. crus-galli</italic>) by about 3- to 4-fold compared with that of the sensitive genotypes ‘IR42’ and <italic>E. colona</italic> under aerobic conditions, with no changes in the sensitive genotypes when flooded. The induction of ALDH under flooded conditions was greater in the tolerant rice genotype than in the tolerant <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>.Immunoblot raised against ALDH2 in (A) ‘Khao Hlan On’ and 'IR42′ and (B) <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and <italic>E. colona</italic>. Samples were sown in the soil flooded with 100 mm of water and harvested daily for 9 days for rice and 8 days for weeds. Black arrows indicate the bands detected in each genotype for ALDH2 proteins. (C) Immunoblot raised against ALDH2 in ‘Khao Hlan On’ (left) and ‘IR42’ (right).One of the major constraints of direct-seeded rice is that both the crop and weeds emerge together. However, controlled flooding can be effectively used for weed management by exploiting differential responses in growth and metabolic responses of rice and weeds to flooding. In flooded soils, low oxygen causes germinating seeds to shift from aerobic respiration to the less efficient but more robust anaerobic fermentation and promote a series of biochemical activities to counter the effect of hypoxic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C37">Rumpho and Kennedy 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C38">1983<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C39"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C47">Vartapetian <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C23">Magneschi and Perata 2009</xref>). Once shoots have emerged above the floodwater, the leaves can switch to aerobic respiration.Past studies on the tolerance of flooding of the two contrasting rice and barnyard grass genotypes brought new knowledge concerning the efficiency of different flooding regimes to suppress weed growth without affecting rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C4">Chauhan and Johnson 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C16">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). However, identifying rice varieties capable of germination under water is essential before effective use can be made of flooding for suppressing weeds that germinate with the rice. Recently, considerable variation in tolerance of flooding during germination was observed in rice and several tolerant landraces were identified and characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C16">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C1">Angaji <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).In this study, we observed that flooding at different intervals after seeding (0, 2 and 4 DAS) and depths (5–20 mm) did not jeopardize the germination of either rice genotypes or the two barnyard grasses (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F1">1</xref>). However, early flooding with 5–20 mm of water immediately after seeding was more effective in partially suppressing the subsequent growth of barnyard grass than when flooding was imposed at 2 or 4 days later, especially for the sensitive <italic>E. colona</italic>. The two rice cultivars recovered after 3 weeks (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU064TB1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU064TB2">2</xref>). These observations suggest that barnyard grass is more sensitive to early flooding than rice, especially when tolerant rice genotypes like ‘Khao Hlan On’ are used. Both tolerant and sensitive barnyard grasses germinated under shallower flooding (0–20 mm) but <italic>E. colona</italic> showed greater reduction in shoot and root growth, especially under earlier floods (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU064TB1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU064TB2">2</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C26">Mujer <italic>et al.</italic> (1993)</xref> also observed variation in tolerance of flooding among <italic>Echinochloa</italic> species. These results thus confirm the relatively higher tolerance of <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and ‘Khao Hlan On’ of flooding during germination and early growth.Seedlings of all four genotypes flooded under 100 mm of water (starting at sowing and continued for 7 days) showed a reduction in germination and growth of roots and shoots (leaves); however, the reduction was much greater in the sensitive <italic>E. colona</italic> and rice ‘IR42’ genotype (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F3">3</xref>). Shoot growth of tolerant <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> was more severely reduced compared with that of ‘Khao Hlan On’, whereas root growth ceased completely in the sensitive rice genotype and in both barnyard grasses under these conditions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F3">3</xref>). This result indicates that tolerant rice genotypes are likely to gain a competitive advantage over barnyard grass during germination and early growth when flooded at the time of seeding. On the other hand, flooding to 100 mm at a later stage (3 DAS) did not suppress the growth of either rice or tolerant <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, indicating that delayed flooding is ineffective compared with flooding at sowing (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F4">4</xref>). Clearly however, early flooding will be effective when combined with the use of a tolerant rice genotype such as ‘Khao Hlan On’. Additional studies on the responses of other weed species to flooding are desirable. One such species might well be <italic>Ludwigia hyssopifolia</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C5">Chauhan <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), which is becoming increasingly prevalent in direct-seeded rice. Broadening the work in this way could help fine-tune water and crop management practices to control these weeds in direct seeding rice systems.Since flooding at 100 mm from Day 0 seemed to be the most effective strategy for weed suppression in direct-seeded rice, further analyses were performed using these conditions alone. Starch concentration in barnyard grass and rice seeds decreased when germinating under aerobic conditions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F5">5</xref>). However, soluble sugar concentration increased during the first 5 days after flooding and decreased afterwards (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F6">6</xref>). This observation is consistent with the breakdown of starch into sugars and then the utilization of sugars in aerobic respiration. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C27">Murata <italic>et al.</italic> (1968)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C29">Nomura <italic>et al.</italic> (1969)</xref> reported an increase in sugar concentration in seeds of aerobically grown rice in the first 3 to 4 days. We also observed more rapid starch utilization in <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, which might contribute to its competitiveness against rice. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C19">Kim and Moody (1989)</xref> noted that, in early growth, barnyard grass had a 4-day ‘head start’ over rice.When rice and barnyard grass germinated and grew under flooded conditions, there was little change in starch concentration and little or no increases in soluble sugar concentration. This reflected a substantial reduction in the ability of these genotypes to mobilize starch into soluble sugars while submerged. The slow increase (albeit statistically not significant) in starch breakdown and sugar concentration over time in the tolerant rice and barnyard grass species is possibly sufficient for slower carbohydrate metabolism in both <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and ‘Khao Hlan On’. Moreover, the lower rate of carbohydrate catabolism agreed with the slower rate of germination and emergence observed in the flooded treatments. Some studies have previously reported carbohydrate metabolism occurring in <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> under anoxia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C18">Kennedy <italic>et al.</italic> 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C46">Vanderzee and Kennedy 1981</xref>). The tolerant rice genotypes degraded starch at a higher rate under flooded conditions compared with intolerant genotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C17">Kato-Noguchi <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> suggested that this ability to degrade starch under low oxygen stress confers anoxia tolerance in rice. The failure of flood-intolerant crops, such as wheat, to germinate under anoxia has been correlated with their inability or decreased ability to degrade starch under these conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C34">Perata <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>). An increased sugar concentration, resulting from starch degradation by amylase or sucrose synthase, has been observed in plants tolerant of anaerobic conditions (e.g. <italic>Cyperus rotundus</italic> L. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C32">Peña-Fronteras <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>]; rice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C12">Guglielminetti <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>]).In this study, we found that both rice and <italic>Echinochloa</italic> spp. have higher PDC and ADH activities when germinating under flooded conditions compared with aerobic soil (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F7">7</xref>). This indicates that enzymes of ethanol fermentation are induced under hypoxic conditions in both rice and barnyard grass. In rice, ‘Khao Hlan On’ showed about twice the activities of PDC and ADH of that of the sensitive ‘IR42’, which might partially account for the greater flood tolerance of this genotype. On the other hand, similar increases in ADH and PDC activities were observed in the two barnyard grasses in flooded soil. This suggests that variation in the induction of this pathway might not be associated with variation in flooding tolerance in these species. A possible cause would be the relatively small pool of total carbohydrate content in the small seeds of these weeds compared with rice seeds. Earlier findings showed that both PDC and ADH activities were induced under hypoxia in rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C11">Fukao <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Increases in PDC and ADH activities have been associated with tolerance in various species. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C45">Valdez (1995)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C15">Ismail <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> reported higher PDC and ADH activities in tolerant rice genotypes when compared with sensitive ones; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C32">Peña-Fronteras <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C10">Fuentes <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> showed similar results in flood-tolerant lowland ecotypes of <italic>C. rotundus;</italic> and this was also reported in other plants such as maize (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C41">Schwartz 1969</xref>) and <italic>A. thaliana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C7">Dolferus <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>).The lower activities of ADH and PDC in barnyard grasses germinating under aerobic conditions and their further reduction observed 3 days after sowing suggest that these enzymes are probably not necessary for barnyard grass seeds germinating in air. In contrast, these enzymes were active in both rice genotypes in aerobic soil, indicating that some degree of anaerobic respiration is taking place, possibly because of their relatively large seed size and the possibility of hypoxic pockets existing within the seed during germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C6">Colmer <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). This supports a more general view that suboptimal oxygen conditions occur in rice and other cereal seeds during germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C48">Zabalza <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Seeds of the two barnyard grasses are very much smaller (1000 grain weight of 1.5 g for <italic>E. colona</italic> and 2.9 g for <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>) compared with the two rice species (1000 grain weight of 23 g for ‘Khao Hlan On’ and 18 g for ‘IR42’).Aldehyde dehydrogenase activity increased substantially in the tolerant rice ‘Khao Hlan On’ and tolerant <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> when grown in flooded soil. However, the enzyme did not show high activity in either of the rice cultivars or barnyard grass species when they were grown in aerobic soil. This observation suggests that this pathway is similarly important for tolerance of hypoxic conditions during germination in both rice and barnyard grass. Increased ALDH activity in <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> var. <italic>formosensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C11">Fukao <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>) and in some rice cultivars (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C28">Nakazono <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C23">Magneschi and Perata 2009</xref>) has been suggested as one of the reasons for tolerance of anaerobic conditions. This could possibly be mediated through detoxification of excess acetaldehyde generated during anaerobic fermentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C25">Miro and Ismail 2013</xref>).Metabolic coping strategies of rice and barnyard grass may not be identical. However, there are similar patterns for changes in starch, soluble sugar and ALDH activities in rice and barnyard grasses. Both barnyard grasses have small seeds that store limited amounts of carbohydrates for germination. Indeed, their germination rates are much faster than those of rice, which has larger seeds and a correspondingly larger carbohydrate store. This correlates with starch and soluble sugar data (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F5">5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F6">6</xref>), where barnyard grass shows faster hydrolyses of reserves than rice. A faster metabolism may be an advantage in delayed and shallow flooding but not in early and deeper flooding.The increase in ALDH activity was seen only in tolerant rice cultivar ‘Khao Hlan On’ and tolerant barnyard grass <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>. Western blots using antibodies raised against ALDH2 from rice and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> were carried out to assess the protein patterns of this family in tolerant and sensitive genotypes. Aldehyde dehydrogenases belong to a well-characterized family of proteins previously studied in relation to submergence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C28">Nakazono <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C44">Tsuji <italic>et al.</italic> 2003<italic>b</italic></xref>). Of the different ALDH family proteins, ALDH2 has been identified as differentially expressed and translated in contrasting rice genotypes via proteomic analyses under anaerobic conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C40">Sadiq <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Of the two enzymes known for ALDH2, we found that both ALDH2a and ALDH2b are present in higher concentrations in the tolerant rice genotype, showing constant levels of translation. The sensitive ‘IR42’, on the other hand, showed low levels of ALDH2b under submergence. The proteins were identified based on their molecular weight. ALDH2b was the lowest band in ‘Khao Hlan On’ and the only band in ‘IR42’ (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F8">8</xref>C). ALDH2a was the middle band in ‘Khao Hlan On’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C43">Tsuji <italic>et al.</italic> 2003<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C20">Kotchoni <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). This observation is in agreement with those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C44">Tsuji <italic>et al.</italic> (2003<italic>b</italic>)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C40">Sadiq <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref>, who also found low levels of ALDH2b protein. In our study, however, ALDH2b protein was present in high concentrations in tolerant rice ‘Khao Hlan On’ and it did not decrease over time. On the other hand, our results on ALDH2a are in agreement with previous findings, suggesting low protein levels in both rice varieties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C44">Tsuji <italic>et al.</italic> 2003<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C40">Sadiq <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). ALDH2a was undetectable by immunoblot in ‘IR42’. Genomic clones of both ALDH2a and ALDH2b were sequenced and compared but were found to be identical. Similar observations have been made for the CDS sequences of both genes (data not shown). Through gene network models, future work will focus on transcription factors, kinases and other pathway-related genes responsible for differential expression of ALDH. These results will shed light on the complex mechanisms involved in the regulation of genes associated with anaerobic metabolism during germination.The immunoblot raised against ALDH2 did not show a very clear banding pattern in barnyard grass. One reason is probably the heterologous nature of the antibody. Since ALDH2 is a highly conserved protein across species, the blotting results can be attributed to ALDH2 in the barnyard grass, especially in <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> on Days 6, 7 and 8. However, it cannot be confirmed with actual data whether ALDH2a or ALDH2b or another similar ALDH were detected. A comparison of the blots obtained from tolerant rice and barnyard grass seems to indicate that one of the ALDH2 forms has been present since the beginning of germination in both ‘Khao Hlan On’ and <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, and that the protein can be detected throughout until Day 8 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU064F8">8</xref>). However, any possible relationship between high levels of ALDH2 and tolerance needs to be explored further.One of the major problems of using flooding of rice fields as a weed control measure is the lack of information on differential responses of rice and weeds to this practice during the first 2 weeks of crop establishment. Unravelling these responses will help design better management options that reduce weed infestation while inflicting minimal damage to the rice. Neither shallow nor delayed flooding was sufficient to suppress the growth of barnyard grass species used in this study; however, flooding with 100 mm of water immediately after sowing was effective with much less inhibitory effect on the growth of the tolerant rice genotype ‘Khao Hlan On’. Flooding of 20–40 mm applied under field conditions was recently reported to be effective in suppressing intolerant weeds such as <italic>E. colona</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU064C3">Chauhan 2012</xref>). Metabolic differences between tolerant and sensitive rice genotypes and barnyard grass were also investigated. Anaerobic respiration was induced similarly in both flood-tolerant and flood-sensitive barnyard grasses but this induction was substantially enhanced in the tolerant rice ‘Khao Hlan On’ compared with flood-sensitive ‘IR42’. Aldehyde dehydrogenase activity was enhanced by flooding only in tolerant <italic>E. crus-galli</italic> and tolerant rice ‘Khao Hlan On’ but not in sensitive <italic>E. colona</italic> and ‘IR42’, suggesting a causal association with tolerance in both barnyard grass and rice. Further studies are needed to unravel the control mechanisms that mediate the upregulation of ALDH in tolerant rice and barnyard grass to establish its role in adaptation to flooding. These findings will ultimately help to develop flooding and other weed management strategies to control weeds effectively while minimizing damage to the rice crop itself.The research was partly funded through the Philippine Council for Advanced Science and Technology Research and Development, the Irrigated Rice Research Consortium of the International Rice Research Institute and the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation.L.P.E. undertook the physiology work and enzymatic activity analyses. B.M. took part in the enzyme activity assays and handled the western blot analyses. All authors contributed to the planning of the research and the preparation of the manuscript.None declared.The following <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu064/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link> is available in the online version of this article –<bold>Figure S1.</bold> Seedlings of barnyard grass and rice after germination under aerobic conditions (left) and under 20 mm of flooding starting at sowing (right): (1) <italic>E. colona</italic>, (2) <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, (3) ‘IR42’ and (4) ‘Khao Hlan On’. Pictures were taken at 7, 14 and 21 DAS. The vertical white bar represents 10 cm. Root length was clearly reduced under submerged conditions in all genotypes. Seedlings of both echinochloa species showed reduced growth, especially at 7 DAS; however, by 21 DAS, surviving seedlings of both rice and barnyard grass seemed to have recovered.<bold>Figure S2.</bold> Fourteen-day-old seedlings of <italic>E. colona</italic> and <italic>E. crus-galli</italic>, ‘IR42’ and ‘Khao Hlan On’ under (A) aerobic and (F) flooding with 100 mm of water after germinating aerobically for 3 days. The vertical white bar represents 10 cm. All genotypes seemed to partially recover after 14 days, except for <italic>E. colona,</italic> which showed reduced growth.The studies were part of the PhD thesis of the senior author. We thank Teodoro Migo, Edwin Dizon, Lamberto V. Licardo, Frederikson Entila, Leodegario dela Rosa, Ofelia Namuco, Evangelina Ella and Gina Vergara for technical advice and assistance. We also thank Prof. Mikio Nakazono for generously providing the antibody against ALDH2.