 Rapid flooding-induced adventitious root development from preformed primordia in  Solanum dulcamara   Root adaptation to soil waterlogging  AFLP-based RNA fingerprinting: novel variants and applications  Flooding stress: acclimations and genetic diversity  Making sense of low oxygen sensing  Adventitious roots of whole plants: their forms, functions, and evolution  Mapping the functional roles of cap cells in the response of  Arabidopsis  primary roots to gravity  Flooding: the survival strategies of plants  Transcriptome analysis during cell division in plants  Enhanced recovery of transformants of  Agrobacterium tumefaciens  after freeze–thaw transformation and drug selection  Global gene expression responses to waterlogging in roots and leaves of cotton ( Gossypium hirsutum  L.)  Genomic analysis of the native European  Solanum  species,  S. dulcamara   Aerenchyma formation  Selection of internal control genes for quantitative real-time RT–PCR studies during tomato development process  Ethylene—a key regulator of submergence responses in rice  The ethylene response factors  SNORKEL1  and  SNORKEL2  allow rice to adapt to deep water  Clearing techniques for the study of vascular plant tissues in whole structures and thick sections  Effect of the spectral composition of light on dry matter production in  Solanum dulcamara  ecotypes of different origin  Rice plant development: from zygote to spikelet  Ethylene and responses of plants to soil waterlogging and submergence  Effects of flooding on growth and metabolism of herbaceous plants  Effects of applying ethylene to the root system of  Zea mays  on growth and nutrient concentration, in relation to flooding tolerance  A revision of the Dulcamaroid Clade of  Solanum  L. (Solanaceae)  Transcript profiling of the anoxic rice coleoptile  Adventitious root growth and cell-cycle induction in deepwater rice  Organization and cell differentiation in lateral roots of  Arabidopsis thaliana   Ethylene induces epidermal cell death at the site of adventitious root emergence in rice  Germination in populations of  Solanum dulcamara  L. from contrasting habitats   Arabidopsis  lateral root development: an emerging story  Effects of flooding on soils  Real-time quantitative RT–PCR: design, calculations, and statistics  An auxin-dependent distal organizer of pattern and polarity in the  Arabidopsis  root  Root responses to flooding  Epidermal cell death in rice is regulated by ethylene, gibberellin, and abscisic acid  Epidermal cell death in rice is confined to cells with a distinct molecular identity and is mediated by ethylene and H 2 O 2  through an autoamplified signal pathway  Emerging roots alter epidermal cell fate through mechanical and reactive oxygen species signaling  The relation between the lenticels and adventitious roots of  Solanum dulcamara   Aux/IAA proteins repress expression of reporter genes containing natural and highly active synthetic auxin response elements  Hormonal interplay during adventitious root formation in flooded tomato plants  Flooding-induced adventitious rooting in  Rumex : morphology and development in an ecological perspective  Ethylene accumulation in waterlogged  Rumex  plants promotes formation of adventitious roots  Ethylene—and oxygen signalling—drive plant survival during flooding  Plant hormones regulate fast shoot elongation under water: from genes to communities  Changes in tomato ovary transcriptome demonstrate complex hormonal regulation of fruit set  Control of adventitious root production and hypocotyl hypertrophy of sunflower ( Helianthus annuus)  in response to flooding  A three-gene phylogeny of the genus  Solanum  (Solanaceae)   Sub1A  is an ethylene-response-factor-like gene that confers submergence tolerance to rice  Revelation on early response and molecular mechanism of submergence tolerance in maize roots by microarray and suppression subtractive hybridization  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Flooding strongly affects plant growth, as it leads to low oxygen concentrations in the submerged tissues. Understanding plant responses to flooding may benefit both management of wetland ecosystems and improve progress in creating flood-tolerant crop species. Bittersweet ( Solanum dulcamara ), a species related to tomato and eggplant, has dormant primordia on the stem that develop into adventitious roots within 3 days of flooding. Changes in gene expression were present within 2 hours and included activation of hypoxia and ethylene signalling genes. Unexpectedly, these early changes in gene expression were closely similar in primordia and adjacent stem tissue, suggesting a dominant general response in tissues during early flooding.  Flooding is a common stress factor in both natural and agricultural systems, and affects plant growth by the slow diffusion rate of gases in water. This results in low oxygen concentrations in submerged tissues, and hence in a decreased respiration rate. Understanding the responses of plants to flooding is essential for the management of wetland ecosystems, and may benefit research to improve the flood tolerance of crop species. This study describes the response to partial submergence of bittersweet ( Solanum dulcamara ). Bittersweet is a Eurasian species that grows both in dry habitats such as coastal dunes, and in wetlands, and therefore is a suitable model plant for studying responses to a variety of environmental stresses. A further advantage is that the species is closely related to flood-intolerant crops such as tomato and eggplant. The species constitutively develops dormant primordia on the stem, which we show to have a predetermined root identity. We investigated adventitious root growth from these primordia during flooding. The synchronized growth of roots from the primordia was detected after 2–3 days of flooding and was due to a combination of cell division and cell elongation. Gene expression analysis demonstrated that the molecular response to flooding began within 2 h and included activation of hypoxia and ethylene signalling genes. Unexpectedly, these early changes in gene expression were very similar in primordia and adjacent stem tissue, suggesting that there is a dominant general response in tissues during early flooding.  Flooding is a significant abiotic stress factor that affects plant growth and development in natural ecosystems ( Blom and Voesenek 1996 ;  Visser  et al.  1996 a  ). It severely reduces the exchange of gaseous compounds between the plant and its environment, because gas diffusion is around 10 000-fold slower in water than in air ( Armstrong  et al.  1991 ). In particular, oxygen deficiency causes poor respiration in submerged plant tissues. This is especially so in organs such as roots when buried in anoxic sediment, resulting in hampered plant growth and survival ( Bailey-Serres and Voesenek 2008 ). Most plants cope with these changes in the short term by changing from aerobic respiration to glycolysis and fermentation for energy production ( Bailey-Serres  et al.  2012 ). Well-adapted plants, such as many wetland species, also display morphological and growth adaptations that enable them to deal with flooding stress over the longer term. Such adaptions include re-orientation of petioles in a more upright position and faster stem or leaf elongation that enables the shoot to regain contact with the water surface and the open atmosphere ( Jackson 1985 ;  Voesenek  et al.  2004 ;  Fukao and Bailey-Serres 2008 ). Growth adaptations to submergence have been studied extensively in rice and  Rumex , showing a pivotal role for the hormone ethylene (reviewed in  Voesenek and Sasidharan 2013 ).  Another common adaptation to flooding is the formation of adventitious roots that contain aerenchyma, i.e. air channels that connect to the shoot and herewith help to maintain gas diffusion under submergence ( Evans 2003 ). Adventitious roots functionally replace primary root systems that may deteriorate during flooding due to oxygen deficiency ( Jackson and Drew 1984 ;  Barlow 1986 ;  Sauter 2013 ), although direct experimental demonstration of their efficacy is still lacking. In some species, the adventitious root primordia are formed  de novo  upon flooding and subsequently continue their development into roots, e.g. in sunflower and in young tomato plants ( Wample and Reid 1978 ;  Vidoz  et al.  2010 ). In other species, the primordia are constitutively preformed on the stem and stay dormant until stimulated to grow out by flooding. This phenomenon is characteristic of the grass family (Poaceae). In rice, preformed primordia are the source of nodal crown roots that grow out during flooding ( Lorbiecke and Sauter 1999 ). Here, the outgrowth of the adventitious roots is associated with vacuolation and elongation of the root cells in the basal region of the stele ( Itoh  et al.  2005 ). In rice, the apical meristem in adventitious root primordia is activated by flooding before the emergence of the roots and involves accumulation of cell cycle gene mRNA ( Lorbiecke and Sauter 1999 ). Just before roots emerge, the epidermal cell layers at the apex of the primordia undergo programmed cell death, which appears to be a necessary process to facilitate protrusion of the roots to the outside ( Mergemann and Sauter 2000 ;  Steffens and Sauter 2005 ,  2009 ;  Steffens  et al.  2012 ). To test whether or not this flood-responsive developmental pattern is limited only to rice, and whether it occurs more generally in angiosperms, we analysed adventitious root emergence in the dicot species  Solanum dulcamara  (bittersweet).   Solanum dulcamara  is a diploid Eurasian species of the section Dulcamaroid in the subgenus  Potatoe  of the Solanaceae, which includes the crop species tomato and potato ( Weese and Bohs 2007 ;  D'Agostino  et al.  2013 ;  Knapp 2013 ). The species occupies a wide range of ecologically contrasting habitats ( Horvath  et al.  1977 ) but prefers sites that are wet throughout the year and often flooded. It is therefore commonly found along river banks, canals, ditches, and in mires and damp woods ( Pegtel 1985 ). However, it can also grow in sandy soil on the slopes of primary coastal dunes (T. Dawood, C. Mariani and E. J. W. Visser, pers. observ.). The main stem and branches of  S. dulcamara  typically carry numerous adventitious root primordia, derived from the parenchyma of the rays in the xylem, where cells situated near the phloem region undergo cell division to make up a conical base that connects with the vascular bundle ( Terras 1897 ). Importantly, the fully developed primordia are clearly visible and easily accessible, making  S. dulcamara  an excellent model system to analyse the developmental and signalling processes taking place during primordium activation and early root growth.  In this study, the floodwater was deep enough both to flood the original roots and submerge the lower part of the stem of the  S. dulcamara  plants. From the latter region, we sampled preformed adventitious root primordia at different time intervals after the onset of flooding to determine the timing of events preceding outgrowth of the roots. This was done by histological analysis and complementary DNA-amplified fragment length polymorphism (cDNA-AFLP) profiling to reveal early responsive genes. The minimum period during which the lower part of a plant needed to be submerged to develop adventitious roots was also determined.  Seeds of  S. dulcamara  wild-type plants growing in a wet habitat near Wychense Ven (Wijchen, The Netherlands) were collected in 2005 and stored at 4 °C by the Experimental Garden and Genebank (Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands) (accession no. A54750008). Seeds from this seed stock were sown in vermiculite in small round plastic pots 10 cm tall and 13 cm in diameter, kept in the dark at 4 °C for 3 days and then grown in a greenhouse, with a daily temperature regime of 20–23 °C (day) and 15–18 °C (night), with additional light supplied by high-pressure sodium lamps (SON-T; 600 W; Philips Nederland B.V., Eindhoven, The Netherlands). Three-week-old seedlings were individually transplanted into 12 × 11 × 11 cm (h × w × d) plastic pots filled with potting soil (Stekgrond, Holland Potgrond, Grubbenvorst, The Netherlands) and kept further under the same conditions. The plants were watered daily and fertilized once every 2 weeks until 10–12 weeks old, when they were experimentally treated. By 8 weeks, the position of primordia gradually became visible as small bumps on the epidermis of the stem.  To isolate the primordia samples, external excisions were made around the primordia, which were distinguishable by their white dome-shaped structure. This was followed by peeling off of the primordia while minimizing contamination with surrounding stem tissue. To isolate stem samples, similar sections were taken from green stem tissue in which no primordia were present.  About 15 primordia on the basal section of the stem were marked with a marker pen 2 or 3 days prior to the treatment of the plants. One day before treatment, glass containers (60 × 21 × 21 cm, h × w × d) were filled with tap water to a level that would allow flooding of the plants to 15 cm above the soil surface. Plants were placed individually in the containers at 1100 h. After the plants were flooded, emergence of the adventitious roots was scored by eye every day for 1 week. Untreated control plants were placed in identical containers without floodwater. A localized flooding experiment was conducted by enclosing a randomly chosen stem section containing primordia in a glass cuvette containing water and sealing water-tight with Terostat Butyl-IX (Henkel AG &amp; Co., Düsseldorf, Germany).  To create a high-humidity treatment, glass containers similar to those used for flooding were lined with wet filter paper (standard filter paper; Schleicher and Schuell GmbH, Dassel, Germany). Then plants were placed individually in the containers and the open top was covered with plastic film. During this treatment, air was flushed at 1.75 L min −1  through each glass container to prevent accumulation of plant-derived volatiles such as CO 2  or ethylene. The flushing air was first humidified by directing it through a water column. Humidity in the containers was measured with a thermohygrometer (type 605-H1, Testo AG, Lenzkirch, Germany) and showed levels of 90–93 % relative humidity. Control plants were kept in similar but open containers and flushed with dry air. Light and temperature were kept at standard conditions (see above). In one experiment, flooding treatment for 2 days was followed by transfer to humid air. Adventitious roots were counted 7 days after the start of the experiment.  Dissected primordia were fixed for 2 h in 2 % glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M phosphate buffer (pH 7.2), rinsed in buffer for 2 h and then treated with 1 % (w : v) osmium tetroxide solution overnight at 4 °C. Subsequently, the primordia were dehydrated in 100 % ethanol and embedded in Spur's medium. Sections of 1 µm were stained with aqueous toluidine blue solution (0.1 % (v : v) in 1 % (w : v) borax) and viewed under a Leitz Orthoplan microscope with a Leica DFC420C camera (both Leica Microsystems B.V., Rijswijk, The Netherlands). For each time point of the experiment (0, 24, 48 and 72 h after the onset of flooding), median and transverse sections of four primordia were examined. The area of the meristematic region (mm 2 ) included cells containing at least two-thirds cytoplasm, as identified by dense staining with toluidine blue. The size of meristematic cells (µm 2 ) was determined in a projected oval around the quiescent centre (QC). To determine the number of meristematic cortical cells in the proximal–distal direction, numbers were counted in the cortical rows right and left of the vascular bundle in the primordia.  Primordia were dissected after 0, 24 and 48 h of flooding, sectioned in 100 µm pieces with a vibrating microtome (Leica VT1000 S; Leica Biosystems, Rijswijk, The Netherlands) and placed directly in Lugol's solution (1 g of iodine and 2 g of potassium iodide dissolved in 300 mL water) for 3 min. Thereafter, sections were kept for 3 days in the clearing agent chlorallactophenol as described in  Herr (1993) . Imaging was done on a Leitz Orthoplan (see above).  The DR5:GUS construct ( Ulmasov  et al.  1997 ) was transformed to  Agrobacterium tumefaciens  strain GV3101 using freeze–thaw transformation ( Chen  et al.  1994 ). Transgenic plants were generated by the leaf disc transformation method. In short, leaves were harvested from 3- or 4-week-old  S. dulcamara  plants, sterilized for 10 min in a solution of 1.5 % bleach and 0.01 % Tween 20 (v : v), and washed four times for 5 min with sterilized demineralized water. The leaf explants were cut without veins and incubated in a 1 : 100 diluted bacterial culture (OD 600  0.4–0.6; diluted with liquid MS20 co-cultivation medium consisting of 20 g L −1  sucrose, 4.4 g L −1  Murashige and Skoog (MS) with Gamborg B5, 0.5 g L −1  2-( N -morpholino)ethanesulfonic acid monohydrate pH 5.8, 2 mg L −1  6-benzylaminopurine (BAP), 0.1 mg L −1  1-naphthaleneacetic acid (NAA) and 10 mg L −1  acetosyringone) and kept packed in aluminium foil for 3 days under standard climate chamber growth conditions (16/8 h day/night, at 20/22 °C). Thereafter, leaf explants were transferred to a selective medium of MS20 supplemented with growth regulators (2 mg L −1  BAP, 0.1 mg L −1  NAA, 300 mg L −1  cefotaxime, 300 mg L −1  vancomycin and 25 mg L −1  kanamycin). The plates were covered with three layers of filter paper and kept for a week in a standard climate chamber. The filter papers were removed gradually (one per week). Every two and a half weeks, the explants were transferred to fresh selective medium. After ∼7 weeks, newly emerged shoots were excised and transferred to MS20 medium supplemented with 300 mg L −1  cefotaxime, 300 mg L −1  vancomycin, 10 mg L −1  kanamycin and 0.25 mg L −1  indole-3-butyric acid (IBA). When roots had formed, plants were transferred to the greenhouse.  Histochemical β-glucuronidase (GUS) staining was performed on 50-µm-thick dissected primordia from DR5:GUS transgenic plants after 0, 24 and 48 h of flooding. β-Glucuronidase activity was tested by incubating sections of the primordia overnight at 37 °C under dark conditions in GUS staining buffer, containing 10 mM EDTA, 0.1 % (v : v) Triton X-100, 0.5 mM ferricyanide, 0.5 mM ferrocyanide and 2 µg L −1  X-Gluc, in 50 mM Na-phosphate buffer, pH 7.5. Sections were cleared and stored in 70 % (v : v) ethanol.  Primordia and stem explants were dissected from the flooded plants at 0, 6, 12, 24, 48 and 72 h after flooding, and frozen directly in liquid nitrogen. Three biological replicates were collected for each time point. Total RNA was isolated from the frozen primordia samples with Trizol (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). PolyA + -RNA was captured from 5 µg of total RNA using biotinylated oligodT-coated streptavidin beads (Dynabeads ®  MyOne™ Streptavidin C1; Invitrogen), according to the manufacturer's protocol. First and second strands of cDNA were synthesized as described by  Vriezen  et al.  (2008) . Double-stranded cDNA was used for cDNA-AFLP and the liberated BsYI–MseI fragments were used for the next steps of this procedure as described by  Bachem  et al.  (2008) . Gene expression in the RNA samples was covered using 128 primer combinations for selective amplification as described by  Breyne  et al.  (2002) . This was estimated to cover circa 60 % of the transcriptome. For a list of primers  [see  Supporting Information]  . We selected 114 fragments ranging from 34 to 582 bp.  To identify the genes represented by the transcript-derived fragments (TDFs), two independent fragments of each differentially expressed gene were cut out from the gel and DNA was re-amplified under the same conditions as for selective amplification. Subsequently, the fragments were blunted and cloned in pJET 1.2/blunt cloning vector (Fermentas, Thermo Scientific Molecular Biology Solutions, Landsmeer, The Netherlands) and sequenced using the Beckman DTCS quick start mix, cat.# 608120 (Beckman Coultier, Brea, CA, USA), and the Beckman CEQ™ 2000 DNA analysis system. The sequences that corresponded to the correct size of the cDNA-AFLP fragments were aligned to the  S. dulcamara  transcriptome assembly ( D'Agostino  et al.  2013 ), the tomato transcript database (ITAG2.3;  http://www.sgn.cornell.edu ) and the  Arabidopsis  transcript database (TAIR10), using BLASTn with an  E  value &lt;1 × 10 −10 .  From the total 114 TDFs, 22 were discarded because multiple different sequences were obtained from the fragment and 11 were excluded because they had the same hit in tomato as another TDF, but at a different position. This might indicate a multiple enzymatic restriction in the same transcript. Among the 81 TDFs that were considered to be the representative sequences for our analysis, 37 were up-regulated and 44 down-regulated  [see    Supporting Information   ] . We found significant homology for 72 of these TDFs; only nine fragments, ranging from 34 to 222 bp, did not show any homology. These were further blasted to the tomato genome (version SL2.40), but only one of them, namely TDF 22-5, could be aligned to the intron region of  Solyc12g008710 . Our not finding any homology for the other eight TDFs might be explained by the small size of the fragments or because they represent less conserved regions of transcripts. For several TDFs, we could not obtain a hit in the  S. dulcamara  transcriptome assembly, even though a hit was found in the tomato database  [see    Supporting Information   ] .  Primordia and stem tissues were dissected from flooded and control plants at 2, 4, 6, 12 and 24 h after flooding in two biological replicas. Control samples were taken at the same time of the day to avoid the influence of a circadian rhythm. For this experiment, 10- to 12-week-old plants were used and prepared as described above. Each sample was a pool of two plants to minimize biological variation. Total RNA was isolated from the frozen primordia and stem tissues using the RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany). Contaminating genomic DNA was removed using DNase I, RNase-free (Fermentas, Thermo Scientific Molecular Biology Solutions). The total DNA-free RNA (250 ng) was then reverse-transcribed using a cDNA synthesis kit (iScript™ cDNA synthesis kit; Bio-Rad Laboratories B.V., Veenendaal, The Netherlands) in a reaction volume of 20 µL. For quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR), 5 µL of 10-fold diluted cDNA were used in a 25-µL PCR reaction containing 400 nM each primer and 12.5 µL of iQ™ SYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad Laboratories B.V.). The PCR reactions were performed in a 96-well thermocycler (Bio-Rad iCycler) by starting with 3 min at 95 °C followed by 45 cycles consisting of 15 s at 95 °C and 60 s at 60 °C. Melt curves were generated by raising the temperature from 65 to 95 °C in 0.5 °C increments per 10 s to verify the presence of a specific product. Expression of the  S. dulcamara  homologues of the tomato genes  TIP4 I ,  SAND ,  CAC  and  Expressed  ( Expósito-Rodrìguez  et al.  2008 ) was used as the endogenous control. The stability of the reference genes was evaluated with geNorm software. The transcripts level was quantified as described in  Rieu and Powers (2009) . The primers used for real-time quantitative-PCR were  TIP4 I : Forw: 5′-AGTCATGCCTAGTGGTTGGTTCC-3′; Rev: 5′-TGAGCACTCCATCAACCCTAAGC-3′;  SAND : Forw: 5′-TGCTTACACATGTCTTCCACTTGC-3′; Rev: 5′-AAACAGGACCCCTGAGTC AGTTAC-3′;  Exp : Forw: 5′-CTAAGAACGCTGGACCTAATGACAAG-3′; Rev: 5′-AAAGTCGATTTAGCTTTCTCTGCATATTTC-3′;  CAC : Forw: 5′-AGTTTGTTGTTGAGGCTGTTACAC-3′; Rev: 5′-ACCGGACACCTTCCTGAGTAATG-3′;  21-8 : Forw: 5′-AGACGAGCATCGCCTGAACC-3′; Rev: 5′-GCTGCAACAATGGCTTTTCTTCTC-3′;  16-1 : Forw: 5′-GCACATTCACTACA AAACTTTCAGACTC-3′; Rev: 5′-TAGTTGTGAAATCTTCGAGGAGATGTTG-3′;  21-10 : Forw: 5′-CGGGTCTGAGTCAACAGAGGAC-3′; Rev: 5′-TCATCCAGCTTCAACGGTGAGG-3′;  18-14 : Forw: 5′-GATCCCAATAAAGGGTGGCGAATC-3′; Rev: 5′-TGCTGGTGCCTCCTCCAAAC-3′;  17-6 : Forw: 5′-TGAGGAAGAGAGGGAGCAATAAGTG-3′; Rev: 5′-GCAGCAAACTTTATTC CATAATACATAGTG-3′;  17-4 : Forw: 5′-GGATTGTTATGTGTTCAAGAAGATGTCAG-3′; Rev: 5′-AGTGGTGATAGAGTAACTATTAAGCATGAG-3′.  All data were log transformed before analysis to correct for heterogeneity of variance ( Gomez and Gomez 1984 ;  Rieu and Powers 2009 ). One-way analysis of variance with uncorrected least significant difference was applied to assess the significance of differences between flooding and the control condition, using SPSS, version 18 (IBM, New York, NY, USA).  Adventitious root formation on stems of  S. dulcamara  during flooding. (A) Adventitious roots grown on a plant during a flood in a natural floodplain. (B) Adventitious root primordia on the stem of a plant grown under greenhouse conditions prior to flooding. (C) Adventitious roots grown after flooding in the greenhouse. The water level was kept at about 15 cm above the soil (blue bar) for 2 weeks and then removed for photography. (D) Adventitious root growth on a locally flooded stem section. The stem of the intact  S. dulcamara  plant was surrounded with water in a sealed cuvette for 1 week. Adventitious roots developed only on the stem part that was inside the cuvette.  Rate of adventitious root emergence in  S. dulcamara  during flooding. Plants were partially submerged or kept in air and root emergence was scored every day by eye for 1 week after the start of the treatment. The mean percentage of primordia grown out into adventitious roots (±SE) is indicated ( n  = 12 plants for each treatment).  Cytological changes in adventitious root primordia of  S. dulcamara  during flooding. Analysis was performed on longitudinal sections of the primordia. Values indicate the mean (SE in parentheses). *Significantly different from 0-h flooding,  P  &lt; 0.01.  Histological analysis of adventitious root primordia of  S. dulcamara  during flooding. (A) Non-flooded primordium; the dashed red line represents the area of the meristematic region (mm 2 ), which includes the densely stained and non-vacuolated cells of the root tip; (B) primordium flooded for 24 h; (C) cross-section and (D) longitudinal section of primordia flooded for 48 h; (E) emergence of the adventitious root after 72 h of flooding. Arrows indicate the parenchymatic cortex cells at the base of the primordium that elongate. The scale bar in (A) also applies to (B), (D) and (E) and represents 100 µm. The scale bar in (C) is 50 µm.  Root meristem identity markers in the adventitious root primordia. (A) Representative longitudinal sections of primordia flooded for 0, 24 and 48 h are shown; (B) Lugol's staining marks starch granules in the differentiated columella cells; (C) expression of the  DR5-GUS  auxin reporter gene in the distal domain of the meristem.  In conclusion, flooding induces both division and elongation of the primordia cells, leading to emergence of adventitious roots with a mature internal root anatomy becoming evident after 48 h flooding.  Expression of transcripts selected from cDNA-AFLP analysis of the flooding response. Column (A) shows the expression patterns obtained by cDNA-AFLP for the selected TDFs at 0, 6, 12, 24, 48 and 72 h after flooding. Column (B) shows the relative mRNA level of the transcripts corresponding to the TDFs in flooded stem (FS), flooded primordia (FP), control stem (CS) and control primordia (CP) at the time points 0, 2, 4, 6, 12 and 24 h after flooding. Data are means ± SE,  n  = 2. Column (C) shows the corresponding  S. dulcamara  unigene ID ( D'Agostino  et al.  2013 ) and annotation.  To improve our understanding of the timing of the early signalling events involved in primordia activation, we studied in more detail the expression of a subset of transcripts from the ‘signalling’ and ‘transcription regulation’ categories. Samples were taken at shorter time intervals up to 24 h after flooding, and from both primordia and adjacent stem tissue. Non-flooded control samples were taken in parallel to correct for the influence of a circadian rhythm. In general, the qPCR results showed that the expression of the analysed genes was modified very early during flooding, starting within 2 h (Fig.  5 B). For most of the up-regulated genes, the change in expression was transient, with expression of the LOB domain protein 42 transcript (TDF 21-10) peaking within 2 h. Also, the modulation of down-regulated genes started after 2 h with the exception of auxin response factor (ARF4), which decreased more gradually during flooding. Notably,  ERF1a  (TDF 16-1) was very strongly up-regulated, increasing almost 350-fold in the stem after 12 h. Furthermore, the qPCR analysis showed that all six transcripts, either up- or down-regulated, were expressed with a similar pattern in both the stem and primordia (Fig.  5 B), and thus no primordia-specific changes in gene expression were detected.  Time needed for activation of preformed primordia in  S. dulcamara  under flooding to emerge into adventitious roots. Plants were treated with continuous flooding or in air for 7 days, exposed to high humidity, or first flooded for 1 (1DF) or 2 days (2DF) and then transferred to humid air (H) for the remainder of the 7 days. Grey indicates the percentage of primordia grown out into adventitious roots at the switch of treatment; black indicates the percentage of primordia grown out into adventitious roots after 7 days.  Formation of preformed primordia in stems of  S. dulcamara  was first described more than a century ago ( Terras 1897 ). The occurrence of these primordia, with their distinctive dome shape on the stem, is important in vegetative propagation, as roots may grow out from these primordia when parts of the slender stem touch wet soil ( Terras 1897 ). We show that the preformed primordia of this species also grow into adventitious roots upon flooding, suggesting a function as an adaptation to flooding of the soil when the water also covers the lower stem. When the normal roots are flooded and lose contact with the atmosphere, they commonly die due to the anoxic conditions that prevail in flooded soil ( Ponnamperuma 1984 ). Indeed, we observed that the original root system of  S. dulcamara  deteriorates quickly upon flooding (data not shown), making the newly formed adventitious roots, with their aerenchymatous connections linking root apices with the shoot, likely to be important in replacing the former roots.  The formation of adventitious and lateral root primordia involves cell de-differentiation and then division to organize the cell layers from which the root meristem develops ( Malamy and Benfey 1997 ;  Itoh  et al.  2005 ). In lateral roots, the developmental process continues with cell division to establish the primordia and is then directly followed by cell elongation to propel the root emergence ( Malamy and Benfey 1997 ). In  S. dulcamara , where the established primordia normally remain dormant, their activation involves cell divisions coupled with cell expansion to increase the size of the meristematic region, followed by cell elongation at the basal region to push the apex radially outwards. Together, these processes drive root emergence. This sequence of events is analogous to the situation in deepwater rice, where the expression of cell cycle genes precedes adventitious crown root emergence upon flooding and ethylene treatments ( Lorbiecke and Sauter 1999 ), and cell elongation occurs in the basal region of the primordia at the time of root emergence ( Itoh  et al.  2005 ). Whether growth of the adventitious root through the surrounding tissue involves enzymatic weakening of the cell walls, such as during lateral root development in  Arabidopsis  ( Péret  et al.  2009 ), and programmed death of the epidermal cells, such as in rice ( Steffens  et al.  2012 ), is not clear as yet.  A rapid outgrowth of adventitious roots from preformed primordia is consistent with the function of these roots in survival under flooding. Anoxic conditions develop within several hours in a flooded soil ( Ponnamperuma 1984 ), and this might not only be fatal for the original non-aerenchymatous roots, but also inhibit the formation of replacement roots within the soil. In contrast, the stem base will have ready access to oxygen, thus permitting adventitious root formation above the soil. If  de novo  initiation of root primordia was required for this, it might be too slow to have adaptive value. However, outgrowth of preformed primordia, as in  S. dulcamara , would be much faster. In other flood-adapted species, flooding- or submergence-induced adventitious root growth from preformed primordia can be detected within a few hours, e.g. after 10 h in deepwater rice ( Lorbiecke and Sauter 1999 ), to a few days, e.g. in  Rumex palustris  ( Visser  et al.  1996 a  ). Our results showed that in  S. dulcamara  the emergence of these roots started to be visible after 2–3 days from the onset of flooding. Molecular analysis and short-term flooding experiments, however, indicated that the response to flooding started much faster and some of the primordia were irreversibly activated within 24 h. The variation in time of emergence of adventitious roots may thus be explained by the variation in the time it takes for the individual primordia to perceive the ‘flooding signal’ and get activated. In rice, it has been hypothesized that the differences in emergence time are caused by the differences in the age of the nodal primordia before the start of submergence ( Lorbiecke and Sauter 1999 ). As we also noticed variation in the size of the root meristems between primordia, it is possible that the older, slightly larger primordia get activated more easily. Furthermore, the idea that each primordium perceives the activation signal autonomously is consistent with our observation that the response is strictly local: non-flooded primordia never get activated.  What signalling pathways could be involved in adventitious root activation? Hypoxia commonly induces changes in the expression of genes related to carbohydrate metabolism ( Zhang  et al.  2006 ;  Lasanthi-Kudahettige  et al.  2007 ;  Christianson  et al.  2010 ). Also in  S. dulcamara  genes belonging to the category ‘glycolysis’ were rapidly up-regulated, after 6 h of flooding, indicating a metabolic adjustment to flooding stress and suggesting that hypoxia signalling is taking place. In the category ‘transcription regulation’, we found three genes encoding ethylene response factors ( ERF1a ,  ERF2b ) to be up-regulated, suggesting involvement of ethylene signalling. Ethylene has been associated with flooding responses in many species, including the outgrowth of adventitious root primordia ( Jackson  et al.  1981 ;  Visser  et al.  1996 b  ), and ERFs have been found to participate in several morphological and metabolic adaptations. For example, the ERF-type genes  SNORKEL1  and - 2  are up-regulated in deepwater rice varieties within 3 h after submergence ( Hattori  et al.  2009 ) and confer tolerance to flooding with gradually increasing depth by stimulating the growth of internodes and thus stem elongation to above the water surface. On the other hand, a mutated ERF ( SUB1A ) prevents ethylene-promoted elongation in rice, thereby effecting energy conservation ( Xu  et al.  2006 ) and conferring tolerance to deep transient floods that cannot be overcome by shoot elongation.  Interestingly, the detailed characterization of six differentially expressed TDFs showed that their transcriptional response, whether up- or down-regulated, was highly similar in primordia and stem. This can imply that a large part of the transcriptional reprogramming which is needed to cope with flooding is independent of tissue type. Activation of primordia may therefore depend more on a tissue-specific response to the common signals present in all plant parts during flooding.  We conclude that  S. dulcamara  is a suitable model system to study activation of dormant adventitious root primordia by flooding. Physiological and molecular analysis in combination with genetic modification are planned to shed further light on the roles of the various signalling pathways.  This research was supported by the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO) under project number 017.005.041.  T.D., I.R., C.M. and E.V. designed the experiments and wrote the paper; T.D., I.R., E.V., M.W.-A. and E.D. performed the experiments and analyses.  None declared.  The following  Supporting Information  is available in the online version of this article –   Table S1.  List of the up- and down-regulated transcript-derived fragments obtained from the cDNA-AFLP data.  We thank Dr Jose Luis Garcia-Martinez (Universidad Politécnica de Valencia, Spain) for the construct of  DR5 :: GUS . We are grateful to Gerard van der Weerden (Botanical Gardens, Radboud University Nijmegen, The Netherlands) for seed material, the gardeners who helped to grow and maintain our plants, Dr Liesbeth Pierson for helping with microscopic imaging, and Jan Zethof and Peter de Groot for general technical assistance. We also thank Judith Rotink for her contribution to the transformation of  S. dulcamara . 