Suppression of annual <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> by perennial <italic>Agropyron cristatum</italic>: roles of soil nitrogen availability and biological soil spaceSeedling growth of intermountain perennial and weedy annual grassesMerits of native and introduced Triticeae grasses on semiarid rangelandsEcological impacts of cheatgrass and resultant fire on ecosystems in the Western Great BasinIntraspecific and interspecific pair-wise seedling competition between exotic annual grasses and native perennials: plant–soil relationshipsMineral nitrogen in a crested wheatgrass stand: implications for suppression of cheatgrassSuppression of <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> L. by established perennial grasses: I. Potential mechanismsSoil engineering facilitates downy brome (<italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>) growth—a case studyPlant–soil relationships of <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> L: interactions among labile carbon additions, soil invasion status, and fertilizerGeographical aspects of invasion: the annual bromesGrowth patterns of perennial grasses in the annual grassland type of southwest OregonEffects of established perennial grasses on yields of associated annual weedsEffects of increased soil nitrogen on the dominance of alien annual plants in the Mojave DesertRestoration ecology and invasive plants in the semiarid WestNitrogen availability indicesResilience to stress and disturbance, and resistance to <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> L. invasion in cold desert shrublands of western North AmericaAnnual and perennial grass growth on nitrogen-depleted decomposed graniteStability of exotic annual grasses following restoration efforts in southern California coastal sage scrubIncreasing native diversity of cheatgrass-dominated rangeland through assisted successionExotic plant species as problems and solutions in ecological restoration: a synthesisEcological resistance in theory and practiceBiological invasions by exotic grasses, the grass/fire cycle, and global changeRestoring the sagebrush component in crested wheatgrass–dominated communitiesInvasive weeds in rangelands: species, impacts, and managementAlien plant invasion and their impact on indigenous species diversity at global scale: a reviewEffectiveness of rehabilitation practices following wildfire in a degraded big sagebrush-downy brome communityA place for alien species in ecosystem restorationCrested wheatgrass-cheatgrass seedling competition in a mixed-density designFire, native species, and soil resource interactions influence the spatio-temporal invasion pattern of <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>Morphology and response of roots of pasture species to phosphorus and nitrogen nutritionEffects of soil resources on plant invasion and community structure in Californian serpentine grasslandCompetition as a barrier to establishment of a native perennial grass (<italic>Elymus elymoides</italic>) in alien annual grass (<italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>) communitiesRevegetating weed-infested rangeland: what we've learnedLinking nitrogen partitioning and species abundance to invasion resistance in the Great BasinNitrogen-inorganic formsCheatgrass (<italic>Bromus tectorum L</italic>) dominance in the Great Basin desert: history, persistence, and influences to human activitiesDirect and indirect effects of exotic annual grasses on species composition of a South Australian grasslandDevelopment of a DTPA soil test for zinc, iron, manganese, and copperInvasion of <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> L. into western North America: an ecological chronicleNitrogen uptake by perennial and invasive annual grass seedlings: nitrogen form effectsIs physical space a soil resource?The occupation and fragmentation of space: consequences of neighbouring rootsInvasion resistance and persistence: established plants win, even with disturbance and high propagule pressureEffects of nitrogen limitation on species replacement dynamics during early secondary succession on a semiarid sagebrush siteGrasses as invasive alien plants in South AfricaContrasting responses of Intermountain West grasses to soil nitrogenEffects of shade, litter and root competition on old-field vegetation in South CarolinaImmiscible displacement of the soil solution by centrifugationComponents of relative growth rate and sensitivity to nitrogen availability in annual and perennial species of <italic>Bromus</italic>Inhibition of nitrite-oxidizers by roots of grassPlant diversity increases resistance to invasion in the absence of covarying extrinsic factorsImpacts of exotic annual brome grasses (<italic>Bromus</italic> spp.) on ecosystem properties of northern mixed grass prairieRestoration of <italic>Themeda australis</italic> swards suppresses soil nitrate and enhances ecological resistance to invasion by exotic annualsRoot competition: beyond resource depletion<italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> invasion in South America: Patagonia under threat?Community invasibility, recruitment limitation, and grassland biodiversityNitrogen enhances the competitive ability of cheatgrass (<italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>) relative to native grassesInteractions between individual plant species and soil nutrient status in shortgrass steppeSpecies effects on nitrogen cycling: a test with perennial grassesSurvival of downy brome (<italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>) seed in four environmentsEcology and management of medusahead (<italic>Taeniatherum caput-medusae</italic> ssp. <italic>asperum</italic> [SIMK.] MELDERIS)Nitrogen interactions with medusahead (<italic>Taeniatherum caput-medusae</italic> ssp. <italic>asperum</italic>) seedbanks<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> InderjitSagebrush (<italic>Artemisia</italic>) rangelands of the western United States are becoming dominated by the exotic annual grass cheatgrass (<italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>). Rehabilitation of invaded rangelands is predicated on establishing healthy and dense perennial grass communities, which suppress cheatgrass. Our research investigated how established plants of the perennial grass, crested wheatgrass (<italic>Agropyron cristatum</italic>), suppress cheatgrass. Our data suggest that established crested wheatgrass reduces soil nitrogen availability and occupies biological soil space such that growth of cheatgrass is significantly reduced. Greater understanding of the role of biological soil space could be used to breed and select plant materials with traits that are more suppressive to invasive annual grasses.Worldwide, exotic invasive grasses have caused numerous ecosystem perturbations. Rangelands of the western USA have experienced increases in the size and frequency of wildfires largely due to invasion by the annual grass <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic>. Rehabilitation of invaded rangelands is difficult; but long-term success is predicated on establishing healthy and dense perennial grass communities, which suppress <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. This paper reports on two experiments to increase our understanding of soil factors involved in suppression. Water was not limiting in this study. Growth of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> in soil conditioned by and competing with the exotic perennial <italic>Agropyron cristatum</italic> was far less relative to its growth without competition. When competing with <italic>A. cristatum</italic>, replacing a portion of conditioned soil with fresh soil before sowing of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> did not significantly increase its growth. The ability of conditioned soil to suppress <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was lost when it was separated from growing <italic>A. cristatum</italic>. Soil that suppressed <italic>B. tectorum</italic> growth was characterized by low mineral nitrogen (N) availability and a high molar ratio of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> in the solution-phase pool of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> Moreover, resin availability of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> explained 66 % of the variability in <italic>B. tectorum</italic> above-ground mass, attesting to the importance of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> growth in reducing N availability to <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. Trials in which <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was suppressed the most were characterized by very high shoot/root mass ratios and roots that have less root hair growth relative to non-suppressed counterparts, suggesting co-opting of biological soil space by the perennial grass as another suppressive mechanism. Greater understanding of the role of biological soil space could be used to breed and select plant materials with traits that are more suppressive to invasive annual grasses.Invasive exotic grasses are causing ecosystem perturbations with lasting consequences worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C36">Lenz <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C51">Ogle <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C44">Milton 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C24">Dogra <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C54">Speziale <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). Especially pernicious invaders are the exotic annual grasses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C23">DiTomaso 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C9">Blumler 2006</xref>). Rehabilitation of annual grass-degraded lands can be exceedingly difficult, expensive and prone to failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C60">Young 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C32">Jacobs <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C17">Cox and Allen 2008</xref>).(A) A far too typical landscape scene in northern Nevada, USA, several years after a wildfire. This landscape, once occupied by <italic>Artemisia wyomingesis</italic> and perennial grasses, is now dominated by <italic>B. tectorum</italic> and represents an environment exceedingly difficult to rehabilitate. Photographic examples showing perennial grass suppression of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. (B) A high-elevation community in the Virginia Range, Nevada, USA. In the foreground is the native perennial <italic>Pseudoroegneria spicata</italic> with no presence of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. (C) <italic>Agropyron cristatum</italic> sown after a wildfire in the early 1990s near Midas, Nevada. Although individual plants suppress <italic>B. tectorum</italic>, the density of perennial grasses is insufficient to prevent re-invasion by the exotic annual. Surface soil litter is mainly from <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. (D) A dense and robust community of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> planted after a 1985 wildfire near the Peterson Range, Nevada, which should resist re-invasion by <italic>B. tectorum</italic> if managed properly. Characteristic of all these suppressed areas is a ring around the perennial grasses that contain no plants of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> even though seedbank analyses indicate the presence of germinable seeds.Fortunately, some plant communities resist invasion by <italic>B. tectorum</italic>; they are able to suppress its growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C33">James <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C5">Blank and Morgan 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C15">Chambers <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). Common threads to this resistance/suppression are well-established, healthy, and properly-spaced populations of perennial grasses (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV006F1">1</xref>B–D, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C31">Humphrey and Schupp 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C42">McGlone <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Understanding how soil biochemical attributes affect suppression and how these attributes interact with a perennial grass offers hope of greater success in rehabilitating exotic annual grass-degraded ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C20">D'Antonio and Thomsen 2004</xref>). The nature of suppression is complex and involves biotic and abiotic processes that temporally interact with soil type, the array of plant communities and characteristics of the invasive species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C30">Huenneke <italic>et al</italic>. 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C55">Tilman 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C50">Naeem <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C28">Gundale <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Established perennial plants can simply reduce soil resources to levels below which annual grasses are no longer as competitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C58">Wedin and Tilman 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C16">Claassen and Marler 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C52">Prober and Lunt 2009</xref>). Suppression of annual grasses may also involve root competition other than nutrient depletion whence perennial roots simply occupy biological soil space and, through chemical signalling, allelopathy included, may forestall competing roots from entering their space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C46">Monk and Gabrielson 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C41">McConnaughay and Bazzaz 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C53">Schenk 2006</xref>).In a previous study, we explored the mechanistic underpinnings of perennial grass suppression of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C6">Blank and Morgan 2012<italic>b</italic></xref>). The data suggest that perennial grass roots reduced soil nitrogen (N) and phosphorous (P) availability and occupied biological soil space, thereby reducing <italic>B. tectorum</italic> growth. This paper reports on additional experiments to more definitively elucidate soil factors involved in suppression of <italic>B. tectorum.</italic> The perennial grass used was <italic>Agropyron cristatum</italic>, a native to Russia and central Asia. This grass is often used to rehabilitate degraded rangelands in the western USA, and well-established stands effectively suppress <italic>B. tectorum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C25">Evans and Young 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C59">Wicks 1997</xref>). Two hypotheses were tested: (i) soil conditioning brought about by established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> will reduce availability of soil mineral N and P to levels low enough to significantly reduce growth <italic>of B. tectorum</italic>, and (ii) occupation of biological soil space by roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> will cause roots of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> to alter their architecture, morphology and activity resulting in reduced growth, i.e. suppression.Two experiments were conducted in a greenhouse at Reno, NV, USA (39°32′17.20″N; 119°48′22.89″W). Prior to each experiment, soil substrate was freshly collected from a <italic>Krascheninnikovia lanata</italic> (winterfat) site, invaded by <italic>B. tectorum</italic> for about 12 years, ∼80 km northwest of Reno, NV, USA (40°7′59.43″N; 120°6′56.18″W). This soil, conditioned by <italic>B. tectorum</italic>, has elevated soil N availability relative to nearby soil conditioned by native vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C7">Blank and Morgan 2013</xref>). Surface soils (0–25 cm, corresponding to the A horizon) were composited from an area of ∼10 m<sup>2</sup>. Soils, loamy sand in texture, were sieved to &lt;4 mm to remove coarse fragments and medium-to-large roots and homogenized by hand mixing on a greenhouse bench. Four replicates of this soil were analysed for various attributes (see below). This original soil—referred to as fresh soil—is taken from a soil classified as a coarse-loamy, mixed, superactive, calcareous, mesic Typic Torriorthent.Experiment 1 quantified the suppression of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> (cheatgrass) by established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> (crested wheatgrass). Twelve replicate clear plastic rhizotrons, 5 × 30 × 100 cm depth, were filled with equal volumes of soil. The outsides of the rhizotrons were covered with insulation that could be removed from the back to observe rooting patterns. Prior to seed planting, rhizotrons were paired in adjoining plastic containers to maintain a slight angle so that roots would readily intercept the clear rhizotron backing for observation, and deionized water was added to reach field capacity—∼6 % by weight for the soils used—over the entire rhizotron. Two seeds of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> were sown in the rhizotrons 6 cm from each edge to leave an 18 cm space in between for later planting of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>, and allowed to establish for 68 days, the conditioning phase. We define conditioning as the plant species-dependent engendering specific traits such as carbon flow, root exudation, nutrient uptake, root occupancy of soil space, alteration of the soil microbial community etc. that might affect competitive interactions. During establishment, <italic>A. cristatum</italic> was supplemented with 500–1000 mL of deionized water per week depending on depletion in the rhizotron as gauged by visual inspection when opaque backs were removed. After establishment, four treatments were randomly imposed to three replicate rhizotrons. In one treatment, <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was sown directly between <italic>A. cristatum</italic> in the conditioned soil as a test for maximal suppression. For the next treatment, 500 g of soil were removed from between the established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> plants, replaced with 500 g of fresh soil and <italic>B. tectorum</italic> sown in the new soil. The purpose of this treatment was to test how fresh soil mitigated against suppression. In another treatment, 500 g of conditioned soil were removed from between the established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> plants; then a nylon mesh (2-mm opening) was placed in the excavated area, 500 g of fresh soil were placed over the mesh and <italic>B. tectorum</italic> sown. Our purpose was to examine how reduced root movement into the fresh soil from <italic>A. cristatum</italic>, but still allowing diffusion of gases, solutes and microbes from the adjacent conditioned soil, affects suppression. For the last treatment, 500 g of soil were removed from between the established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> plants; then a plastic barrier was placed in the hole and filled with 500 g of fresh soil, and sown to <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. This treatment tested <italic>B. tectorum</italic> suppression upon total blocking of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> roots, which would affect biological soil space and exposure to potential pathogenic organisms and allelochemicals in soil conditioned by <italic>A. cristatum</italic>. Deionized water was immediately applied to soil above the newly sown seeds of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. A small subsample of the homogenized 500 g conditioned soil was analysed for several soil attributes (see below). We also grew <italic>B. tectorum</italic> without competition in small containers filled with 500 g of either fresh soil or conditioned soil (from the soil excavated from rhizotrons). During growth of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>, rhizotrons and containers were watered twice weekly; water was not limiting to <italic>B. tectorum</italic> in this study. Supplemental lighting, using four high-pressure sodium lamps each producing 124 000 lumens at 2100 K temperature, was used to assure at least 12 h of daylight. After 70 days of growth, <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was clipped at the soil surface, dried for 48 h at 70 °C and weight recorded. Soil within the rooting zone of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was excavated and roots reserved. Subsamples of roots from each treatment and replicates were washed, immediately observed with a light microscope and photographs taken. These subsamples were then added to the original sample, dried for 48 h at 70 °C and weight recorded. After harvest, soil within the rooting zone of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> of each treatment was homogenized and analysed for solution-phase anions (Cl<sup>−</sup>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>ortho</italic>-P) using immiscible displacement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C47">Mubarak and Olsen 1976</xref>) with quantification by ion chromatography (Dionex<sup>®</sup> AS11-HC column with gradient elution) and mineral N, defined as <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> by 1.5 M KCl extraction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C34">Keeney and Nelson 1982</xref>).Experiment 2 explored the role of soil nutrient availability of N and P in the suppression process and tested to a greater extent if and how conditioned soil affects suppression. Twelve rhizotrons were filled with freshly collected soil and planted to <italic>A. cristatum</italic> (see Experiment 1). Soil was conditioned by <italic>A. cristatum</italic> for 64 days with lighting and watering as described for Experiment 1. Four treatments were imposed following conditioning by <italic>A. cristatum</italic>. In four randomly chosen rhizotrons, <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was sown directly between established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> to test for maximal suppression (Treatment 1). The remaining eight rhizotrons had their backs removed and soil was separated by depths (0–30 cm (Treatment 2), 30–60 cm (Treatment 3) and 60–90 cm (Treatment 4)), and homogenized along with any roots present. For each soil depth separate, 2500 g was placed in containers and <italic>B. tectorum</italic> immediately sown. These treatments tested the suppressive ability of conditioned soil, by depth, without live plants of <italic>A. cristatum</italic>, but with different amounts of now inactive roots present depending on soil depth, greatest in the 0–30 cm depth increment and least in the 60–90 cm depth increment. In similar-sized containers, <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was sown in fresh soil to serve as unsuppressed controls (six replicates). To gauge the influence of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> growth on post-harvest soil attributes, five replicates of unplanted controls in fresh soil were prepared in similar-sized containers. For all experimental units, one anion and cation exchange resin capsule (Unibest<sup>®</sup>) was placed at 15 cm directly beneath where <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was sown to gauge nutrient availability. After 64 days of growth, above-ground and root biomass of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> were harvested, dried and weighed. Resin capsules were removed, washed extensively with deionized water, dried and treated with 40 mL of 1 N HCl and shaken for 30 min. Resin availability of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>ortho</italic>-P were quantified using a Lachat<sup>®</sup> autoanalyser. Soil in the rooting zone of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was homogenized and analysed for mineral N and soil-solution anions as stated in Experiment 1. Availability of micronutrients was determined using the DTPA method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C37">Lindsay and Norvell 1978</xref>). Nitrogen mineralization potential was quantified using a moist 30-day incubation procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C14">Bundy and Meisinger 1994</xref>). Total soil C and N were quantified using a LECO Truspec<sup>®</sup> analyser.The data structure for Experiment 1 includes eight treatments with replication for a total of 38 experimental units. Experiment 2 had 10 treatments with replication for a total of 43 experimental units. For each experiment, a separate ANOVA was performed and means separated using Tukey's honest significant difference test. A backward selective regression was used to identify variables possibly related to above-ground <italic>B. tectorum</italic> biomass. The procedure was applied separately to Experiments 1 and 2 and to the combined data set.Above-ground biomass and shoot/root mass ratios of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> plants following harvest of Experiments 1 and 2. For each panel, ANOVA results are provided and bars with non-overlapping letters are significantly different at the ≤0.05 level.Selected soil attributes for Experiment 1.<sup>1</sup><sup>1</sup>For each column, means with different superscripted letters are significantly different at the &lt;0.05 level; mineral N is total <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation10" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> extractable by KCl; mole <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> is the molar proportion of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> in the solution-phase pool of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation13" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> Attributes unaffected by treatment included solution-phase <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation14" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation15" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><sup>2</sup>Soil from a homogenized subsample taken between <italic>A. cristatum</italic> that established for 60 days in rhizotrons.<sup>3</sup>Soil from a homogenized subsample taken from the rooting zone of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> in competition with <italic>A. cristatum</italic> in rhizotrons.<sup>4</sup>Soil from homogenized subsamples of the fresh soil and the fresh soil placed above the mesh or plastic barrier in rhizotrons.<sup>5</sup>Soil from a homogenized subsample of entire container.Similar to Experiment 1, established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> suppressed the growth of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> relative to its non-competed growth in fresh or conditioned soil (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV006F1">1</xref>). Suppressed <italic>B. tectorum</italic>, akin to Experiment 1, had very high shoot to root mass ratios. Growth of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> was not nearly as suppressed when grown in conditioned soil taken from three depths in rhizotrons planted to <italic>A. cristatum</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV006F1">1</xref>). Moreover, shoot to root mass ratios of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> grown non-competed in this conditioned soil were similar to those of non-competed <italic>B. tectorum</italic> grown in fresh soil (Experiment 1).Selected soil attributes for Experiment 2.<sup>1</sup><sup>1</sup>For each column, means with different superscripted letters are significantly different at the &lt;0.05 level; mineral N is total <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation23" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> extractable by KCl; resin N includes <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation24" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> mole <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation25" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> is the molar proportion of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation26" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> in the solution-phase pool of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation27" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> nd, not determined. Attributes unaffected by treatment included 30-day aerobic incubated NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> and NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>, net N mineralization potentials, total C and N, and DTPA extractable Fe and Cu.<sup>2</sup>Soils taken after 64 days conditioning by <italic>A. cristatum</italic> from rhizotrons and homogenized by depth.<sup>3</sup>Soils collected from within rooting zone of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> in rhizotrons that were conditioned by <italic>A. cristatum</italic> for 64 days.<sup>4</sup>Soils from homogenized sample of entire container.Graphs showing variables strongly related to above-ground biomass as determined by backward selection regression. Top graph, combined Experiments 1 and 2, relates root biomass with above-ground biomass. Middle graph relates resin availability of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation29" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> with above-ground biomass; resin data were only collected for Experiment 2. Bottom graph, combined Experiments 1 and 2, relates predicted above-ground biomass using the combination of root biomass and solution-phase <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation30" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>It is not surprising that lowered soil N availability, due to established <italic>A. cristatum</italic>, would suppress the growth of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. Many annual grasses, including <italic>B. tectorum</italic>, are nitrophiles and their growth is stimulated by additions of mineral N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C30">Huenneke <italic>et al</italic>. 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C12">Brooks 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C56">Vasquez <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Conversely, growth of annual grasses are often suppressed when mineral N is lowered by manipulating solution culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C48">Muller and Garnier 1990</xref>) or by addition of labile C sources that immobilize soil N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C43">McLendon and Redente 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C61">Young <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C8">Blank and Young 2009</xref>).Besides availability of N, other aspects of the soil N cycle may be involved, at least tangentially, in suppression of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. Soil conditioned by <italic>A. cristatum</italic> and competing with <italic>B. tectorum</italic> had very high molar proportions of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation31" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> in the solution-phase <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation32" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> pool (Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV006TB1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV006TB2">2</xref>). Moreover, that soils only conditioned by <italic>A. cristatum</italic> prior to sowing <italic>B. tectorum</italic> had far lower molar <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation33" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> levels suggests that the grasses interact with the soil differently when combined than they do individually. Perennial grasses differentially affect soil N cycling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C58">Wedin and Tilman 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C57">Vinton and Burke 1995</xref>), but we are unaware of any literature that tested the combined effect of a perennial grass and an annual grass on the soil N cycle. Roots of grasses can inhibit nitrite-oxidizers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C49">Munro 1966</xref>); but why then did the greatest molar content occur only upon growth of <italic>B. tectorum. Bromus tectorum</italic> has high affinity to uptake N in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation34" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> form relative the <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation35" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C39">MacKown <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>), but we are unaware of any data on its ability to uptake the <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation36" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> form. If <italic>B. tectorum</italic> does not have a high affinity to uptake the <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation37" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> form, then perennial grasses that inhibit nitrate-oxidizers would likely elevated their suppressive ability.We accept hypothesis 2 that occupation of biological soil space by established roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> will suppress growth of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. Compelling aspects of our data include high shoot to root ratios of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> when competing with established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV006F2">2</xref>), response of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> to varying soil treatments (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV006F2">2</xref>), and distinct elongated root architectures with far fewer root hairs in the most suppressed trials. The concept of biological soil space implies that physical space is a resource in itself, beyond that of access to nutrients and water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C40">McConnaughay and Bazzaz 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C41">1992</xref>). In this construct, occupation of physical space by roots of established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> will constrain root growth of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. The mechanistic underpinnings of suppression via biological soil space may involve root signalling or root toxicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C53">Schenk 2006</xref>). It is possible that the elevated shoot to root ratios in <italic>B. tectorum</italic> competing against established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> in this study is likely less due to reduced availability of N than interactions with pre-existing roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic>. Low soil N availability should stimulate rather than decrease root growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C29">Hill <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). If reduced biological soil space due to established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> roots is partly responsible for suppression of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>; then replacement of conditioned soil between established <italic>A. cristatum</italic> plants should have increased biological space for <italic>B. tectorum</italic> root growth and also increased nutrient availability resulting in less suppression—yet suppression still occurred. One possibility is that roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> may have proliferated in the fresh soil and simply occupied soil space faster than roots of the newly sown <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. Visual inspection upon harvesting <italic>B. tectorum</italic> did reveal the presence of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> roots. Moreover, very low post-harvest mineral N levels in the fresh soil (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV006TB1">1</xref>) lend support to the re-occupation of biological soil space by <italic>A. cristatum</italic> as such small plants of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> simply could not have depleted that much mineral N. We also expected a mesh would limit new root encroachment by <italic>A. cristatum</italic> and the fresh soil placed above the mesh would have much un-occupied biological soil space for roots of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> to proliferate; yet, <italic>B. tectorum</italic> planted in this soil was still suppressed and had high shoot to root ratios. Indeed, as the mesh was removed from the rhizotrons following harvest of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>, visible inspection indicated very few roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> had penetrated the mesh. Nonetheless, the fresh soil added above the mesh had very low mineral N content after harvest, in fact the lowest among all the treatments. Clearly, enough <italic>A. cristatum</italic> roots had penetrated the mesh to reduce mineral N content and thereby partially suppressed <italic>B. tectorum</italic> via lowered N availability. In all individual trials of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> competing with established <italic>A. cristatum</italic>, no matter the treatment, post-harvest <italic>B. tectorum</italic> had high shoot to root ratios (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV006F2">2</xref>) and decreased root hair formation. Recent research has demonstrated that root competition is far more complex than simple resource depletion (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C53">Schenk 2006</xref>). In this new construct of root to root interactions, it is possible that newly establishing roots of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> sense the presence of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> roots and do not grow appreciably into the fresh soil provided. Alternatively, established roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> may exude toxic substances that affect <italic>B. tectorum</italic> root architecture; unfortunately our experimental protocols are not able to rigorously test this conjecture.Soil conditioned by <italic>A. cristatum</italic>, then homogenized (roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> were also homogenized), potted and sown to <italic>B. tectorum</italic> produced far more above-ground biomass than it did when competing with <italic>A. cristatum</italic>. Our expectation was that the conditioned soil separated from <italic>A. cristatum</italic> would retain its ability to suppress <italic>B. tectorum</italic> because the soil would have depleted N availability, at least initially. Moreover, we expected conditioned soil from the 0–30 cm depth increment would have greater filling of biological soil space with established roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> and therefore be more suppressive to <italic>B. tectorum</italic> than conditioned soil from lower depths. In fact, conditioned soil removed from rhizotrons did not suppress <italic>B. tectorum</italic> and shoot to root mass ratios were not elevated as in competed trials. Lack of suppression in this situation may be explained by the following. Firstly, the now dead roots of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> have mineralized and contributed N to enhance <italic>B. tectorum</italic> growth. The relatively high mineral N and resin available N levels post-harvest for these trials lend credence to this possibility. Secondly, the lack of an established root system of <italic>A. cristatum</italic> due to homogenization prior to sowing <italic>B. tectorum</italic> in containers may free up biological soil space for <italic>B. tectorum</italic> resulting in lower root to root signalling and exudation of toxins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C53">Schenk 2006</xref>).We expected that <italic>B. tectorum</italic> growing in the fresh soil above the plastic barrier in the rhizotrons would have above-ground biomass similar to its growth, non-competed, in fresh soil. Why then did the plastic barrier facilitate even greater growth of <italic>B. tectorum</italic>? Speculating, given the equal watering regimes used in all experimental units, the plastic barrier could have reduced water flow beyond the rooting zone of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> and essentially provided greater water availability.The non-native perennial grass <italic>A. cristatum</italic>, when established, suppresses the growth of the exotic annual grass, <italic>B. tectorum</italic>. Reduced soil N availability and co-opting of soil space by perennial grass roots are potential soil factors involved in suppression. If only it were as easy to establish perennial grasses on <italic>B. tectorum</italic>-invaded rangelands as it is in the greenhouse, rehabilitation of <italic>B. tectorum</italic> degraded rangelands would be easier and far less expensive. The use of non-native plant materials to facilitate rehabilitation of exotic annual grass-invaded rangelands is controversial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C19">D'Antonio and Meyerson 2002</xref>). Some researchers, however, make the case that particular non-natives possess attributes that allow faster and more effective rehabilitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C2">Asay <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C26">Ewel and Putz 2004</xref>). The reality that <italic>A. cristatum</italic> suppresses <italic>B. tectorum</italic> so effectively offers opportunities to use this species and other non-native competitive grasses as a successional bridge to encourage subsequent native plant recruitment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C18">Cox and Anderson 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C13">Brown <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C22">Davies <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Perennial grasses differ markedly in their ability to suppress annual grasses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C10">Borman <italic>et al</italic>. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C11">1991</xref>). A portion of the suppressive ability <italic>of A. cristatum</italic> is via utilization of soil N resources such that it is less available to <italic>B. tectorum</italic>; however, the annual is also an effective competitor for soil N (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV006C45">Monaco <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>). If perennial grasses do not strongly couple root uptake of N with the timing of its availability in soil, pulses of availability can occur leading to less suppression. We believe greater understanding of aspects of suppression via biological soil space can be a fruitful area of research. What specific properties do established perennial grasses engender to biological soil space to resist subsequent growth of alien annual grasses? Is allelopathy involved? Is alteration of the soil microbial community involved? Understanding specific mechanisms could direct plant breeding strategies to develop perennial grasses more suppressive to exotic annual grasses.This research is funded through <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">USDA-Agricultural Research Service</grant-sponsor> Project No: <grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">5370-13610-001-00D</grant-num>.R.R.B. designed the experiment, analysed the data and was the principle writer. T.M. designed and built rhizotrons. T.M. and F.A. collected soils, monitored the experiments and conducted soil analyses.None declared.We thank the associate editor and anonymous reviewers for constructive criticisms leading to a more impactful paper.