Chloroplast genes as genetic markers for inferring patterns of change, maternal ancestry and phylogenetic relationships among <italic>Eleusine</italic> speciesDevelopment and use of chloroplast microsatellites in <italic>Phaseolus</italic> spp. and other legumesPhylogenetic relationships in the ‘true citrus fruit trees’ revealed by PCR–RFLP analysis of cpDNAComparative analysis organelle DNAs in acid citrus grown in Japan using PCR–RFLP methodAn overview of the DNA barcoding of plantsProtein, calcium, iron and amino acid content of selected wild and domesticated cultivars of finger milletMapping of rDNA on the chromosomes of <italic>Eleusine</italic> species by fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridizationGenomic in situ hybridization identifies genome donor of finger millet (<italic>Eleusine coracana</italic>)Identification of genome donors to the wild species of finger millet, <italic>Eleusine africana</italic> by genomic <italic>in situ</italic> hybridizationGenome organization and polyploid evolution in the genus <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Poaceae)Polymorphic simple sequence repeat markers in chloroplast genomes of solanaceous plantsFinger millet <italic>Eleusine coracana</italic>Genome analysis of <italic>Eleusine coracana</italic> (L.) GaertnA set of universal primers for amplification of polymorphic non-coding regions of mitochondrial and chloroplast DNA in plantsGenome interrelationship in the genus <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Poaceae) as revealed through heteroploid crossesChromosome pairing analysis in interspecific hybrids among tetraploid species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Poaceae)ASAP: amplification, sequencing &amp; annotation of plastomesFinger milletThe genetic map of finger millet, <italic>Eleusine coracana</italic>Population structure and diversity in finger millet (<italic>Eleusine coracana</italic>) germplasmIdentification of the ‘A’ genome of finger millet using chloroplast DNAEvolution of finger millet: evidence from random amplified polymorphic DNAEvolutionary implications of <italic>MATK</italic> indels in PoaceaeDomestication of <italic>Eleusine coracana</italic>Ribosomal DNA variation in finger millet and wild species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Poaceae)Systematics of <italic>Eleusine</italic> Gaertn. (Poaceae, Chloridoideae): chloroplast DNA and total evidenceFlavonoids and systematics of <italic>Eleusine</italic>Phylogeny of Poaceae inferred from matK sequencesThe complete sequence of the rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) chloroplast genome: intermolecular recombination between distinct tRNA genes accounts for a major plastid DNA inversion during the evolution of cerealsCytogenetical studies in wild and cultivated species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Gramineae)The quantitative nuclear DNA changes in <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Gramineae)The ‘A’ genome donor of <italic>Eleusine coracana</italic> (L.) Gaertn. (Gramineae)PCR–RFLP analysis of the whole chloroplast DNA from three cultivated species of cotton (<italic>Gossypium</italic> L.)Microsatellites and microsynteny in the chloroplast genomes of <italic>Oryza</italic> and eight other Gramineae speciesMolecular phylogeny in Indian <italic>Citrus</italic> L. (Rutaceae) inferred through PCR–RFLP and trnL–trnF sequence data of chloroplast DNAIdentification of chloroplast DNA variations by PCR–RFLP analysis in <italic>Dendranthema</italic>Phylogenetic analysis based on 18S rRNA gene and <italic>mat</italic>K gene sequences of <italic>Panax vietnamensis</italic> and five related speciesPCR–RFLP analysis of chloroplast gene regions in <italic>Cajanus</italic> (Leguminosae) and allied generaAllotetraploid origin and divergence in <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Chloridoideae, Poaceae): evidence from low-copy nuclear gene phylogenies and a plastid gene chronogramNomenclature of finger millet (Poaceae)Rapid isolation of high molecular weight plant DNANuclear DNA content in species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Gramineae): a critical re-evaluation using laser flow cytometryMathematical model for studying genetic variation in terms of restriction endonucleasesEleusinePhylogeny of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Poaceae: Chloridoideae) based on nuclear ITS and plastid <italic>trnT</italic>–<italic>trnF</italic> sequencesSectional relationship in the genus <italic>Musa</italic> L. inferred from the PCR–RFLP of organelle DNA sequencesMolecular phylogeny of mangroves VII. PCR–RFLP of <italic>trn</italic>S–<italic>psb</italic>C and <italic>rbc</italic>L gene regions in 24 mangrove and mangrove-associated speciesSpecies identification in seven small millet species using polymerase chain reaction–restriction fragment length polymorphism of <italic>trn</italic>S–<italic>psb</italic>C gene regionA survey of the <italic>Eleusine</italic> Gaertn. (Gramineae) in AfricaPoaceae (Gramineae)Genetic diversity and relationships in <italic>Solanum</italic> subg. <italic>Archaesolanum</italic> (Solanaceae) based on RAPD and chloroplast PCR–RFLP analysesPolymorphic simple sequence repeat regions in chloroplast genomes: applications to the population genetics of pinesHypervariable microsatellites provide a general source of polymorphic DNA markers for the chloroplast genomeGenepool variation in genus <italic>Glycine</italic> subgenus <italic>soja</italic> revealed by polymorphic nuclear and chloroplast microsatellitesDietary management of finger millet (<italic>Eleusine coracana</italic> L. Gaerth) controls diabetesChloroplast DNA variability in wild and cultivated rice (<italic>Oryza</italic> spp.) revealed by polymorphic chloroplast simple sequence repeatsPolymorphic chloroplast simple sequence repeat primers for synthetic and population studies in the genus <italic>Hordeum</italic>Chloroplast microsatellites: new tools for studies in plant ecology and evolutionThe neighbour-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic treesCytology and genome relations in some species of Eleusine and its alliesAssessment of genome origins and genetic diversity in the genus <italic>Eleusine</italic> with DNA markersGenome differentiation patterns in diploid species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Poaceae)Chloroplast DNA diversity reveals the contribution of the two wild species in the origin and evolution of diploid safflower (<italic>Carthamus tinctorius</italic> L.)The complete nucleotide sequence of tobacco chloroplast genome: its gene organization and expressionUniversal primers for amplification of three non-coding regions of chloroplast DNAMEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methodsThe Clustal X Windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis toolsMolecular phylogeny of conifers using RFLP analysis of PCR-amplified specific chloroplast genesMolecular phylogeny of Dipterocarpaceae in Southeast Asia using RFLP of PCR-amplified chloroplast genesPhylogenetic analysis of highland papayas (<italic>Vasconcellea</italic>) and allied genera (Caricaeae) using PCR–RFLPA set of conserved PCR primers for the analysis of simple sequence repeat polymorphisms in chloroplast genomes of dicotyledonous angiospermsDuplicated gene expression for isocitrate dehydrogenase and 6-phosphogluconate dehydrogenase in diploid species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Gramineae)Isozyme of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (Gramineae) and the origin of finger milletPhylogenetic relationship in the genus <italic>Panax</italic>: inferred from chloroplast <italic>trn</italic>K gene and nuclear 18S rRNA gene sequencesThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Phylogenetic relationship between the nine species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> was investigated based on RFLP of the seven amplified chloroplast genes/intergenic spacers, <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence and cpSSR markers. The maternal genome donor (<italic>E. indica</italic>, 2n=2x=18) of the allotetraploid (2n=4x=36, 2n=2x=38) <italic>Eleusine</italic> species, and the phylogenetic relationships between cultivated <italic>E. coracana</italic> (2n=4x=36) and wild species have been successfully resolved. The species-specific markers were also identified. The explicit identification of the maternal parent and that of the immediate wild progenitor of finger millet will be immensely useful for future genetic improvement and biotechnological program(s) of the crop species.Assessment of phylogenetic relationships is an important component of any successful crop improvement programme, as wild relatives of the crop species often carry agronomically beneficial traits. Since its domestication in East Africa, <italic>E</italic><italic>leusine coracana</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36), a species belonging to the genus <italic>Eleusine</italic> (<italic>x</italic> = 8, 9, 10), has held a prominent place in the semi-arid regions of India, Nepal and Africa. The patterns of variation between the cultivated and wild species reported so far and the interpretations based upon them have been considered primarily in terms of nuclear events. We analysed, for the first time, the phylogenetic relationship between finger millet (<italic>E. coracana</italic>) and its wild relatives by species-specific chloroplast deoxyribonucleic acid (cpDNA) polymerase chain reaction–restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR–RFLP) and chloroplast simple sequence repeat (cpSSR) markers/sequences. Restriction fragment length polymorphism of the seven amplified chloroplast genes/intergenic spacers (<italic>trn</italic>K, <italic>psb</italic>D, <italic>psa</italic>A, <italic>trn</italic>H–<italic>trn</italic>K, <italic>trn</italic>L–<italic>trn</italic>F, <italic>16</italic>S and <italic>trn</italic>S–<italic>psb</italic>C), nucleotide sequencing of the chloroplast <italic>trn</italic>K gene and chloroplast microsatellite polymorphism were analysed in all nine known species of <italic>Eleusine</italic>. The RFLP of all seven amplified chloroplast genes/intergenic spacers and <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequences in the diploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 16, 18, 20) and allotetraploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 36, 38) species resulted in well-resolved phylogenetic trees with high bootstrap values. <italic>Eleusine coracana</italic>, <italic>E. africana</italic>, <italic>E. tristachya</italic>, <italic>E. indica</italic> and <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> did not show even a single change in restriction site. <italic>Eleusine intermedia</italic> and <italic>E. floccifolia</italic> were also shown to have identical cpDNA fragment patterns. The cpDNA diversity in <italic>Eleusine multiflora</italic> was found to be more extensive than that of the other eight species. The <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence data complemented the results obtained by PCR–RFLP. The maternal lineage of all three allotetraploid species (AABB, AADD) was the same, with <italic>E. indica</italic> being the maternal diploid progenitor species. The markers specific to certain species were also identified.The wild relatives of crop species often carry beneficial alleles that are effective against various biotic and abiotic stresses. They hold the key to successful crop improvement programmes through introgression of desired genes from wild to cultivated crop species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C18">Dida and Devos 2006</xref>). In this context, the assessment of phylogenetic relationships at the inter-specific level and the identification of gene pools are considered important. Based on chloroplast deoxyribonucleic acid (cpDNA) diversity, we obtained information on the molecular phylogeny of finger millet (<italic>Eleusine coracana)</italic> <italic>vis-à-vis</italic> its wild relatives.The genus <italic>Eleusine</italic> is a member of the tribe Eragrosteae, subfamily Chloridoideae and the family Poaceae. It is a small genus of nine species, which includes six diploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 16, 18, 20) and three polyploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36, 38) species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C9">Bisht and Mukai 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). These species are widely distributed in the tropical and subtropical regions of Africa, Asia and South America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C51">Phillips 1972</xref>). East Africa is considered to be the centre of diversity for the genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C9">Bisht and Mukai 2002</xref>).<italic>Eleusine coracana</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36), commonly known as finger millet or ragi, is the only economically important species of the genus. After sorghum and pearl millet, finger millet ranks third in cereal production in the semi-arid regions of the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C9">Bisht and Mukai 2002</xref>). It is widely cultivated in the arid and semi-arid regions of East Africa, India, Nepal and many other Asian countries for its grain and fodder value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C75">Verma 2009</xref>). The grain is widely used for preparing bread, cakes, soup, puddings, porridge and fermented beverages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C26">Hilu and deWet 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C11">Chandrashekar 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C46">Neves 2011</xref>). Finger millet is a rich source of essential amino acids and polyphenols, and it has comparatively higher levels of calcium and iron than other known cereals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C5">Barbeau and Hilu 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C11">Chandrashekar 2010</xref>). It has a number of medicinal properties as well, particularly in controlling blood sugar levels in diabetic patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C21">Duke and Wain 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C11">Chandrashekar 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C57">Pradhan <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).Plant materials used in the present study. <sup>a</sup>Dr. Mathews M. Dida, Kenya; USDA, United States Department of Agriculture, USA; ILRI, International Livestock Research Institute, Ethopia; NBPGR, National Bureau of Plant Genetic Resources, India. <sup>b</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C9">Bisht and Mukai (2002</xref>).In spite of the enormous amount of information, there still exists considerable disagreement over the identification of the diploid ancestors of the three polyploid species and the level of speciation and evolutionary relationships among the nine species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C51">Phillips 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C52">1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C28">Hilu and Johnson 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C42">Lye 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C6">Bisht and Mukai 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C7">2001<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C9">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C15">Devarumath <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). <italic>Eleusine coracana</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36) (AABB) is considered to be an allotetraploid and has been domesticated from its wild progenitor, <italic>Eleusine africana</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36) (AABB) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C12">Chennaveeraiah and Hiremath 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C26">Hilu and deWet 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C29">Hilu <italic>et al.</italic> 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C23">Hilu 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C24">1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C34">Hiremath and Salimath 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C78">Werth <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C28">Hilu and Johnson 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C6">Bisht and Mukai 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C7">2001<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C8"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C15">Devarumath <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C19">Dida <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C20">2008</xref>). The genetic maps generated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C19">Dida <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> showed that <italic>E. coracana</italic> and <italic>E. africana</italic> are allotetraploids. There is also strong evidence to suggest that <italic>Eleusine indica</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 18) (AA) is the maternal genome donor of <italic>E. coracana</italic> and <italic>E. africana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C23">Hilu 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C34">Hiremath and Salimath 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C28">Hilu and Johnson 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C6">Bisht and Mukai 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C7">2001<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C6">Bisht and Mukai (2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C7">2001<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C9">2002</xref>) indicated that <italic>Eleusine floccifolia</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 18) could be the BB donor species of <italic>E. coracana</italic>. This has, however, been refuted by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C34">Hiremath and Salimath 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C16">Devarumath <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). According to these authors, the BB genome donor species remains unidentified and may possibly be extinct. <italic>Eleusine kigeziensis</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36 or 38) (AADD) is the third tetraploid species of the genus. <italic>Eleusine indica</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 18) (AA) and <italic>E. jaegeri</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 20) (DD) are proposed to be the wild progenitors of <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C9">Bisht and Mukai 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C16">Devarumath <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). On the contrary, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> proposed <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> to be autotetraploid, with <italic>E. indica</italic> being closely related to <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> but not the direct genome donor to <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> have concluded that all three tetraploids (<italic>E. coracana, E. africana and E. kigeziensis</italic>) are of allotetraploid origin. They suggested independent origins of <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> and <italic>E. africana</italic>—<italic>E. coracana</italic>. They are of the view that both events may have involved the diploids <italic>E. indica</italic> and <italic>E. tristachya</italic> as maternal parents, but the paternal parents remain unidentified. <italic>Eleusine indica</italic> and <italic>E. tristachya</italic> are considered to be very similar and the degree of relationship between the two remains unresolved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C32">Hiremath and Chennaveeraiah 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C33">Hiremath and Salimath 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C27">Hilu and Johnson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C78">Werth <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C7">Bisht and Mukai 2001<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C8"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).In the present study, the cpDNA restriction site pattern variation of seven amplified chloroplast genes/intergenic spacers, the chloroplast <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence and cp microsatellite polymorphism were investigated for the first time in all nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species, with the objective of constructing the phylogeny of the genus <italic>Eleusine</italic> and identifying the maternal genome donors of the polyploid species including <italic>E. coracana</italic>. Both direct sequencing of the <italic>trn</italic>K gene and polymerase chain reaction–restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR–RFLP) of cpDNA regions and chloroplast simple sequence repeats (cpSSRs) are considered to be very good markers for detecting cpDNA variation. The chloroplast <italic>trn</italic>K gene (which also contains the <italic>mat</italic>K gene within the <italic>trn</italic>K gene intron) sequence has been effectively used for the construction of grass phylogenies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C25">Hilu and Alice 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C30">Hilu <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). The <italic>mat</italic>K gene sequence is one of the seven loci widely utilized for the DNA barcoding of plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C4">Babbar <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Specific chloroplast genes and/or intergenic spacers can be amplified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C69">Taberlet <italic>et al.</italic> 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C14">Demesure <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C72">Tsumura <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C73">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C17">Dhingra and Folta 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C22">Heinze 2005</xref>). The amplicons can be directly sequenced or restriction endonuclease digested (PCR–RFLP or cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence), and the occurrence of microsatellites (cpSSRs) in the chloroplast genome has been widely utilized for species identification, reconstruction of phylogenetic relationships, taxonomic studies and the identification of maternal parents in polyploids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C72">Tsumura <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C73">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C76">Weising and Gardner 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C36">Ishii and McCouch 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C40">Lakshmi <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C49">Parani <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C50">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C39">Komatsu <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C60">Provan <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C38">Kishimoto <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C48">Nwakanma <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C79">Zhu <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C2">Asadi Abkenar <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C3">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C74">Van Droogenbroeck <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C35">Ibrahim <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C1">Angioi <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C65">Sehgal <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C37">Jena <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C53">Poczai <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).Seeds of the <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and one outgroup species (<italic>Dactyloctenium aegyptium</italic>) utilized in the present study were obtained from the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) (Beltsville, MD, USA), the International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI) (Addis Ababa, Ethiopia), Dr Mathews M. Dida (Maseno University, Maseno, Kenya) and the National Bureau of Plant Genetic Resources (NBPGR) (New Delhi, India). The accession numbers and source of the seed material are given in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLT056TB1">1</xref>. The seeds were grown under controlled conditions in the experimental field of the Department of Botany, University of Delhi.The total genomic DNA of the <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and <italic>D. aegyptium</italic> was isolated from fresh young leaves using the cetyl trimethyl ammonium bromide method as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C43">Murray and Thompson (1980)</xref> with some modifications. Instead of a CsCl–ethidium bromide ultracentrifugation step, the DNA was purified by phenol–chloroform extraction.List of chloroplast genes/intergenic spacers amplified in the present study. <sup>a</sup>Sizes in source.Seven genes and intergenic spacers amplified from the chloroplast genome were separately restricted with 31 four-, five- and six-base cutter restriction endonucleases (AluI, AvaI, AccI, AfaI, BamHI, BalI, BglI, BglII, ClaI, DraI, EcoRV, EcoRI, HaeIII, HinfI, HindIII, HincII, MspI, KpnI, MboI, MluI, PstI, PvuII, SacI, SalI, SpeI, SphI, SmaI, SspI, TaqI, XhoI and XbaI). The 12.20 μL reaction mix contained 10 μL of the amplified gene product, 1.2 μL of enzyme buffer and 10 U of the restriction enzyme. After gentle mixing the mixture was incubated overnight at 37 °C (except for TaqI, which was incubated at 60 °C). The digestion was terminated by adding 1.5 μL of 10× loading buffer. The digested products were fractionated on 1.5 % agarose gels containing ethidium bromide (0.05 μg mL<sup>−1</sup>) in 0.5× TBE buffer. A DNA ladder mix was loaded alongside the digested products to serve as size markers. After agarose gel electrophoresis, the gel was photographed in ultraviolet light. Reproducibility of the patterns was tested by repeating all the reactions at least twice.For PCR–RFLP analysis, the presence (1) or absence (0) of a restriction fragment was recorded. Total and mean character differences between pairs of species were calculated using PAUP* 4.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C68">Swofford 2002</xref>). Nei and Li's coefficient of genetic distance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C45">Nei and Li 1979</xref>) was calculated between each pair of species after the optimality criterion was set to DISTANCE. Cluster analysis was carried out using the unweighted pair-group method using arithmetic averages (UPGMA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C67">Sneath and Sokal 1973</xref>) and neighbour-joining (NJ) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C61">Saitou and Nei 1987</xref>) methods. Bootstrap values were calculated from 100 replicates using the BOOTSTRAP command in PAUP.The <italic>trn</italic>K gene was amplified from the nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and one outgroup as described above. The amplification products were separated on a 1 % agarose gel, excised from the gel and purified using a QIA quick gel extraction kit (Qiagen, Germany). The purified amplification products were cloned and sequenced with an ABI PRISM 377 automated DNA sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). BLAST similarity searches were performed using the National Centre for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) BLASTN algorithm to confirm the identity of the <italic>trn</italic>K sequences. The nucleotide sequences have been submitted to GenBank with accession numbers KF357736–KF357745. The nucleotide sequence of the partial <italic>trn</italic>K gene from <italic>Acrachne racemosa</italic> available in GenBank (accession number JN681616.1) was also utilized for phylogenetic analysis. The consensus sequence for the <italic>trn</italic>K gene from the nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> taxa and one outgroup (<italic>D. aegyptium</italic>) was generated using the software CLC Sequence viewer 6.1.The sequences were aligned using Clustal-X, version 1.8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C71">Thompson <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses were carried out with the software MEGA 5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C70">Tamura <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Pairwise sequence divergence rates between species were calculated using the maximum composite likelihood method. Phylogeny construction was carried out using NJ, minimum evolution (ME), maximum likelihood (ML) and maximum parsimony (MP) methods. Neighbour-joining and ME trees were obtained using the maximum composite likelihood criterion while ML and MP trees were constructed using the nearest-neighbour-interchange (NNI) and tree-bisection-reconnection algorithms, respectively. In all the analyses, all positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated from the dataset (complete deletion option). Support values of the internal branches of NJ, ME, ML and MP trees were evaluated by bootstrap (500 replicates).List of chloroplast microsatellites amplified in the present study.An equal volume (10 mL) of formamide dye (98 % formamide, 10 mM EDTA, 0.026 g of bromophenol blue, 0.026 g of xylene cyanol) was added to each amplified product. The samples were heated for 5 min at 94 °C and immediately placed on ice. A total of 2.5 mL of each sample was loaded on a 6 % polyacrylamide gel (19 : 1 acrylamide : bisacrylamide, 7.5 M urea and 1× TBE buffer), and electrophoresis was conducted at 55 W and 55 °C for ∼2 h.For silver staining, the gel was fixed in 10 % (v:v) acetic acid for 30 min. It was subsequently rinsed three times in de-ionized water (2 min per rinse). The gel was then kept for staining for 30 min in a 2 L solution containing 2 g of silver nitrate and 3 mL of 37 % formaldehyde (Promega, USA). The stained plate was rinsed with de-ionized water for 20 s and developed in a prechilled (10 °C) developer (2 L) solution containing 60 g of sodium carbonate, 3 mL of 37 % formaldehyde and 400 µL of sodium thiosulfate (10 mg mL<sup>−1</sup>). When bands became visible, the gel was immediately transferred to 10 % acetic acid solution to stop further reaction. The gel was finally rinsed with distilled water and air dried.The PCR products of eight primer–template combinations were characterized by direct sequencing. A PCR was performed in 100 µL volumes as described above. An aliquot of the PCR product was checked by agarose gel electrophoresis, and the remainder was purified through a QIA quick PCR clean up kit (Qiagen). Nucleotide sequencing was performed using an ABI PRISM 377 automated DNA sequencer (Applied Biosystems). The nucleotide sequences have been submitted to GenBank with accession numbers KF357730–KF357735.Grouping of <italic>Eleusine</italic> and outgroup species based on restriction fragment patterns of seven cpDNA amplified genes/intergenic spacers.Restriction fragment size patterns of the amplified <italic>trn</italic>K gene with AfaI (A), the amplified <italic>trn</italic>S<italic>–psb</italic>C intergenic spacer with AfaI (B), the amplified <italic>trn</italic>L<italic>–trn</italic>F gene with MboI (C) and the amplified <italic>16</italic>S gene with MboI (D) in <italic>E. coracana</italic> (lane 1), <italic>E. africana</italic> (2), <italic>E. tristachya</italic> (3), <italic>E. indica</italic> (4), <italic>E. floccifolia</italic> (5), <italic>E. intermedia</italic> (6), <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> (7), <italic>E. multiflora</italic> (8), <italic>E. jaegeri</italic> (9) and <italic>D. aegyptium</italic> (10). Marker DNA (M). The size of the fragments in base pairs is indicated on the left.Genetic distance (Nei and Li's coefficient) matrix generated from cpDNA PCR–RFLP data of nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and an outgroup, <italic>D. aegyptium</italic>.Unweighted pair-group method using arithmetic averages dendrogram based on the restriction fragment data of amplified chloroplast gene/intergenic spacers. Numbers at the nodes represent bootstrap probability values out of 100 replicates.The <italic>trn</italic>K gene codes for tRNA-Lys<sup>UUU</sup>. In rice, the chloroplast <italic>trn</italic>K gene is 2576 bp long, of which the exon is only 72 bp long. The exon is divided into two parts by a long intron of ∼2500 bp. The 5′ exon consists of 37 bp and the 3′ exon consists of 35 bp. The <italic>mat</italic>K gene, which codes for maturaseK, is 1536 bp in length and is located within the chloroplast <italic>trn</italic>K intron. In the present study, the <italic>trn</italic>K gene was sequenced from the nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and <italic>D. aegyptium</italic>. The aligned <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence of <italic>Eleusine</italic> corresponded to position 45 at the 5′ end to position 2531 at the 3′ end of rice. The length of the <italic>trn</italic>K gene in the nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species ranged between 2463 (<italic>E. jaegeri</italic>) and 2467 bp (<italic>E. tristachya</italic> and <italic>E. floccifolia</italic>). The length of <italic>trn</italic>K in <italic>A. racemosa</italic> and <italic>D. aegyptium</italic> was 2466 and 2472 bp, respectively <bold>[see</bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plt056/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information</bold></ext-link><bold>]</bold>. The GC content of the <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence varied from 32.3 to 33 % with an average of 32.6 %. The nucleotide frequencies were 0.162 for G, 0.164 for C, 0.324 for A and 0.350 for T. The dataset including alignment gaps and missing data comprised 2486 nucleotide positions, out of which 2254 were conserved, 214 were variable and 57 were parsimony informative sites.Consensus sequence of the <italic>trn</italic>K gene for nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and one outgroup (<italic>D. aegyptium</italic>) showing major restriction sites.Genetic divergence (maximum composite likelihood method) from <italic>trn</italic>K sequence data for nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and two outgroups, <italic>A. racemosa</italic> and <italic>D. aegyptium.</italic>Dendrograms based on the sequence data of the <italic>trn</italic>K gene of <italic>Eleusine</italic> and outgroup taxa. (A) Neighbour-joining bootstrap consensus tree, (B) ML bootstrap consensus tree and (C) MP consensus tree. Numbers at the nodes represent bootstrap probability values out of 500 replicates.The robustness of the present data lies in the fact that the dendrograms based on ME, ML and MP analysis showed almost the same topology as that of the NJ tree (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT056F4">4</xref>). Maximum parsimony analysis resulted in most parsimonious trees (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT056F4">4</xref>C) with a tree length of 232. The bootstrap consensus tree had a consistency index of 0.943, a retention index of 0.859 and a rescaled consistency index of 0.811.Silver-stained polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis patterns generated by ccmp5 (A) and ccmp6 (B) in <italic>E. coracana</italic> (1), <italic>E. africana</italic> (2), <italic>E. tristachya</italic> (3), <italic>E. indica</italic> (4), <italic>E. floccifolia</italic> (5), <italic>E. intermedia</italic> (6), <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> (7), <italic>E. multiflora</italic> (8), <italic>E. jaegeri</italic> (9) and <italic>D. aegyptium</italic> (10). The size of the fragments in base pairs is indicated on the left.Nucleotide sequences of cpDNA of <italic>E. coracana</italic> amplified using six cpSSR primer pairs. The location of repeats is underlined.The restriction site variation identified in the amplified chloroplast gene/intergenic spacers has provided new insights into the origin and evolution of the three polyploid species, and the genetic relationships between the cultivated and wild <italic>Eleusine</italic> species. Species-specific markers were also identified. None of the amplicon–enzyme combinations could discriminate between <italic>E. coracana</italic> (AABB, 2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36), <italic>E. africana</italic> (AABB, 2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36), <italic>E. tristachya</italic> (AA, 2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 18), <italic>E. indica</italic> (AA, 2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 18) and <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> (AADD, 2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 38) on the one hand, and between <italic>E. floccifolia</italic> (BB, 2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 18) and <italic>E. intermedia</italic> (AB, 2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 18) on the other hand. Although the maximum number of polymorphic and phylogenetically informative markers was obtained in eight <italic>trn</italic>K amplicon–enzyme combinations, the amount of variation that can be tapped with the PCR–RFLP method was lower than the variation tapped with sequencing of the <italic>trn</italic>K gene. A total of 214 SNPs were found in the <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence, of which only 10 were causative to 8 polymorphic profiles. This clearly demonstrates that sequencing of the <italic>trn</italic>K gene is more informative than the PCR–RFLP method. Moreover, the nucleotide sequence of the chloroplast <italic>trn</italic>K gene fine-tuned the species relationships. The nine species of <italic>Eleusine</italic> were grouped into two clades, in both PCR–RFLP and <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence data analyses. The <italic>trn</italic>K sequence data clearly showed that the three tetraploids were closer to <italic>E. indica</italic> than to <italic>E. tristachya</italic>, as concluded from PCR–RFLP data.The present observations based on restriction site variation and the <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence of cpDNA are congruent with the conclusions reached by various authors based on the multiple marker nuclear DNA assay, chloroplast markers and chromosome research. The strong affinities between <italic>E. coracana</italic>, <italic>E. africana</italic> and <italic>E. indica</italic> have been highlighted in earlier studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C27">Hilu and Johnson 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C28">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C24">Hilu 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C6">Bisht and Mukai 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C7">2001<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C8"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C19">Dida <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C20">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) as well. A number of studies based on chromosome research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C32">Hiremath and Chennaveeraiah 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C33">Hiremath and Salimath 1991</xref>), 2C DNA content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C33">Hiremath and Salimath 1991</xref>), crossability data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C64">Salimath <italic>et al.</italic> 1995<italic>b</italic></xref>) and ribosomal DNA polymorphism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C27">Hilu and Johnson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C78">Werth <italic>et al.</italic> 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C6">Bisht and Mukai 2000</xref>), ITS sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>) and cpDNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C28">Hilu and Johnson 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) also support the close affinity between <italic>E. indica</italic> and <italic>E. tristachya</italic>. The allotetraploid <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> exhibits the same maternal lineage as that of the two other allotetraploid species, <italic>E. coracana</italic> and <italic>E. africana</italic>. The five species share some common morphological features, such as 1–3 nerved lower glumes with a winged keel, 3–7 nerved upper glumes with a more or less winged keel, the presence of 1–3 subsidiary nerves adjacent to the central nerve of the lemma and the generally winged keel of the palea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C51">Phillips 1972</xref>).The present data unambiguously support the view of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C12">Chennaveeraiah and Hiremath (1974)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C23">Hilu (1988)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C34">Hiremath and Salimath (1992)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C28">Hilu and Johnson (1997)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C6">Bisht and Mukai (2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C7">2001<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C8"><italic>b</italic></xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> (2005)</xref> that <italic>E. africana</italic> is the wild progenitor of the cultivated species, <italic>E. coracana</italic>, and that <italic>E. indica</italic> is one of the diploid progenitors of the two polyploid species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The present results further indicate that <italic>E. indica</italic> with the AA genome might be the maternal parent for all three tetraploid species, viz. <italic>E. coracana</italic>, <italic>E. africana</italic> and <italic>E. kigeziensis.</italic> Morphologically, <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic> resembles <italic>E. indica</italic>. It is considered to be a hybrid between <italic>E. indica</italic> and one of the perennial species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C51">Phillips 1972</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C62">Salimath (1990)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C9">Bisht and Mukai (2002)</xref> have also proposed <italic>E. indica</italic> as one of the genome donors of <italic>E. kigeziensis</italic>.The close affinity in the cpDNA PCR–RFLP profiles and <italic>trn</italic>K sequences between <italic>E. floccifolia</italic> and <italic>E. intermedia</italic> is also supported by the occurrence of the same chromosome number (2<italic>n</italic> = 18), 2C DNA values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C32">Hiremath and Chennaveeraiah 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C33">Hiremath and Salimath 1991</xref>) and ITS sequence data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C47">Neves <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Close association between <italic>E. jaegeri</italic>, <italic>E. floccifolia</italic> and <italic>E. intermedia</italic> suggested in earlier studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C33">Hiremath and Salimath 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C27">Hilu and Johnson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C41">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) is further supported by our data. <italic>Eleusine jaegeri</italic> in all combinations grouped together with <italic>E. floccifolia</italic> and <italic>E. intermedia</italic> except in the <italic>psa</italic>A–MspI combination, where it shows a unique profile <italic>vis-à-vis</italic> the remaining species. In the case of <italic>trn</italic>K sequence analysis also these three species are found to be closely associated. <italic>Eleusine multiflora</italic> also behaves in the same fashion. The species exhibits unique profiles <italic>vis-à-vis</italic> the remaining species in <italic>trn</italic>K–DraI, <italic>trn</italic>K–MspI, <italic>trn</italic>K–SpeI, <italic>psa</italic>A–TaqI and <italic>psb</italic>D–HaeIII combinations, with the result that it represents the most diverged taxon among all the <italic>Eleusine</italic> species. These amplicon–enzyme combinations can therefore be used as species-specific markers for <italic>E. jaegeri</italic> and <italic>E. multiflora</italic>. The position of <italic>E. multiflora</italic> within the genus <italic>Eleusine</italic> is questionable mainly on the basis of its unusual inflorescence morphology [considered to be intermediate between <italic>Eleusine</italic> and <italic>Acrachne</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C51">Phillips 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C13">Clayton and Renvoize 1986</xref>)], distinct chemical composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C29">Hilu <italic>et al.</italic> 1978</xref>), molecular data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C27">Hilu and Johnson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C24">Hilu 1995</xref>), chromosome number (2<italic>n</italic> = 16), 2C DNA value and other cytogenetic features (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C44">Mysore and Baird 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C6">Bisht and Mukai 2000</xref>) including the present results. <italic>Dactyloctenium aegyptium</italic> in restriction site analysis, and <italic>A. racemosa</italic> and <italic>D. aegyptium</italic> in <italic>trn</italic>K sequence analysis indicate that they are the most diverged species <italic>vis-à-vis</italic> <italic>Eleusine</italic> species analysed and thus represented as outgroups.Chloroplast microsatellites are known to have potential for phylogenetic studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C54">Powell <italic>et al.</italic> 1995<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C55"><italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C56">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C58">Provan <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C60">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C36">Ishii and McCouch 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C1">Angioi <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The present cpSSR data on <italic>Eleusine</italic> species, however, were not helpful as very little polymorphism was obtained for various amplified microsatellites. Only two cpSSR loci (ccmp2 and ccmp5) were found to be polymorphic, displaying a total of four alleles. In the case of ccmp2, the variant allele was found in <italic>E. tristachya</italic>, while for ccmp5 the variant allele was found in <italic>E. jaegeri</italic>. Overall, the sequences seem to be highly conserved. This is in strong contrast to the observations made in the other genera such as <italic>Glycine</italic>, <italic>Oryza</italic> and <italic>Hordeum</italic>, where different species within the genus and even within different subspecies displayed characteristic haplotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C55">Powell <italic>et al.</italic> 1995<italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C56">1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C58">Provan <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C59">1999</xref>). The reason for not obtaining polymorphism in the present study could be attributed to the fact that it is very difficult to design universal primers for microsatellites that show widespread polymorphism at the inter-specific level and at the same time are able to amplify across a broad range of plant genera. Although there are primers available that amplify across wide-ranging taxa, these rarely show widespread inter-specific polymorphism. This could be due to the contrasting requirements in a short stretch of DNA of extreme stability and sequence conservation for priming sites and consistently high levels of polymorphism in the intervening region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C60">Provan <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). Second, size homoplasy may not necessarily mean identical intervening microsatellite regions; it may also be due to variation in flanking regions. It is also possible that back mutations have taken place, which might result in identical size but not identical sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT056C10">Bryan <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>).Our results based on RFLP of the seven amplified chloroplast genes/intergenic spacers, and the <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence in the nine diploid and allotetraploid <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and two outgroup species resulted in well-resolved phylogenetic trees. The maternal genome donor (<italic>E. indica</italic>, 2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 18) of the allotetraploid (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36, 2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 38) <italic>Eleusine</italic> species, and the phylogenetic relationships between cultivated <italic>E. coracana</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 4<italic>x</italic> = 36) and wild species could be successfully resolved. The species-specific markers were also identified. The two diploid species <italic>E. indica</italic> and <italic>E. tristachya</italic> could not be resolved separately by PCR–RFLP of seven chloroplast genic/intergenic spacers, as not a single site change could be scored. However, the <italic>trn</italic>K gene sequence clearly demonstrated that <italic>E. indica</italic> is more closely related to all three allotetraploids as compared with <italic>E. tristachya</italic>. Therefore, <italic>E. indica</italic> is most likely the maternal parent to all three allotetraploids. <italic>Eleusine multiflora</italic> (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 16) was found to be the most diverged among all the species. The explicit identification of the maternal parent and that of the immediate wild progenitor of finger millet will be immensely useful for future genetic improvement and biotechnological programmes of the crop species.This work was supported by the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), Government of India and the National Academy of Sciences, India (NASI).R.A. was involved in planning and performing all the experiments, data analyses and manuscript writing. N.A. was involved in the data analysis. R.T. was involved in relevant research discussions. S.N.R. was involved in the planning and supervision of all the experimental work and in writing the manuscript. All authors have seen and agreed to the submitted manuscript.None declared.The nucleotide sequences of the <italic>trn</italic>K gene from the nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and one outgroup <italic>D. aegyptium</italic> have been submitted to GenBank with accession numbers KF357736–KF357745. The nucleotide sequences of six cpSSRs isolated from <italic>E. coracana</italic> have been submitted to GenBank with accession numbers KF357730–KF357735.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plt056/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">The following additional information is available in the online version of this article –</ext-link><bold>File 1.</bold> Sequence data matrix of the aligned partial <italic>trn</italic>K gene region of cpDNA of nine <italic>Eleusine</italic> species and two outgroups, <italic>A. racemosa</italic> and <italic>D. aegyptium</italic>. Nucleotide sequences are displayed 5′–3′. Dots indicate the same nucleotide as in <italic>E. coracana</italic>; dashes indicate gaps.Thanks are due to the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA), the International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI), the National Bureau of Plant Genetic Resources (NBPGR) and Dr Mathews M. Dida for supplying the seed samples. We thank Dr Vishnu Bhat and Dr Shailendra Goel for their help and support.