An effective nutrient medium for asymbiotic seed germination and large-scale <italic>in vitro</italic> regeneration of <italic>Dendrobium hookerianum</italic>, a threatened orchid of northeast IndiaThe effect of nitrogen nutrition on growth, chemical composition and response of cucumbers (<italic>Cucumis sativus</italic> L.) to nitrogen forms in solution cultureThe reintroduction of <italic>Platanthera ciliaris</italic> in CanadaOrchid seed germination and seedling culture—a manualPhysiology of germinating orchid seedsStudies on growth and development of <italic>Cymbidium aloifolium</italic> Sw. seedling <italic>in vitro</italic>Orchid diversity in North-East IndiaOptimization of nutrient requirements for asymbiotic seed germination of <italic>Dendrobium longicornu</italic> and <italic>D. formosum</italic>The effect of activated charcoal on tissue culture; absorption of metabolites inhibiting morphogenesisNutrient requirement of suspension cultures of soyabean root cellsMicropropagation and restoration of endangered Malabar daffodil orchid <italic>Ipsea malabarica</italic><italic>In vitro</italic> multiplication of <italic>Vanilla planifolia</italic> using axillary bud explants<italic>In vitro</italic> propagation of the medicinal orchid <italic>Dendrobium chrysanthum</italic><italic>In vitro</italic> germination and regeneration of <italic>Dendrobium transparens</italic> LindlNonsymbiotic germination of orchid seedsA new nutrient solution for germination of orchid seed<italic>s</italic>Developmental morphology of seed micropropagation of <italic>Orchis aristata</italic> Fisher (Orchidaceae) in axenic cultureAsymbiotic germination of <italic>Dendrobium fimbriatum</italic> var. <italic>oculatum</italic> Hk. F. seeds on different mediaClonal propagation and establishment of <italic>Dendrobium fimbriatum</italic> varAsymbiotic germination of immature seeds, plantlet development and <italic>ex vitro</italic> establishment of plants of <italic>Dendrobium tosaenso</italic> Makino—a medicinally important orchidInorganic correlated salts and differentiation of protocorms in seed of an orchid (<italic>Dendrobium fimbriatum</italic>) and correlated changes in its free amino acid contextA revised medium for rapid growth and bio-assays with tobacco tissue culturesResponse of <italic>Cymbidium lunavian</italic> Atlas protocorms to media and benzyl aminopurineInfluence of <italic>in vitro</italic> media on asymbiotic germination, plantlet development and <italic>ex vitro</italic> establishment of <italic>Coelogyne ovalis</italic> and <italic>Coelogyne nitida</italic>The use of charcoal in <italic>in vitro</italic> culture — a review<italic>In vitro</italic> seed germination and seedling development of <italic>Dendrobium ovatum</italic>. (W) KrunzlInorganic nitrogen nutrition of the seedlings of the orchid <italic>Cattleya</italic>Tissue culture in the orchid industryAsymbiotic seed germination, mass propagation and seedling development of <italic>Vanda coerulea</italic> Griff ex. Lindl. (Blue Vanda): an <italic>in vitro</italic> protocol for an endangered orchidProblems and prospects of orchid mycorrhizal researchAxenic germination of some epiphytic orchid of Meghalaya, IndiaVitamins as related to axenic seed germination and seedling of <italic>Cymbidium elegans</italic> Lindl. and <italic>Coelogyne punctulata</italic> LindlAsymbiotic seed germination and <italic>in vitro</italic> seedling development of <italic>Habenaria macroceratitis</italic> (Orchidaceae), a rare Florida terrestrial orchidThe effects of ethephon on <italic>Cattleya aurantiaca</italic> (Orchidaceae) seedlingsEffect of activated charcoal on in vitro propagation of Western European orchids<italic>In vitro</italic> germination of some Western European orchids<italic>In vitro</italic> germination capacity and plant recovery of some native and rare orchidsThe role of tissue culture in preserving threatened and endangered plant speciesThe use of darkening agents in seed germination and tissue culture media for orchids: a reviewStomatal limitation of carbon gain in <italic>Paphiopedilum</italic> sp. (Orchidaceae) and its reversal by blue lightThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Submergence inhibits photosynthesis by terrestrial wetland plants, but less so in species that possess leaf gas films when submerged. Floodwaters are often supersaturated with dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> enabling photosynthesis by submerged terrestrial plants, although rates remain well-below those in air. This important adaptation that enhances survival in submerged conditions is reviewed.<italic>Dendrobium hookerianum</italic> is a rare and threatened epiphytic orchid of northeast India. Prospects for conservation would be strengthened by developing an <italic>in vitro</italic> method for mass propagation. Seeds are minute and difficult to use directly in the field for this purpose, being non-endospermous with a low nutrient content and dependent on a specific fungus for germination and early seedling development. Although produced in large numbers (2–3 million per capsule), &lt;5 % germinate naturally in the wild. Our objective was to develop a rapid and successful method for <italic>in vitro</italic> propagation based on an initial <italic>in vitro</italic> asymbiotic seed germination step that achieved high percentages.Effects of four different media, i.e. (i) Murashige and Skoog (MS), (ii) Mitra <italic>et al</italic><italic>.</italic>, (iii) Knudson (KC) and (iv) Gamborg <italic>et al</italic>. (B<sub>5</sub>), were evaluated for large-scale multiplication by asymbiotic seed germination. Seedling leaf number, shoot number, shoot length, root number and root length were scored. After 7–8 months, large numbers of well-rooted plantlets were transferred to a glasshouse in thermocol pots containing compost. Six different composts based on broken brick and charcoal were compared for their ability to support further development over 90 days of hardening.The fastest and highest percentage seed germination was achieved using MS medium. Seeds on MS medium germinated in 3–4 weeks compared with 7–8 weeks on B<sub>5</sub> medium. Seedling development was also superior on MS medium. The inclusion of plant growth regulators was unnecessary. Compost comprising broken brick and charcoal with an upper layer of moss was found to be the most suitable for the survival of transferred plantlets. Ninety per cent survival of plantlets was achieved 90 days after transfer to a glasshouse.The use of MS culture medium is well suited for the mass multiplication of <italic>D. hookerianum</italic> plants intended for re-introducing this threatened orchid into the wild.The northeast region of India harbours ∼750–800 species of orchid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C8">Chowdhery 2001</xref>). However, this rich diversity, both in the region and in the country as a whole, is under threat for various reasons. These include deforestation, uncontrolled commercial exploitation, illegal export and the practice of slash and burn cultivation that is widespread in northeast India. At present, all the orchids are listed in the International Union of Conservation of Nature and Natural Resouces (IUCN) Red Data Book. The family Orchidaceae is also included in Appendix-II of the Convention of International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C32">Senthilkumar 2001</xref>). <italic>Dendrobium hookerianum</italic> is an epiphytic orchid included in these lists as a rare and threatened species in northeast India. The orchid has ornamental value and is commercially important due to its bright yellow flower, the pigment from which is used by the textile industry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C7">Chowdhery 1998</xref>). There is a clear need to conserve this rare, beautiful and useful species from extinction. We believe that it will be possible to increase its population size by using mass <italic>in vitro</italic> seed germination to generate large numbers of plants to re-introduce into the wild (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C40">Wochok 1981</xref>). However, at present, there is no established means of achieving mass <italic>in vitro</italic> germination and plantlet culture.The minute orchid seeds are produced profusely (2–3 million per capsule) but are non-endospermous and contain almost no nutrients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C39">Vu Quoc Luan et al. 2006</xref>). In nature, germination and early development are therefore reliant upon a highly specialized fungal association (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C30">Rao 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C15">Hazarika and Sarma 1995</xref>). Consequently, &lt;5 % of the seeds germinate in the wild. A method for mass <italic>in vitro</italic> seed germination and propagation will need to circumvent these requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C4">Arditti and Ernst 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C33">Sharma and Tandon 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C20">Kumaria and Tandon 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C18">Kondo <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C12">Gangaprasad <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C25">Nagaraju <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C31">Roy <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). The appropriate choice of nutrient medium is crucial in this regard, but it is known that responses of orchid seeds to different nutrient media vary between species.The technique of asymbiotic seed germination by <italic>in vitro</italic> culture was first introduced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C16">Knudson (1922)</xref>. Since then, <italic>in vitro</italic> seed germination protocols have been established for many orchid species, and a number of media and salts have been used for germination and propagation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C5">Arditti and Ernst 1993</xref>). Orchid seeds and seedlings have often been reported not to require exogenous auxin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C36">Tamanaha <italic>et al</italic>. 1979</xref>). In the present study, we describe an efficient method for mass propagation of <italic>D. hookerianum</italic> through asymbiotic seed germination that is intended to underpin <italic>ex situ</italic> conservation.Plants of <italic>D. hookerianum</italic> were collected from Upper Shillong, Meghalaya, India, during October–November 2009 and grown in a glasshouse at the Plant Biotechnology Laboratory, Centre for Advance Studies in Botany, North-Eastern Hill University, Shillong, Meghalaya, India. Purplish-green fruit capsules were collected after 8–9 months, washed in tap water followed by sterile distilled water, dipped in 70 % (v/v) alcohol and flamed 3–4 times with a spirit burner. The surface-sterilized capsules were then opened using a sterile surgical blade and seeds removed. Approximately 1 g of seeds was distributed thinly over the surface of 15 mL of four different basal liquid media, i.e. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C24">Murashige and Skoog (MS, 1962)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C23">Mitra <italic>et al</italic>. (1976)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C17">Kundson (KC, 1946)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C11">Gamborg <italic>et al</italic>. (B<sub>5</sub>, 1968)</xref>, in test tubes. The pH was adjusted to 5.8 ± 0.02 using 1 N NaOH before autoclaving at 121 °C for 15 min. Culture tubes were kept in the dark for 2 weeks followed by dim white illumination (60 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>) for a 12-h photoperiod at 25 ± 2 °C and at 70–75 % relative humidity (RH). There were 10 replicates and the experiment was repeated twice. Percentage seed germination was determined microscopically after 60 days of culture and calculated by using the formula: % seed germination = number of germinated seeds/total number of seeds × 100. At intervals, the development of protocorms was categorized into four stages: (i) embryo swollen, (ii) appearance of protomeristem, (iii) initiation of leaf and (iv) initiation of roots.After germination, the growth and development of seedlings in different media were also studied. Ninety-day-old seedlings with leaf initials but without roots were cultured on the same media used for germination and monitored for leaf number, shoot number, shoot length, root number and root length. Data were analysed using one-way analysis of variance Fisher's least significant difference (LSD) test at the 5 % level of probability (software Origin 7.0).Seedlings ∼4–5 cm tall and with well-defined roots were obtained after 7–8 months. These were removed from culture vessels and washed thoroughly with tap water, to remove adhering medium without damaging the roots, before transplanting into perforated free-draining plastic pots (10 × 7 cm size) containing different mixtures of compost: broken brick and charcoal (1 : 1); broken brick and charcoal (1 : 1) + a top layer of moss; broken brick and charcoal + decaying litter (1 : 1 : 1); broken brick and charcoal + decaying litter (1 : 1 : 1) + a top layer of moss; broken brick and charcoal + coconut husk (1 : 1 : 1); broken brick and charcoal + coconut husk (1 : 1 : 1) + a top layer of moss.A single plantlet was grown in each pot and each was covered for 2–3 weeks with a pierced polythene bag, sprayed with water to inhibit dehydration and moved to a glasshouse for growing on. The minimum and maximum temperatures were 18 and 25 °C, respectively, and RH was 70–80 %. Plantlets were watered on alternate days and fed with 1/10 strength MS nutrient salt solutions (diluted 10 times) every 2 weeks. Plants were assessed after 90 days.Effect of different media on seed germination and time taken for protocorm formation and development (in weeks) of D. hookerianum.*Data recorded after 60 days of inoculation.**I, embryo swollen; II, appearance of protomeristem; III, leaf initial stage; IV, root initial stage.Values are mean ± SE. Means followed by the same letter in the column are not significantly different as indicated by Fisher's LSD (<italic>P</italic>= 0.05).Means of 10 values were taken and the experiment was repeated twice.Effect of different media on growth and development of D. hookerianum seedlings after 90 days of culture.Values are mean ± SE. Means followed by the same letter in the column are not significantly different as indicated by Fisher's LSD (<italic>P</italic>= 0.05).Means of 10 values were taken and the experiment was repeated twice.Re-establishment of D. hookerianum plantlets obtained in MS medium after 90 days of hardening under glasshouse conditions.Values represent means ± SE.Means of 10 values were taken and the experiment was repeated twice.<bold>Asymbiotic seed germination of <italic>D. hookerianum</italic> on different media after 60 days: (A) MS, (B) Mitra, (C) KC, (D) B<sub>5</sub> (bar = 1 mm).</bold> Different stages of protocorm development on MS medium: (E) embryo swollen, (F) protomeristem, (G) leaf initial, (H) root initials (bar = 1 mm), (I) seedlings on MS medium after 90 days, (J) <italic>in vitro</italic> rooted plantlets from activated charcoal and (K) hardened plants.Inorganic and organic components, and gelling agent of the media.Our plantlets were sub-cultured from time to time in MS medium with activated charcoal (1 g L<sup>−1</sup>). As is well known, activated charcoal adsorbs phenolic substances released by the plantlets into the media (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C10">Fridborg <italic>et al</italic>. 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C27">Pan and Van Staden 1998</xref>), and stimulates rooting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C37">Van waes 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C13">George and Ravishankar 1997</xref>) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLR032F1">1</xref>J). The survival rate of the transferred plantlets in a compost mixture made up of broken brick and charcoal pieces with a covering layer of moss was 90 %. The brick and charcoal provided good drainage and aeration to the roots, and the moss is thought to retain moisture content at an optimal level. In the present study, feeding the plantlets with diluted 1/10 MS nutrient solution was beneficial for growth of the transferred plantlets. This is consistent with the earlier report of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLR032C21">Kumaria and Tandon (1994)</xref>.The present study is the first to report a successful and efficient protocol for asymbiotic seed germination and for the regeneration of a large number of plantlets of <italic>D. hookerianum</italic>. For conservation of plants, the seeds are, in general, preferred for propagation because they maintain maximum genetic diversity. <italic>In vitro</italic> seed germination ensures germination in this hard-to-germinate taxon and this enabled us to study morphogenetic changes during seedling development. The mass propagation of orchids through asymbiotic seed germination was achieved and can now be considered as a viable tool in the conservation of the declining native orchid population. It offers a ready means for raising the large numbers of plants needed for <italic>ex situ</italic> conservation of this threatened orchid.The first author acknowledges a meritorious fellowship from the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">University Grants Commission, India</grant-sponsor>.All authors contributed to a similar extent overall and have seen and agreed to the submitted manuscript.None declared.The first author thanks Shrawan Kumar, Research Scholar who helped prepare the manuscript.