Variation in body condition indices of crimson finches by sex, breeding stage, age, time of day, and yearIndividual quality mediates trade-offs between reproductive effort and immune function in tree swallowsHaematology and blood chemistry of healthy and clinically abnormal great black-backed gulls (<italic>Larus marinus</italic>) and herring gulls (<italic>Larus argentatus</italic>)Mean corpuscular volume (MCV) as a measure of condition in birdsPost-release survival of river otters: effects of exposure to crude oil and captivityOptimal hematocrit: theory, regulation and implicationsAssessing body condition in birds. In VJ NolanAvian and Exotic Animal Hematology and CytologyBird hematocrits: effects of high altitude and strength of flightWhat is conservation physiology? Perspectives on an increasingly integrated and essential scienceThe use of leukocyte profiles to measure stress in vertebrates: a review for ecologistsVariation in hematocrit and total plasma proteins of nestling American Kestrels (<italic>Falco sparverius</italic>) in the wildParasitism, immune response and reproductive success in the house martin <italic>Delichon urbica</italic>National recovery plan for the white-bellied subspecies of the crimson finch <italic>Neochmia phaeton evangelinae</italic> and the Northern subspecies of the star finch <italic>Neochmia ruficauda clarescens</italic>. Report to the Austrlaian Government Department of the Environment and Water Resources, CanberraFitness and nutrtional assessment of greater sage grouse (Centrocercus urophasianus) using hematologic and serum chemistry parameters through a cycle of seasonal habitats in northern NevadaSite and age class variation of hematologic parameters for female Greater Sage Grouse of northern NevadaElevated hormonal stress response and reduced reproductive output in Yellow-eyed penguins exposed to unregulated tourismIntegrating landscape ecology and conservation physiologySources of variation in haematocrit in birdsGeographic patterns and correlates of the decline of granivorous birds in northern AustraliaThe Action Plan for Australian Birds 2010Do male ornaments signal immunity in the common yellowthroat?Blood constituents and their relation to diet in urban and rural House SparrowsThe usefulness and limitations of hand-held refractometers in veterinary laboratory medicine: an historical and technical reviewReproductive state but not testosterone reduces immune function in male house sparrows (<italic>Passer domesticus</italic>)Total plasma protein and renesting by Greater Sage-GrouseClinical Avian Medicine and Surgery, Including AvicultureArrival timing and hematological parameters in Gray Catbirds (<italic>Dumetella carolinensis</italic>)Abundance may be a misleading indicator of fragmentation-sensitivity: the case of fig-eating batsHandbook of Australian, New Zealand &amp; Antarctic Birds: Boatbill to Starlings Part BEvaluating habitat quality of vertebrates using conservation physiology toolsHealth and reproduction: the sex-specific clinical profile of great tits (<italic>Parus major</italic>) in relation to breedingHaematological health state indices of reproducing Great Tits: a response to brood size manipulationBeyond occurrence: body condition and stress hormone as integrative indicators of habitat availability and fragmentation in the common toadMeasuring habitat quality: a reviewDoes habitat fragmentation cause stress in the agile antechinus? A haematological approachInterpreting indices of physiological stress in free-living vertebratesChanges in hematological parameters in free-living pigeons (<italic>Columba livia f. urbana</italic>) during the breeding cycleHematological parameters in brood-rearing great tits in relation to habitat, multiple breeding and sexHematological health state indices predict local survival in a small passerine bird, the Great Tit (<italic>Parus major</italic>)Dynamics of food availability, body condition, and physiological stress response in breeding Black-legged KittiwakesDefining individual quality over lifetimes and selective contextsThe value of fat reserves and the tradeoff between starvation and predationDistribution and individual condition reveal a hierarchy of habitat suitability for an area-sensitive passerineCorticosterone levels as indicators of habitat quality: effects of habitat segregation in a migratory bird during the non-breeding seasonVariation in the health of tropical finches in relation to conservation status, season and land tenureBreeding biology and life-history traits of an Australasian tropical granivore, the Crimson Finch (<italic>Neochmia phaeton</italic>)Hematocrits in montane sparrows in relation to reproductive scheduleVariation in body condition of breeding Savi's Warblers <italic>Locustella luscinioides</italic>: the reproductive stress and flight adaptation hypothesis revisitedHaematozoa infections in a Great Tit <italic>Parus major</italic> population in Central Portugal: relationships with breeding effort and healthVariation of adult Great Tit <italic>Parus major</italic> body condition and blood parameters in relation to sex, age, year and seasonHealth impact of blood parasites in breeding great titsHabitat and sex differences in physiological condition of breeding Southwestern Willow Flycatchers (<italic>Empidonax trailliextimus</italic>)New perspectives for estimating body condition from mass/length data: the scaled mass index as an alternative methodManagement of fat reserves and food caches in tufted titmice (<italic>Parus bicolor</italic>) in relation to unpredictable food supplyIdentification Guide to North American Birds Part I: Columbidae to PloceidaeR: A language and environment for statistical computingFood limitation among wintering birds. In R Greenberg, PP MarraAvian protein disorders. In AM FudgeHaematocrit correlates with tail ornament size in three populations of the Barn Swallow (<italic>Hirundo rustica</italic>)Immunoglobulin plasma concentration in relation to egg laying and mate ornamentation of female barn swallows (<italic>Hirundo rustica</italic>)Does differential access to protein influence differences in timing of breeding of Florida scrub-jays (<italic>Aphelocoma coerulescens</italic>) in suburban and wildland habitats?Hematological differences between stingrays at tourist and non-visited sites suggest physiological costs of wildlife tourismHematological condition indexes in greenfinches: effects of captivity and diurnal variationInfluence of proximity to a geographical range limit on the physiology of a tropical birdWeak association between measures of health and reproductive success in green-rumped parrotlets (<italic>Forpus passerinus</italic>) in VenezuelaCondition indices for conservation: new uses for evolving toolsForest management is associated with physiological stress in an old-growth forest passerineEffects of haematophagous mites on nestling house sparrows (<italic>Passer domesticus</italic>)Genic capture and resolving the lek paradoxRelationship of hemoglobin concentration to packed cell volume in avian blood samplesHaematological health assessment in a passerine with extremely high proportion of basophils in peripheral bloodHematological changes associated with egg production: estrogen dependence and repeatabilityField endocrinology and conservation biologyNoninvasive physiological measures of distubance in the northern spotted owlConservation physiologyWhat causes the decrease in haematocrit during egg production?The disappearing mammal fauna of northern Australia: context, cause, and response<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Assessing an animal's body condition may be useful in conservation if condition reflects habitat quality. We found that interpretation of most body condition indices can be confounded by effects of breeding stage, sex and age, and only some vary in ways consistent with the idea that they reflect environmental quality.Body condition indices are increasingly applied in conservation to assess habitat quality, identify stressed populations before they decline, determine effects of disturbances, and understand mechanisms of declines. To employ condition indices in this manner, we need first to understand their baseline variability and sources of variation. Here, we used crimson finches (<italic>Neochmia phaeton</italic>), a tropical passerine, to describe the variation in seven commonly used condition indices by sex, age, breeding stage, time of day, and year. We found that packed cell volume, haemoglobin, total plasma protein, and scaled mass were all significantly affected by an interaction between sex and breeding stage. Furcular fat varied by sex and breeding stage and also trended by year, scaled mass showed a positive trend with age and varied by time of day, and haemoglobin additionally varied by year. Pectoral muscle scores varied and heterophil to lymphocyte ratio trended only by year. Year effects might reflect a response to annual variation in environmental conditions; therefore, those indices showing year effects may be especially worthy of further investigation of their potential for conservation applications. Pectoral muscle scores and heterophil to lymphocyte ratio may be particularly useful due to the lack of influence of other variables on them. For the other indices, the large variation that can be attributed to individual covariates, such as sex and breeding stage, suggests that one should not interpret the physiological condition of an individual as measured by these indices from their absolute value. Instead, the condition of an individual should be interpreted relative to conspecifics by sex, breeding stage, and possibly age.Body condition is the physiological state of an individual and reflects how successful that individual is in interacting with its environment. Condition is higher when an individual acquires and assimilates more resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C70">Tomkins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), and is usually employed in a relative sense to compare individuals within populations or between places and times. Without a single or direct measure of condition itself, researchers employ body condition indices as tools to measure specific aspects of that physiological state (e.g. nutritional status, stress levels, and immune function), in both basic ecological and applied conservation frameworks.Examples of body condition indices being applied in conservation, including those that reflect resource (e.g. food) acquisition and allocation, such as body mass and measures of fat reserves, as well as haematological, biochemical, and endocrine indices that assess other aspects of physiological conditionFor a review of body condition indices used in conservation broadly, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C67">Stevenson and Woods (2006)</xref>, and for reviews of the use of body condition indices to assess habitat quality in particular, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C35">Johnson (2007)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C17">Ellis <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C31">Homyack (2010)</xref>. Abbreviations: H/L ratio, heterophil to lymphocyte ratio; N/L ratio, neutrophil to lymphocyte ratio; and WBC, white blood cell.Condition indices have also been used to assess impacts of stressors and disturbances other than habitat alteration (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COT020TB1">1</xref>). Condition indices were employed, for example, to detect deleterious effects of ecotourism on wildlife (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C74">Walker <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C16">Ellenberg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C63">Semeniuk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), of the presence of logging roads and nearby timber harvesting on northern spotted owls (<italic>Strix occidentalis caurina</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C75">Wasser <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>), and of oiling on sea otters even after they were treated (<italic>Lontra canadensis</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C4">Ben-David <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Other applications of condition indices in conservation are in testing hypotheses about the agents of population decline (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C53">Owen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and elucidating the mechanisms of declines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C46">Maute, 2011</xref>). Finally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C9">Cooke <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> encourage us to move beyond the identification of problems and towards the constructive use of this knowledge in providing conservation solutions.Use of condition indices in conservation is hampered by the paucity of data on their baseline variability and sources of variation. Despite their frequent use, condition indices are poorly described for many species in the wild and, in particular, for those from the tropics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C67">Stevenson and Woods, 2006</xref>). The covariates that may affect these indices are even less well documented, and understanding of this variability is needed to inform our interpretation of condition indices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C11">Dawson and Bortolotti, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C18">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).Likely sources of variation that may affect condition indices include sex, age, breeding stage, time of day, and annual and seasonal variation in the environment. While the last two parameters represent the sort of interaction between environment and individual that reflects uses of these indices in conservation, the first four parameters represent variables that potentially confound these uses. Condition indices may vary between males and females because of influences of sex hormones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C65">Shallin Busch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) and because of differences in sex-specific workload, especially during breeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C33">Hõrak <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998b</xref>). Age may affect condition indices if individuals experience physiological senescence, have variable exposure to immune challenges with age, or allocate their resources differently with age. Condition indices may vary across the different stages of the breeding cycle because of hormonal changes and different energy requirements associated with these stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C77">Williams <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C18">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Finally, time of day is known to affect the mass and fat stores of diurnal birds due to overnight fasting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C55">Pravosudov and Grubb, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C64">Sepp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).This study is part of a larger research project, the objectives of which are to assess the consequences of different land-management regimens on wildlife physiology and to test whether condition indices predict fitness such that they can inform habitat management. The habitats under consideration are northern Australia's tropical savanna and interstitial areas embedded within this matrix, including riparian habitats, all of which are threatened by non-native herbivores (cattle, horses, donkeys, buffalo, and pigs) and inappropriate fire regimens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C20">Franklin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C78">Woinarski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Broadly, we are examining the impacts of differing fire and introduced herbivore management on the persistence and physiology of native species, and more specifically, we are investigating whether condition indices can be used to provide prior warning of impending species declines. To examine this, we are comparing condition indices in relationship to the presence/absence of introduced herbivores, and to whether fire is managed (small-scale and low-intensity fires) or unmanaged (frequent, extensive, and high-intensity fires).Here, we take the first step towards assessing the impact of land-management regimens on wildlife physiology by reporting baseline condition indices sampled from a native passerine in habitat that has been managed for conservation. We then explore the variability of these indices by sex, breeding stage, age, time of day, and year. Our goal in describing this variation is to inform our interpretation of condition indices as conservation tools when comparing across populations.Crimson finches (<italic>Neochmia phaeton</italic>, Family Estrildidae) are restricted to riparian zones throughout the tropical savannas of northern Australia and New Guinea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C30">Higgins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Two subspecies of crimson finches are recognized, <italic>N. p. phaeton</italic> and <italic>N. p. evangelinae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C30">Higgins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>); the latter includes populations in southern Papua New Guinea and four populations on the Cape York peninsula, Australia and is listed as vulnerable in the Commonwealth of Australia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C13">Dorricott and Garnett, 2007</xref>) and as near threatened internationally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C21">Garnett <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The main threats to <italic>N. p. evangelinae</italic> in Australia include fire regimens and invasive plant species that alter the vegetation structure used by the finches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C13">Dorricott and Garnett, 2007</xref>). In contrast, <italic>N. p. phaeton</italic> is widely distributed throughout northern Australia and is listed as being of least concern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C21">Garnett <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). <italic>Neochmia phaeton phaeton</italic> is not as threatened as its congener, but it is a riparian habitat specialist and is therefore susceptible to habitat fragmentation caused by land-management practices such as burning and grazing.<italic>Neochmia phaeton phaeton</italic> are small (females 9.7 g and males 10.0 g), sedentary passerines that breed during the wet season (roughly December–April in our study area; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C47">Milenkaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). They breed as socially monogamous pairs, in which the male builds the nest, the female lays a clutch of an average of five eggs, and both sexes incubate the eggs, and provision and defend the young (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C47">Milenkaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Detailed breeding biology and life-history traits of crimson finches from our study area are described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C47">Milenkaya <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref>.We monitored a population of <italic>N. p. phaeton</italic> at the Australian Wildlife Conservancy's Mornington Wildlife Sanctuary in northwest Australia (17°30′49″ S, 126°06′39″ E). The study area was a 2 km stretch of riparian habitat along Annie Creek that is actively managed for conservation. Here we monitored the crimson finch population for breeding activity and sampled the individuals for condition indices over four consecutive breeding seasons (from 15 November 2006 to 11 April 2007, from 5 December 2007 to 31 May 2008, from 9 December 2008 to 29 May 2009, and from 10 December 2009 to 10 May 2010).We captured adult crimson finches in mist-nets during the morning (up to 6 h) to minimize time-of-day effects on condition indices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C51">Norte <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C64">Sepp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). We banded the birds with a metal band (Australian Bird and Bat Banding Scheme) and up to three plastic colour bands for individual recognition. We determined the sex of each bird based on their sexually dimorphic plumage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C30">Higgins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). To sample for haematological condition indices, we punctured the birds' brachial vein with a needle and collected whole blood (up to 40 µl) into plastic, sodium-heparinized micro-haematocrit capillary tubes. We plugged the tubes and stored them on ice until further processing (within several hours; see subsection Condition indices below).We sampled 372 individual birds, which we aged based on known hatch dates, juvenal plumage, and molt limits. We were able to assign an accurate age to the individuals that were originally banded as nestlings or juveniles (25%, <italic>n</italic> = 92). Birds that were in adult plumage upon first capture were aged as being in their first year (23%, <italic>n</italic> = 85) if they had a molt limit between their retained, juvenal primary coverts and adjacent newer feathers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C47">Milenkaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), and in at least their second year if they had newly molted and fresh primary coverts at the beginning of the breeding season (10%, <italic>n</italic> = 39). Together, we refer to these individuals as known-aged birds. In contrast, all other individuals could not be aged because they were first captured as adults, and data on their molt were not collected (42%, <italic>n</italic> = 156).We monitored the breeding attempts of individual birds closely and could therefore attribute captured birds as being in one of the following stages of the breeding cycle at the time of capture: pre-breeding, nest building, egg laying, incubating, nestling, or post-breeding. Crimson finches in our study area are multi-brooded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C47">Milenkaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), so the nest building, egg laying, incubating, and nestling stages occur throughout the breeding season and do not necessarily represent the first breeding attempt of the season. The pre- and post-breeding stages, however, correspond to the beginning and end of the breeding seasons, respectively. Individuals were considered to be in the post-breeding stage when it was 3 weeks or more after their final breeding attempt ended (either through nest failure or because the last set of young became independent at 3 weeks post-fledging).Scoring criteria for furcular fat and pectoral muscleOther readily available condition indices include haematological parameters that are a result of an individual's nutritional status, stress level, and immune function. Packed red blood cell volume (PCV) is the proportion of red blood cells to the total volume of blood, and is often considered an aggregate indicator of overall health (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C22">Garvin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Low PCV and anaemia (PCV &lt;35% in birds; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C7">Campbell and Ellis, 2007</xref>) may be caused by blood loss (e.g. parasitism; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C69">Szabó <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), by destruction of erythrocytes (e.g. infectious agents or toxins), or by decreased production of erythrocytes [e.g. disease, nutritional stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C27">Harrison and Harrison, 1986</xref>, but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C18">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), or toxin exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C7">Campbell and Ellis, 2007</xref>)]. High PCV may be due either to dehydration or to an increased energy demand and resultant need for increased oxygen-carrying capacity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C8">Carpenter, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C32">Hõrak <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998a</xref>). The relationship between PCV and the oxygen-carrying capacity of blood is parabolic, such that both very low and very high PCV values result in decreased oxygen transport capability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C5">Birchard, 1997</xref>). Packed cell volume is related to haemoglobin concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C71">Velguth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), which also reflects the oxygen-carrying capacity of the blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C5">Birchard, 1997</xref>) and is lower in clinically sick birds compared with healthy birds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C2">Averbeck, 1992</xref>). Before collecting blood with a capillary tube, we collected ∼5 µl of it in a Hemacue cuvette and used the portable HemoCue Hb 201+ Analyzer (HemoCue, Inc., Cypress, CA, USA) in the field to estimate haemoglobin concentration (haemoglobin) from whole blood. Within a few hours of collecting blood in capillary tubes, we centrifuged (Hettich Haematokrit 210) the tubes for 15 min at 1433.6<italic>g</italic> and read the proportion of red blood cells to the total volume of blood (packed cell volume).Total plasma protein is a measure of proteins present in plasma; primarily albumin and globulin. Dehydration causes increases in both albumin and globulin, but an increase in globulin alone suggests inflammation and immune system stimulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C59">Rosenthal, 2000</xref>), and some have found that overall total plasma protein increases with inflammation/infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C12">de Lope <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C52">Ots and Hõrak, 1998</xref>). Decreases in total plasma protein may be caused by parasites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C50">Norte <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009a</xref>), and poor nutrition may result in decreased albumin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C59">Rosenthal, 2000</xref>), suggesting that albumin levels may reflect diet. Total plasma protein is therefore sometimes interpreted as an indicator of nutritional status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C23">Gavett and Wakeley, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C6">Brown, 1996</xref>) and as a measure of body condition (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C62">Schoech and Bowman, 2003</xref>). During the 2008–09 and 2009–10 field seasons, we extracted the plasma from the capillary tube after centrifugation and read the total plasma protein value (in grams per decilitre) with a hand-held refractometer (HR-200 ATC refractometer; AFAB Enterprises, Eustis, FL, USA). The total plasma protein values for bird samples obtained with this technique are sometimes consistent with and sometimes higher than values of those obtained from chemical analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C24">George, 2001</xref>).Heterophils and lymphocytes are white blood cells primarily involved in the immune response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C7">Campbell and Ellis, 2007</xref>). A high heterophil to lymphocyte ratio (H/L ratio) suggests an active inflammation response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C7">Campbell and Ellis, 2007</xref>) and can be correlated with elevated corticosterone levels in response to chronic stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C10">Davis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). We sampled for H/L ratio only during the 2008–09 and 2009–10 field seasons. During these years, we prepared blood smears immediately from collected blood and fixed the slides in 100% methanol on the same day. We then stained the smears with Dip Quick Stain Set (Jorgensen Laboratories, Inc., Loveland, CO, USA) at a later date. One of us (O.M.) performed a leucocyte differential count under ×1000 magnification by identifying 100 leucocytes as a heterophil, lymphocyte, eosinophil, basophil, or monocyte. The H/L ratio was calculated as the relative proportion of heterophils to lymphocytes counted in the blood smear.We used all sampled individuals to describe the distribution (mean ± SD, range) of each condition index and to test for pairwise correlations between the indices. If an individual was sampled more than once, we used the average value for that individual for each condition index in these descriptive analyses. We tested whether the continuous variables [packed cell volume, haemoglobin, total plasma protein, scaled mass, and log(H/L ratio)] were correlated with one another by using Pearson's correlation (cor function in R version 2.14.1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C57">R Development Core Team, 2012</xref>). We tested whether these continuous indices are correlated to muscle and fat scores, and whether muscle and fat scores are correlated to each other, by using polyserial and polychoral correlations, respectively (package polycor in R version 2.14.1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C19">Fox, 2010</xref>).To test the effects of sex, age, year, time of day, and breeding stage, as well as the interaction between sex and breeding stage, on each condition index we used restricted maximum likelihood to fit linear regression models. For these analyses, we included only known-aged individuals in the data set. To determine normality, we used the Shapiro–Wilk test and visual examination of the model residuals. The H/L ratios were base e log transformed to fit the assumptions of normality, whereas other condition indices were normally distributed. We included individual as a random effect in each of these models because some individuals were sampled more than once. To determine whether this analysis missed any significant effects due to small sample size, we conducted a second analysis in which all individuals were included, regardless of whether they were of known age or not. We calculated the time of day of capture as the length of time (in minutes) since sunrise.After finding significant effects of year and of the interaction between sex and breeding stage on many condition indices (see Results), we examined the parameter estimates and inferred statistical significance from the 95% confidence intervals for those estimates to better understand the effects of these terms on the condition indices. We set statistical significance at α = 0.05. Our figures show least-square means (±SEM) which are consistent with the raw data. We ran all models in JMP 9.0 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA).The distribution of observed values for each condition index among crimson finches, including the mean, standard deviation, minimum, maximum, and sample size (<italic>n</italic>)Pairwise correlations between condition indices, including the correlation coefficient, the sample size in parentheses, and asterisks indicating significance after Bonferroni correction for the Pearson's correlations (**<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001)Correlations between a continuous variable [packed cell volume, haemoglobin, total plasma protein, scaled mass, and log(H/L ratio)] and either muscle score or fat score are polyserial correlations, the correlation between muscle score and fat score is a polychoral correlation, and neither are tested for significance.The variation of each condition index by sex, year, age, breeding stage, sex by breeding stage interaction, and time of day, including the sample size (<italic>n</italic>) and r<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C2">2</xref></sup> for each model, and the degrees of freedom (d.f.), F-ratio (<italic>F</italic>) and <italic>P</italic>-value, with an asterisk denoting significance after Bonferroni correction for each covariate in the modelThe variation in condition indices among crimson finches by sex and breeding stage. Least-squares means (±SEM) of each condition index by sex and breeding stage, including packed cell volume (<bold>A</bold>), haemoglobin (<bold>B</bold>), total plasma protein (<bold>C</bold>), scaled mass (<bold>D</bold>), muscle score (<bold>E</bold>), fat score (<bold>F</bold>), and heterophil to lymphocyte ratio (H/L ratio; <bold>G</bold>). Sample sizes are given within each bar.The variation in scaled mass among crimson finches by age. Least-squares means (±SEM) of scaled mass (in grams) by age. Scaled mass trended positively with age, but the variable age was no longer significant in the model after Bonferroni correction. Sample sizes are given within each bar. Other condition indices did not vary significantly by age and are not illustrated here.Annual variation in haemoglobin, muscle, H/L ratio, and fat score among crimson finches. Least-squares means (±SEM) of haemoglobin (<bold>A</bold>), muscle score (<bold>B</bold>), H/L ratio (<bold>C</bold>), and fat score (<bold>D</bold>) by year. We include the H/L ratio and fat score here because they trended with year (both <italic>P</italic>-values = 0.002) even though these trends were not significant after Bonferroni correction. The H/L ratio values (C) were back transformed from a base e log to a linear scale. Sample sizes are given within each bar. Other condition indices did not significantly vary by year and are not illustrated here.We describe condition indices for a small tropical granivore, the crimson finch, and demonstrate that these indices vary by sex, breeding stage, and to a lesser extent age, year, and time of day. Our results demonstrate that researchers should control for these sources of variation (statistically or via sampling design) to interpret differences in condition correctly between individuals and populations.We found that most of the condition indices varied significantly by an interaction between sex and breeding stage. For females, much of this effect is most parsimoniously explained as a consequence of egg laying. Packed cell volume and haemoglobin decrease while total plasma protein and scaled mass increase in egg-laying females. This pattern has been reported previously (packed cell volume, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C18">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; and total plasma protein, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C32">Hõrak <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C61">Saino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C73">Wagner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The nadir for packed cell volume among egg-laying females is probably caused by changes in hormone levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C73">Wagner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), and this decrease in the proportion of red blood cells, and subsequently of haemoglobin, is not sufficiently low to be considered anaemia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C7">Campbell and Ellis, 2007</xref>). The high total plasma protein levels among egg-laying females may reflect female investment in their offspring's immunity by their transfer of immunoglobulins to the eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C61">Saino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>), but this hypothesis should be tested. Finally, the increased scaled mass among egg-laying females is an artifact of the developing egg mass and clearly does not reflect improved body condition. Generally, the changes in condition indices during egg laying for a given female cannot be interpreted as changes in her condition reflective of her interaction with the environment; however, a comparison of the magnitude of change between females in different environments may be informative in some cases.Consistent with the result that packed cell volume and haemoglobin are positively and strongly correlated in crimson finches (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COT020TB4">4</xref>) and in birds generally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C71">Velguth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), we found that the interaction between sex and breeding stage was very similar between these two indices. Males did not vary in either index with breeding stage, while females did. Their egg-laying decrease persisted through the incubating stage, when females still had lower values than males; however, female values increased thereafter and were again comparable to males during the nestling and post-breeding stages. A similar pattern was found among mountain white-crowned sparrows (<italic>Zonotrichia leucophrys oriantha</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C48">Morton, 1994</xref>).The interaction between sex and breeding stage may explain the inconsistent results of studies that considered only sex, but did not consider both sex and breeding stage. Some studies found males to have higher PCV values than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C60">Saino <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C53">Owen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), while another found females to have higher values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C39">Kilgas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006a</xref>), and still others found no sex difference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C11">Dawson and Bortolotti, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C38">Kasprzak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C28">Hatch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). In a meta-analysis of previously published articles, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C18">Fair <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> concluded that PCV was not different between the sexes. We suggest that the sexes may vary in their packed cell volume and haemoglobin values, but that this difference is stage dependent. We would not have found a sex effect had we not tested for the interaction term between sex and breeding stage, because the main effect of sex was not significant in our models.Significant decreases in protein concentration from the pre-breeding to the nestling stage occurred in both sexes, consistent with the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C32">Hõrak <italic>et al.</italic> (1998a)</xref> (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C61">Saino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). The low total plasma protein levels in females during the nestling stage may be due to depleted protein levels following egg production, but this does not explain why males also have their lowest total plasma protein levels during this stage, suggesting that a different mechanism is involved. Breeding birds may be suppressing their immune function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C25">Greenman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>) and thereby causing a decrease in total plasma protein levels during the nestling stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C1">Ardia, 2005</xref>). However, this condition index is also influenced by other factors. Total plasma protein levels increase with the nutritional value of food (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C23">Gavett and Wakeley, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C6">Brown, 1996</xref>), so the variability in total plasma protein among crimson finches may reflect the variability of food resources across the breeding season (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C32">Hõrak <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998a</xref>). Total plasma protein levels also increase with disease through an increase in circulating globulins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C52">Ots and Hõrak, 1998</xref>), as well as with dehydration. Dehydration is unlikely to be a factor among crimson finches, because they inhabit riparian areas where they have ready access to water. The changes between the pre-breeding and nestling stages we documented may therefore be interpreted as reflecting either changes in diet or changes in immune challenges, response, and/or function. The interpretation of total plasma protein levels in ecological studies is complicated by the fact that several factors can impact this index, and disentangling the mechanism behind a given trend is challenging. For example, high total plasma protein levels may be attributed to an individual being in good condition due to good nutrition, to an individual being in poor condition due to disease, or to dehydration. The lack of a clear and consistent interpretation of total plasma protein suggests that it should be interpreted with caution.Body mass is known to increase with time of day in diurnal birds due to overnight fasting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C55">Pravosudov and Grubb, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C64">Sepp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), and we found the same among crimson finches, although fat and muscle scores did not change with time of day.Both sexes had lower fat scores while breeding compared with the pre-breeding stage, but the timing of fat loss differed between the sexes, with males losing their fat during the nest-building stage, whereas females maintained high fat levels until the nestling stage. Crimson finch males, and not females, build the nests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C47">Milenkaya <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). This activity may explain the loss of fat among males during this stage, either because it is energetically costly or because it is adaptive to maintain lower fat stores during a period of high mobility. Crimson finch females not only had less fat but also had their lowest muscle scores during the nestling stage, suggesting that this is the most challenging time of the breeding season for them. Similar results were found among chick-rearing black-legged kittiwakes (<italic>Rissa tridactyla</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C41">Kitaysky <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>), American kestrels (<italic>Falco sparverius</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C11">Dawson and Bortolotti, 1997</xref>), and Savi's warblers (<italic>Locustella luscinioides</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C49">Neto and Gosler, 2009</xref>). However, male and female crimson finches provision the young to an approximately equal extent (personal observation by Olga Milenkaya, Virginia Tech), and males did not lose any muscle, fat, or scaled mass during the nestling stage, suggesting that more than simply the cost of provisioning young is involved in the changes we observed in females at this stage.The optimal body mass of a bird is influenced by physiological and ecological trade-offs between essential activities. The trade-off between starvation and predation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C43">McNamara and Houston, 1990</xref>) is an example; fat reserves decrease starvation risk but may increase predation risk, while pectoral muscle reserves lower predation risk through increased flight performance (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C58">Rogers, 2005</xref>). Food availability and predictability, in conjunction with predatory pressure and physiological demands such as thermoregulation, migration, and molt, may all impact optimal mass and the optimal allocation of resources between fat and muscle reserves. All of these variables may change throughout the breeding season of crimson finches, which may in turn affect optimal levels of scaled mass, fat, and muscle. Unfortunately, most of what we know about adaptive mass and its associated trade-offs, and the role of fat and muscle, comes from the study of migrants and northern-hemisphere temperate species, with little being known about sedentary birds in the tropics, such as crimson finches. We suggest that if fat and muscle scores are to be used as indicators of condition among sedentary and tropical birds, then we need to understand the costs and benefits of these reserves better for species that do not face the challenge of migration and that live in climates that are less variable or thermally challenging.Most of the condition indices we measured also varied significantly by sex. The mechanism behind the variation due to sex is important for interpreting condition because if, for example, this variation is solely due to hormones during the breeding season then sex may be a less important covariate if birds are sampled during the non-breeding season. Moreover, given that sex also interacts with breeding stage, condition indices should not be collected during the breeding season without detailed knowledge of the reproductive state of the individuals, a suggestion also made by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C61">Saino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>).Scaled mass was the only condition index to vary with age in crimson finches (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COT020TB5">5</xref>). Lack of pervasive effects of age on condition indices is consistent with some studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C66">Sheridan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>), but inconsistent with others, which found that age correlates with total plasma protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C15">Dyer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), PCV (through an interaction with sex), haemoglobin and H/L ratios (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C51">Norte <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009b</xref>). Ultimately, age effects are best tested longitudinally, which we were unable to do because we sampled few individuals across years and within the same breeding stage.Two condition indices varied significantly between years in crimson finches, including haemoglobin and muscle scores; H/L ratio and fat scores also varied by year, but these trends were not significant after Bonferroni correction. Others have also found that these and additional condition indices vary by year or season, suggesting an environmental effect on condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C51">Norte <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C72">Vinkler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). However, the annual variation we found was not consistent between condition indices. For example, muscle was lowest during the 2009–10 breeding season, but this was an average year for haemoglobin. Haemoglobin, muscle scores, H/L ratio, and fat scores reflect different aspects of the physiological state of the individual, which may explain the inconsistent trends between these condition indices across years.We suspect that the year effects we observed are likely to have resulted from differences in environmental conditions between years, for example variation in food supply mediated by weather. It is this type of relationship between individual condition and environmental conditions that is useful in conservation. If the year effect indeed reflects the environment, then the condition indices that show these year effects, i.e. haemoglobin, pectoral muscle scores, and to a lesser extent, H/L ratio and fat scores, may be the most appropriate ones for conservation applications. We documented considerable variability in condition indices attributable to sex, breeding stage, and the interaction between sex and breeding stage, and to a lesser extent age and time of day. This variation must be accounted for, either statistically or via sampling design, in order to interpret condition indices as indicators of environmental conditions. For example, in interpreting differences between two habitats using haemoglobin as an index, one would need to control for the confounding effects of breeding stage and a sex by stage interaction. In such cases, one should not view an absolute value of a given index as a measure of the physiological condition of an individual, but rather the condition of an individual is relative to conspecifics of the same sex, breeding stage, and possibly age. This has previously been suggested for at least some condition indices (e.g. PCV, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C18">Fair <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).If we assume for the moment that the year effects in our analyses do represent responses to annual variation in environmental conditions, then the two condition indices that exhibited no confounding effects such as sex and stage but did exhibit a year effect, i.e. pectoral muscle score and to a lesser extent H/L ratio, represent better choices for conservation applications. Those condition indices that exhibit several confounding effects but no year effect are the poorest choices, because the link between the environment and the condition index is not as direct and is confounded by other variables. However, our assumption about the source of year effects could be incorrect. Although others have demonstrated that condition indices do vary with habitat or environmental quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C45">Marra and Holberton, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C53">Owen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C35">Johnson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C31">Homyack, 2010</xref>), we cannot exclude the possibility that some or all of the year effects we observed in our study were a function of something other than environmental variation, such as a cohort effect. Understanding the mechanism of how pectoral muscle scores and H/L ratio are affected by environmental conditions, and what the consequences of that are for individuals and populations, are topics for further research.Underlying the use of condition indices in conservation is the often implicit assumption that condition and fitness are positively correlated; that is, even if a condition index exhibits a relationship to habitat or environmental conditions, if this relationship has no consequences for survival or reproduction then it does not inform conservation. Indeed, some condition indices have been found to correlate with primary components of fitness, such as reproductive success (mean corpuscular volume, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C3">Bearhop <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; total plasma protein, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C26">Gregg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) and survival (haemoglobin, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C4">Ben-David <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; and H/L ratio, globulin concentration, and albumin to globulin ratio, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C40">Kilgas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006b</xref>). Of the four condition indices that we suggest may be useful in conservation, both haemoglobin and H/L ratio have been found to predict survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C4">Ben-David <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C40">Kilgas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006b</xref>), indicating that they may be particularly useful indices, and we are not aware of any studies that tested whether muscle or fat score relate to fitness. However, the hypothesis that condition indices are meaningful indicators of fitness has been questioned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C11">Dawson and Bortolotti, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C42">Lailvaux and Kasumovic, 2011</xref>) and needs to be validated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C67">Stevenson and Woods, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C76">Wikelski and Cooke, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C35">Johnson, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT020C37">Johnstone <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012b</xref>) if condition indices are to be useful tools for conservation.We are especially grateful to our field assistants Roy Churchwell, Evan Rehm, and Jennifer Bruce for helping to collect these data. Thanks to Michelle Hall, Kim Maute, and Butch Maher for their invaluable help during the field seasons, and to J. Lindley McKay for his unwavering moral support. We thank two anonymous reviewers for helping to improve this manuscript. We thank the personnel at Mornington Wildlife Sanctuary and members of the Avian Ecology Laboratory at Virginia Tech. This study was based out of the WildlifeLink Centre for Research and Conservation at Mornington Wildlife Sanctuary. This work was supported by the Australian Wildlife Conservancy.