 Suppression of annual  Bromus tectorum  by perennial  Agropyron cristatum : roles of soil nitrogen availability and biological soil space  Seedling growth of intermountain perennial and weedy annual grasses  Merits of native and introduced Triticeae grasses on semiarid rangelands  Ecological impacts of cheatgrass and resultant fire on ecosystems in the Western Great Basin  Intraspecific and interspecific pair-wise seedling competition between exotic annual grasses and native perennials: plant–soil relationships  Mineral nitrogen in a crested wheatgrass stand: implications for suppression of cheatgrass  Suppression of  Bromus tectorum  L. by established perennial grasses: I. Potential mechanisms  Soil engineering facilitates downy brome ( Bromus tectorum ) growth—a case study  Plant–soil relationships of  Bromus tectorum  L: interactions among labile carbon additions, soil invasion status, and fertilizer  Geographical aspects of invasion: the annual bromes  Growth patterns of perennial grasses in the annual grassland type of southwest Oregon  Effects of established perennial grasses on yields of associated annual weeds  Effects of increased soil nitrogen on the dominance of alien annual plants in the Mojave Desert  Restoration ecology and invasive plants in the semiarid West  Nitrogen availability indices  Resilience to stress and disturbance, and resistance to  Bromus tectorum  L. invasion in cold desert shrublands of western North America  Annual and perennial grass growth on nitrogen-depleted decomposed granite  Stability of exotic annual grasses following restoration efforts in southern California coastal sage scrub  Increasing native diversity of cheatgrass-dominated rangeland through assisted succession  Exotic plant species as problems and solutions in ecological restoration: a synthesis  Ecological resistance in theory and practice  Biological invasions by exotic grasses, the grass/fire cycle, and global change  Restoring the sagebrush component in crested wheatgrass–dominated communities  Invasive weeds in rangelands: species, impacts, and management  Alien plant invasion and their impact on indigenous species diversity at global scale: a review  Effectiveness of rehabilitation practices following wildfire in a degraded big sagebrush-downy brome community  A place for alien species in ecosystem restoration  Crested wheatgrass-cheatgrass seedling competition in a mixed-density design  Fire, native species, and soil resource interactions influence the spatio-temporal invasion pattern of  Bromus tectorum   Morphology and response of roots of pasture species to phosphorus and nitrogen nutrition  Effects of soil resources on plant invasion and community structure in Californian serpentine grassland  Competition as a barrier to establishment of a native perennial grass ( Elymus elymoides ) in alien annual grass ( Bromus tectorum ) communities  Revegetating weed-infested rangeland: what we've learned  Linking nitrogen partitioning and species abundance to invasion resistance in the Great Basin  Nitrogen-inorganic forms  Cheatgrass ( Bromus tectorum L ) dominance in the Great Basin desert: history, persistence, and influences to human activities  Direct and indirect effects of exotic annual grasses on species composition of a South Australian grassland  Development of a DTPA soil test for zinc, iron, manganese, and copper  Invasion of  Bromus tectorum  L. into western North America: an ecological chronicle  Nitrogen uptake by perennial and invasive annual grass seedlings: nitrogen form effects  Is physical space a soil resource?  The occupation and fragmentation of space: consequences of neighbouring roots  Invasion resistance and persistence: established plants win, even with disturbance and high propagule pressure  Effects of nitrogen limitation on species replacement dynamics during early secondary succession on a semiarid sagebrush site  Grasses as invasive alien plants in South Africa  Contrasting responses of Intermountain West grasses to soil nitrogen  Effects of shade, litter and root competition on old-field vegetation in South Carolina  Immiscible displacement of the soil solution by centrifugation  Components of relative growth rate and sensitivity to nitrogen availability in annual and perennial species of  Bromus   Inhibition of nitrite-oxidizers by roots of grass  Plant diversity increases resistance to invasion in the absence of covarying extrinsic factors  Impacts of exotic annual brome grasses ( Bromus  spp.) on ecosystem properties of northern mixed grass prairie  Restoration of  Themeda australis  swards suppresses soil nitrate and enhances ecological resistance to invasion by exotic annuals  Root competition: beyond resource depletion   Bromus tectorum  invasion in South America: Patagonia under threat?  Community invasibility, recruitment limitation, and grassland biodiversity  Nitrogen enhances the competitive ability of cheatgrass ( Bromus tectorum ) relative to native grasses  Interactions between individual plant species and soil nutrient status in shortgrass steppe  Species effects on nitrogen cycling: a test with perennial grasses  Survival of downy brome ( Bromus tectorum ) seed in four environments  Ecology and management of medusahead ( Taeniatherum caput-medusae  ssp.  asperum  [SIMK.] MELDERIS)  Nitrogen interactions with medusahead ( Taeniatherum caput-medusae  ssp.  asperum ) seedbanks   Associate Editor:  Inderjit  Sagebrush ( Artemisia ) rangelands of the western United States are becoming dominated by the exotic annual grass cheatgrass ( Bromus tectorum ). Rehabilitation of invaded rangelands is predicated on establishing healthy and dense perennial grass communities, which suppress cheatgrass. Our research investigated how established plants of the perennial grass, crested wheatgrass ( Agropyron cristatum ), suppress cheatgrass. Our data suggest that established crested wheatgrass reduces soil nitrogen availability and occupies biological soil space such that growth of cheatgrass is significantly reduced. Greater understanding of the role of biological soil space could be used to breed and select plant materials with traits that are more suppressive to invasive annual grasses.  Worldwide, exotic invasive grasses have caused numerous ecosystem perturbations. Rangelands of the western USA have experienced increases in the size and frequency of wildfires largely due to invasion by the annual grass  Bromus tectorum . Rehabilitation of invaded rangelands is difficult; but long-term success is predicated on establishing healthy and dense perennial grass communities, which suppress  B. tectorum . This paper reports on two experiments to increase our understanding of soil factors involved in suppression. Water was not limiting in this study. Growth of  B. tectorum  in soil conditioned by and competing with the exotic perennial  Agropyron cristatum  was far less relative to its growth without competition. When competing with  A. cristatum , replacing a portion of conditioned soil with fresh soil before sowing of  B. tectorum  did not significantly increase its growth. The ability of conditioned soil to suppress  B. tectorum  was lost when it was separated from growing  A. cristatum . Soil that suppressed  B. tectorum  growth was characterized by low mineral nitrogen (N) availability and a high molar ratio of    N     O  2     −      in the solution-phase pool of    N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −    .    Moreover, resin availability of    N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −      explained 66 % of the variability in  B. tectorum  above-ground mass, attesting to the importance of  A. cristatum  growth in reducing N availability to  B. tectorum . Trials in which  B. tectorum  was suppressed the most were characterized by very high shoot/root mass ratios and roots that have less root hair growth relative to non-suppressed counterparts, suggesting co-opting of biological soil space by the perennial grass as another suppressive mechanism. Greater understanding of the role of biological soil space could be used to breed and select plant materials with traits that are more suppressive to invasive annual grasses.  Invasive exotic grasses are causing ecosystem perturbations with lasting consequences worldwide ( Lenz  et al . 2003 ;  Ogle  et al . 2003 ;  Milton 2004 ;  Dogra  et al . 2010 ;  Speziale  et al . 2014 ). Especially pernicious invaders are the exotic annual grasses ( DiTomaso 2000 ;  Blumler 2006 ). Rehabilitation of annual grass-degraded lands can be exceedingly difficult, expensive and prone to failure ( Young 1992 ;  Jacobs  et al . 1998 ;  Cox and Allen 2008 ).  (A) A far too typical landscape scene in northern Nevada, USA, several years after a wildfire. This landscape, once occupied by  Artemisia wyomingesis  and perennial grasses, is now dominated by  B. tectorum  and represents an environment exceedingly difficult to rehabilitate. Photographic examples showing perennial grass suppression of  B. tectorum . (B) A high-elevation community in the Virginia Range, Nevada, USA. In the foreground is the native perennial  Pseudoroegneria spicata  with no presence of  B. tectorum . (C)  Agropyron cristatum  sown after a wildfire in the early 1990s near Midas, Nevada. Although individual plants suppress  B. tectorum , the density of perennial grasses is insufficient to prevent re-invasion by the exotic annual. Surface soil litter is mainly from  B. tectorum . (D) A dense and robust community of  A. cristatum  planted after a 1985 wildfire near the Peterson Range, Nevada, which should resist re-invasion by  B. tectorum  if managed properly. Characteristic of all these suppressed areas is a ring around the perennial grasses that contain no plants of  B. tectorum  even though seedbank analyses indicate the presence of germinable seeds.  Fortunately, some plant communities resist invasion by  B. tectorum ; they are able to suppress its growth ( James  et al . 2008 ;  Blank and Morgan 2012 a  ;  Chambers  et al . 2014 ). Common threads to this resistance/suppression are well-established, healthy, and properly-spaced populations of perennial grasses (Fig.  1 B–D,  Humphrey and Schupp 2004 ;  McGlone  et al . 2011 ). Understanding how soil biochemical attributes affect suppression and how these attributes interact with a perennial grass offers hope of greater success in rehabilitating exotic annual grass-degraded ecosystems ( D'Antonio and Thomsen 2004 ). The nature of suppression is complex and involves biotic and abiotic processes that temporally interact with soil type, the array of plant communities and characteristics of the invasive species ( Huenneke  et al . 1990 ;  Tilman 1997 ;  Naeem  et al . 2000 ;  Gundale  et al . 2008 ). Established perennial plants can simply reduce soil resources to levels below which annual grasses are no longer as competitive ( Wedin and Tilman 1990 ;  Claassen and Marler 1998 ;  Prober and Lunt 2009 ). Suppression of annual grasses may also involve root competition other than nutrient depletion whence perennial roots simply occupy biological soil space and, through chemical signalling, allelopathy included, may forestall competing roots from entering their space ( Monk and Gabrielson 1985 ;  McConnaughay and Bazzaz 1992 ;  Schenk 2006 ).  In a previous study, we explored the mechanistic underpinnings of perennial grass suppression of  B. tectorum  ( Blank and Morgan 2012 b  ). The data suggest that perennial grass roots reduced soil nitrogen (N) and phosphorous (P) availability and occupied biological soil space, thereby reducing  B. tectorum  growth. This paper reports on additional experiments to more definitively elucidate soil factors involved in suppression of  B. tectorum.  The perennial grass used was  Agropyron cristatum , a native to Russia and central Asia. This grass is often used to rehabilitate degraded rangelands in the western USA, and well-established stands effectively suppress  B. tectorum  ( Evans and Young 1978 ;  Wicks 1997 ). Two hypotheses were tested: (i) soil conditioning brought about by established  A. cristatum  will reduce availability of soil mineral N and P to levels low enough to significantly reduce growth  of B. tectorum , and (ii) occupation of biological soil space by roots of  A. cristatum  will cause roots of  B. tectorum  to alter their architecture, morphology and activity resulting in reduced growth, i.e. suppression.  Two experiments were conducted in a greenhouse at Reno, NV, USA (39°32′17.20″N; 119°48′22.89″W). Prior to each experiment, soil substrate was freshly collected from a  Krascheninnikovia lanata  (winterfat) site, invaded by  B. tectorum  for about 12 years, ∼80 km northwest of Reno, NV, USA (40°7′59.43″N; 120°6′56.18″W). This soil, conditioned by  B. tectorum , has elevated soil N availability relative to nearby soil conditioned by native vegetation ( Blank and Morgan 2013 ). Surface soils (0–25 cm, corresponding to the A horizon) were composited from an area of ∼10 m 2 . Soils, loamy sand in texture, were sieved to &lt;4 mm to remove coarse fragments and medium-to-large roots and homogenized by hand mixing on a greenhouse bench. Four replicates of this soil were analysed for various attributes (see below). This original soil—referred to as fresh soil—is taken from a soil classified as a coarse-loamy, mixed, superactive, calcareous, mesic Typic Torriorthent.  Experiment 1 quantified the suppression of  B. tectorum  (cheatgrass) by established  A. cristatum  (crested wheatgrass). Twelve replicate clear plastic rhizotrons, 5 × 30 × 100 cm depth, were filled with equal volumes of soil. The outsides of the rhizotrons were covered with insulation that could be removed from the back to observe rooting patterns. Prior to seed planting, rhizotrons were paired in adjoining plastic containers to maintain a slight angle so that roots would readily intercept the clear rhizotron backing for observation, and deionized water was added to reach field capacity—∼6 % by weight for the soils used—over the entire rhizotron. Two seeds of  A. cristatum  were sown in the rhizotrons 6 cm from each edge to leave an 18 cm space in between for later planting of  B. tectorum , and allowed to establish for 68 days, the conditioning phase. We define conditioning as the plant species-dependent engendering specific traits such as carbon flow, root exudation, nutrient uptake, root occupancy of soil space, alteration of the soil microbial community etc. that might affect competitive interactions. During establishment,  A. cristatum  was supplemented with 500–1000 mL of deionized water per week depending on depletion in the rhizotron as gauged by visual inspection when opaque backs were removed. After establishment, four treatments were randomly imposed to three replicate rhizotrons. In one treatment,  B. tectorum  was sown directly between  A. cristatum  in the conditioned soil as a test for maximal suppression. For the next treatment, 500 g of soil were removed from between the established  A. cristatum  plants, replaced with 500 g of fresh soil and  B. tectorum  sown in the new soil. The purpose of this treatment was to test how fresh soil mitigated against suppression. In another treatment, 500 g of conditioned soil were removed from between the established  A. cristatum  plants; then a nylon mesh (2-mm opening) was placed in the excavated area, 500 g of fresh soil were placed over the mesh and  B. tectorum  sown. Our purpose was to examine how reduced root movement into the fresh soil from  A. cristatum , but still allowing diffusion of gases, solutes and microbes from the adjacent conditioned soil, affects suppression. For the last treatment, 500 g of soil were removed from between the established  A. cristatum  plants; then a plastic barrier was placed in the hole and filled with 500 g of fresh soil, and sown to  B. tectorum . This treatment tested  B. tectorum  suppression upon total blocking of  A. cristatum  roots, which would affect biological soil space and exposure to potential pathogenic organisms and allelochemicals in soil conditioned by  A. cristatum . Deionized water was immediately applied to soil above the newly sown seeds of  B. tectorum . A small subsample of the homogenized 500 g conditioned soil was analysed for several soil attributes (see below). We also grew  B. tectorum  without competition in small containers filled with 500 g of either fresh soil or conditioned soil (from the soil excavated from rhizotrons). During growth of  B. tectorum , rhizotrons and containers were watered twice weekly; water was not limiting to  B. tectorum  in this study. Supplemental lighting, using four high-pressure sodium lamps each producing 124 000 lumens at 2100 K temperature, was used to assure at least 12 h of daylight. After 70 days of growth,  B. tectorum  was clipped at the soil surface, dried for 48 h at 70 °C and weight recorded. Soil within the rooting zone of  B. tectorum  was excavated and roots reserved. Subsamples of roots from each treatment and replicates were washed, immediately observed with a light microscope and photographs taken. These subsamples were then added to the original sample, dried for 48 h at 70 °C and weight recorded. After harvest, soil within the rooting zone of  B. tectorum  of each treatment was homogenized and analysed for solution-phase anions (Cl − ,    N     O  2     −    ,   N     O  3     −    ,   S     O  4     2  −      and  ortho -P) using immiscible displacement ( Mubarak and Olsen 1976 ) with quantification by ion chromatography (Dionex ®  AS11-HC column with gradient elution) and mineral N, defined as    N     H  4     +    +  N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −    ,    by 1.5 M KCl extraction ( Keeney and Nelson 1982 ).  Experiment 2 explored the role of soil nutrient availability of N and P in the suppression process and tested to a greater extent if and how conditioned soil affects suppression. Twelve rhizotrons were filled with freshly collected soil and planted to  A. cristatum  (see Experiment 1). Soil was conditioned by  A. cristatum  for 64 days with lighting and watering as described for Experiment 1. Four treatments were imposed following conditioning by  A. cristatum . In four randomly chosen rhizotrons,  B. tectorum  was sown directly between established  A. cristatum  to test for maximal suppression (Treatment 1). The remaining eight rhizotrons had their backs removed and soil was separated by depths (0–30 cm (Treatment 2), 30–60 cm (Treatment 3) and 60–90 cm (Treatment 4)), and homogenized along with any roots present. For each soil depth separate, 2500 g was placed in containers and  B. tectorum  immediately sown. These treatments tested the suppressive ability of conditioned soil, by depth, without live plants of  A. cristatum , but with different amounts of now inactive roots present depending on soil depth, greatest in the 0–30 cm depth increment and least in the 60–90 cm depth increment. In similar-sized containers,  B. tectorum  was sown in fresh soil to serve as unsuppressed controls (six replicates). To gauge the influence of  B. tectorum  growth on post-harvest soil attributes, five replicates of unplanted controls in fresh soil were prepared in similar-sized containers. For all experimental units, one anion and cation exchange resin capsule (Unibest ® ) was placed at 15 cm directly beneath where  B. tectorum  was sown to gauge nutrient availability. After 64 days of growth, above-ground and root biomass of  B. tectorum  were harvested, dried and weighed. Resin capsules were removed, washed extensively with deionized water, dried and treated with 40 mL of 1 N HCl and shaken for 30 min. Resin availability of    N     H  4     +    ,   N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −      and  ortho -P were quantified using a Lachat ®  autoanalyser. Soil in the rooting zone of  B. tectorum  was homogenized and analysed for mineral N and soil-solution anions as stated in Experiment 1. Availability of micronutrients was determined using the DTPA method ( Lindsay and Norvell 1978 ). Nitrogen mineralization potential was quantified using a moist 30-day incubation procedure ( Bundy and Meisinger 1994 ). Total soil C and N were quantified using a LECO Truspec ®  analyser.  The data structure for Experiment 1 includes eight treatments with replication for a total of 38 experimental units. Experiment 2 had 10 treatments with replication for a total of 43 experimental units. For each experiment, a separate ANOVA was performed and means separated using Tukey's honest significant difference test. A backward selective regression was used to identify variables possibly related to above-ground  B. tectorum  biomass. The procedure was applied separately to Experiments 1 and 2 and to the combined data set.  Above-ground biomass and shoot/root mass ratios of  B. tectorum  plants following harvest of Experiments 1 and 2. For each panel, ANOVA results are provided and bars with non-overlapping letters are significantly different at the ≤0.05 level.  Selected soil attributes for Experiment 1. 1    1 For each column, means with different superscripted letters are significantly different at the &lt;0.05 level; mineral N is total    N     H  4     +    +  N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −      extractable by KCl; mole    N     O  2     −      is the molar proportion of    N     O  2     −      in the solution-phase pool of    N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −    .    Attributes unaffected by treatment included solution-phase    N     O  2     −    ,   N     O  3     −      and    S     O  4     2  −    .      2 Soil from a homogenized subsample taken between  A. cristatum  that established for 60 days in rhizotrons.   3 Soil from a homogenized subsample taken from the rooting zone of  B. tectorum  in competition with  A. cristatum  in rhizotrons.   4 Soil from homogenized subsamples of the fresh soil and the fresh soil placed above the mesh or plastic barrier in rhizotrons.   5 Soil from a homogenized subsample of entire container.  Similar to Experiment 1, established  A. cristatum  suppressed the growth of  B. tectorum  relative to its non-competed growth in fresh or conditioned soil (Fig.  1 ). Suppressed  B. tectorum , akin to Experiment 1, had very high shoot to root mass ratios. Growth of  B. tectorum  was not nearly as suppressed when grown in conditioned soil taken from three depths in rhizotrons planted to  A. cristatum  (Fig.  1 ). Moreover, shoot to root mass ratios of  B. tectorum  grown non-competed in this conditioned soil were similar to those of non-competed  B. tectorum  grown in fresh soil (Experiment 1).  Selected soil attributes for Experiment 2. 1    1 For each column, means with different superscripted letters are significantly different at the &lt;0.05 level; mineral N is total    N     H  4     +    +  N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −      extractable by KCl; resin N includes    N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −    ;    mole    N     O  2     −      is the molar proportion of    N     O  2     −      in the solution-phase pool of    N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −    ;    nd, not determined. Attributes unaffected by treatment included 30-day aerobic incubated NH 4  +  and NO 3  − , net N mineralization potentials, total C and N, and DTPA extractable Fe and Cu.   2 Soils taken after 64 days conditioning by  A. cristatum  from rhizotrons and homogenized by depth.   3 Soils collected from within rooting zone of  B. tectorum  in rhizotrons that were conditioned by  A. cristatum  for 64 days.   4 Soils from homogenized sample of entire container.  Graphs showing variables strongly related to above-ground biomass as determined by backward selection regression. Top graph, combined Experiments 1 and 2, relates root biomass with above-ground biomass. Middle graph relates resin availability of    N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −      with above-ground biomass; resin data were only collected for Experiment 2. Bottom graph, combined Experiments 1 and 2, relates predicted above-ground biomass using the combination of root biomass and solution-phase    N     O  3     −    .     It is not surprising that lowered soil N availability, due to established  A. cristatum , would suppress the growth of  B. tectorum . Many annual grasses, including  B. tectorum , are nitrophiles and their growth is stimulated by additions of mineral N ( Huenneke  et al . 1990 ;  Brooks 2003 ;  Vasquez  et al . 2008 ). Conversely, growth of annual grasses are often suppressed when mineral N is lowered by manipulating solution culture ( Muller and Garnier 1990 ) or by addition of labile C sources that immobilize soil N ( McLendon and Redente 1992 ;  Young  et al . 1998 ;  Blank and Young 2009 ).  Besides availability of N, other aspects of the soil N cycle may be involved, at least tangentially, in suppression of  B. tectorum . Soil conditioned by  A. cristatum  and competing with  B. tectorum  had very high molar proportions of    N     O  2     −      in the solution-phase    N     O  2     −    +  N     O  3     −      pool (Tables  1  and  2 ). Moreover, that soils only conditioned by  A. cristatum  prior to sowing  B. tectorum  had far lower molar    N     O  2     −      levels suggests that the grasses interact with the soil differently when combined than they do individually. Perennial grasses differentially affect soil N cycling ( Wedin and Tilman 1990 ;  Vinton and Burke 1995 ), but we are unaware of any literature that tested the combined effect of a perennial grass and an annual grass on the soil N cycle. Roots of grasses can inhibit nitrite-oxidizers ( Munro 1966 ); but why then did the greatest molar content occur only upon growth of  B. tectorum. Bromus tectorum  has high affinity to uptake N in the    N     O  3     −     −  N     form relative the    N     H  4     +     −  N     form ( MacKown  et al . 2009 ), but we are unaware of any data on its ability to uptake the    N     O  2     −     −  N     form. If  B. tectorum  does not have a high affinity to uptake the    N     O  2     −     −  N     form, then perennial grasses that inhibit nitrate-oxidizers would likely elevated their suppressive ability.  We accept hypothesis 2 that occupation of biological soil space by established roots of  A. cristatum  will suppress growth of  B. tectorum . Compelling aspects of our data include high shoot to root ratios of  B. tectorum  when competing with established  A. cristatum  (Fig.  2 ), response of  B. tectorum  to varying soil treatments (Fig.  2 ), and distinct elongated root architectures with far fewer root hairs in the most suppressed trials. The concept of biological soil space implies that physical space is a resource in itself, beyond that of access to nutrients and water ( McConnaughay and Bazzaz 1991 ,  1992 ). In this construct, occupation of physical space by roots of established  A. cristatum  will constrain root growth of  B. tectorum . The mechanistic underpinnings of suppression via biological soil space may involve root signalling or root toxicity ( Schenk 2006 ). It is possible that the elevated shoot to root ratios in  B. tectorum  competing against established  A. cristatum  in this study is likely less due to reduced availability of N than interactions with pre-existing roots of  A. cristatum . Low soil N availability should stimulate rather than decrease root growth ( Hill  et al . 2006 ). If reduced biological soil space due to established  A. cristatum  roots is partly responsible for suppression of  B. tectorum ; then replacement of conditioned soil between established  A. cristatum  plants should have increased biological space for  B. tectorum  root growth and also increased nutrient availability resulting in less suppression—yet suppression still occurred. One possibility is that roots of  A. cristatum  may have proliferated in the fresh soil and simply occupied soil space faster than roots of the newly sown  B. tectorum . Visual inspection upon harvesting  B. tectorum  did reveal the presence of  A. cristatum  roots. Moreover, very low post-harvest mineral N levels in the fresh soil (Table  1 ) lend support to the re-occupation of biological soil space by  A. cristatum  as such small plants of  B. tectorum  simply could not have depleted that much mineral N. We also expected a mesh would limit new root encroachment by  A. cristatum  and the fresh soil placed above the mesh would have much un-occupied biological soil space for roots of  B. tectorum  to proliferate; yet,  B. tectorum  planted in this soil was still suppressed and had high shoot to root ratios. Indeed, as the mesh was removed from the rhizotrons following harvest of  B. tectorum , visible inspection indicated very few roots of  A. cristatum  had penetrated the mesh. Nonetheless, the fresh soil added above the mesh had very low mineral N content after harvest, in fact the lowest among all the treatments. Clearly, enough  A. cristatum  roots had penetrated the mesh to reduce mineral N content and thereby partially suppressed  B. tectorum  via lowered N availability. In all individual trials of  B. tectorum  competing with established  A. cristatum , no matter the treatment, post-harvest  B. tectorum  had high shoot to root ratios (Fig.  2 ) and decreased root hair formation. Recent research has demonstrated that root competition is far more complex than simple resource depletion (see review by  Schenk 2006 ). In this new construct of root to root interactions, it is possible that newly establishing roots of  B. tectorum  sense the presence of  A. cristatum  roots and do not grow appreciably into the fresh soil provided. Alternatively, established roots of  A. cristatum  may exude toxic substances that affect  B. tectorum  root architecture; unfortunately our experimental protocols are not able to rigorously test this conjecture.  Soil conditioned by  A. cristatum , then homogenized (roots of  A. cristatum  were also homogenized), potted and sown to  B. tectorum  produced far more above-ground biomass than it did when competing with  A. cristatum . Our expectation was that the conditioned soil separated from  A. cristatum  would retain its ability to suppress  B. tectorum  because the soil would have depleted N availability, at least initially. Moreover, we expected conditioned soil from the 0–30 cm depth increment would have greater filling of biological soil space with established roots of  A. cristatum  and therefore be more suppressive to  B. tectorum  than conditioned soil from lower depths. In fact, conditioned soil removed from rhizotrons did not suppress  B. tectorum  and shoot to root mass ratios were not elevated as in competed trials. Lack of suppression in this situation may be explained by the following. Firstly, the now dead roots of  A. cristatum  have mineralized and contributed N to enhance  B. tectorum  growth. The relatively high mineral N and resin available N levels post-harvest for these trials lend credence to this possibility. Secondly, the lack of an established root system of  A. cristatum  due to homogenization prior to sowing  B. tectorum  in containers may free up biological soil space for  B. tectorum  resulting in lower root to root signalling and exudation of toxins ( Schenk 2006 ).  We expected that  B. tectorum  growing in the fresh soil above the plastic barrier in the rhizotrons would have above-ground biomass similar to its growth, non-competed, in fresh soil. Why then did the plastic barrier facilitate even greater growth of  B. tectorum ? Speculating, given the equal watering regimes used in all experimental units, the plastic barrier could have reduced water flow beyond the rooting zone of  B. tectorum  and essentially provided greater water availability.  The non-native perennial grass  A. cristatum , when established, suppresses the growth of the exotic annual grass,  B. tectorum . Reduced soil N availability and co-opting of soil space by perennial grass roots are potential soil factors involved in suppression. If only it were as easy to establish perennial grasses on  B. tectorum -invaded rangelands as it is in the greenhouse, rehabilitation of  B. tectorum  degraded rangelands would be easier and far less expensive. The use of non-native plant materials to facilitate rehabilitation of exotic annual grass-invaded rangelands is controversial ( D'Antonio and Meyerson 2002 ). Some researchers, however, make the case that particular non-natives possess attributes that allow faster and more effective rehabilitation ( Asay  et al . 2001 ;  Ewel and Putz 2004 ). The reality that  A. cristatum  suppresses  B. tectorum  so effectively offers opportunities to use this species and other non-native competitive grasses as a successional bridge to encourage subsequent native plant recruitment ( Cox and Anderson 2004 ;  Brown  et al . 2008 ;  Davies  et al . 2013 ). Perennial grasses differ markedly in their ability to suppress annual grasses ( Borman  et al . 1990 ,  1991 ). A portion of the suppressive ability  of A. cristatum  is via utilization of soil N resources such that it is less available to  B. tectorum ; however, the annual is also an effective competitor for soil N ( Monaco  et al . 2003 ). If perennial grasses do not strongly couple root uptake of N with the timing of its availability in soil, pulses of availability can occur leading to less suppression. We believe greater understanding of aspects of suppression via biological soil space can be a fruitful area of research. What specific properties do established perennial grasses engender to biological soil space to resist subsequent growth of alien annual grasses? Is allelopathy involved? Is alteration of the soil microbial community involved? Understanding specific mechanisms could direct plant breeding strategies to develop perennial grasses more suppressive to exotic annual grasses.  This research is funded through  USDA-Agricultural Research Service  Project No:  5370-13610-001-00D .  R.R.B. designed the experiment, analysed the data and was the principle writer. T.M. designed and built rhizotrons. T.M. and F.A. collected soils, monitored the experiments and conducted soil analyses.  None declared.  We thank the associate editor and anonymous reviewers for constructive criticisms leading to a more impactful paper. 