Genomic sequencing and microsatellite marker development for <italic>Boswellia papyrifera</italic>, an economically important but threatened tree native to dry tropical forestsIncense Woodlands in Ethiopia and Eritrea: regeneration problems and restoration possibilitiesPopulation status of <italic>Boswellia papyrifera</italic> (Del.) Hochst in the dry woodlands of Nuba Mountains, South Kordofan State, SudanMolecular genetic techniques and markers for ecological researchPopulation differentiation and connectivity among fragmented Moor frog (<italic>Rana arvalis</italic>) populations in the NetherlandsBiophysical and chemical investigations of frankincense of <italic>Boswellia papyrifera</italic> from north and northwestern Ethiopia<italic>Phytochemical investigations on Boswellia species. Comparative studies on the essential oils, pyrolysates and boswellic acids of Boswellia carterii</italic> Birdw<italic>., Boswellia serrata</italic> Roxb<italic>., Boswellia frereana</italic> Birdw.<italic>, Boswellia neglecta</italic> S. Moore <italic>and Boswellia rivae</italic> EnglComparative phytochemical analyses of resins of <italic>Boswellia</italic> species (<italic>B. papyrifera</italic> (Del.) Hochst., <italic>B. neglecta</italic> S. Moore, and <italic>B. rivae</italic> Engl.) from Northwestern, Southern, and Southeastern EthiopiaDevelopment, characterization and mapping of microsatellite markers in <italic>Eucalyptus grandis</italic> and <italic>E. urophylla</italic>Modulation of non-templated nucleotide addition by Taq DNA polymerase: primer modifications that facilitate genotypingUsing genetic markers to directly estimate gene flow and reproductive success parameters in plants based on naturally regenerated seedlingsRapid microsatellite identification from Illumina paired-end genomic sequencing in two birds and a snakeMicrosatellite markers for conservation and population genetics of tropical tree speciesBlast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics researchOverview of international trades and marketsAssembly, gene annotation and marker development using 454 floral transcriptome sequences in <italic>Ziziphus celata</italic> (Rhamnaceae), a highly endangered, Florida Endemic PlantApplications of next generation sequencing in molecular ecology of non-model organismsTransferability of newly developed pear SSR markers to other <italic>Rosaceae</italic> speciesMicroprep protocol for extraction of DNA from tomato and herbaceous plantsForest-tree population genomics and adaptive evolutionLimitations to sustainable frankincense production: blocked regeneration, high adult mortality, and declining populationA draft <italic>de novo</italic> genome assembly for the northern Bobwhite (<italic>Colinus virginianus</italic>) reveals evidence for a rapid decline in effective population size beginning in the late PleistoceneRepbase update, a database of eukaryotic repetitive elementsRepARK—<italic>de novo</italic> creation of repeat libraries from whole-genome NGS reads32 species validation of a new Illumina paired-end approach for the development of microsatellitesFast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2Frankincense and myrrh resources of Ethiopia: medicinal and industrial usesGum and Resin resources from some <italic>Acacia</italic>, <italic>Boswellia</italic>, and <italic>Commiphora</italic> species and their economic contributions in Liban, south-east EthiopiaConstraints to smallholders production of frankincense in Metema district, North-western Ethiopia<italic>De novo</italic> assembly of human genomes with massively parallel short read sequencingCOPE: an accurate k-mer-based pair-end reads connection tool to facilitate genome assemblyMusket: a multistage k-mer spectrum-based error corrector for Illumina sequence dataHow and why should we implement genomics into conservation?Current conservation genetics: building an ecological approach to the synthesis of molecular and quantitative genetic methodsCombining transcriptome assemblies from multiple <italic>de novo</italic> assemblers in the allo-tetraploid plant <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>DNA fingerprinting in botany: past, present, futureThe distribution of the francincense tree <italic>Boswellia papyrifera</italic> in Eritrea: the role of environment and land useCharacterisation of microsatellite markers in <italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic> L. and <italic>Fagus orientalis</italic> LipskyFrom conservation genetics to conservation genomicsPrimer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmersQuality control and preprocessing of metagenomic datasetsAn economic method for the fluorescent labelling of PCR fragments: a poor man's approach to genotyping for research and high-throughput diagnosticsMicrosatellites for ecologists: a practical guide to using and evaluating microsatellite markersSNP markers retrieval for a non-model species: a practical approachUse of short microsatellites from database sequences to generate polymorphisms among <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> cultivars and accessions of other <italic>Lycopersicon</italic> speciesTrinucleotide repeat microsatellite markers for black poplar (<italic>Populus nigra</italic> L.)Structure of the genetic diversity in Black poplar (<italic>Populus nigra</italic> L.) populations across European river systems: consequences for conservation and restorationCharacterisation of sugar beet (<italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> L. ssp. vulgaris) varieties using microsatellite markersHigh throughput marker development and application in horticultural cropsFrankincense tree recruitment failed over the past half centuryFrankincense and myrrhCharacterization of microsatellites revealed by genomic sequencing of <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic>Next-Gen phylogeography of rainforest trees: exploring landscape-level cpDNA variation from whole-genome sequencingGAM-NGS: genomic assemblies merger for next generation sequencingEfficient development of highly polymorphic microsatellite markers based on polymorphic repeats in transcriptome sequences of multiple individualsDryland resources, livelihoods and institutions: diversity and dynamics in use and management of gum and resin trees in EthiopiaOptimizing <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of short-read RNA-seq data for phylogenomicsUsing next-generation sequencing approaches to isolate simple sequence repeat (SSR) loci in the plant sciences<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Kermit RitlandThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The world famous aromatic resin Frankincense is tapped from natural populations of <italic>Boswellia</italic> trees. Most of these populations have been shrinking rapidly over recent decades. To help guide conservation efforts for imperilled species of this genus, we developed 46 genetic markers for <italic>Boswellia papyrifera</italic>. Several of these were cross-transferable to other <italic>Boswellia</italic> species that occur in Ethiopia and Yemen. We also identified genes involved in the biosynthesis of the terpenes and terpenoids that are major constituents of frankincense.Microsatellite (or simple sequence repeat, SSR) markers are highly informative DNA markers often used in conservation genetic research. Next-generation sequencing enables efficient development of large numbers of SSR markers at lower costs. <italic>Boswellia papyrifera</italic> is an economically important tree species used for frankincense production, an aromatic resinous gum exudate from bark. It grows in dry tropical forests in Africa and is threatened by a lack of rejuvenation. To help guide conservation efforts for this endangered species, we conducted an analysis of its genomic DNA sequences using Illumina paired-end sequencing. The genome size was estimated at 705 Mb per haploid genome. The reads contained one microsatellite repeat per 5.7 kb. Based on a subset of these repeats, we developed 46 polymorphic SSR markers that amplified 2–12 alleles in 10 genotypes. This set included 30 trinucleotide repeat markers, four tetranucleotide repeat markers, six pentanucleotide markers and six hexanucleotide repeat markers. Several markers were cross-transferable to <italic>Boswellia pirrotae</italic> and <italic>B. popoviana</italic>. In addition, retrotransposons were identified, the reads were assembled and several contigs were identified with similarity to genes of the terpene and terpenoid backbone synthesis pathways, which form the major constituents of the bark resin.To implement an effective conservation programme, it is essential to understand the genetic structure of endangered populations and the dynamics of genetic variation over space and time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C26">Karp <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C10">Burczyk <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C21">González-Martínez <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C19">Frankham <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C39">Nybom <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Microsatellite or simple sequence repeat (SSR) markers have been widely applied in quantifying the level of genetic variation and its spatial organization, describing the demography and history of populations, and analysing the gene flow and parentage in plants and animals (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C4">Arens <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C51">Smulders <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C43">Primmer 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C3">Allan and Max 2010</xref>). These repeats are abundant in the genome, polymorphic and multi-allelic (thus highly informative), have co-dominant inheritance (allowing a direct measurement of heterozygosity), and markers based on them are frequently transferable across related species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C12">Chase <italic>et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C49">Smulders <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C50">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C8">Brondani <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C42">Pastorelli <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C56">Tuskan <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C47">Selkoe and Toone 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C3">Allan and Max 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C17">Fan <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>).Recently, next-generation sequencing technologies have simplified generating large amounts of sequences at affordable cost, thus facilitating the development of molecular markers, including SSRs and single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C15">Edwards <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C16">Ekblom and Galindo 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C11">Castoe <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C53">Smulders <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C28">Lance <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C59">Vukosavljev <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>), as well as chloroplast sequences for phylogeographical studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C57">Van der Merwe <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The development of markers has thus become feasible also for species for which no prior sequence information exists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C53">Smulders <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), including understudied but economically important crops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C62">Zalapa <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>).Marker development can be based on short-length sequences from genomic DNA sequences or cDNA (RNA-seq). Both sets of reads are useful, but they differ with regard to further data mining. RNA-seq data can be <italic>de novo</italic> assembled into a (partial) transcriptome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C61">Yang and Smith 2013</xref>) with some caveats, partly related to the assembler used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C48">Shahin <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). A common denominator appears to be that multiple assemblers need to be compared (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C38">Nakasugi <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>), but the final result can be compared with the transcriptome of other species. In contrast, it is not straightforward (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C58">Vicedomini <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) to assess the quality of a <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of short reads of genomic DNA from a species for which no prior sequence information is available, especially if the genome is large and contains many repeats, and the species is heterozygous or even polyploid. Nevertheless, many studies are based on genomic DNA, as it is easier to extract DNA from dry material of wild species collected in the field (on silica gel) than to try to extract good quality RNA from fresh samples or from samples specifically prepared for RNA extraction. What additional information can be reliably extracted from a single library of short reads of genomic DNA is an open question.<italic>Boswellia papyrifera</italic> is currently the number one frankincense-producing tree species in the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C14">Coppen 2005</xref>). Frankincense is an aromatic resinous gum exudate produced from the bark of trees. Its economic value in the world market stems from its use as an ingredient in pharmaceuticals, cosmetics and as a church incense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C23">Groom 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C55">Tucker 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C30">Lemenih and Teketay 2003</xref>). In Ethiopia, besides its value in the national economy, it has a significant contribution in the local livelihoods, providing up to one-third of annual household income, especially in the northern regions of the country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C31">Lemenih <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C32">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C60">Woldeamanuel 2011</xref>).The population size of <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> is declining in Ethiopia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C1">Abiyu <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C22">Groenendijk <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C54">Tolera <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), Eritrea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C40">Ogbazghi <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>) and Sudan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C2">Abtew <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Little or no tree regeneration occurs in its natural range and mortality of adult trees increases. Despite its endangered status and economic importance, very few conservation efforts exist and none are supported by genetic information. The later situation results because genetic markers for the species have not been developed.In the present study, we applied the Illumina paired-end sequencing technology to sequence genomic DNA of <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> with the goal of identifying microsatellite repeats and developing SSR markers. The reads were also assembled into the first genomic resource for this species, and we present a couple of structural and functional analyses on them.<italic>Boswellia papyrifera</italic> is one of the six <italic>Boswellia</italic> species that grow in various parts of Ethiopia. The <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> genotype used for Illumina paired-end sequencing was collected from a natural population at Kafa Humera Wuhdet (14.05265N latitude; 37.13078E longitude) in north-west Ethiopia. Young leaves were collected from growing shoot tips of the plant and preserved in silica gel while in the field and during transportation to the laboratory for DNA extraction. A genomic DNA library for Illumina paired-end sequencing was prepared from 4 µg of DNA following the PCR-based gel-free illumina TruSeq DNA sample prep protocol and sequenced as 2 × 100 nt paired-end reads on an Illumina HiSeq at Greenomics, Wageningen UR, Wageningen, the Netherlands.For testing of the SSR loci a set of 12 genotypes were used. Ten of the genotypes represented populations of <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> collected from 10 different regions of Ethiopia. Two genotypes of <italic>Boswellia pirrotae</italic> and <italic>B. popovina</italic> were included for testing the cross-transferability of the markers to closely related species. The <italic>B. pirrotae</italic> sample was from the northwestern part of Ethiopia. <italic>Boswellia popoviana</italic> is endemic to Socotra Island, Yemen, and the dried leaf sample was obtained through the Edinburgh Royal Botanical Garden, UK.Total DNA was isolated from silica-dried young leaves following the cetyltrimethylammonium bromide protocol of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C20">Fulton <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref>. As large amounts of phenolic compounds were expected because of the resin content in the leaves, the protocol was modified by the addition of 2 % pvp-40 to the extraction buffer and 1 % mercaptoethanol to the microprep buffer of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C20">Fulton <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref>, added immediately before use. The extraction was followed by purification steps using DNeasy (Qiagen, Venlo, The Netherlands) according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C52">Smulders <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>. DNA yield and quality were visually assessed on a 1 % agarose gel.The raw reads were error-corrected using musket (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C35">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 2012<italic>b</italic></xref>). This error-corrected set was used for the repeat assembly. Prinseq-lite 0.20.04 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C45">Schmieder and Edwards 2011</xref>) was used for quality control and filtering of reads (minimum read length of 50 nt, minimum average base quality of 25, maximum ambiguous nt (N) of 1) after which the data were used for SSR mining. After low complexity trimming (minimum DUST score of 7 for removal of low complexity reads and removal of duplicate reads, also with Prinseq-lite), paired-end reads with overlapping sequences were connected using connecting overlapped pair-end (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C34">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>) in the full mode. Reads were filtered for chloroplast sequences by mapping the reads against the closest chloroplast genome available, which is one of <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic>, using bowtie2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C29">Langmead and Salzberg 2012</xref>, settings -D 20 -R 3 -N 1 -L 20 -i S,1,0.50 -a).Reads from the highly repeated fraction of the genome were extracted and assembled using RepARK (REPetitive motif detection by Assembly of Repetitive k-mers; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C27">Koch <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The motifs present in the repetitive contigs were counted and analysed by blastn (e-value 1e-5) against Repbase v19.08 (database of repetitive DNA elements, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C25">Jurka <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>).A <italic>de novo</italic> draft assembly was created from the filtered reads using SOAPdenovo 2.21 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C33">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>, settings -K 41 -M 3 -d 4). The gaps emerging during the scaffolding process by SOAPdenovo were closed using GapCloser (vs. 1.12). The contigs &gt;1000 bp of the draft assembly were analysed and functionally annotated using Blast2GO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C13">Conesa <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>).Five million of the filtered but not assembled reads were analysed with PAL_FINDER 0.02.03 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C11">Castoe <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) to identify SSRs using slightly adjusted criteria: at least six contiguous repeat units for dinucleotide repeats, four for tri- and tetranucleotide repeats and three for penta- and hexanucleotide repeats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C11">Castoe <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> used six units for trunicleotide repeats). Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C11">Castoe <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> the reads with multiple SSR loci were considered a ‘compound’ repeat if the SSRs had a different repeat motif, but a ‘broken’ repeat if the SSRs had the same motif. Reverse-complement repeat motifs (e.g. TG and CA) and translated or shifted motifs (e.g. TGG, GTG and GGT) were grouped together, so that there were a total of four unique dinucleotide repeats, 10 unique trinucleotide repeats and so on.A subset of over 70 000 trinucleotide to hexanucleotide repeat-containing reads was used to further screen potentially amplifiable SSR loci (PALs): loci for which PCR primers could be designed. Primer designing followed the default parameters specified in Primer3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C44">Rozen and Skaletsky 2000</xref>). The reads were then screened for differences in lengths of those sequences that contained these primers (as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C59">Vukosavljev <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). At these loci the sequenced plant may be heterozygous, thus indicating that the locus is polymorphic. These formed the group of potentially polymorphic loci.Forty-six polymorphic microsatellite markers developed for <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> and their cross-transferability to <italic>B. pirrotae</italic> and <italic>B. popoviana</italic>. <sup>1</sup>A = number of alleles in 10 <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> genotypes. <sup>2</sup>Ho = observed heterozygosity (a tentative figure, as the 10 individuals are from 10 different populations. <sup>3</sup>Amplification was also tested in one individual of <italic>B. pirrotae</italic> (Br) and one of <italic>B. popoviana</italic> (Bv) except where no Bv is indicated. Hom = homozygous and Het = heterozygous, always with products in the same size range as the alleles in <italic>B. papyrifera</italic>, except where noted that they were out of range. No ampl = no amplification.Genomic DNA of one <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> individual was sequenced in order to obtain a library to mine for microsatellite repeats. One lane on an Illumina HiSeq produced 143 458 368 raw reads. Based on k-mer counts, the estimated genome size of <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> was 705 Mb, sequenced at 36× coverage. After error correction and filtering reads for short sequences, sequences with ambiguities (Ns) and low complexity, and excluding redundant sequences, 120 479 203(84 %) paired-end reads and 10 851 777 single-end reads remained.The 20 most frequent SSR motifs obtained, sorted according to frequency.A total of 136 SSR loci (117 randomly picked and 19 loci predicted to be potentially polymorphic as they appeared to have two different alleles in the sequence reads) were tested for amplification and degree of polymorphism in 10 randomly chosen individuals from different populations. Of the 117 randomly picked loci, 82 primer pairs amplified a high-quality PCR product, of which 37 (45 %) were polymorphic with a banding pattern that could be scored clearly (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU086TB1">1</xref>). Of the 19 primer pairs predicted to be polymorphic, 13 amplified bands of which 9 loci (69 %) were polymorphic, indicating a significantly higher rate of polymorphism <italic>(χ</italic><sup>2</sup> <italic>test, P</italic> <italic>&lt;</italic> 0.005) compared with randomly picked loci. The final set of 46 markers included 30 trinucleotide repeat markers, 4 tetranucleotide repeats, 6 pentanucleotides and 6 hexanucleotide repeats. The number of alleles across the polymorphic loci varied between 2 and 12 with an average value of 4.8 alleles in 10 genotypes. Several of the polymorphic markers with 10–12 alleles were TTC repeats. The heterozygosity per locus ranged widely from 0.10 to 0.89 (average 0.43). It is possible that, when used in larger populations, these markers will show higher estimates of Ho, and additional alleles may be found.As shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU086TB1">1</xref>, most of the SSRs successfully amplified in <italic>B. pirrotae</italic> and <italic>B. popoviana</italic> (in the latter species the amount of DNA was insufficient to test all markers). Amplification, even if it is in the same size range as the alleles in <italic>B. papyrifera</italic>, is not proof that the marker is polymorphic, but heterozygosity (two different alleles in the expected range) is. Based on that criterion at least 19 of the 46 markers are polymorphic in <italic>B. pirrotae</italic> and at least 8 of 33 tested are polymorphic in <italic>B. popoviana</italic>.The Illumina reads are the first genomic resource generated in the genus <italic>Boswellia</italic>. The repeat fraction was assembled based on k-mer frequency. This produced 49 576 contigs of repeats that were present at least 50× (median length 139 bp, mean length 224 bp, N50 238 bp, maximum length 21 153 bp, total sum = 574 Mbp). Next, 1533 contigs had blastn hits with RepBase, mostly with Copia (639 hits) and Gypsy (523) retrotransposons, alongside EnSpm (114), hAT (72), Satellite (29), TY (23), Harbinger (16), YPrime (14), Helitron (12) and SCTRANSP (3). Intermixed with these elements were hits to the ribosomal RNAs (LSU 56 hits, SSU 41) and also to Caulimoviridae viruses (11).Representation of ontology assignments of the <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> contigs. (A) The 31 086 GO terms of cellular components, (B) the 42 423 GO terms of molecular function and (C) the 54 256 GO terms of biological processes. Note that these are overlapping classes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C5">Assefa <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> conducted a biophysical and chemical study on resins of <italic>Boswellia</italic> species with special emphasis on <italic>B. papyrifera</italic>. Using the list of identified components, eight contigs of the assembly were found, which represent part of genes of the terpene synthesis pathways, namely pinene synthase, limonene synthase (2×), isoprene synthase (4×) and gamma-terpinene synthase.MEP/DOXP and mevalonate pathway genes found among the contigs of <italic>B. papyrifera</italic>.We have developed the first set of 46 SSR markers for <italic>B. papyrifera.</italic> The markers amplified between 2 and 12 alleles in individuals from 10 different populations across Ethiopia. We based the marker development on DNA sequences from one individual. Most of the markers tested were chosen randomly, but the subset for which we assessed, from the sequence reads, that they probably had two alleles in this individual, gave a significantly higher success rate compared with the randomly chosen ones. This assessment is a technically easy screening step that would improve the efficiency of marker development in an outbreeding species, even if only sequences from one individual have been generated, as is often the case. It is probably not as efficient as a strategy that generates transcriptome sequences from multiple individuals with the specific aim of testing only those loci on gel for which polymorphisms in repeat length exist among the reads obtained from these individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C59">Vukosavljev <italic>et al.</italic> 2015</xref>).The SSR markers were developed based on a set of Illumina paired-end DNA sequence reads from young leaves of a single individual of <italic>B. papyrifera</italic>. The distribution of these reads indicated a genome size of 705 Mb. This is close to the estimate of 682 Mb for <italic>B. serrata</italic>, the only <italic>Boswellia</italic> species listed in the Kew Gardens C-value database.Mobile elements that are present in multiple copies in the genome were analysed based on sequence homology in k-mers that occurred at high frequency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C27">Koch <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). We have identified a series of retrotransposons, the most common being Copia and Gypsy elements. As these elements are present in large numbers, our Illumina reads probably were a sufficiently good source to determine the presence and relative frequency of various elements.We also assembled all reads of our paired-end short-read library and obtained 307 Mb of unique sequences. The quality of this assembly is difficult to assess without other independent sources such as libraries of different insert sizes, and we therefore did not compare the results of various assemblers (as, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C48">Shahin <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref> did) or merged assemblies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C58">Vicedomini <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Our resource was searched for genes that are expected to be involved in production of the major compounds of the resin, which in <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> includes diterpenes, triterpenes and nortriterpenes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C6">Basar 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C5">Assefa <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C7">Bekana <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The contigs of our assembly gave significant hits for most genes of the core terpene and terpenoid pathways. We have not carried out an in-depth analysis of the sequences in these contigs, as extracting the complete <italic>Boswellia</italic> homologues of these genes would need more bioinformatics steps and independent validation, e.g. by PCR and Sanger sequencing. However, the results indicate that for many genes of interest at least partial sequence information is present.Genetic information is one of the several tools that facilitate the management of populations and support efforts to conserve threatened species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C37">Moran 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C15">Edwards <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). The newly developed SSR markers generated here for <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> can be applied for characterizing the genetic diversity, population structure and processes within populations, such as pollen and seed dispersal distances, information which may assist in identifying conservation units for the species. A study of the population differentiation of <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> across Ethiopia using a subset of these SSR markers is ongoing (Addisalem <italic>et al.</italic>, in prep.). The cross-amplification and polymorphism of the SSR markers in the other two <italic>Boswellia</italic> species, <italic>B. pirrotae</italic> and <italic>B. popoviana,</italic> indicate their potential use for genetic studies of these species and possibly also in other <italic>Boswellia</italic> species. <italic>Boswellia popoviana</italic> is declining and vulnerable in Yemen.The sequence data generated form the start of a valuable genomic resource for various applications, including estimating the past and present demographic parameters, phylogenetics and phylogeography. With regard to ‘conservation genomics', <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C36">McMahon <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> suggested that genomic sequences are particularly suited to study local adaptation. For most of these applications, genomic sequences need to be generated from several individuals from different populations. This would complement genetic differentiation studies with neutral molecular markers such as SSRs. An exception is the estimation of the the effective population size from SNP density data based on the differences between the alleles at many loci of the heterozygous tree (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU086C24">Halley <italic>et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).Based on Illumina paired-end sequences, we have developed a set of polymorphic SSR markers for <italic>B. papyrifera</italic> and two sister species, which will be useful for studying genetic diversity within and differentiation between <italic>Boswellia</italic> populations. We also generated the first genomic resource in <italic>Boswellia</italic>.Accession number in ENA/GenBank for the set of DNA sequences on which the SSR markers were developed: ERS403283.This study was funded by the Netherlands' Fellowship programme (NUFFIC).F.B. and M.J.M.S. conceived the study. A.B.A. sampled the plants, carried out the testing and analysed the data. G.D.E. did the bioinformatics analyses. A.B.A., F.B. and M.J.M.S. wrote the paper. All authors have read and approved the submitted manuscript.None declared.The authors thank Alan Forrest, the Edinburgh Botanical Garden, for providing the <italic>B. popoviana</italic> sample. Koen Pelgrom and Doret Wouters are thanked for helping in the laboratory and Robert van Loo for help in analysing the genes involved in secondary component synthesis.