Morphological, photosynthetic and water relations traits underpin the contrasting success of two tropical lichen groups at the interior and edge of forest fragmentsDiversity of lichenized fungi in the tropicsHeterogeneity of chlorophyll fluorescence over thalli of several foliose macrolichens exposed to adverse environmental factors: interspecific differences as related to thallus hydration and high irradianceIs ‘life-form’ a useful concept in bryophyte ecology?Performance of macrolichens and lichen genera as indicators of lichen species richness and compositionPrinciples of forest fragmentation and conservation in the AmazonDetermination of the quantum efficiency of photosystem II and of nonphotochemical quenching of chlorophyll fluorescence in the fieldPhoton yield of O<sub>2</sub> evolution and chlorophyll fluorescence characteristics at 77 K among vascular plants of diverse originsEdge effects on epiphytic lichens in remnant stands of managed landscapes in the eastern boreal forest of CanadaPhorophyte specificity and environmental parameters versus stochasticity as determinants for species composition of corticolous crustose lichen communities in the Atlantic rain forest of northeastern BrazilComplex edge effects on soil moisture and microclimate in central Amazonian forestContrasting microclimates among clearcutDistribution and ecology of epiphytic bryophytes and lichens in dry evergreen forest of GuyanaComparative cryptogam ecology: a review of bryophyte and lichen traits that drive biogeochemistryBiased seed rain in forestDifferences in the utilization of water vapour and free water in two co-occurring foliose lichens from semi-arid southern AustraliaContrasting functional traits maintain lichen epiphyte diversity in response to climate and autogenic successionEdge influence on the old-growth forest indicator lichen <italic>Alectoria sarmentosa</italic> in natural ecotonesEdge effects on an epiphytic lichen in fragmented forestsContinuous response functions for quantifying the strength of edge effectsEffects of different chlorophyll concentrations on photosynthesis in foliage leavesDifferences in the susceptibility to light stress between epiphytic lichens of ancient and young boreal forestThe relationship between the quantum yield of photosynthetic electron transport and quenching of chlorophyll fluorescenceEffects of thallus temperature and hydration on photosynthetic parameters of <italic>Cetraria islandica</italic> from contrasting habitatsδ<sup>18</sup>O characteristics of lichens and their effects on evaporative processes of the subjacent soilEpiphytic lichen response to the edge environment in a boreal <italic>Picea abies</italic> forest in central NorwayAssessment of lichen vitality by the chlorophyll fluorescence parameter Fv/FmThe effect of short-time heating on wet <italic>Lobaria pulmonaria:</italic> a chlorophyll fluorescence studyEffects of isolation on the water status of forest patches in the Brazilian AmazonPhotosynthetic performance of <italic>Vigna radiata</italic> L. leaves developed at different temperature and irradiance levelsEdge effects on the epiphytic lichen flora of <italic>Picea abies</italic> in middle boreal FinlandDiversity and vertical distribution of lichens in a Venezuelan tropical lowland rain forestFunctional characteristics of corticolous lichens in the understory of a tropical lowland rain forestField measurements of water relation and CO<sub>2</sub> exchange of the tropical, cyanobacterial basidiolichen <italic>Dictyonema glabratum</italic> in a Panamanian rainforestLichen carbon gain under tropical conditions: water relations and CO<sub>2</sub> exchange of three <italic>Leptogium</italic> species of a lower montane rainforest in PanamaDifferential wetting in some lichens and mosses: the role of morphologyStudies on lichen-dominated systems. XVIII. Morphological control of evaporation in lichensEcosystem decay of Amazonian forest fragments: a 22-year investigationThe effects of photoinhibition on the photosynthetic light-response curve of green plant cells <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic>An <italic>in situ</italic> study of photosynthetic oxygen exchange and electron transport rate in the marine macroalga <italic>Ulva lactuca</italic> (Chlorophyta)Long-term erosion of tree reproductive trait diversity in edge-dominated Atlantic forest fragmentsMicroenvironment variation within and among forest edge sites in the eastern United StatesEdge effects in fragmented forests: implications for conservationTanzanian forest edge microclimatic gradients: dynamic patternsPhotosynthetic light-response curves: I. The influence of carbon dioxide partial pressure and leaf inversionPartitioning of transfer and carboxylation components of intracellular resistance to photosynthetic carbon dioxide fixation: a critical analysis of the methods usedRapid light curves: a powerful tool to assess photosynthetic activityEvaluation of instant light-response curves of chlorophyll fluorescence parameters obtained with a portable chlorophyll fluorometer on site in the fieldWind and temperature structure in a coniferous forest and a contiguous fieldGrowth and vitality of epiphytic lichens. 1. Responses to microclimate along a forest edge-interior gradientEdge effects on epiphytic lichens in managed black spruce forests of eastern North AmericaWhen family matters: an analysis of Thelotremataceae (Lichenized Ascomycota : Ostropales) as bioindicators of ecological continuity in tropical forestsPhotosynthesis and water relations and the role of anatomy in Umbilicariaceae (lichens) from Central SpainAssessment of photosynthetic performance of <italic>Prochloron</italic> in <italic>Lissoclinum patella</italic> in hospite by chlorophyll fluorescence measurements<italic>In situ</italic> photosynthetic differentiation of the green algal and the cyanobacterial photobiont in the crustose lichen <italic>Placopsis contortuplicata</italic>Growth rates of two epiphytic cyanolichen species at the edge and in the interior of a 700-year-old Douglas fir forest in the western Cascades of OregonTree species impoverishment and the future flora of the Atlantic forest of northeastern BrazilLichen zonation in the Parque los Nevados transectLichensSpecies richness of lichen functional groups in relation to land use intensityGrowth and vitality of epiphytic lichens. II. Modelling of carbon gain using field and laboratory dataEdge effects drive tropical forest fragments towards an early-successional systemCrustose lichens as indicators of forest continuity in boreal coniferous forestsTexture and hygroscopic features of the upper surface of the thallus in the lichen family UmbilicariaceaeThe distribution of epiphyte growth-forms in the canopy of a Columbian cloud-forestRapid light curves: a new fluorescence method to assess the state of the photosynthetic apparatusPlant herbivore interactions at the forest edgeMicroclimate and vegetation edge effects in a fragmented podocarp-broadleaf forest in New ZealandAltitudinal changes in diversity and abundance of non-vascular epiphytes in the tropics: an ecophysiological explanationGrowth and survival of the foliose lichen <italic>Parmotrema endosulphureum</italic> in the lowland tropics of PanamaPhotosynthesis and carbon gain of the lichen <italic>Leptogium azureum</italic> in a lowland tropical forest<italic>In situ</italic> studies of water relations and CO<sub>2</sub> exchange of the tropical macrolichen <italic>Sticta tomentosa</italic>Are tropical lowlands a marginal habitat for macrolichens? Evidence from a field study with <italic>Parmotrema endosulphureum</italic> in PanamaThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Microclimatic edge effects and morpho-physiological characteristics are shaping lichen functional group distribution. Thus, lichen functional groups may be used as indicator for forest disturbanceForest edges created by fragmentation strongly affect the abiotic and biotic environment. A rarely studied consequence is the resulting impact on non-vascular plants such as poikilohydric lichens, known to be highly sensitive to changes in the microenvironment. We evaluated the impact of forest edge and forest interior on the distribution of two groups of crustose lichens characterized by the presence or absence of a cortex and sought explanations of the outcome in terms of photosynthetic response and water relations.Microclimate, distribution patterns and physiology of cortical and non-cortical lichens were compared at the edge and in the interior of an Atlantic rainforest fragment in Alagoas, Brazil. Ecophysiological aspects of photosynthesis and water relations were studied using chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> fluorescence analysis, and hydration and rehydration characteristics.Cortical and non-cortical functional groups showed a clear preference for interior and edge habitats, respectively. The cortical lichens retained liquid water more efficiently and tolerated low light. This explains their predominance in the forest interior, where total area cover on host tree trunks reached ca. 40 % (versus ca. 5 % for non-cortical lichens). Although non-cortical lichens exchanged water vapour efficiently, they required high light intensities. Consequently, they were able to exploit well-lit edge conditions where they achieved an area cover of ca. 19 % (versus ca. 7 % for cortical lichens). We provide some of the first data for lichens giving the relative quantity of incident light absorbed by the photosystem (absorptivity). The cortical group achieved higher absorptivity and quantum efficiencies, but at the expense of physiological plasticity; non-cortical lichens showed much decreased values of <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> and electron transport rates in the forest interior.Morphological and physiological features largely determine the ecophysiological interaction of lichen functional groups with their abiotic environment and, as a consequence, determine their habitat preference across forest habitats. In view of the distinctiveness of their distribution patterns and ecophysiological strategies, the occurrence of cortical versus non-cortical lichens can be a useful indicator of undisturbed forest interiors in tropical forest fragments.In the light of progressive fragmentation of tropical rainforests, the creation of forest margins represents an increasing pressure on the remaining biota of forest remnants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C5">Bierregaard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C38">Laurance <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Forest margins are commonly exposed to various impacts generally referred to as edge effects. These can be abiotic, biotic, direct or indirect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C43">Murcia, 1995</xref>). On the biotic level, edge effects may, among others, directly influence functional diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C14">de Melo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C62">Tabarelli <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C41">Lopes <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) and species composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C57">Silva and Tabarelli, 2000</xref>) or indirectly influence plant–herbivore interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C67">Wirth <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). These biotic effects are always based upon changes in abiotic conditions which are variable over space and time, and therefore difficult to quantify (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C42">Matlack, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C10">Camargo and Kapos, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C44">Newmark, 2001</xref>). It is generally held that edges are characterized by higher temperature, light intensity and wind disturbance, and lower relative humidity (RH) compared with forest interiors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C49">Raynor, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C11">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C42">Matlack, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C68">Young and Mitchell, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C44">Newmark, 2001</xref>). In the tropics, however, very few studies have addressed microclimatic edge effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C28">Kapos, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C10">Camargo and Kapos, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C44">Newmark, 2001</xref>) and even less is understood regarding their impact on non-vascular plants.As poikilohydric non-vascular plants are well known to interact quickly with their abiotic environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C24">Hartard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), it is recognized that growth form and morphology play a major role in their successful establishment under varying environmental conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C37">Larson and Kershaw, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C36">Larson, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C53">Sancho and Kappen, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C3">Bates, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Across several biomes, microclimatic edge effects have been shown to change the biomass and distribution of numerous species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C56">Sillett, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C18">Esseen and Renhorn, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C25">Hilmo and Holien, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C51">Rheault <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C17">Esseen, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C8">Boudreault <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), and diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C30">Kivisto and Kuusinen, 2000</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C61">Sundberg <italic>et al.</italic> (1997)</xref> attributed strongly decreased growth rates of two foliose lichens, <italic>Lobaria pulmonaria</italic> and <italic>Platismatia glauca</italic>, at the forest edge to physiological limitations which prevented the adjustment of photosynthetic acclimation to higher irradiances. As a consequence, lichens are frequently used as sensitive indicators of environmental change. Further, it has been shown that placing poikilohydric organisms into functional groups rather than just considering species composition can help elucidate microclimatic conditions as well as environmental impacts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C16">Ellis and Coppins, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C13">Cornelissen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and land use change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C4">Bergamini <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C60">Stofer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). In the tropical understory, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> identified the following four functional groups of microlichens: (i) squamulous, (ii) filamentous umbrella-like, (iii) crustose with cortex and (iv) crustose without cortex. The latter two constitute the majority of lichens present, whereas macrolichens (e.g. foliose or fruticose forms) are restricted to montane forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C58">Sipman, 1989<italic>a</italic></xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C59"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C65">van Leerdam <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>) or sporadic occurrences in the canopy of lowland forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C19">Cornelissen and Steege, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C31">Komposch and Hafellner, 2000</xref>) due to climatic limitations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C69">Zotz 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).Crustose lichen groups are easily distinguished by the presence or absence of an upper cortex layer. This layer is formed by very dense glutinated fungal hyphae, creating a very firm, smooth and shiny upper surface, as exemplified in <italic>Dimerella, Lecidea, Myriotrema, Thallotrema, Thelotrema</italic> and <italic>Porina</italic>. In contrast, the upper surface of non-cortical lichens is composed of loosely interwoven hyphae, resulting in a byssoid-like structure. The resulting thalli are susceptible to mechanical damage and are of a non-shiny, somewhat whitish colour, as represented in the genera <italic>Chiodecton, Cryptothecia, Dichosporidium</italic> and <italic>Herpothallon</italic> (for more details on group characterization, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Thallus morphology as well as upper surface characteristics have a strong impact on physiological processes such as water uptake and evaporation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C53">Sancho and Kappen, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C64">Valladares, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C15">de Vries and Watling, 2008</xref>), and hence largely determine photosynthetic activity. However, there has been little research into the physiology of tropical lichens. Although there are some studies on the ecophysiology of macrolichens in tropical montane forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C34">Lange <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C35">2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C72">Zotz <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), studies in tropical lowland forests are extremely rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C70">Zotz and Winter, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C71">Zotz and Schleicher, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C73">Zotz <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Only one study has addressed the ecophysiology of crustose microlichens to date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).In the present work, we expected to confirm the presence of microclimatic edge effects, which define two distinct microenvironments (forest edge and interior), on the performance and distribution of lichen. We hypothesized that cortical and non-cortical crustose lichens interact differently with their abiotic environment, and that this affects their different relative distributions across forest edge and interior. To test this hypothesis, we investigated microclimate, functional group composition and physiological mechanisms linked to morphology. We also studied light adaptation, desiccation and reactivation with water vapour, via chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> (Chl <italic>a</italic>) fluorescence, to provide possible explanations for differences in adaptation to edge and interior of the tropical forest understory.The study was conducted in the Atlantic forest north-east of Brazil at Usina Serra Grande (9°S, 35°52′W, 500–600 m above sea level), a private property located in the state of Alagoas. The region has a tropical climate with a 3-month dry season (&lt;60 mm rain month<sup>−1</sup>). The annual rainfall is about 2000 mm with the wettest period occurring between April and August. The vegetation is characterized as a lower montane rainforest. This occurs at 100–600 m above sea level for Brazilian Atlantic rainforests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C14">de Melo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Within this fragmented area, the study was carried out at Coimbra, comprising an area of 3500 ha. The fragment, created ∼60 years ago, is surrounded on all sides by sugarcane plantations, but currently shows no large-scale human disturbances. On a small scale, however, the forest is used by locals for firewood and hunting. Nevertheless, Coimbra is considered to be one of the largest preserved fragments in this region. Within the northern sector of the fragment, four plots (25 m × 25 m) were established at the forest edge and in the interior, respectively. Edge plot sites were 2–3 m from the forest border line. Undisturbed old-growth forest areas more than 150 m from the forest border were defined as interior sites.The microclimate was recorded intermittently during field trips from 14 January 2007 to 19 April 2007. Temperature and RH at the forest edge and interior plots were measured 1 m above ground level at 1-min intervals using two-channel loggers with internal sensors (HOBO pro series; Onset Computer Corporation, NH, USA). One sensor operated as a reference outside the forest, being installed fully exposed over pasture to resemble matrix conditions closely. The period of investigation included a shift from dry (ending in February) to wet season. Hence, days of observation were grouped into three categories (dry, overcast and wet) according to the minimal daily RHref<sub>min</sub> as measured by the reference sensor. Categories reflect sunny dry days (RHref<sub>min</sub> &lt; 50 %), overcast days where a very slight rain event might occur (RHref<sub>min</sub> = 50–60 %) and wet days with at least one heavy rain event (RHref<sub>min</sub> = 60–80 %).Relative light intensity for trunk environments was measured using a 2π-quantum sensor and datalogger (190-A, LI 1400; LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA) at dusk and dawn to avoid direct radiation. Measurements were taken vertically in each direction (north, east, south and west) along the trunk 1.30 m above the ground. Values per direction (<italic>n</italic> = 3) and all directions per tree were averaged to obtain a representative value for the lichen light environment per tree.Parameters of epiphytic lichen vegetation were assessed using a functional group approach according to the theoretical perspective adopted in this study. For this, all lichen thalli were classified into the two functional groups (with and without cortex) without further taxonomic identification. In view of the high species diversity of corticolous crustose lichen communities in the Atlantic forest of north-eastern Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C9">Cáceres <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), the functional group approach is expected to reduce the impact of species-specific characters and to increase the explanatory power of the variables studied. Examples from <italic>post hoc</italic> identifications of sampled thalli included species from the genera <italic>Letrouitia, Myriotrema, Porina</italic> and <italic>Thelotrema</italic> for the lichen functional group with cortex, whereas the group without cortex comprised genera such as <italic>Herpothallon</italic> and <italic>Cryptothecia</italic>. For information on the total species composition of corticolous crustose lichen communities in the region, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C9">Cáceres <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>.For the assessment of functional group abundance, the relative area covered by lichens and the number of thalli were recorded on target trees in edge and interior plots. Only trees with a relatively smooth bark and a diameter at breast height (dbh) of 12–32 cm were sampled. A sample grid of 20 cm × 20 cm was placed on each selected tree using transparent plastic sheets fixed to the tree trunk 1.3 m above the ground. Five trees were sampled per plot on their north- and south-facing sides. In total, 40 records (20 trees) were sampled for each interior and edge habitat. A three-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) tested whether site, type of lichen or exposure (reflecting highest and lowest potential light impact at the microsite) affected lichen cover. Relative lichen cover (%) was square root transformed to meet the assumptions of ANOVA. Bonferroni's least significant difference (LSD) and Tukey's honestly significant difference (HSD) were applied as <italic>post hoc</italic> tests for multiple comparisons to determine significant differences between group means. Counts of thallus numbers were square root transformed and treated as ordinal data (Weißberg–Bingham test, WB = 0.994, <italic>P</italic> = 0.2). All statistical analysis, modelling and graphical diagnostics to check for compliance with the arithmetic assumptions of the tests and transformations were performed using the R Program (R 2.3.1; R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria).All physiological characteristics were determined via Chl <italic>a</italic> fluorescence measurements using pulse amplitude modulated equipment (IMAGING-PAM; H. Walz, Effeltrich, Germany). Parameters of maximum quantum yield of photosystem II (PSII) (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>), quantum yield of PSII (Ф<sub>PSII</sub> = (<italic>F</italic>′<sub>m</sub> − <italic>F</italic><sub>t</sub>)/<italic>F</italic>′<sub>m</sub>), non-photochemical quenching (NPQ = (<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> − <italic>F</italic>′<sub>m</sub>)/<italic>F</italic>′<sub>m</sub>) and electron transport rate (ETR = Ф<sub>PSII</sub> × PFD × <italic>A</italic> × 0.5, where PFD is the photon flux density and <italic>A</italic> the absorptivity) were derived according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C22">Genty <italic>et al.</italic> (1989)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C6">Bilger <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref>. Absorptivity measures the relative quantity of incident light that is actually absorbed by the photosystem. Whereas for higher plants a general value of 0.84 is representatively used for the absorptivity (<italic>A</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C20">Gabrielsen, 1948</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C7">Björkman and Demmig, 1987</xref>), absorptivity values for lichens have not been quantified. The chosen chlorophyll fluorometer provided the opportunity to actually measure the absorptivity, which was recorded for each sample and used to calculate accurate ETRs (see above).The desiccation and reactivation behaviour exposed to water vapour was investigated <italic>ex situ</italic> under controlled conditions in the laboratory of the University of Recife. Three trees with relatively smooth bark were chosen for sample collection, each providing three individuals of cortical and non-cortical lichen thalli of ∼30 mm in diameter (<italic>n</italic> = 9 for both experiments). Bark pieces holding one sample each were carefully removed from the tree and samples were immediately transported to Recife under moist conditions. In the laboratory, samples were kept under humid conditions with low light (∼20 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>). Experiments were conducted within a week of collection. Moist samples were fully hydrated by standardized spraying with liquid water. After 10 min, samples were carefully blotted and the maximum quantum yield was determined to ensure physiological fitness and sufficient hydration. Samples were exposed to desiccating conditions ranging within 30–33 °C and 55–65 % RH at low light conditions of 8 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> (which were well below saturation). A pair of lichens (cortical and non-cortical) was measured consecutively to ensure homogeneous ambient conditions for one set of samples. The quantum yield of PSII was recorded at 1-min intervals until lichens were desiccated. Lichens were regarded as physiologically desiccated when the quantum yield was below 0.1 over the entire thallus. Differences in desiccation time between the groups were tested using paired <italic>t</italic>-tests.Samples were placed in a box over silica and <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> was measured at 1-h intervals until lichens were desiccated (yield &lt;0.1). Dry lichens were exposed to RH of 80–85 % at 27.5 ± 1.5 °C. The entire experiment was conducted in darkness and the maximal quantum yield was taken every minute for half an hour to explore the recovery of PSII by rehydration of the thallus with water vapour. Samples were subsequently fully hydrated as described above and the maximum quantum yield was taken.Differences in microclimate between forest edge and interior could be detected with respect to temperature and incident light. Diurnal ambient temperature ranges were always 1–3 °C higher at the edge: from 27 to 32 °C on sunny days, declining on overcast days to 25–28 °C and dropping to 22.5–25.2 °C on wet days. Average daily maximum temperature was significantly higher at the edge (26.9 ± 0.4 °C) than in the interior (25.9 ± 0.3 °C) on overcast days, but there were no differences regarding daily minimum temperature (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB1">1</xref>). The diurnal temperature amplitude was larger at the forest edge: ∼6 °C compared with 4 °C in the interior on overcast days. At the forest edge, 1.5 % (±0.4 %) of the incident light reached the understory. In the intact forest interior, light intensity was significantly lower with only 0.7 % (±0.3 %) of the incident insolation reaching the understory (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB1">1</xref>).<bold>Table of means (±SD) for daily microclimatic parameters at the forest edge and interior, with</bold> <bold><italic>T</italic><sub>min</sub></bold>, <bold>minimal temperature (°C);</bold> <bold><italic>T</italic><sub>max</sub></bold>, <bold>maximum temperature;</bold> <bold><italic>T</italic><sub>amp</sub></bold>, <bold>temperature amplitude;</bold> <bold>RH<sub>min</sub>, minimal RH (%); and rel. light, relative light intensity (%).</bold> Means were compared via Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. Days of observation were grouped into different weather categories with reference to the minimal daily RH outside the forest, with &lt;50 % for sunny, &lt;60 % for overcast and &gt;60 % for wet days.A, log-transformed for statistical testing, means are back transformed in this table.Data on lichen abundance were pooled (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ004F1">1</xref>) since no effect could be detected between northern and southern exposures on the trunk. However, there was a significant habitat effect on lichen cover interacting with the lichen group (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,152</sub> = 8.24, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), indicating the preferences of non-cortical lichens for the edge and corticals for the interior habitat. Mean lichen cover for lichens with a cortex (7 ± 2.5 %) was lower compared with non-cortical lichens (19.1 ± 8.9 %) at the forest edge. In contrast, this pattern reversed at the forest interior, where lichens with cortex showed an area cover of 39.6 ± 9.9 %, whereas non-cortical lichens only reached 4.6 ± 4.8 % (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,152</sub> = 17.3, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). A similar pattern was observed regarding the number of individual lichen thalli. At the edge, the thallus number of cortical and non-cortical lichens averaged 10.1 ± 3.1 per 400 cm<sup>2</sup> and 13.7 ± 5.6 per 400 cm<sup>2</sup>, respectively. Again, in the forest interior, lichens with cortex were more abundant, reaching 23.3 ± 5.4 thalli compared with 7.4 ± 4.9 per 400 cm<sup>2</sup> for non-cortical lichens (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,152</sub> = 80.2, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).<bold>Lichen cover and number of thalli for cortical (C) and non-cortical (NC) lichens at the forest edge and interior (<italic>n</italic> = 40).</bold> Lower case letters indicate significant differences according to Tukey's HSD. If lower case letters are the same, groups cannot be distinguished at the <italic>P</italic> = 0.05 significance level.The physiological performance of lichens was related to effects of both habitat and functional group. Although the cortical group showed no physiological difference in performance in edge and interior habitats (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB2">2</xref>), the non-cortical group exhibited greater physiological plasticity in photosynthetic performance. Both lichen functional groups show similar photosynthetic performance in general (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ004F2">2</xref>), although two fundamental photophysiological parameters differed significantly between them: absorptivity and quantum efficiency of the ETR (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB2">2</xref>). The cortical group achieved higher values of absorptivity of around 0.83, compared with 0.71 for non-cortical lichens. Moreover, the cortical group reached higher quantum efficiencies of 0.17 and 0.16, compared with 0.12 for the non-cortical group. The physiological plasticity of the non-cortical group is reflected by decreased values of <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> and ETRs in the forest interior, reaching only half the rates of the other functional group (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB2">2</xref>). Moreover, non-corticals showed differences in absorptivities (Fisher's LSD) and light saturation PFD<sub>sat</sub> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB2">2</xref>). There were no differences between groups or habitats for NPQ at a PFD of 70 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> as variation was quite large.<bold>Response of ETR to increasing light intensity (PFD) for cortical (closed circles) and non-cortical (open circles) lichens at the forest edge (A) and interior (B).</bold> Curves were fitted by a non-rectangular hyperbola (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C46">Prioul and Chartier, 1977</xref>). Means of each individual fit are shown with 1 SEM (<italic>n</italic> = 14–20).<bold>Cardinal points of light–response curves for lichens with and without a cortex.</bold> Absorptivity, proportion of photosynthetically active radiation that is absorbed; <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>, maximum quantum yield in the dark-adapted state; NPQ, non-photochemical quenching at a PFD of 70 µmol m<sup>−</sup><sup>2</sup>s<sup>−</sup><sup>1</sup>; Φ, quantum efficiency; ETR<sub>max</sub>, maximum electron transport rate; PFD<sub>sat</sub>, photon flux density at 0.9 ETR<sub>max</sub>; θ, convexity value. The latter four are derived by the fitted model. Means are shown with 1 SD (<italic>n</italic> = 14–20). If superscripts are the same, means cannot be distinguished significantly by Tukey's HSD or Fisher's LSD (in parentheses) at the <italic>P</italic> = 0.05 significance level. Numbers indicate transformation used for statistical testing: 1, log; 2, arcsinus transformation. Means are back transformed in this table.The duration required for desiccation until no photochemical processes could be detected via Chl <italic>a</italic> fluorescence was significantly different for the two lichen functional groups (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB3">3</xref>). While, under controlled conditions, non-cortical lichens desiccated on average after ∼25 min, lichens with cortex retained photosynthetic activity for twice the time until the entire thallus was desiccated (∼50 min).<bold>Results of desiccation and reactivation experiments</bold>. Samples were desiccating at 30–33 °C, 55–65 % RH and 8 µmol m<sup>−</sup><sup>2</sup>s<sup>−1</sup> PFD (<italic>n</italic> = 9). Samples were considered desiccated when the quantum yield of PSII was below 0.1 over the entire thallus. Desiccated samples were exposed to an average 27.5 °C and 80–85 % RH in darkness for 30 min (<italic>n</italic> = 5). <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>mrehy</sub>, <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> (maximum quantum yield) measured upon the experiment when rehydrated with liquid water.A distinct difference in behaviour was also observed during reactivation of photosynthesis by rehydration. Non-cortical lichens exhibited fast reactivation when exposed to high humidity at 80–86 % and 25–31 °C. After 5 min, the mean Φ<sub>PSII</sub> of lichens without a cortex was more than twice the Φ<sub>PSII</sub> for lichens possessing a cortex (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ004F3">3</xref>). In contrast to non-cortical lichens, those with a cortex did not reach steady-state conditions within the 30 min period of the experiment. Values of <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> after rehydration were lower compared with those observed for lichens <italic>in situ</italic> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB3">3</xref>). Both types of lichen reached 58 % (with cortex) and 60 % (without cortex) of their maximum quantum yield prior to the experiment when subsequently allowed to rehydrate with liquid water, indicating some vulnerability to drought in both types.<bold>Quantum yield of PSII (ϕPSII) of (A) cortical and (B) non-cortical lichens during reactivation with water vapour in the dark.</bold> The RH of the air was 80–85% at 27.5 ± 1.5 °C. Bold lines represent mean values, whereas grey lines show individual samples (<italic>n</italic> = 4–5).The response of organisms after environmental change reflects their adaptive capacity in terms of morphological and physiological plasticity. This is particularly relevant for non-mobile and slow-growing organisms such as lichens inhabiting the understory of tropical humid rainforests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C69">Zotz, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). As poikilohydric non-vascular plants, they are sensitive to environmental changes because their photosynthetic activity is largely dictated by the availability of light and water. Several studies have characterized forest edges by increased light levels, temperature and wind penetration, in association with lower relative humidities, compared with forest interiors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C49">Raynor, 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C28">Kapos, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C11">Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C42">Matlack, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C68">Young and Mitchell, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C10">Camargo and Kapos, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C44">Newmark, 2001</xref>). Temperature, light and humidity measurements presented in this study confirm that the edge habitat is warmer, brighter and dryer than the forest interior (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB1">1</xref>), suggesting that edge creation confronts lichens with a greater risk of desiccation. In contrast, the interior is characterized by more stable conditions that provide ready access to moisture at low light levels.According to the microclimatic heterogeneity across forest habitats and based on distinct lichen functional groups, we expected different physiological performance to translate into group-specific habitat preferences. Our findings indeed revealed a pronounced shift in the distribution pattern of two lichen functional groups from the forest edge to its interior. Lichens without a cortex were significantly more abundant at the forest edge compared with the interior, where they were almost entirely non-existent (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ004F1">1</xref>). In the interior, the cortical group was highly dominant, reaching a mean area cover of 40 %, while in certain instances covering up to 90 % of the bark surface. This distinct pattern is surprising since the criterion for classifying functional groups was only based on the simple morphological distinction of the presence versus absence of an upper cortex, while lichen species composition was random. In consideration of both the enormous tree species diversity and the known lack of host specificity of crustose tropical lichens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C12">Cornelissen and ter Steege, 1989</xref>; Montfoort and Ek, 1989; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C59">Sipman, 1989<italic>b</italic></xref>), it seems unlikely that the observed distribution pattern is strongly affected by tree species composition. Moreover, community formation is only weakly correlated with bark characteristics and microclimate in north-eastern Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C59">Sipman, 1989<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C9">Cáceres <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). We only considered trees with a relatively smooth bark in order to avoid biases caused by substrate heterogeneity and to provide comparable conditions. Thus, there are strong indications that the observed lichen functional group distribution is a consequence of microclimatic edge effects.In accordance with our hypothesis, we found that the presence of a cortex strongly correlates with the physiological reactions of lichen functional groups influencing water exchange and light absorption. We found group-specific as well as habitat-specific differences in photosynthetic performance by lichens of the two functional groups. General group-specific differences in photophysiological parameters were uncovered irrespective of habitat for the absorptivity of incident light and the quantum efficiency of the ETR. Thus, while in cortical lichens the relative quantity of incident light that was absorbed by the photosystem (absorptivity) was estimated to be 0.83, a value similar to that of higher plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C20">Gabrielsen, 1948</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C7">Björkman and Demmig, 1987</xref>), lichens with no cortex showed markedly lower values of about 0.7 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB2">2</xref>). These are, to the best of our knowledge, the first published absorptivities for lichens. The values have implications for the calculation of absolute ETRs in lichens, which in the past have wrongly been assumed to be similar to those of higher plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C2">Bartak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C23">Hajek <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). The reason for low light absorptivity in non-cortical lichens might be the byssoid thallus surface which scatters light to a much larger degree compared with a smooth cortex. Its white colour will also reflect more light. Therefore, the lower absorptivities of non-cortical lichens will contribute to their significantly lower quantum efficiency of photosynthesis. Non-cortical lichens require 8 quanta of incident light for the transport of one electron, compared with 6 quanta required by the cortical group (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLQ004TB2">2</xref>). This low light efficiency may well be crucial under the limiting light regimes present in the forest interior. Success in the interior environment requires effective exploitation of the limited amounts of light. This is achieved in cortical lichens by means of high absorptivities, high quantum efficiencies, maximal ETRs and maximum quantum yields (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub>). In these respects, the non-cortical lichens were inferior, indicating an inherent limitation to their photosynthetic performance in interior conditions. Moreover, their low <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> of 0.53 further suggests a decreased photosynthetic capacity of the non-cortical group when in the interior habitat. An overall average <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> of 0.58 was representative for tropical crustose lichens in this study. This value is similar to those for tropical crustose lichens studied previously (0.57–0.61; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), but lower than those of crustose or foliose lichens of temperate and boreal regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C26">Jensen, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C55">Schroeter, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C21">Gauslaa and Solhaug, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C27">Jensen <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C50">Renhorn <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>).At the forest edge, in contrast, photosynthetic performance by the non-cortical group was superior to that observed in the interior, and physiologically competitive with the cortical group in edge conditions where both groups revealed similar photosynthetic capacities (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLQ004F2">2</xref>). Despite these similar photosynthetic capacities, non-cortical lichens exhibited higher abundances at the forest edge. This implies some advantage in this microhabitat. One possibility is that their low absorptivities may be advantageous in the context of photoprotection, particularly with regard to more frequent sunflecks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Another reason for the superior overall success is a basic difference in water retention characteristics. We found two contrasting strategies for regulating water relations in the cortical and non-cortical lichens: (i) rapid exchange of water vapour and (ii) efficient water retention. Because a cortex constitutes a diffusion barrier for water vapour, reactivation of photosynthesis with water vapour is slower than for non-cortical lichens. Exploitation of vapour is photosynthetically important since lichens already gain 60 % of their maximum photosynthetic capacity when in equilibrium with an RH of 80 % if water vapour is the exclusive source of water during rehydration. The same photosynthetic capacities were confirmed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C32">Lakatos (2002)</xref> when rehydrating tropical crustose lichens at 70 % RH. However, the low resistances to water vapour diffusion created by the absence of a cortex will also favour fast desiccation. This, in turn, might serve as protection against the excessive light expected at the edge. In the forest interior, in contrast, greater water retention by cortical lichens enables this group to maintain an extended photophysiological activity, which is pivotal to exploiting the low light and infrequent sunflecks of this habitat (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C33">Lakatos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).In tropical forest fragments, the identification of undisturbed interior conditions is often pivotal for management plans and conservation practices, especially in small fragments. However, assessment of the penetration depth of edge effects is difficult and laborious (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C19">Ewers and Didham, 2006</xref>). Because the distribution pattern of crustose lichens can be understood as a response of lichen functional traits to the microclimate regime, the two lichen functional groups could serve as useful bio-indicators of the presence of undisturbed forest interiors. In European boreal forests, crustose lichen species have been successfully identified as indicators of forest continuity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C63">Tibell, 1992</xref>). However, species identification of tropical crustose lichens is often impossible for non-experts and requires sexually reproductive units, which are rare. Moreover, it is estimated that 50 % of the tropical lichens remain unidentified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C1">Aptroot and Sipman, 1997</xref>). For tropical forests, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C52">Rivas Plata <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> proposed the use of species diversity of understory crustose lichen of the family Thelotremataceae as an index of ecological continuity. They found that Thelotremataceae diversity, all species of which possess a cortex, negatively correlates with the degree of disturbance and light exposure. To introduce this method to a broader spectrum of potential users, they suggested using a classification of 24 morphotypes based on apothecial and thallus morphology. Here, we suggest an even more straightforward classification to assess microclimatic conditions via classification into two easily identified groups. The proposed groups are easily recognized even by non-lichenologists due to the dichotomous distinction of the presence or absence of an upper cortex. This allows for rapid assessment of undisturbed forest interior and abiotic edge conditions. The low growth rates of tropical crustose lichens range from the almost immeasurably slow in the forest interior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C32">Lakatos, 2002</xref>) to 4 ± 2 mm year<sup>−1</sup> in a foliose lichen at the forest edge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLQ004C71">Zotz and Schleicher, 2003</xref>). This should allow the detection of disturbances that persist for several years. Unpublished results (M. Lakatos) suggest that lichen functional group composition follows microclimatic gradients and may even thus be used to assess small-scale environmental heterogeneity.At the well-lit forest edge, where non-cortical lichens dominate over those possessing a cortex, their inherent low light absorptivity and rapid desiccation rates of non-cortical lichens appear as adaptive photoprotective strategies. Furthermore, their capacity for especially rapid PSII reactivation when rehydrated at high relative humidities, and photosynthetic characteristics of high quantum efficiency and physiological plasticity, as indicated by decreased values of <italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>m</sub> and ETRs in the forest interior allow for an efficient response to fluctuating conditions. We therefore suggest that the non-cortical lichens can be characterized ecologically as light-demanding plants with physiological traits that appear unfavourable for the exploitation of low light conditions of the forest interior. On the other hand, lichens that possess a cortex benefit from enhanced interception of light and long water-holding capacities, and can be classified as shade tolerant. The substantial differences in photophysiological characteristics and hydration capacities between the cortical and the non-cortical groups clearly indicate a difference in thallus morphology (i.e. the presence and absence of a cortex in the thallus) as a crucial factor for the interaction with the abiotic environment. This, in turn, determines the distribution pattern of functional groups of crustose lichens across forest edge and interior habitats. Therefore, the relative distribution of lichen functional groups, based on the easily recognized presence or absence of a cortex, can be used as a rapid and dependable bio-indicator of undisturbed interiors and forest continuity in tropical forest fragments.The study was financed by the A.F.W. Schimper-Foundation for ecological research, the German Science Foundation (DFG, LA 1426/3-1) and the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD, D/06/46401).M.L. was the principal investigator and supervisor of B.H. and A.P. The three authors were engaged in fund raising, field work, design of methods and data analyses. The project was a main part of the MSc thesis of A.P.None declared.We are very grateful to Inara Leal, Marcello Tabarelli, Mauro G. Santos and Sebastian Meyer for their hospitality and provision of facilities. Robert Lücking is thanked for species determination, Rainer Wirth and Gerhard Zotz for helpful comments on the manuscript, and Wanessa R. Almeida for committed assistance with field work.