Evaluating physiological stress in Sumatran tigers (<italic>Panthera tigris</italic> ssp. <italic>sumatrae</italic>) managed in Australian zoosModifications of a field method for fecal steroid analysis in baboonsAssessing reproductive status in wild felids by noninvasive fecal steroid monitoringNoninvasive endocrine data for behavioural studies: the importance of validationNoninvasive monitoring of adrenocortical function in captive jaguars (<italic>Panthera onca</italic>)What is conservation physiology? Perspectives on an increasingly integrated and essential scienceSocial dominance and stress hormonesNon–invasive monitoring of hormones: a tool to improve reproduction in captive breeding of the Eurasian lynxEffects of natural weathering conditions on glucocorticoid metabolite measurements in the greater bilby faecesComparative patterns of adrenal activity in captive and wild Canada lynx (<italic>Lynx canadensis</italic>)Noninvasive fecal monitoring of glucocorticoids in spotted hyenas, <italic>Crocuta crocuta</italic>Social, state-dependent and environmental modulation of fecal corticosteroid levels in free-ranging female spotted hyenasMeasuring zoo animal welfare: theory and practiceA review of factors influencing the stress response in Australian marsupialsIn defense of zoos and aquariums: the ethical basis for keeping wild animals in captivityLong-term monitoring of fecal steroid hormones in female snow leopards (<italic>Panthera uncia</italic>) during pregnancy or pseudopregnancyAre cats really solitary?Sex differences in HPA axis responses to stress: a reviewEnvironmental enrichment for felids: an integrated approachUse of fecal glucocorticoid metabolite measures in conservation biology research: considerations for application and interpretationEffect of housing and environmental enrichment on adrenocortical activity, behavior and reproductive cyclicity in the female tigrina (<italic>Leopardus tigrinus</italic>) and margay (<italic>Leopardus wiedii</italic>)Activity of the hypothalamo-pituitary-adrenals axis in the Siberian tiger (<italic>Panthera tigris altaica</italic>) in captivity and in the wild, and its dynamics throughout the yearNon-invasive reproductive and stress endocrinology in amphibian conservation physiologyUrinary corticosterone metabolite responses to capture, and annual patterns of urinary corticosterone in wild and captive endangered Fijian ground frogs (<italic>Platymantis vitiana</italic>)Non-invasive evaluation of physiological stress hormone responses in a captive population of the Greater Bilby (<italic>Macrotis lagotis</italic>)Fecal cortisol metabolite levels in Bengal (<italic>Panthera tigris tigris</italic>) and Sumatran tigers (<italic>Panthera tigris sumatrae</italic>)Non-invasive evaluation of physiological stress in an iconic Australian marsupial: the Koala (<italic>Phascolarctos cinereus</italic>)Monitoring physiological stress in semi-free ranging populations of an endangered Australian marsupial, the Greater Bilby (<italic>Macrotis lagotis</italic>)High fecal glucocorticoid levels predict mortality in ring-tailed lemurs (<italic>Lemur catta</italic>)Physiological stress in ecology: lessons from biomedical researchNoninvasive approach to the assessment of activity of the hypothalamic-pituitary adrenal system of the Amur tigersHow do glucocorticoids influence stress responses? Integrating permissive, suppressive, stimulatory, and preparative actionsThe many uses of non-invasive fecal steroid monitoring in zoo and wildlife speciesScientific approaches to enrichment and stereotypies in zoo animals: what's been done and where should we go next?Enrichment for captive tigers (<italic>Panthera tigris</italic>): current knowledge and future directionsEvidence for chronic stress in captive but not free-ranging cheetahs (<italic>Acinonyx jubatus</italic>) based on adrenal morphology and functionStress and distress: evaluating their impact for the well-being of zoo animalsNoninvasive assessment of adrenal activity associated with husbandry and behavioral factors in the North American clouded leopard populationImpact of social management on reproductive, adrenal and behavioural activity in the cheetah (<italic>Acinonyx jubatus</italic>)Noninvasive monitoring of adrenocortical activity in carnivores by fecal glucocorticoid analyses<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.We have successfully employed non-invasive fecal based glucocorticoid monitoring to evaluate fecal cortisol metabolites in male and females Sumatran tigers from Australian Zoos. Our study provides baseline FCM data which will be crucial for evaluting the health and welfare of big cats in zoos around the world.Glucocorticoid quantification using non-invasive methods provides a powerful tool for assessing the health and welfare of wildlife in zoo-based programmes. In this study, we provide baseline data on faecal-based glucocorticoid (cortisol) monitoring of Sumatran tigers (<italic>Panthera tigris</italic> ssp. <italic>sumatrae</italic>) managed at the Melbourne Zoo in Victoria, Australia. We sampled five tigers daily for 60 days. Faecal cortisol metabolites (FCMs) in tiger faecal extracts were quantified using enzyme immunoassays that were successfully validated using parallelism and accuracy recovery checks. Two female tigers had significantly higher mean FCM levels than the two males and another female, suggesting that females may have higher FCM levels. A significant elevation was noted in the FCM levels for one female 2 days after she was darted and anaesthetized; however, the FCM levels returned to baseline levels within 3 days after the event. Comparative analysis of FCM levels of tigers sampled at Melbourne Zoo with tigers sampled earlier at two other Australian Zoos (Dreamworld Themepark and Australia Zoo) showed that FCM levels varied between zoos. Differences in the enclosure characteristics, timing of sampling, size and composition of groupings and training procedures could all contribute to this variation. Overall, we recommend the use of non-invasive sampling for the assessment of adrenocortical activity of felids managed in zoos in Australia and internationally in order to improve the welfare of these charismatic big cats.<italic>Ex situ</italic> management of wildlife through zoological programmes is of particular importance for endangered species at risk of extinction in their natural environment and whose existence relies on human intervention and support through captive management strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C15">Hutchins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C8">Dehnhard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Understanding the physiology of animals in captivity and how their health can be jeopardized by physiological stress from novel environments and husbandry practices are crucial for maintaining sustainable and healthy captive populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C14">Hing <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Conservation physiology is an emerging discipline of conservation biology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C6">Cooke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), which applies non-invasive technologies to provide quantitative assessment of the various effects of environmental stress in wildlife (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C38">Wielebnowski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C39">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C27">b</xref>). Faecal cortisol metabolite (FCM) enzyme immunoassay (EIA) and radioimmunoassay are widely used to measure baseline levels of FCMs, and the magnitude of change (rise or fall) in FCM is a widely accepted index of physiological stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C40">Young <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Quantitative assessments of physiological stress can also support zoo programmes through improvements to husbandry practices so that the physiological adaptation and wellbeing of animals is enhanced and reproductive success achieved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C40">Young <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>).The wild population of the Sumatran tiger sub-species is exclusively found on the Indonesian island of Sumatra. With fewer than 400 individuals remaining in the wild, this sub-species is of particularly high priority for captive breeding programmes due to their critically endangered status (CR; IUCN Red List; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C4">Chundawat <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Acquiring new knowledge about tiger stress physiology will allow zoos to progress and excel in areas of husbandry practices, veterinary care, nutrition, exhibit designs and population genetics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C37">Wielebnowski, 2003</xref>). Despite its usefulness and practicality, only limited research to date has focused on non-invasive methods for evaluating the stress physiology of tigers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C22">Naidenko <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C36">Terio <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> highlighted the need for more data on baseline FCM concentrations for felids in captivity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C29">Pride (2005)</xref> also suggested that identification of sub-clinical physiological stress using FCM indices can allow managers to focus on high-risk animals that are most vulnerable. We urgently require information on baseline FCM profiles of tigers obtained from as many zoos as possible to develop a comprehensive understanding of how captive tigers respond to different environmental and management interventions. This information will allow us to compare the stress hormone levels of tigers between zoo facilities, which will significantly improve our ability to identify, manage, minimize and mitigate threats to tigers in zoos. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic> (2013a)</xref> published the first detailed study on the stress physiology of tigers in captivity at two Australian zoos (Dreamworld Themepark and Australia Zoo), including laboratory and biological validation of faecal cortisol metabolite analysis for two tiger sub-species, the Bengal (<italic>Parthera tigris tigris</italic>) and Sumatran tigers (<italic>Parthera tigris sumatrae</italic>).In this study, we aimed to quantify baseline FCM levels of Sumatran tigers managed at the Melbourne Zoo (Victoria, Australia). The main objectives were as follows: (i) to quantify and compare the range and magnitude of FCM levels between male and female Sumatran tigers; (ii) to examine the physiological response of individual tigers to specific stressors (darting and anaesthesia); and (iii) to compare the mean FCM levels of male and female Sumatran tigers at three Australian zoos (Melbourne Zoo, Australia Zoo and Dreamworld Themepark).Descriptive statistics for faecal cortisol metabolite values of tigers (<italic>n</italic> = 5) at Melbourne Zoo, Victoria, AustraliaAbbreviations: CV, coefficient of variation; FCMs, faecal cortisol metabolites.Extraction of FCMs followed methods previously described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C38">Wielebnowski <italic>et al.</italic> (2002a)</xref> for the clouded leopard (<italic>Neofelis nebulosa</italic>) and used recently in numerous studies by our research group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C25">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">2013a</xref>, b, 2014; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C9">Evans <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Briefly, all faecal samples were dehydrated in a lyophilizer, then sieved and pulverized. Homogenized faecal powder (0.2 g) was boiled in a 90% ethanol solution for 20 min to achieve maximal binding of the hormone metabolites to the aqueous solution. The samples were centrifuged for a 5 min period at 6050 × <italic>g</italic>, allowing separation of any remaining solids. From this, the supernatant was recovered and taken to dryness in a fume cupboard. Extracted particles adhering to the vessel wall were reconstituted in an assay buffer (39 m<sc>m</sc> NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O, 61 m<sc>m</sc> NaHPO<sub>4</sub>, 15 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl and 0.1% bovine serum albumin, pH 7.0) in preparation for analysis of FCMs by EIA.Laboratory protocols followed those based on established work on the greater bilby (<italic>Macrotis lagotis</italic>) described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C25">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>, the koala (<italic>Phascolactus cinereus</italic>) described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C27">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic> (2013b)</xref> and, most recently, on the tiger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>). This procedure involved the quantification of the FCM concentration of each sample through duplicate assays performed in 96-well Nunc MaxiSorp™ plates. Cortisol antisera and horseradish peroxidase were procured from the University of California, UC Davis. Concentrations were determined using a polyclonal anti-cortisol antiserum (R4866) diluted at 1:15 000, horseradish peroxidase-conjugated cortisol label diluted at 1:80 000 and cortisol standards (1.56–400 pg per well). Specificity of the R4866 anti-cortisol antiserum to the targeted cortisol antigen is reported at 100%, in comparison to 10% with other steroids tested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C24">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).Nunc MaxiSorp™ plates were coated with 50 μl of antibody diluted in a coating buffer (50 mmol<sup>−1</sup> bicarbonate buffer, pH 9.6) to the appropriate concentration. Plates were then incubated for at least 12 h at 4°C before being washed using an automated plate washer supplied with phosphate-buffered saline containing 0.5 ml Tween 20 to rinse off all unbound antibody. Dilutions in assay buffer to the appropriate concentration were prepared for stocks of standards, high- and low-binding internal controls, faecal extracts and horseradish peroxidase labels. For all EIAs, 50 μl of standard, internal control and diluted faecal extract was added to each well. Then, 50 μl of the corresponding horseradish peroxidase label was added to each well. These plates were then incubated at room temperature for 2 h. Plates were washed again after incubation, and 50 μl of a substrate buffer (0.01% tetramethylbenzidine and 0.004% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in 0.1 <sc>m</sc> acetate citrate acid buffer, pH 6.0) was added to each well. Stopping solution (50 μl of 0.5 mol l<sup>−1</sup> H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) was added so that the optical density of the zero wells would read between 0.7 and 1.0, after ∼20 min incubation at room temperature. Plates were then read at 450 nm (reference 630 nm) on a microplate reader to determine the FCM concentration detected for each assay.Methods necessary to validate the EIA methodology for measuring FCMs in the tiger required the following conditions to be met: (i) parallelism, i.e. parallel displacement of serial dilutions of the pooled tiger faecal extracts to the respective cortisol standard curve; and (ii) extraction efficiency, i.e. significant recovery of exogenous steroid standard added to faecal extracts.All hormone data are expressed as the FCM concentration (in nanograms per gram) on a dry faeces weight basis. As individuals were repeatedly sampled over time, time series analysis was employed. This enabled the construction of a unique profile for each individual, providing graphical representation of baseline FCM levels and the coefficient of variation (CV%) in FCM levels to be determined. For all analyses, FCM was the dependant variable. For each individual, the mean FCM concentration (FCM ± SEM), and mean CV% were calculated. Variance in the data was high, and the underlying distribution was not normal, so analysis required all data to be log-transformed. A general linear model (repeated-measures ANOVA; SPSS) tested the difference in mean FCM levels within and between tigers, investigating the effects of time and sex as factors in the model (FCM = tiger × time × sex) and significance was reported at a level of <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05. <italic>Post hoc</italic> multiple comparisons were made using Tukey's tests (Tukey's HSD; SPSS). Husbandry details for each individual studied at Melbourne Zoo are provided in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="COU038TB1">1</xref>.Furthermore, mean FCM values and ranges of FCMs were compared with tigers from Dreamworld Themepark and Australia Zoo (Queensland, Australia: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>). Results from all three facilities were analysed using a general linear model (GLM; SPSS) to test for significance differences in FCM between zoos and sexes. Dreamworld Themepark manages one male and four female individuals of the Sumatran sub-species. Australia Zoo manages three male and three female individuals of the Sumatran sub-species.Binding displacement curves of serially diluted pooled-faecal extracts against the cortisol standard to validate the enzyme immunoassay. The <italic>y</italic>-axis shows the percentage of hormone bound/total binding. The 50% binding point (represented by the dashed line) determined the dilution factor (1:16) for Melbourne Zoo tiger faecal extracts.Regression plot for recovery of cortisol standard in the extract pool to achieve extraction efficiency (extraction efficiency = 99%).Individual faecal cortisol metabolite profiles obtained from enzyme immunoassays on faecal samples collected from tigers (<italic>n</italic> = 5) at Melbourne Zoo (Victoria) over a 2 month period. One data point was excluded from statistical analysis because it was attributed to the unnatural stress event of darting and anaesthesia of Female 1.Husbandry details for tigers (<italic>n</italic> = 5) at Melbourne Zoo, Victoria, AustraliaMean faecal cortisol metabolite concentration (±1 SEM) for Melbourne Zoo's tigers (<italic>n</italic> = 5), clustered by sex.Mean faecal cortisol metabolite values (±1 SEM) for male (blue) and female tigers (green) at Melbourne Zoo (<italic>n</italic> = 2 males and 3 females), Dreamworld (<italic>n</italic> = 8 males and 5 females) and Australia Zoo (<italic>n</italic> = 4 males and 4 females).We successfully quantified FCM levels in the Sumatran tigers at Melbourne Zoo using EIAs. These baseline FCM data provide valuable foundation for long-term monitoring of health and wellbeing of tigers, to allow for improvements in management and husbandry for Sumatran tigers (important members of Australia's on-going tiger captive breeding programme). These data will also be valuable for comparisons with new FCM data in the event of any illnesses, environmental modifications (such as the implementation of new enrichment programmes) or changes in social arrangement. This study, therefore, provides necessary reference FCM data for Sumatran tigers to enable the impacts and effects of potential stressors associated with captivity to be assessed quantitatively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C13">Hill and Broom, 2009</xref>).Comparisons of average FCM concentrations with tigers at two other Australian zoos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>) suggest that the tigers in Australian zoos have a range of FCM levels, and future studies could refer to the reported baseline FCM data when monitoring the welfare of individuals managed in Australian zoos. Throughout the literature, there is a range of FCM values obtained from studies on closely related tiger species; however, inter-species comparisons of FCMs were limited due to the potential difference in assay systems (antibodies) used in these reports. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C22">Naidenko <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> report a range of FCM levels between 363 and 783 ng  g<sup>−1</sup> in Siberian tigers, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C40">Young <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> have reported information on several other carnivore species, returning mean values of 234.1 ng g<sup>−1</sup> for the domestic cat (<italic>Felis catus</italic>), 751.1 ng g<sup>−1</sup> for the cheetah (<italic>Acinonyx jubatus</italic>) and 282.9 ng g<sup>−1</sup> for the clouded leopard (<italic>Neofelis nebulosa</italic>). Physiological stress responses and the activity of the hypothalamic–pituitary–adrenal axis not only vary between closely related species but are specific to individuals of the same species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C30">Romero, 2004</xref>), which will account for much of the variation in FCM levels found among tigers in Australian zoos. The variability in FCMs among individuals in this study most probably reflects unique intra-specific metabolic patterns, as well as each individual's capacity to adapt and cope with their environmental surroundings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C38">Wielebnowski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002a</xref>), providing useful information for keepers about the stress reactivity of tigers at an individual level.Some degree of individual variation in FCM levels might be explained by sex differences. Female Sumatran tigers at Melbourne Zoo had a higher average mean FCM than male tigers, as reported in previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C2">Brown and Wildt, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C10">Fanson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>). Higher variation in FCM levels within and between females has commonly been associated with differences in stages of the reproductive cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C18">Kudielka and Kirschbaum, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C10">Fanson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), including oestrous, gestation and lactation, which may have differing metabolic demands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C36">Terio <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C29">Pride, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C16">Kinoshita <italic>et al</italic>, 2011</xref>). Sex-related differences could also be due to differences in FCM excretion owing to variation in metabolic rates, excretion routes and pituitary responsiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C11">Goymann <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C12">2001</xref>).An acute physiological stress response was detected following the darting and anaesthesia of Female 1, in preparation for transportation to another local facility. This stressful event resulted in a significant elevation in FCM levels above baseline levels in 2 days. This lag time of 2 days for the expression of these elevated FCMs was consistent with the delay time of FCMs in response to acute stressors (such as transportation and blood sampling events) reported in earlier studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C5">Conforti <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>). Such information related to the stress endocrine activity can allow zoo management to understand the effect of human interventions and find alternatives or improvements when they incur a negative impact. Although the darting and anaesthesia resulted in a significant elevation in FCMs, this response can be considered as acute (FCMs returning to baseline 3 days after the event) and should have had no direct long-term consequences for the animal's health and wellbeing.The physiological responses of animals to external stressors can also be influenced greatly by the environment in which they live (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C33">Schwarzenberger, 2007</xref>). Previous studies on a range of other felid species have shown that stress results from novel housing conditions and lack of environmental enrichment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C38">Wielebnowski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C21">Moreira <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C35">Szokalski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). However, the enclosures at Melbourne Zoo are spacious and naturalistic in design, with dense vegetation coverage. Furthermore, the regular addition of enrichment items offered in the enclosures also prevents boredom, stimulates the tigers and encourages active behaviours to reduce stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C35">Szokalski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).Comparison of the present results with our previous study using the same protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C26">Narayan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013a</xref>) showed that Melbourne Zoo's tigers have slightly lower FCM averages than the tigers in two other Australian zoos. This could be related to a range of factors including differences in social group size, composition and relatedness, management approaches, enclosures characteristics, climatic differences or time of the year. For example, the Melbourne Zoo animals are related to each other, while the other two zoos have sourced animals from a variety of other facilities. Therefore, the smaller social groupings of closely related animals at Melbourne Zoo might translate to reduced social dominance or subordination that have previously been reported to result in heightened FCM levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C7">Creel, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C12">Goymann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C39">Wielebnowski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002b</xref>). Alternatively, the differences between zoos may simply represent individual/genetic variation in baseline FCM levels. The degree of keeper interaction and handling of tigers also differs between these zoos but it is not possible to attribute variation in FCM levels to such management differences because of the many other differences. Moreover, while human (i.e. keeper) interaction that includes positive re-enforcement during training can increase arousal, and consequently elevated FCM levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C35">Szokalski <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), it has also been associated with increased reproductive success, reduced pacing and enhanced cognitive abilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C19">Mellen and Shepherdson, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C34">Swaisgood and Shepherdson, 2005</xref>).In conclusion, continued non-invasive assessments of stress endocrinology will enable us to evaluate the effectiveness of enrichment strategies for tigers and improving wellbeing in captivity through such management approaches. The influence of many factors, such as diet, seasonal rhythms, sample storage and preservation techniques, reproductive status, social arrangements and exposure to visitors are widely discussed in published literature but are yet to be explored rigorously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C32">Sapolsky <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C12">Goymann <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COU038C20">Millspaugh and Washburn, 2004</xref>). These effects could all contribute to variation when interpreting results to gain meaningful insight into the tiger's stress endocrine function. With these considerations, the use of FCMs to monitor stress in tigers has the potential to act as a powerful biomarker for the physiological effects of the captive environment on the health and welfare of these charismatic big cats.We gratefully acknowledge the co-operation of staff at the tiger captive breeding facility at Melbourne Zoo for collection of samples and husbandry information. The work represents a component of the Honours research by T.P. that was supervised jointly by J.-M.H. and E.J.N. E.J.N. supervised T.P. for the laboratory enzyme immunoassays.