Brassinosteroids alleviate high-temperature injury in <italic>Ficus concinna</italic> seedlings via maintaining higher antioxidant defence and glyoxalase systems24-Epibrassinolide protects against the stress generated by salinity and nickel in <italic>Brassica juncea</italic>Reactive oxygen species: metabolism, oxidative stress, and signal transductionModulation of cadmium-induced oxidative stress in <italic>Ceratophyllum demersum</italic> by zinc involves ascorbate–glutathione cycle and glutathione metabolismBrassinosteroid enhanced the level of abscisic acid in <italic>Chlorella vulgaris</italic> subjected to short-term heat stressEffects of brassinosteroids on the plant responses to environmental stressesReactive oxygen species and oxidative burst: roles in stress, senescence and signal transduction in plantsAntioxidants, oxidative damage and oxygen deprivation stress: a reviewA rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye bindingEpibrassinolide induces changes in indole-3-acetic acid, abscisic acid and polyamine concentrations and enhances antioxidant potential of radish seedlings under copper stressBrassinosteroids: essential regulators of plant growth and developmentTreatment with 24-epibrassinolide, a brassinosteroid, increases the basic thermotolerance of <italic>Brassica napus</italic> and tomato seedlingsBrassinosteroid functions to protect the translational machinery and heat-shock protein synthesis following thermal stressLeaf senescence: correlation with increased levels of membrane permeability and lipid peroxidation, and decreased levels of superoxide dismutase and catalaseRoles for glutathione transferases in plant secondary metabolismAntioxidant responses and bioaccumulation in <italic>Ictalurus melas</italic> under mercury exposureUnderstanding oxidative stress and antioxidant functions to enhance photosynthesisHeat stress-induced abortion of buds and flowers in pea: is sensitivity linked to organ age or to relations between reproductive organs?Exogenous sodium nitroprusside alleviates arsenic-induced oxidative stress in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) seedlings by enhancing antioxidant defence and glyoxalase systemSelenium-induced up-regulation of the antioxidant defence and methylglyoxal detoxification system reduces salinity-induced damage in rapeseed seedlingsNitric oxide modulates antioxidant defence and the methylglyoxal detoxification system and reduces salinity-induced damage of wheat seedlingsExogenous selenium pretreatment protects rapeseed seedlings from cadmium-induced oxidative stress by upregulating antioxidant defence and methylglyoxal detoxification systemsExogenous nitric oxide alleviates high temperature induced oxidative stress in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) seedlings by modulating the antioxidant defence and glyoxalase systemPhysiological, biochemical, and molecular mechanisms of heat stress tolerance in plantsBrassinosteroid enhanced the level of antioxidants under cadmium stress in <italic>Brassica juncea</italic>Effect of 28-homobrassinolide on photosynthesis, fluorescence and antioxidant system in the presence or absence of salinity and temperature in <italic>Vigna radiata</italic>Responses of the anti-oxidative system in leaves of <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> to elevated ozone concentration in an urban areaMethylglyoxal inhibition of cytosolic ascorbate peroxidase from <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>Purification of glyoxalase I from onion bulbs and molecular cloning of its cDNAEvidence for a role of exogenous glycinebetaine and proline in antioxidant defence and methylglyoxal detoxification systems in mung bean seedlings under salt stressA proteomics study of the mung bean epicotyl regulated by brassinosteroids under conditions of chilling stressSalt- and glyphosate-induced increase in glyoxalase I activity in cell lines of groundnut (<italic>Arachis hypogaea</italic>)Cellular glutathione redox homeostasis plays an important role in the brassinosteroid-induced increase in CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation in <italic>Cucumis sativus</italic>Brassinosteroids accelerate recovery of photosynthetic apparatus from cold stress by balancing the electron partitioning, carboxylation and redox homeostasis in cucumberEffects of high temperature stress on photosynthesis in <italic>Ficus concinna</italic> var. subsessilisResponse of photosynthesis and antioxidant systems to high-temperature stress in <italic>Euonymus japonicus</italic> seedlingsReactive oxygen species in plants: their generation, signal transduction, and scavenging mechanismsEffect of 24-epibrassinolide on drought stress-induced changes in <italic>Chorispora bungeana</italic>Influence of brassinosteroids on antioxidant enzymes activity in tomato under different temperaturesSalicylic acid alleviates copper toxicity in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) seedlings by up-regulating antioxidative and glyoxalase systemsSpermidine pretreatment enhances heat tolerance in rice seedlings through modulating antioxidative and glyoxalase systemsAscorbate and glutathione: keeping active oxygen under controlInteractions between biosynthesis, compartmentation and transport in the control of glutathione homeostasis and signallingGlutathione in plants: an integrated overviewBrassinosteroids alleviate heat-induced inhibition of photosynthesis by increasing carboxylation efficiency and enhancing antioxidant systems in <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>Increase in ascorbate-glutathione metabolism as local and precocious systemic responses induced by cadmium in durum wheat plantsBrassinosteroid-stimulated branch elongation in the Marubakaido apple rootstockShooting control by brassinosteroids: metabolomic analysis and effect of brassinazole on <italic>Malus prunifolia</italic>, the Marubakaido apple rootstockAscorbate and glutathione: guardians of the cell cycle, partners in crime?Brassinosteroids regulate pectin methylesterase activity and AtPME41 expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> under chilling stressPhysiological actions of brassinosteroids: an updateCloning and characterization of a mitochondrial glyoxalase II from <italic>Brassica juncea</italic> that is upregulated by NaCl, Zn, and ABAPrimary antioxidant free radical scavenging and redox signaling pathways in higher plant cellsEffects of moderate heat stress on photosynthesis: importance of thylakoid reactions, rubisco deactivation, reactive oxygen species, and thermotolerance provided by isopreneA role for brassinosteroids in germination in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Temperature-induced changes of malondialdehyde, heat-shock proteins in relation to chlorophyll fluorescence and photosynthesis in <italic>Conocarpus lancifolius</italic>Reactive oxygen species and temperature stresses: a delicate balance between signaling and destructionTransgenic potato overproducing L-ascorbic acid resisted an increase in methylglyoxal under salinity stress via maintaining higher reduced glutathione level and glyoxalase enzyme activityInduction of glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase and glutathione by toxic compounds and elicitors in reed canary grassPutrescine alleviation of growth in salt stressed <italic>Brassica juncea</italic> by inducing antioxidative defence systemHeat tolerance in plants: an overviewBrassinosteroids protect photosynthesis and antioxidant system of eggplant seedlings from high-temperature stressEffects of heat acclimation pretreatment on changes of membrane lipid peroxidation, antioxidant metabolites, and ultrastructure of chloroplasts in two cool-season turfgrass species under heat stressMethylglyoxal levels in plants under salinity stress are dependent on glyoxalase I and glutathioneTransgenic tobacco plants overexpressing glyoxalase enzymes resist an increase in methylglyoxal and maintain higher reduced glutathione levels under salinity stressEffects of short-term heat stress on oxidative damage and responses of antioxidant system in <italic>Lilium longiflorum</italic>A role for brassinosteroids in the regulation of photosynthesis in <italic>Cucumis sativus</italic>Effect of brassinosteroids on drought resistance and abscisic acid concentration in tomato under water stress<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Mikio NakazonoThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Brassinosteroids play a significant role in the amelioration of various biotic and abiotic stresses. To investigate the effects of exogenously applied brassinosteroids on the thermotolerance of plants, reactive oxygen species (ROS), antioxidant defense and methylglyoxal (MG) detoxification systems were examined in <italic>Ficus concinna</italic> seedlings with or without 24-epibrassinolide (EBR) application. Our results showed that EBR treatment reduced high temperature-induced increases in the levels of ROS, MG and lipid peroxidation. We also demonstrate that EBR attenuates high temperature-induced oxidative stress by simultaneously increasing non-enzymatic and enzymatic antioxidant responses, as well as MG detoxification systems.Although brassinosteroids (BRs) play crucial roles in plant development and stress tolerance, the mechanisms by which they have these effects are poorly understood. Here, we investigated the possible mechanism of exogenously applied BRs on reactive oxygen species (ROS), antioxidant defence and methylglyoxal (MG) detoxification systems in <italic>Ficus concinna</italic> seedlings grown under high-temperature (HT) stress for 48 h. Our results showed that the activities of ascorbate peroxidase (APX), superoxide dismutase (SOD), glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase (GST), glutathione peroxidase (GPX) and glyoxalase II (Gly II) were increased under two levels of HT stress. Compared with control the activities of catalase (CAT) and dehydroascorbate reductase (DHAR) were not changed due to HT stress. The activities of glutathione reductase (GR), monodehydroascorbate reductase (MDHAR) and glyoxalase I (Gly I) were increased only at moderate HT stress. Despite these protective mechanisms, HT stress induced oxidative stress in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings, as indicated by the increased levels of ROS, malondialdehyde (MDA) and MG, and the reductions in chlorophyll levels and relative water content. The contents of reduced glutathione (GSH) and ascorbate (AsA) were not changed under moderate HT stress. Spraying with 24-epibrassinolide (EBR) alone had little influence on the non-enzymatic antioxidants and the activities of antioxidant enzymes. However, EBR pretreatment under HT stress resulted in an increase in GSH and AsA content, maintenance of high redox state of GSH and AsA, and enhanced ROS and MG detoxification by further elevating the activities of SOD, GST, GPX, APX, MDHAR, GR, DHAR, Gly I and Gly II, as evident by lower level of ROS, MDA and MG. It may be concluded that EBR could alleviate the HT-induced oxidative stress by increasing the enzymatic and non-enzymatic antioxidant defence, and glyoxalase systems in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings.Climatic models predict that greenhouse gases will gradually increase the world's average ambient temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C53">Sharkey 2005</xref>). Hence, plants growing in temperate climates will more often be exposed to high-temperature (HT) stress conditions, adversely affecting plant growth and survival in a number of ways. High temperature is known to affect membrane-linked processes due to alteration in membrane fluidity and permeability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C60">Wahid <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). High temperature stress may scorch leaves, delay seed germination, disrupt photosynthesis and respiration systems, retard growth, damage plant organs and eventually lead to plant death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C17">Guilioni <italic>et al</italic>. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C60">Wahid <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C23">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). High temperature-induced limitation in photosynthesis causes light energy absorbed by photosystem antennae in excess of what is required to drive photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C35">Jin <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). The excess energy accumulated in plant cells results in producing large amounts of reactive oxygen species (ROS) including superoxide <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), singlet oxygen (<sup>1</sup>O<sub>2</sub>) and hydroxyl radicals (•OH), which all have greater toxicity potentials on biomolecules and biomembranes in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C65">Yin <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C23">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). In addition to the generation of ROS, accumulation of methylglyoxal (MG), a toxic compound, has been reported under various extreme environmental stress condition and its detoxification might be a strategy for tolerance against various abiotic stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C63">Yadav <italic>et al</italic>. 2005<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C64"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C19">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C20"><italic>b</italic></xref>). Disruption of these protective mechanisms can cause oxidative stress, leading to oxidative damage.Previous studies have shown that plants have developed a series of both enzymatic and non-enzymatic detoxification systems to counteract ROS, thereby protecting cells from oxidative damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C2">Apel and Hirt 2004</xref>). These enzymatic antioxidant systems include superoxide dismutase (SOD), peroxidase (POD), catalase (CAT), ascorbate peroxidase (APX) monodehydroascorbate reductase (MDHAR), dehydroascorbate reductase (DHAR), glutathione reductase (GR), glutathione peroxidase (GPX) and glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase (GST) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C2">Apel and Hirt 2004</xref>). Non-enzymatic antioxidants include ascorbate (AsA), reduced glutathione (GSH), tocopherol, flavonoids, alkaloids, carotenoids and anthocyanins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C7">Blokhina <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C2">Apel and Hirt 2004</xref>). Likewise, plant cells also possess an MG detoxifying glyoxalase system comprising two enzymes; glyoxalase I (Gly I) and glyoxalase II (Gly II). Gly I utilizes GSH to convert MG into its thioester, whereas the Gly II hydrolyzes this thioester to regenerate GSH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C63">Yadav <italic>et al</italic>. 2005<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C64"><italic>b</italic></xref>). Therefore, antioxidant resistance mechanisms may provide a strategy to enhance heat tolerance, and processes underlying antioxidant responses to HT stress must be clearly understood.<italic>Ficus concinna</italic> var. <italic>subsessilis</italic> is a very important tree species in the tropical and subtropical area, and it is mainly distributed in Southeast Asia and the south of China. High temperature prevailing at the sowing time often imposes severe limitation on early germination pattern and subsequent seedling establishment of <italic>F. concinna</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C34">Jin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). To better understand plant responses to HT stress, it is necessary to identify the mechanisms involved in protection during HT stress. Brassinosteroids (BRs), a recent class of plant hormone, play a critical role in various physiological and biochemical processes in plants, like stem elongation, pollen tube growth, vascular differentiation, leaf bending and epinasty, root inhibition, induction of ethylene biosynthesis, proton pump activation, regulation of gene expression, nucleic acid and protein synthesis and photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C10">Clouse and Sasse 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C54">Steber and McCourt 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C50">Sasse 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C66">Yu <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C46">Pereira-Netto <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C47">2009</xref>). In addition to their role in plant development, BRs have been reported to provide protection to plant from various environmental stresses, including heat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C11">Dhaubhadel <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C12">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C38">Mazorra <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C4">Bajguz 2009</xref>), salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C1">Ali <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C25">Hayat <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>), drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C67">Yuan <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C37">Li <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>), chilling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C30">Huang <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C49">Qu <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and metal stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C24">Hayat <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C1">Ali <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C9">Choudhary <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). One mechanism that may be involved in resistance to many types of stresses by escalating activity of enzymes involved in antioxidant defence system. For instance, BRs increased the activity of CAT, peroxidase and SOD in responding to HT in tomato leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C38">Mazorra <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). Numerous recent studies have claimed that efficient induction of ascorbate–glutathione and glyoxalase systems using exogenous protectants such as nitric acid, salicylic acid and selenium could improve the resistance to various stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C19">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C20"><italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C21">2012<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C22"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C18">Hasanuzzaman and Fujita 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C39">Mostofa and Fujita 2013</xref>). However, there is little evidence for the involvement of BRs in the regulation of ascorbate–glutathione and glyoxalase systems in higher plants. The mechanism by which HT stress affects ascorbate–glutathione and glyoxalase systems also remains unclear. Thus, the present study aimed to evaluate the effect of exogenous BRs on the activity of the antioxidant and glyoxalase pathway enzymes under HT stress. To our knowledge, currently there is no information available on the possible beneficial effects of exogenous application of BRs on MG detoxification system in plants grown under HT stress.Two-year-old seedlings of <italic>F. concinna</italic> var. <italic>subsessilis</italic> were obtained from Zhejiang Subtropical Crop Institute in Wenzhou, China. The seedlings were transplanted to plastic tubes (20.5 cm tall, 18 cm top diameter) filled with a 1 : 1 (v/v) mixture of coarse sand and soil and grown in a shaded greenhouse with natural sunlight during the day (maximum of 800 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>) and relative humidity of 65 % (±5 %). Mean daytime maximum and the minimum temperature in the greenhouse were 28 and 22 °C, respectively. Plants were fertilized once per week with a half-strength Hoagland solution. About 2 months later, selected uniform-sized seedlings were randomly separated into the several groups of 10 plants each for further experiment. Nine groups were placed into nine identical growth chambers with a 12-h photoperiod, photosynthetic flux density (PPFD) of 500 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> at leaf height and constant relative humidity of ∼65 %. The chambers differed only in temperature. Three chambers were kept at 28 °C throughout the experimental period as non-stressed control, three chambers were kept at 35 °C as moderate HT stresses and the others were kept at 40 °C as severe HT stresses. In the HT growth chambers, water was regularly supplied during the day to prevent drought stress. At the beginning of the experiment (0 h), half of the control or HT-stressed plants in each chamber were treated with 24-epibrassinolide (EBR) at 0.25 μM at the rate of 15 mL per plant and the other half was simultaneously sprayed with distilled water containing same ratio of ethanol. In all cases, EBR were first dissolved in ethanol at concentrations of 0.2 mM, and then diluted to the designated concentrations with distilled water. The EBR concentration was selected on the basis of our preliminary experiments (data not shown). After 48 h of HT stress treatment, the leaves were harvested from the seedlings of each treatment for estimations of various physiological and biochemical parameters. Throughout the experiment, all the measurements were performed on the second fully expanded leaf from the top for each treatment. Each treatment was replicated at least three times under the same conditions.Leaf tissue (0.5 g) was ground in liquid nitrogen and homogenized in 3.5 mL cooled 5 % (w/v) metaphosphoric acid containing 1 mM EDTA at 4 °C using a mortar and pestle. The homogenate was centrifuged at 12 000<italic>g</italic> for 15 min at 4 °C, and the supernatant was collected for analysis of AsA and GSH. Ascorbate and DHA levels in the supernatant were determined according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C33">Jiang <italic>et al</italic>. (2013)</xref>. The glutathione pool was assayed according to previously described methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C19">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>). The content of GSH was calculated by subtracting oxidized glutathione (GSSG) from total GSH.About 0.50 g of frozen leaves were ground to a powder using a chilled mortar and pestle with liquid nitrogen and a small amount of insoluble polyvinylpolypyrrolidone, then homogenized with 3.5 mL cooled extraction buffer containing 50 mM K-phosphate (pH 7.5), 1 mM EDTA, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM ascorbic acid, 12 % (v/v) glycerol and 0.1 % (v/v) β-mercaptoethanol. Samples assayed for SOD and CAT activities were extracted in the same buffer without the ascorbic acid. The homogenates were centrifuged at 12 000<italic>g</italic> for 10 min and the supernatants were used for determination of enzyme activity. All enzyme extractions and centrifugations were carried out at 4 °C. The enzyme activity of each sample was measured four times at 25 °C. The total soluble protein (TSP) content was determined with the dye-binding method introduced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C8">Bradford (1976)</xref> using bovine serum albumin (BSA) as a standard. Activities of SOD (EC 1.15.1.1) and CAT (EC: 1.11.1.6) were assayed with the methods previously described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C59">Verma and Mishra (2005)</xref>. The activity of APX (EC 1.11.1.11), MDHAR (EC 1.6.5.4), DHAR (EC 1.8.5.1) and GR (EC 1.6.4.2) were tested according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C19">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. (2011<italic>a</italic>)</xref>. Glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferase (EC: 2.5.1.18) activity was estimated with 1-chloro-2,4-dinitrobenzene (CDNB) substrate as was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C58">Urbanek <italic>et al</italic>. (2005)</xref> with some modifications. The concentrations of reagents in 3 mL were: 100 mM Tris–HCl buffer (pH 6.5), 2 mM GSH, 1 mM CDNB and 200 μL enzyme extract. The enzyme reaction was initiated by the addition of CDNB and the increase in absorbance was measured at 340 nm for 2 min. Glutathione peroxidase (EC 1.11.1.9) activity was followed by the decrease in A340, resulting from NADPH oxidation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C15">Elia <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>).Gly I (EC: 4.4.1.5) activity was assayed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C57">Upadhyaya <italic>et al</italic>. (2011)</xref> with some modifications. The concentrations of reagents in 3 mL were: 100 mM K-phosphate buffer (pH 7.0), 15 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 1.7 mM GSH and 3.5 mM MG and 200 μL enzyme extract. The reaction was initiated by the addition of MG and the increase in absorbance was recorded at 240 nm. The determination of Gly II (EC: 3.1.2.6) activity was done by monitoring the decrease in the absorbance at 240 nm due to the hydrolysis of the substrate, <italic>S</italic>-<sc>d</sc>-lactoylglutathione (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C51">Saxena <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>). The specific activity for glyoxalases I and II is expressed in units per milligram of protein (U/mg protein).The production rate of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation2" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> was measured by monitoring the nitrite formation from hydroxylamine in the presence of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation3" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> following the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C59">Verma and Mishra (2005)</xref>. The content of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was measured by monitoring the A415 titanium-hydro peroxide complex following the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C26">He <italic>et al</italic>. (2006)</xref>.Lipid peroxidation was determined by estimating the malondialdehyde (MDA) content according to the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C13">Dhindsa <italic>et al</italic>. (1981)</xref>. Methylglyoxal (MG) level was determined according to the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C63">Yadav <italic>et al</italic>. (2005<italic>a</italic>)</xref>. The assay mixture of 1 mL contains 250 μL 7.2 mM 1,2-diaminobenzene, 100 μL 5 M perchloric acid and 650 μL sample extract. The absorbance was read at 336 nm. Final concentration of MG was calculated from standard curve of pure MG.All statistical analyses were conducted using SYSTAT version 13 (SYSTAT Software Inc. 2009). Data were statistically analysed using ANOVA, and tested for significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) treatment differences using Tukey's honestly significant difference (HSD) test.Relative water content (RWC), total chlorophyll (Chl <italic>a</italic> + <italic>b</italic>) and ratio of chlorophyll <italic>a</italic> to <italic>b</italic> (Chl <italic>a</italic>/<italic>b</italic>) in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings subjected to EBR (0.25 μM) and high-temperature treatments. <italic>Ficus concinna</italic> seedlings were grown for 48 h with three different temperatures with or without EBR pretreatment. Data are means and SE of 6–8 replicate plants per treatment. Values indicated with different letters are significantly different (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) content (A), superoxide radical <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> producing rate (B), malondialdehyde (MDA, C) and methylglyoxal (MG, D) content in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings grown under three different temperatures with or without EBR pretreatment. All measurements were made at 48 h after treatment. Each bar represents the mean ± SE calculated from three independent experiments. Bars with different letters are significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Glutathione accumulation in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings grown under three different temperatures with or without EBR pretreatment. (A) Reduced glutathione (GSH), (B) oxidized glutathione (GSSG), and (C) GSH/GSSG ratio. All measurements were made at 48 h after treatment. Each bar represents the mean ± SE calculated from three independent experiments. Bars with different letters are significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Redox states of ascorbate in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings grown under three different temperatures with or without EBR pretreatment. (A) Reduced ascorbate (AsA), (B) oxidized ascorbate (DHA), (C) AsA/DHA ratio. All measurements were made at 48 h after treatment. Each bar represents the mean ± SE calculated from three independent experiments. Bars with different letters are significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Activities of APX (A), MDHAR (B), DHAR (C) and GR (D) in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings grown under three different temperatures with or without EBR pretreatment. All measurements were made at 48 h after treatment. Each bar represents the mean ± SE calculated from three independent experiments. Bars with different letters are significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Activities of SOD (A), CAT (B), GST (C) and GPX (D) in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings grown under three different temperatures with or without EBR pretreatment. All measurements were made at 48 h after treatment. Each bar represents the mean ± SE calculated from three independent experiments. Bars with different letters are significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Activities of GlyI (A) and GlyII (B) in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings grown under three different temperatures with or without EBR pretreatment. All measurements were made at 48 h after treatment. Each bar represents the mean ± SE calculated from three independent experiments. Bars with different letters are significantly different at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Decreases in chlorophyll content and disruptions in plant water-balance are general consequences of HT stress. As expected, we found that HT induced declines in chlorophyll and RWC (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV009TB1">1</xref>), indicating that HT exerted its injury by inhibiting chlorophyll biosynthesis and generating osmotic stress. These effects were reverted by EBR-pretreatment, suggesting the protecting role of EBR against heat injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C61">Wu <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). It has been previously reported that HT may induce oxidative stress and ROS generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C35">Jin <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C55">Suleman <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Lipid peroxidation is an oxidative stress marker used to indicate membrane damage. Reactive oxygen species cause the autocatalytic peroxidation of membrane lipids and pigments thus leading to the loss of membrane semi-permeability and modifying its functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C62">Xu <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). Although ROS initiate several oxidatively destructive processes, they also trigger various signalling pathways, and maintenance of appropriate ROS levels might represent a survival response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C2">Apel and Hirt 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C56">Suzuki and Mittler 2006</xref>). Reactive oxygen species at low concentrations are suggested to be involved in the signalling of many processes; however, excessive accumulation of ROS is one of the indicators of oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C6">Bhattacharjee 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C56">Suzuki and Mittler 2006</xref>). In this study, HT significantly increased the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and content (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV009F1">1</xref>). However, the magnitude of increase in MDA and MG content was much less than that in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in 35 °C-treated plants, which indicated that the increase in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> content in 35 °C-treated plants might play a key role in mediating important signal transduction events, activating stress-response pathways and inducing defence mechanisms. On the other hand, the higher levels of MDA, <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation10" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> observed in 40 °C-treated plants indicated that extreme HT induced severe oxidative <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation11" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> stress and that the defence system by antioxidant enzymes was insufficient to protect the plants. Our results showed that EBR pretreatment followed by HT stresses displayed attenuated thermal injury coupled with lower MG and MDA content and less accumulation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation12" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> at 40 °C, which indicated that exogenous EBR has a key role in ROS scavenging and reduction of oxidative stress in HT-stressed <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings. Similar protective effects of BRs in different herbaceous plants were observed under HT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C38">Mazorra <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C44">Ogweno <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>), cold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C33">Jiang <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) and salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C1">Ali <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C25">Hayat <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) stress conditions.Brassinosteroids can interact with ROS in various ways, inhibiting lipid peroxidation and serving an antioxidant function including enzymatic and non-enzymatic systems during various stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C5">Bajguz and Hayat 2009</xref>). AsA can directly scavenge <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation13" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, <sup>1</sup>O<sub>2</sub> and •OH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C41">Noctor and Foyer 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C36">Karuppanapandian <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Glutathione is also regarded as an integral part of antioxidative system of the plant cell against oxidative stress, and contributed to the cellular defence and protection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C48">Potters <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). AsA and GSH are important antioxidants in plants, and high levels of both AsA and GSH pools are a requisite for AsA–GSH cycle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C16">Foyer and Shigeoka 2011</xref>). AsA–GSH cycle plays an important role in keeping the equilibrium between the ROS production and scavenging. The cycle includes APX, MDHAR, DHAR and GR that are involved in detoxification of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in a series of cyclic reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C41">Noctor and Foyer 1998</xref>). In this study, the activities of APX, MDHAR, DHAR and GR were increased at 35 °C (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV009F4">4</xref>), which suggested that under such condition the activities of AsA–GSH cycle enzymes could efficiently regenerated AsA and GSH. The maintained AsA and GSH may eliminate overproduced ROS as observed by lower levels of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation14" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> thereby resulted in the lower levels of MDA at 35 °C. However, at 40 °C, the activities of DHAR and GR were decreased, suggesting that the AsA–GSH cycle was interrupted under severe HT stress. Our findings support those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C40">Mostofa <italic>et al</italic>. (2014)</xref> who reported that the AsA–GSH cycle was highly sensitive to severe heat stress. Our results also showed that severe HT (40 °C) led to substantial declines in AsA and AsA/DHA ratio (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV009F3">3</xref>), which might be one of the ways inducing HT injury probably due to increased oxidation for scavenging overproduced ROS and inefficient AsA–GSH cycle. Additionally, the increased APX activity also results in decreasing in AsA content (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV009F4">4</xref>). However, amendment of this trend by EBR pretreatment might restrict the membrane damage and prevent oxidative injury, and ultimately shepherd to a better antioxidant capacity against HT. Epibrassinolide might take part in the regeneration of AsA by upregulating the activities of MDHAR and DHAR (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV009F4">4</xref>). The increase in AsA levels can be demanded for the increased APX activity in order to control the increase in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> generated by the HT stress. Epibrassinolide-pretreatment also enhanced activities of AsA–GSH cycle enzymes and AsA content in cucumber under cold stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C33">Jiang <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Additionally GSH/GSSG ratio plays a drastic role in the maintenance of the cellular homeostasis and signalling system in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C32">Jiang <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C33">2013</xref>), and the ratio also may be involved in ROS perception (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C52">Shao <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). Our findings suggested that higher ROS content under 40 °C HT stress might contribute to the oxidation of GSH to GSSG and concomitant decrease of GSH/GSSG ratio (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV009F2">2</xref>). On the other hand, GSH is linked to the detoxification of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> via GR in the AsA–GSH cycle and organic peroxides via GPX (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C45">Paradiso <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C18">Hasanuzzaman and Fujita 2013</xref>). Therefore, the less increase of GSH in 40 °C-treated leaves may be due to decreased activities of GR and/or the reaction of GSH with oxyradicals generated due to oxidative stress. The GSSG content was largely increased while the DHAR activity was slightly decreased or remained unchanged at 40 °C, which indicated that the increased GSSG content in 40 °C-treated plant may be due to the reaction of GSH with oxyradicals generated by oxidative stress or decreased GR activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C3">Aravind and Prasad 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C19">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>). However, corresponding with GR activity, HT-stressed or non-stressed plants which were pretreated with EBR, showed a higher increase in GSH content and GSH/GSSG ratio than did the plants grown without EBR pretreatment. These results provide a clear demonstration of the role of EBR in both regulation redox regulation and GSH biosynthesis or regeneration. Enhanced GSH contents in EBR pretreatment plants may partly account for the higher capacity for oxidative defence during HT stress.The improvement in stress tolerance is also associated with the antioxidant system in plants. Superoxide dismutase, CAT, GPX and GST are the most important antioxidant enzymes in plants. Our results showed that the HT-stressed <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings fought against ROS production by raising the activities of SOD, CAT, GPX and GST (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV009F5">5</xref>), and that the increase in SOD activity correlated with the increase in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> content. However, at 40 °C, the increased SOD, CAT, GPX and GST activities in HT-stressed seedlings might not be sufficient to deal with excess H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation15" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> since the AsA–GSH cycle was depressed under the condition. Our results support the finding of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C22">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. (2012<italic>b</italic>)</xref> who observed significant increase in GPX and GST activities under heat stress. Glutathione peroxidases are a family of isozymes that use GSH to reduce H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and lipid hydroperoxides (LOOHs), and therefore protect plant cells from oxidative stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C42">Noctor <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>). Glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferases are another important antioxidative component often involved in nucleophilic conjugation of GSH to a wide variety of organic molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C14">Dixon <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). Therefore, the enhancement of GPX and GST activities may be two important reasons of the less increase of GSH content under severe HT stress. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C40">Mostofa <italic>et al</italic>. (2014)</xref> reported that the activities of GPX and GST in the rice seedlings during heat stress correlated with the fluctuation in GSH level. Glutathione <italic>S</italic>-transferases can also eliminate H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and electrophilic xenobiotics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C43">Noctor <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Therefore, EBR-pretreated HT-stressed seedlings significantly enhanced the activities of SOD, GPX and GST, and slightly increased the CAT activity and thus contributed to the reduction of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation16" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and MDA levels under HT stress, and subsequently affirmed higher tolerance to HT stress. Glutathione reductase-mediated regeneration of GSH in leaves of EBR-treatment seedlings may contribute to substrates for GPX and GST. This effect may represent the antioxidant property of EBR for suppressing the high levels of HT-triggered ROS.Methylglyoxal is a potent cytotoxic compound produced spontaneously from the glycolysis pathway under abiotic stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C63">Yadav <italic>et al</italic>. 2005<italic>a</italic></xref>). An increase in MG level in plant cells further intensifies the production of ROS by inactivating the antioxidant enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C27">Hoque <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Therefore, detoxification of this compound is also a priority to register higher tolerance to oxidative stress. Higher Gly I and Gly II activities could protect plants against MG accumulation during abiotic stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C31">Jain <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C28">Hossain and Fujita 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C29">2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C20">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). In this study, MG content increased under HT stress conditions despite the increased activities of Gly I and Gly II in HT-treated seedlings compared with the control plants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV009F6">6</xref>), suggesting that the detoxification of MG via the glyoxalase system was not sufficient. Additionally, HT-treated seedlings supplemented with EBR further increased the activities of Gly I and Gly II. This enhanced activities of glyoxalase system decreased the MG content in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings under HT stress condition. Our work is the first study to illustrate the role of EBR in maintaining the higher glyoxalase activity and resulting in decrease in MG content. High Gly I and Gly II activities also create the possibility of upregulating the GSH level and the GSH/GSSG ratio via the glyoxalase system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C20">Hasanuzzaman <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV009C18">Hasanuzzaman and Fujita 2013</xref>).In conclusion, the oxidative damage was occurred in <italic>F. concinna</italic> seedlings under HT stress, as indicated by the higher levels of <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation17" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, MDA and MG, and the lower levels of RWC and chlorophyll content, likely due to inefficient induction of non-enzymatic and enzymatic antioxidants as well as of the glyoxalase systems. On the other hand, our results with <italic>F. concinna</italic> under HT stress clearly showed that EBR treatment reduced HT-induced increases in <inline-formula><mml:math id="ImEquation18" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∙</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and MG levels and this process is likely associated with a decrease in lipid peroxidation. Epibrassinolide attenuated the HT-induced oxidative stress by simultaneously increasing non-enzymatic and enzymatic antioxidant responses, as well as MG detoxification systems. However, a complete elucidation of the regulatory role of endogenous EBR, as well as its detailed signalling mechanism, would be helpful in improving our understanding of EBR-mediated HT stress tolerance.The work was partly supported by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">National Natural Science Foundation of China</grant-sponsor> (nos <grant-num xlink:type="simple">31170584</grant-num>, <grant-num xlink:type="simple">31200525</grant-num> and <grant-num xlink:type="simple">30901144</grant-num>) and the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Zhejiang Provincial Natural Science Foundation of China</grant-sponsor> (nos <grant-num xlink:type="simple">Y3090276</grant-num> and <grant-num xlink:type="simple">Y3110286</grant-num>).S.H.J. planned the work and wrote the paper. S.H.J. and X.Q.L. were responsible for the experimental design and carried out the experiments. G.G.W. analysed the data and edited the manuscript. X.T.Z. assisted in the performance of the experiments.None declared.