  SEPALLATA1/2 -suppressed mature apples have low ethylene, high auxin and reduced transcription of ripening-related genes  Down-regulation of  TM29 , a Tomato  SEPALLATA  homolog, causes parthenocarpic fruit development and floral reversion  Regulation of ethylene biosynthesis  Last exit: senescence, abscission, and meristem arrest in Arabidopsis  Sequestration of auxin by the indole-3-acetic acid-amido synthetase GH3-1 in grape berry ( Vitis vinifera  L.) and the proposed role of auxin conjugation during ripening  Changes in indole-3-acetic acid and abscisic acid levels during tomato ( Lycopersicon esculentum  Mill.) fruit development and ripening  Effect of down-regulation of ethylene biosynthesis on fruit flavor complex in apple fruit  A genomics approach to understanding the role of auxin in apple ( Malus ×  domestica ) fruit size control  Bioconductor: open software development for computational biology and bioinformatics  Hormonal regulation of ripening in the strawberry, a non-climacteric fruit  Mining the apple genome reveals a family of nine ethylene receptor genes  Apple  SEPALLATA1/2  like genes control fruit flesh development and ripening  Co-ordination of early and late ripening events in apples is regulated through differential sensitivities to ethylene  Presence of a pathway for the biosynthesis of auxin via indole-3-acetamide in trifoliata orange  Cross-regulatory mechanisms in hormone signaling  Changes in transcriptional profiles are associated with early fruit tissue specialization in tomato  The  1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase  gene family of  Arabidopsis thaliana   A  GH3 -like gene,  CcGH3 , isolated from  Capsicum chinense  L. fruit is regulated by auxin and ethylene  ShortRead: a bioconductor package for input, quality assessment and exploration of high-throughput sequence data  Cloning of a complementary DNA for auxin-induced 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase and differential expression of the gene by auxin and wounding  The NtAMI1 gene functions in cell division of tobacco BY-2 cells in the presence of indole-3-acetamide   Arabidopsis thaliana  auxotrophs reveal a tryptophan-independent biosynthetic pathway for indole-3-acetic acid  The onset of starch degradation during banana ripening is concomitant to changes in the content of free and conjugated forms of indole-3-acetic acid  Abscission, dehiscence, and other cell separation processes  Plant hormone interactions: how complex are they?  A genomics approach reveals that aroma production in apple is controlled by ethylene predominantly at the final step in each biosynthetic pathway  A  SEPALLATA  gene is involved in the development and ripening of strawberry ( Fragaria  ×  ananassa  Duch.) fruit, a non-climacteric tissue  A regulated auxin minimum is required for seed dispersal in Arabidopsis  The Arabidopsis YUCCA1 flavin monooxygenase functions in the indole-3-pyruvic acid branch of auxin biosynthesis  Biosynthesis of the halogenated auxin, 4-chloroindole-3-acetic acid  The involvement of auxin in the ripening of climacteric fruits comes of age: the hormone plays a role of its own and has an intense interplay with ethylene in ripening peaches  One for all and all for one: cross-talk of multiple signals controlling the plant phenotype  Ethylene in vegetative development: a tale with a riddle  The genome of the domesticated apple ( Malus  ×  domestica  Borkh.)  A MADS-box gene necessary for fruit ripening at the tomato  ripening-inhibitor (rin)  locus  Null mutation of the  MdACS3  gene, coding for a ripening-specific 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate synthase, leads to long shelf life in apple fruit  Role of brassinosteroids, ethylene, abscisic acid, and indole-3-acetic acid in mango fruit ripening  Trp-dependent auxin biosynthesis in Arabidopsis: involvement of cytochrome P450s CYP79B2 and CYP79B3  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Free auxin and expression of auxin-related genes were measured at ripening in  MADS8  suppressed apple fruit. It was found that the delayed ripening in these fruit was associated with high auxin and changes in auxin homeostasis and response genes.  Fruit ripening is an important developmental trait in fleshy fruits, making the fruit palatable for seed dispersers. In some fruit species, there is a strong association between auxin concentrations and fruit ripening. We investigated the relationship between auxin concentrations and the onset of ethylene-related ripening in  Malus  ×  domestica  (apples) at both the hormone and transcriptome levels.  Transgenic apples suppressed for the  SEPALLATA1/2  ( SEP1/2 ) class of gene ( MADS8/9 ) that showed severely reduced ripening were compared with untransformed control apples. In each apple type, free indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) concentrations were measured during early ripening. The changes observed in auxin were assessed in light of global changes in gene expression.  It was found that mature  MADS8/9- suppressed apples had a higher concentration of free IAA. This was associated with increased expression of the auxin biosynthetic genes in the indole-3-acetamide pathway. Additionally, in the  MADS8/9 -suppressed apples, there was less expression of the  GH3  auxin-conjugating enzymes. A number of genes involved in the auxin-regulated transcription ( AUX/IAA  and  ARF  classes of genes) were also observed to change in expression, suggesting a mechanism for signal transduction at the start of ripening.  The delay in ripening observed in  MADS8/9 -suppressed apples may be partly due to high auxin concentrations. We propose that, to achieve low auxin associated with fruit maturation, the auxin homeostasis is controlled in a two-pronged manner: (i) by the reduction in biosynthesis and (ii) by an increase in auxin conjugation. This is associated with the change in expression of auxin-signalling genes and the up-regulation of ripening-related genes.   Apple fruit ripening working model.  Mature apple fruit progress through a series of physiological changes, with differences in their sensitivity to and dependency on ethylene.  While many ripening characters are dependent on ethylene, other developmental factors within the fruit can control early ripening events and it has been shown that  MADS -box transcription factors are playing an important role in this process. The  SEP4 -like  RIPENING INHIBITOR  ( RIN ) gene in tomato ( Vrebalov  et al.  2002 ) and the  SEP1/2 -like gene,  FaMADS9 , in strawberry have been shown to play a key role in the developmental control of fruit ripening ( Seymour  et al.  2011 ) as down-regulation of these genes inhibits all ripening-related traits. In apple, we have recently shown that suppression of the  SEP1/2 -like genes  MADS8/9  can also inhibit all ripening events ( Ireland  et al.  2013 ).  There is now a growing body of literature demonstrating the complex interaction of plant hormones with one another ( Vandenbussche and Van Der Straeten 2007 ;  Kuppusamy  et al.  2009 ;  Ross  et al.  2011 ), which suggests that individual hormones do not act independently. The interactions between ethylene and auxin are complex and depend on both developmental stage and cell/tissue type; for example, they are each able to induce the other's biosynthesis only in certain temporal and spatial contexts ( Trainotti  et al.  2007 ;  Vandenbussche  et al.  2012 ). It has previously been shown that in fruits which have ripening traits that are less dependent on ethylene (often referred to as non-climacteric fruits), auxin plays a role in inhibiting the fruit ripening effect. In strawberries, for example, removal of the seed from developing fruit can cause early ripening, which can be repressed by the addition of exogenous auxins ( Given  et al.  1988 ). The reduction of auxin concentrations before the initiation of ripening has been observed in a number of fruits, and has been suggested to be a prerequisite for ripening to occur ( Given  et al.  1988 ;  Buta and Spaulding 1994 ;  Purgatto  et al.  2002 ;  Zaharah  et al.  2012 ). It has been proposed that this reduction in auxin concentration is controlled by the action of the GH3 class (group II) of auxin conjugation enzymes. Indeed, other non-climacteric fruits such as grapes ( Bottcher  et al.  2010 ) and capsicum ( Liu  et al.  2005 ) have high levels of GH3 expression at fruit maturity. Surprisingly, when capsicum  GH3  is over-expressed in tomato, an ethylene-requiring fruit (climacteric), the fruit are able to ripen more rapidly when exogenous ethylene is applied ( Liu  et al.  2005 ). This demonstrates the complexity of auxin action, where different concentrations can lead to different physiological responses ( Ross  et al.  2011 ). In this case it points to low auxin-facilitating ethylene action. The expression patterns of the  GH3  class of gene in apple are consistent with a low auxin requirement for ripening, where there is an increase in two  GH3 -like genes ( GH3.1  and  GH3.101 ) at fruit maturation ( Devoghalaere  et al.  2012 ).  While fruit ripening in many species has been shown to be controlled through ethylene, auxin and developmental pathways, the links between these pathways have not yet been established. In this study, the role of auxin in  MADS8/9 -suppressed apple fruit ( MADS8/9as ) was assessed by comparing free indole-3-acetic-acid (IAA) concentrations and the associated changes in gene expression at fruit maturity.  All apple plants were grown in contained greenhouse conditions, with  Malus  ×  domestica  ‘Royal Gala’ controls grown next to  M. domestica  ‘Royal Gala’ transformed with an antisense construct for the  MADS8  gene. In one line  MADS8as-9  both  MADS8  and  MADS9  homeologues were suppressed ( Ireland  et al.  2013 ) and it was subsequently named  MADS8/9as . Flowers of both the ‘Royal Gala’ control and  MADS8/9as  were pollinated at ‘full bloom’ with pollen from ‘Granny Smith’. When the ‘Royal Gala’ control fruit began to show a change in background skin colour, and representative fruit had a starch index of 1–2 (0–7 scale), all fruit were harvested for both genotypes.  Tissues from each part of the apple (skin, cortex and core) were collected at fruit maturity and 2 weeks after harvest. All samples were frozen immediately in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80 °C. Free IAA concentration was assessed using methods described in  Devoghalaere  et al . (2012) .  RNA was extracted from mature apples left to ripen for 4 days at 20 °C. Individual tissues from apple fruit (skin, cortex and core) were collected in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80 °C until needed. RNA extraction was conducted using the method described in  Schaffer  et al . (2007) . RNA was cleaned using Qiagen cleanup columns as per the manufacturer's instructions. RNA from each tissue type was combined in equal quantities to produce a pool of ‘Royal Gala’ RNA and  MADS8/9as  RNA. Ten micrograms of the pooled RNA were sequenced at the Australian Genomics Resource Facility (Brisbane, Australia) using Illumina HiSeq 2000. These samples were two of a total of nine barcoded samples used in a single lane. A total of 7.8 and 8.1 M, 100-bp reads were obtained from the ‘Royal Gala’ pooled fruit tissue and the  MADS8as  pooled fruit tissue, respectively.  The frequency of gene expression was assessed using the ShortRead package ( Morgan  et al.  2009 ) in a bioconductor ( Gentleman  et al.  2004 ) using the statistical software package ‘R’. A Pdict library of each of the sequencing reads was created using the 5–40 bp region of each of the 100-bp reads. Any Pdict library containing the ambiguous nucleotide ‘N’ in this region was removed before analysis. A sequence frequency was obtained for each  Malus  ×  domestica  gene model ( Velasco  et al.  2010 ) for each Pdict library. Frequencies were normalized by dividing the number of reads by the total number of reads in each cleaned Pdict library and dividing by the length of the predicted gene, giving a value of RPMK (reads per million per kb). Four of these key genes were confirmed using qPCR [see  Additional Information 1 ].   Free auxin content in mature  MADS8/9as  and ‘Royal Gala’ apples.  Changes in free IAA content (ng g −1  fresh weight; FW) in different tissue zones of the fruit (core, cortex, skin), 2 weeks before full maturity (−2w), at maturation (H: harvest) and at an early stage of ripening (+2w: +2 weeks). Measurements were performed on a pool sample of 10 fruit.   Expression of ethylene-related genes.  Expression of ethylene-related genes in early ripening ‘Royal Gala’ control apples and  MADS8/9as  apples harvested at the same day post pollination and kept for 4 days after harvest. RPMK, reads per million per kb.  It has been postulated that, in plants, production of 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) by ACC SYNTHASE (ACS) is the rate-limiting step in ethylene biosynthesis ( Argueso  et al.  2007 ). In ‘Royal Gala’, fruit ripening is associated with an initial increase in  ACS3 , followed by a sustained increase in  ACS1  ( Wang  et al . 2009 ). In the  MADS8/9as  apples, there was a much lower level of  ACS3  than in ‘Royal Gala’ (Fig.  3 A), and no detectable transcripts of  ACS1  compared with low expression in ‘Royal Gala’. The ethylene receptors  ETHYLENE RESPONSE SENSOR 1 (ERS1)  and  ETHYLENE RESPONSE 2  ( ETR2 ), which have been shown to be induced by ethylene ( Ireland  et al.  2012 ), had low expression in both fruit at this time point (Fig.  3 B).  Auxin synthesis genes.   Expression of genes involved in auxin homeostasis and auxin perception.  Expression of auxin-related genes in early ripening ‘Royal Gala’ control apples and  MADS8/9as  apples harvested at the same day post pollination and kept for 4 days after harvest.  Other auxin homeostasis genes previously mined from the apple genome ( Devoghalaere  et al.  2012 ) were screened for differences in expression (Fig.  4 B). These included the transport genes ( PIN ) and conjugation enzymes ( GH3 ). From these gene families, there was a higher level of  PIN4  and  PIN7  expression in the  MADS8/9as  fruit and higher amounts of  GH3.1  and  GH3.101 -conjugating enzymes in the ‘Royal Gala’ control.   Expression of auxin-signalling genes.  Expression of auxin-signalling genes in early ripening ‘Royal Gala’ control apples and  MADS8/9as  apples harvested at the same day post pollination and kept for 4 days after harvest.  The severe ripening inhibition phenotype in  MADS8/9as  fruit compared with ‘Royal Gala’ was also observed at the transcriptional level, with many ripening-related genes such as the cell wall genes  PG1  and  β-GAL1 , and aroma volatile genes  AFS  strongly up-regulated in the ‘Royal Gala’ controls compared with the  MADS8/9as  fruit (Fig.  3 ). To identify other genes that were potentially involved in ripening, the expression levels of genes from the two lines were compared.  Summary of mRNA-seq gene classes.  In many fruit species, ripening is controlled through ethylene and/or auxin concentrations. Recent studies are beginning to establish a link between these two hormones through the conjugation of free IAA by the GH3 family of enzymes ( Liu  et al.  2005 ). The lack of ripening observed in the  MADS8/9as  apples has previously been linked to a low ethylene production, with concentrations of ethylene barely detectable in the  MADS8/9as  fruit, similar to the  ACO1  knockout apples ( Ireland  et al.  accepted ). Here we present data that may suggest a second way in which ripening is inhibited in these fruit, through the maintenance of high auxin concentrations. The suppression of the  MADS8/9  genes results in high auxin concentration, at amounts similar to those observed in rapidly expanding apple fruit ( Devoghalaere  et al.  2012 ). Molecular analysis presented here suggests that this is achieved by a combination of a high level of expression of auxin synthesis genes and a lack of expression of the auxin-conjugating enzymes  GH3.1  and  GH3.101 .  There is now a growing body of literature showing that hormones do not act independently of one another, with strong interactions between auxin and ethylene, and auxin and gibberellins ( Ross  et al.  2011 ). The auxin relationship with ethylene is complex and, so far, models of interaction have been established during vegetative growth ( Ross  et al.  2011 ;  Vandenbussche  et al.  2012 ). Low auxin concentrations seem to be required at the onset of ripening to promote ethylene action; this might seem counterintuitive, as auxin has also long been known to promote ethylene biosynthesis ( Nakagawa  et al.  1991 ;  Liang  et al.  1992 ). However, an analogy can be made to the leaf abscission process, where auxin and ethylene have opposite effects, i.e. ethylene will promote abscission, while auxin will delay it ( Bleecker and Patterson 1997 ). The generally accepted model is that a basipetal IAA flux through the abscission zone, i.e. maintaining high IAA concentrations, prevents abscission by rendering the abscission zone insensitive to ethylene ( Roberts  et al.  2002 ).  The synthesis of auxin in Arabidopsis has been mapped to three pathways, one that appears to be specific to  Brassica  species. There are few studies in the literature that examine the pathways that regulate auxin concentration in fruits. In this study, based on expression patterns it appears that, in the Trp-dependent pathway, auxin synthesis in apple fruit is through the IAM pathway. This is consistent with a microarray experiment performed on developing tomato fruit that showed that a tomato  AMI -like gene is up-regulated in expanding tomato locular tissue ( Lemaire-Chamley  et al.  2005 ), and this pathway is the dominant pathway in developing pea pods ( Tivendale  et al.  2012 ). An earlier report looking specifically at AMI activity in different tissues of trifoliate orange led to the conclusion that the IAM pathway for auxin biosynthesis was occurring in the very young fruit of  Poncirus trifoliata  but only transiently ( Kawaguchi  et al.  1993 ).  This study suggests that in apple the  MADS  box,  SEP  class of genes can regulate the concentrations of IAA, either directly or indirectly. In untransformed ‘Royal Gala’, the expression pattern of  MADS8/9  shows high expression early in fruit development, which then decreases as the fruit expands. The expression then increases as the fruit matures ( Ireland  et al.  accepted ). Auxin concentrations in ‘Royal Gala’ apples show an inverse correlation to this expression pattern, peaking during the cell expansion phase ( Devoghalaere  et al.  2012 ). Interestingly, down-regulation of the homologue of  MADS8/9  in tomato,  TM29 , led to the production of parthenocarpic fruit ( Ampomah-Dwamena  et al.  2002 ). While IAA content had not been measured in the fruit, one possibility would be that parthenocarpy might result from high auxin concentration. While this is a new observation for  SEP  gene function, other  MADS  box genes have been shown to affect auxin local concentration indirectly by affecting the auxin transporter, PIN1, during silique maturation ( Sorefan  et al.  2009 ). The data showed that a local low auxin concentration is required for dehiscence of the Arabidopsis silique valves at pod maturity ( Sorefan  et al.  2009 ).  This study demonstrates a strong link between the  MADS8/9  gene and a low auxin concentration through transcriptional control of biosynthesis and conjugating enzymes at fruit maturation. This will be an additional ripening inhibition signal and ties in with the lack of ripening phenotype in these apples. Future work is needed in apples to establish how ethylene interacts with auxin during the ripening process.   The following additional information is available in the online version of this article –    File 1.  qPCR confirmation of mRNA-seq results of four key genes mentioned in this study.   File 2.  mRNA-seq-based expression of the different apple gene models in mature ‘Royal Gala’ apples and  MADS8/9as  harvested at the same time post pollination.   File 3.  Table of genes showing a 10-fold change in gene expression between ‘Royal Gala’ control and  MADS8/9as  apples.  This work was funded by the  New Zealand Ministry of Science and Innovation FRST  contract  C06X0705 ; Pipfruit, a juicy future; and by the  Faculty Research Development Fund  of the  University of Auckland .  R.J.S. and K.M.D. mined the genes, analysed the expression patterns, performed extraction for IAA measurements and co-wrote the paper. H.S.I. undertook the molecular experimentation. J.J.R. and T.J.L. measured the auxin concentrations.  None declared.  We thank Monica Dragulescu and G. Wadasinghe for caring for the transgenic apple plants. 