 Molecular basis of floral petaloidy: insights from androecia of  Canna indica   Tracking the development of the petaloid fertile stamen in  Canna indica : insights into the origin of androecial petaloidy in the Zingiberales  Molecular and genetic analyses of the  silky1  gene reveal conservation in floral organ specification between eudicots and monocots  A novel class of MADS box genes is involved in ovule development in petunia  Evidence for the involvement of Globosa-like gene duplications and expression divergence in the evolution of floral morphology in the Zingiberales  Evolutionary conservation of angiosperm flower development at the molecular and genetic levels  Genetic interactions among floral homeotic genes of  Arabidopsis   Complementary floral homeotic phenotypes result from opposite orientations of a transposon at the plena-locus of  Antirrhinum   Floral organ identity: 20 years of ABCs  Genetic footprints of stamen ancestors guide perianth evolution in  Persea  (Lauraceae)  The war of the whorls: genetic interactions controlling flower development  Monocotyledon evolution—characters and phylogenetic estimation  The  SEP4  gene of  Arabidopsis thaliana  functions in floral organ and meristem identity  Isolation of two putative homologues of  PISTILLATA  and  AGAMOUS  from  Alpinia oblongifolia  (Zingiberaceae) and characterization of their expression  Pollination biology of  Canna indica  (Cannaceae) with particular reference to the functional morphology of the style  Function and regulation of the  Arabidopsis  floral homeotic gene  PISTILLATA   Regulation of the  Arabidopsis  floral homeotic gene  Apetala1   Bracteomania, an inflorescence anomaly, is caused by the loss of function of the MADS-box gene  Squamosa  in  Antirrhinum majus   The homeotic gene  Apetala3  of  Arabidopsis thaliana  encodes a MADS box and is expressed in petals and stamens  Control of  Arabidopsis  flower and seed development by the homeotic gene  APETALA2   Identification of class B and class C floral organ identity genes from rice plants  Heterotopic expression of class B floral homeotic genes supports a modified ABC model for tulip ( Tulipa gesneriana )  Floral organ identity genes involved in tepal development in  asparagus   Class B gene expression and the modified ABC model in nongrass monocots  Expression of floral MADS-box genes in basal angiosperms: implications for the evolution of floral regulators  A simple method for estimating evolutionary rate of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences  Floral organogenesis in five genera of the Marantaceae and in  Canna  (Cannaceae)  Complex patterns of gene duplication in the  APETALA3  and  PISTILLATA  lineages of the Ranunculaceae  The Phylogeny and classification of the Zingiberales  Molecular characterization of the  Arabidopsis  floral homeotic gene  APETALA1    WAG , a wheat  AGAMOUS  homolog, is associated with development of pistil-like stamens in alloplasmic wheats  Diversification of C-function activity in maize flower development  Floral vasculature and ontogeny in  Canna indica  L  MADS about the evolution of orchid flowers  Why are orchid flowers so diverse? Reduction of evolutionary constraints by paralogues of class B floral homeotic genes  Characterization of three GLOBOSA-like MADS-box genes from maize: evidence for ancient paralogy in one class of floral homeotic B-function genes of grasses  B and C floral organ identity functions require  SEPALLATA  MADS-box genes  Evolution of zygomorphy in monocot flowers: iterative patterns and developmental constraints   Deficiens , a homeotic gene involved in the control of flower morphogenesis in  Antirrhinum majus —the protein shows homology to transcription factors  Isolation and characterization of three MADS-box genes from  Alpinia hainanensis  (Zingiberaceae)  Estimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions in the control region of mitochondrial DNA in humans and chimpanzees  Development of floral organ identity: stories from the MADS house  Plant biology—floral quartets  The CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools  Phylogeny of the Scitamineae—morphological and anatomical considerations   Globosa —a homeotic gene which interacts with deficiens in the control of  Antirrhinum  floral organogenesis  Floral organogenesis in  Tulipa   The protein encoded by the  Arabidopsis  homeotic gene agamous resembles transcription factors   Associate Editor:  Chelsea D. Specht  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Floral organs usually take on the characteristics of petals in ginger plants. In  Canna indica , the most ornamental parts of the flowers are considered to be staminode, which means rudimentary and sterile stamen. However, the precise nature of these petaloid organs is yet to be determined. Two floral organ identity genes GLOBOSA (GLO) and AGAMOUS (AG) are isolated from  Canna indica . Their expression patterns suggest that petaloid staminodes and labellum are of androecium identity, in agreement with their position within the flower. But the current molecular, morphological and anatomical data, are still not sufficient to explain the distinct morphology observed in staminodes and fertile stamen in  Canna indica .  Floral organs that take on the characteristics of petals can occur in all whorls of the monocot order Zingiberales. In  Canna indica , the most ornamental or ‘petaloid’ parts of the flowers are of androecial origin and are considered staminodes. However, the precise nature of these petaloid organs is yet to be determined. In order to gain a better understanding of the genetic basis of androecial identity, a molecular investigation of B- and C-class genes was carried out. Two MADS-box genes  GLOBOSA  ( GLO ) and  AGAMOUS  ( AG ) were isolated from young inflorescences of  C. indica  by 3′ rapid amplification of cDNA ends polymerase chain reaction (3′-RACE PCR). Sequence characterization and phylogenetic analyses show that  CiGLO  and  CiAG  belong to the B- and C-class MADS-box gene family, respectively.  CiAG  is expressed in petaloid staminodes, the labellum, the fertile stamen and carpels.  CiGLO  is expressed in petals, petaloid staminodes, the labellum, the fertile stamen and carpels. Expression patterns in mature tissues of  CiGLO  and  CiAG  suggest that petaloid staminodes and the labellum are of androecial identity, in agreement with their position within the flower and with described  Arabidopsis thaliana  expression patterns. Although B- and C-class genes are important components of androecial determination, their expression patterns are not sufficient to explain the distinct morphology observed in staminodes and the fertile stamen in  C. indica .  A landmark accomplishment in plant developmental biology was the proposition of the ABC model of flower organ identity. This model provides a framework for describing a conserved pattern of gene expressions associated with the specification of floral organs in model species ( Bowman  et al.  1991 ;  Coen and Meyerowitz 1991 ). Soon after its proposition, other floral identity genes including D- and E-class genes were identified and the ABC model was then extended to an ABCDE model ( Angenent  et al.  1995 ;  Pelaz  et al.  2000 ;  Ditta  et al.  2004 ). ABC model genes, with the exception of  APETALA2  ( AP2 ) ( Jofuku  et al.  1994 ), belong to the MADS-box family of transcription factors. In angiosperms, MADS-box transcription factors are important components of various developmental processes, although the most well-characterized MADS-box genes to date are involved in floral organ identity and initiation ( Theißen and Saedler 2001 ).  The ABC model has been extensively characterized due to molecular studies in two model plants,  Arabidopsis thaliana  ( Yanofsky  et al.  1990 ;  Jack  et al.  1992 ;  Mandel  et al.  1992 ;  Goto and Meyerowitz 1994 ;  Gustafsonbrown  et al.  1994 ) and  Antirrhinum majus  ( Sommer  et al.  1990 ;  Huijser  et al.  1992 ;  Trobner  et al.  1992 ;  Bradley  et al.  1993 ). Studies in other angiosperm lineages generally support the idea that the expression patterns described by the ABC model are widely conserved, at least among eudicots. However, the extent to which the eudicot-based ABC model of flower organ identity describes floral morphologies in monocots is still not well understood ( Ambrose  et al.  2000 ).  The role of A-class genes appears to be conserved only in the lineage containing  Arabidopsis  ( Causier  et al.  2010 ), and to date the A-function of the ABC model has not been shown to play a role in organ identity in monocots. Studies carried out in maize, rice and wheat ( Mena  et al.  1996 ;  Kang  et al.  1998 ;  Ambrose  et al.  2000 ;  Munster  et al.  2001 ;  Meguro  et al.  2003 ), however, do indicate that B- and C-class genes and gene activities are somewhat conserved between grasses and eudicots, despite evidence for gene duplication in various lineages. However, the derived morphology of grass flowers results in inconclusive debates regarding the interpretation of the lemma and palea as equivalent to sepals and petals of eudicots ( Bowman 1997 ;  Ambrose  et al.  2000 ). Also, studies in other monocot lineages such as the Liliaceae show divergent results from those predicted by the canonical BC model. In this family, flowers have two outer whorls of almost identical petaloid organs called tepals. In order to explain such a derived pattern, a modified BC model has been proposed ( Van Tunen  et al.  1993 ) and ascertained ( Kanno  et al.  2003 ). In this modified model, B-class genes are expressed in whorl 1 as well as whorls 2 and 3, resulting in similar expression patterns in whorls 1 and 2 and, therefore, similar petaloid structure ( Kanno  et al.  2007 ). However, the expression patterns of B-class genes in asparagus, for instance, do not fit this model ( Kanno  et al.  2004 ).  Furthermore, the intricate morphology and unprecedented diversity of orchid floral morphology has resulted in a proposed ‘orchid code’ that builds on the BC model. This idea assumes that the identity of the different perianth organs is specified by the combinatorial interaction of four  DEF -like MADS-box genes with other floral homeotic genes ( Mondragón-Palomino and Theißen 2008 ,  2009 ).  Owing to the lack of consistency regarding the conservation of the BC model in monocots, it is likely that further studies on other non-grass, petaloid monocots will provide a novel understanding of the evolution of floral organ identity specification outside the eudicots.  The Zingiberales is an order of tropical monocots and consists of eight families ( Tomlinson 1962 ;  Dahlgren and Rasmussen 1983 ). The families are often divided into two groups: the paraphyletic ‘banana group’ (including Musaceae, Streliziaceae, Heliconiaceae and Lowiaeae) with five (occasionally six) fertile stamens, and the monophyletic ‘ginger group’ (including Zingiberaceae, Costaceae, Cannaceae and Marantaceae) with one or a half fertile stamen ( Kress 1990 ;  Rudall and Bateman 2004 ). Thus, an impressive reduction in the number of fertile stamens occurred in the ancestor of the ginger clade.  The Cannaceae family is derived within the Zingiberales with only a single fertile stamen, further reduced to a single theca (half of a fertile stamen) with a prominent, expanded petaloid appendage ( Kirchoff 1983 ). For many years, the interpretation of the androecium members of the Cannaceae has sparked much debate, especially regarding the developmental origins of the stamen and the labellum in  Canna indica  (see the brief review by  Miao  et al.  2014 ). In recent years, this scientific problem has been the subject of both morphological observations and molecular studies.  Almeida  et al.  (2013)  combined a developmental study of the petaloid fertile stamen with data on the expression of three B-class and two C-class floral organ identity genes to elucidate the organogenesis of the petaloid stamen and staminodes. In that study, the authors ( Almeida  et al.  2013 ) proposed that the canonical BC model is not sufficient to explain petaloidy in the androecial whorl in  Canna  sp. In addition, based on floral vasculature and ontogeny,  Miao  et al.  (2014)  suggested that the labellum incorporates two androecial members from both the outer and inner whorls, one diverging from the carpellary dorsal bundle and the other from the parietal bundle. The functional stamen also incorporates two androecial members from both the outer and inner whorls. In order to obtain a better understanding of the identity of the androecium members, we carried out a molecular investigation of  C. indica  B- and C-class genes. Based on our molecular results, we discuss the identity of the androecium members in  C. indica  in the context of the current molecular, morphological and anatomical data.  Complete (left) and dissected (right) mature flower of  C. indica . S, sepal; P, petal; PS, petaloid staminode; L, labellum; FS, fertile stamen; St, style; C, carpel.  Fresh floral materials were wrapped in aluminium foil, flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and preserved at −80 °C to avoid RNA degradation. To ensure RNase-free materials, the plastic experimental apparatus were dipped in DEPC dH 2 O overnight, whereas all the glass apparatus and mortar are sterilized at 180 °C in the pressure vapour sterilizer overnight before the experiment. Total RNA was extracted from at least 100 mg of floral materials using the Plant RNA Extraction Reagent kit according to the manufacturer's instructions (Bioteke, China). The RNA pellet was re-eluted in 40 μL of RNase-free ddH 2 O and stored at −80 °C. RNA quality was characterized by running 4 μL of extracted RNA through 1.0 % agarose gel electrophoresis. Four microlitres (∼10 μg) of RNA was used in a reverse transcription into cDNA using a poly-T primer designed with software Primer Premier 5 (3′-RACE primer: AAG CAG TGG TAT CAA CGC AGA GTA CTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT TTT T) and M-MLV (Invitrogen SuperScriptIII First-Strand Synthesis System for RT-PCR, USA) following the manufacturer's protocol. The success of the reverse transcription reaction was assessed by amplifying 18sRNA from the cDNA, using the following primer pair: 1265S: GGC TAC CAC ATC CAA GGA AG; 1265AS: CCA TTA AAT AGG TAG GAG C.  cDNA was diluted 10 times in dH 2 O, and 4 μL of the dilution was used in 20 μL polymerase chain reaction (PCR) reactions containing 1 μL of 20 μM of each of the forward and reverse primers, 1 U of Taq DNA polymerase (TaKaRa, Japan), 2 μL of dNTP (2 mM) and 2 μL of 10× PCR buffer. The forward primers were designed according to the MADS domain and a RACE-AP Reverse. Two degenerate primer pair combinations were designed according to the conserved region in some monocot plants and were used for each cDNA sample: RACE-AP(R): AAGCAGTGGTATCAACGCAGAGTACGCGGG; GLO-F: ATGGGGCGMGGRAAGATCGAGATCAAG; AG-F: ATGGGSMGRGGRAAGATCGAGATC.  Cycling conditions were set as follows: initial denaturation at 94 °C for 3 min, touchdown procedure from 62 to 48 °C, 15 amplification cycles (94 °C for 30 s, 62 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 1 min), the cycle of 48 °C followed by another 15 amplification cycles (94 °C for 30 s, 54 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 1 min) and a final extension step carried out at 72 °C for 10 min.  The full volumes of the PCR reactions were run on 1.0 % agarose gels and bands of the appropriate size (800 bp–1 kb) were excised and cloned on PMD18-T vectors (TaKaRa). Positive colonies were identified by bacterial colony PCR. Then, all the positive clones (six to eight) were picked from each cloning reaction and sequenced using T-vector-specific primers M13-47 and M13-48. All colonies were sequenced to verify identity, and two sequences were submitted to GenBank.  Analyses of the obtained sequences as well as their inferred amino acid translations were performed using the NCBI Blast program ( http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov ). Alignments of the deduced amino acid sequences were carried out by ClustalX v2.0 ( Thompson  et al.  1997 ).  Forty MADS-box B-, C- and D-class genes including the two genes of this study were downloaded from NCBI ( http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore ) and a multiple sequence alignment was performed. Gene and species names as well as accession numbers are as follows:  AG  (X53579),  AtSHP1  (M55550),  AtSHP2  (M55553),  AtAGL1  (NM_001084842),  AtAP3  (M86357) and  STK  (U20182) of  A. thaliana ;  AmGLO  (AB516403) and  PLE  (S53900) of  A. majus ;  AhMADS5  (AY621154),  AhMADS6  and  AhMADS8  (AY621156) of  Alpinia hainanensis ;  AoAP3  (EF521817),  AoAG  (DQ286724) and  AoPI  (DQ286723) of  Alpinia oblongifolia ;  FBP11  (X81852),  FBP6  (X68675) and  PMADS2  (X69947) of  Petunia × hybrida ;  TAG1  (XM_004232947),  TAGL1  (NM_001247258) and  TAGL11  (NM_001247265) of  Solanum lycopersicum ;  WAG  (AB084577) and  WAG2  (AB465688) of  Triticum aestivum ;  ZMM2  (NM_001111456),  ZmAG  (NM_001112476),  ZMM19  (NM_001111678),  ZMM29  (AJ292961) and  ZMM25  (AJ430638) of  Zea mays ;  BAG1  (M99415) of  Brassica napus ;  LrGLOA  (AB071379) and  LrGLOB  (AB071380) of  Lilium regale ;  TgGLO  (AB094967) of  Tulipa gesneriana ;  OsMADS2  (L37526),  OsMADS3  (L37528),  OsMADS13  (AF151693) and  OsMADS58  (AB232157) of  Oryza sativa ;  NtGLO  (X67959),  NAG1  (L23925) and  GLO  (X67959) of  Nicotiana tabacum ; and  CiAG  (JQ180191) and  CiGLO  (JQ180192) of  C. indica . The evolutionary history of the genes in the multiple sequence alignment was inferred by using maximum likelihood and the Tamura–Nei model ( Tamura and Nei 1993 ). The Kimura two-parameter model ( Kimura 1980 ) was also tested and resulted in the same tree topology. Initial trees for the heuristic search were obtained automatically by applying neighbour-joining and BioNJ algorithms to a matrix of pairwise distances estimated using the maximum composite likelihood (MCL) approach, and then selecting the topology with superior log likelihood value. Evolutionary analyses were conducted in MEGA6. Bootstrap values on the consensus trees were derived from 1000 bootstrap replicates.  Because the gene sequences (accession numbers GU594899–GU594995) submitted by  Bartlett and Specht (2010)  and  Almeida  et al.  (2013)  are only partial CDS, they were not included in this phylogenetic construction.  Four whorls of floral organs were dissected from  C. indica  flowers just before anthesis. The dissected whorls are as follows: sepals in whorl 1, petals in whorl 2, petaloid staminodes and the labellum in whorl 3o (outer androecial whorl), petaloid staminodes and a single fertile stamen in whorl 3i (inner androecial whorl) and carpels in whorl 4. These materials were then separately put into liquid nitrogen to avoid RNA degradation. Meanwhile, a fresh leaf was also collected, flash frozen and used as a reference material. RNA for real-time reverse transcription (RT)-PCR was extracted separately from the four whorls of the floral organs and leaf. RNA extraction was carried out using the Plant RNA Extraction Reagent Kit according to the manufacturer's instructions as described above (Bioteke). The RNA pellet was re-eluted in 40 μL of RNase-free ddH 2 O and stored at −80 °C. RNA quality was tested by running 2 μL of the extracted RNA through a 1.0 % agarose gel electrophoresis (AGE). RNA was quantified using a NanoDrop 1000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, USA). One microgram of RNA from each sample was reverse transcribed into cDNA for real-time RT-PCR following the manufacturer's protocol (TaKaRa, PrimeScript RT Master Mix Perfect Real Time).  Primer pairs of the reference gene were designed according to the  β-actin  sequence of  Musa acuminata , a member of the banana family. The primer pairs used for real-time RT-PCR are actin-F: TCCTTTCCCTCTATGCTAGTGGC; actin-R: CCTCCAATCCAGACACTGTACTTA; AG-F: TAGAGATTATGGGGCGAGGAA; AG-R: ATCCGAGTTGGAGGGCAGT; GLO-F: GAGGCACTCCAGATTGGGCTTAC; and GLO-R: TGGGAAAAGGATGACGGGAAG. Reagent concentrations were used as follows: 2× SYBR buffer solution (TaKaRa) 10 μL, RoxII 0.4 μL, dH 2 O 2 μL, reverse primer 0.8 μL (10 μM, 0.052 μg) and forward primer 0.8 μL (10 μM, 0.065 μg) and diluted cDNA 3 μL for the  GLO  reaction system and 6 μL for the  AG  reaction system. Owing to the already described low expression of  AG , the volume of diluted cDNA was doubled for the  AG  reaction. Each reaction was amplified by two pairs of primers and processed with three biological replicates of the six floral organs extracted from multiple flowers: sepals, petals, petaloid staminodes, labellum, fertile stamens and carpels.  β-Actin  was amplified from the six floral organs as a reference. The real-time RT-PCR was run on an ABI7500 (USA) for 45 cycles, and cycling conditions were set as follows: pre-heating at 95 °C for 30 s, PCR reaction at 95 °C for 3 s followed by 60 °C for 30 s, and melt curve stage at 95 °C for 15 s, 60 °C for 60 s and 95 °C for 15 s. The relative quantization approach through a DeltaDelta CT method was used to analyse the results of real-time PCR experiments. ABI 7500 software v2.0.1 was used to collect data and carry out the statistical analysis.  Two positive sequences of MADS-box genes were obtained and identified as B- and C-class MADS-box homologue genes. The cDNA clones were named  CiGLO  and  CiAG , respectively. Both cDNA clones encode MIKC-type proteins.  Alignments of deduced amino acid sequences. Identical amino acids with a consensus sequence are shaded, and a hyphen represents a gap inserted to optimize alignment. (A)  CiAG  and other proteins of the AG-like subfamily. (B)  CiGLO  and other proteins of the GLOBOSA subfamily.   CiGLO  cDNA is 870 bp long containing a poly-A signal encoding a protein of 210 amino acids, and the coding region is 633 bp long.  CiGLO  is similar in sequence to the GLOBOSA subfamily in comparison to other MADS-box genes from GenBank including  Canna  sp .  (GU594945),  A. oblongifolia  (ABB92623),  A. hainanensis  (AAT99429),  A. thaliana  (NP_197524),  O. sativa ( NP_001045012) and  N. tabacum ( Q03416). The  CiGLO  gene shows strong homology with members in the GLO-like subfamily, and with 99 % similarity to  CsGLO2  (GU594945) of  Canna  sp. (a species located in America) ( Bartlett and Specht 2010 ) as illustrated in Fig.  2 B.  CiGLO  also has no less than 90 % similarity to  PoGLO2  (GU594953) of  Phrynium oliganthum ,  HwGLO2  (GU594953) of  Heliconia wagneriana ,  SjGLO2  (GU594935) of  Stromanthe jacquinii ,  OmGLO2  (GU594936) of  Orchidantha maxillarioides  as well as  MlGLO2  (GU594949.1) of  Marantochloa leucantha  as reported by  Bartlett and Specht (2010) .  Phylogenetic tree constructed using maximum likelihood methods in MEGA. Numbers above the internal branches give bootstrap probabilities of &gt;50. Genes of  C. indica  isolated in this study are underlined. Groups are indicated by the vertical bars at the right margin.  Expression patterns of  CiAG  and  CiGLO  in different floral organs and leaves of  C. indica . The bars on top of each lane in the histogram mean standard error (SE).   CiAG  expression signals were observed in both the outer and inner whorls of staminodes (including petaloid staminodes and the labellum), the fertile stamen and carpels. However,  CiAG  expression was not observed in sepals and petals as previously reported ( Almeida  et al.  2013 ). In other words,  CiAG  was expressed in floral organs of whorls 3 and 4, and not expressed in whorls 1 and 2, similar to the expression pattern of other AG-like homologues' based on the BC model. The strongest expression signal of  CiAG  was detected in the labellum of whorl 3o.   CiGLO  expression was observed in petals, the outer whorl of petaloid staminodes, the labellum and the fertile stamen as well as carpels, while it was not observed in sepals. In other words,  CiGLO  was expressed in the floral organs of whorls 2, 3 and 4, but was not expressed in whorl 1. The strongest expression signal of  CiGLO  was detected in the inner whorl where the single fertile stamen is initiated.  In addition, the  CiAG  expression signal was also detected in the leaf, whereas no  CiGLO  expression signal was detected in the leaf.  Morphological and anatomical studies of  C. indica  ( Kirchoff 1983 ) have shown that the sequence of floral organ initiation is as follows: calyx (sepals), corolla (petals), inner androecial whorl, outer androecial whorl and gynoecium. The developmental work of  Kirchoff (1983)  supports the hypothesis proposed by  Eichler (1875) , that the stamen, the labellum and one of the staminodes (the inner staminode) represent the inner androecial whorl while the remaining one or two petaloid staminodes represent the outer androecial whorl. The nature of the labellum was not formulated by  Kirchoff (1983 ).  The most extraordinary and ornamental parts in the flower of  Canna  L. are staminodes, which are usually taxonomically interpreted as petals by people ( Wu and Chen 1981 ,  2000 ). In the flora of China,  Canna  flowers are interpreted as having two whorls of petaloid staminodes, with the reflexed staminode in the inner whorl referred to as the ‘labellum’. The labellum is narrower than the outer whorl of staminodes and is useful in distinguishing among species of  Canna . In the light of their statements ( Wu and Chen 1981 ,  2000 ), the androecium members, except for the fertile stamen, were replaced by petaloid staminodes and the labellum. However, no detailed evidence has been put forward.  In the present study, two genes,  CiGLO  and  CiAG , have been isolated from  C. indica . Sequence characterization and phylogenetic relationships indicate that they belong to B- and C-class gene families, respectively. The described expression patterns in eudicot model species indicate that stamens are determined by B- and C-class genes in whorl 3, whereas C-class genes are essential for carpels in whorl 4 ( Theißen 2001 ). The expression pattern in different floral organs analysed by qPCR shows that  CiAG  was expressed in whorl 3o of petaloid staminodes and the labellum, whorl 3i of petaloid staminodes plus the fertile stamen, and whorl 4 of carpels, while it was not expressed in whorl 1 of sepals and whorl 2 of petals. The qPCR results of  CiAG  are largely consistent with the expression patterns of C-class genes, as described in eudicot model species. In the study of  Almeida  et al.  (2013) , two copies of  AGAMOUS  genes were isolated from  C. indica , and RT-PCR was used to assess the expression pattern. The genes  AG-1  and  AG-2  show an expanded pattern of expression when compared with the canonical BC model.  AG-1  is expressed in a gradient increasing from sepals to gynoecium while  AG-2  is evenly expressed in all floral parts studied except in petals. At that time,  Almeida  et al.  (2013)  did not amplify the full-length sequences for the two genes. According to the accession number,  AG-1  may be a part of  CiAG  of our study. The expression patterns of  AG-1  and  CiAG  are slighly different, which may result from the different reseach methods used. Moreover, the expression signal of  CiAG  has been detected in the leaf.  CiAG  expressed in non-floral tissue as well as in floral organs is in accordance with the research of  Kim  et al.  (2005)  in some basal angiosperms and of  Chanderbali  et al.  (2006)  in  Pe.am.AG  of  Persea  from the Lauraceae family. In this study, the authors proposed that the expression of  AG  in vegetative tissue is an evolutionary novelty ( Chanderbali  et al.  2006 ).  Chanderbali  et al.  (2006)  also hypothesized that the tepals of  Persea  and perhaps in other Lauraceae are derived from stamen primordia on the basis of gene expression and the occasional presence of tepaloid organs in stamen whorls.   CiGLO  was expressed in whorl 2 of petals, whorl 3o of petaloid staminodes and the labellum, whorl 3i of petaloid staminodes and the single fertile stamen, and whorl 4 of carpels, while it was not expressed in whorl 1 of sepals. The expression of  CiGLO  in whorls 2, 3 and 4 seems consistent neither with the aforementioned modified monocot BC model ( Van Tunen AJ 1993 ;  Kanno  et al.  2003 ;  Kanno  et al.  2007 ) nor with the shifting/sliding boundary model ( Bowman 1997 ;  Kramer  et al.  2003 ), although it is still consistent with the canonical BC model of eudicots. The ‘shifting boundary’ ( Bowman  et al.  1991 ) and ‘sliding boundary’ ( Kramer  et al.  2003 ) models allow the boundary of expression of the B-class genes to ‘slide’ from that observed in  Arabidopsis  and  Antirrhinum  to one that includes the outer perianth whorl (outer tepals) of  Ranunculus ,  Tulipa  and other species with an entirely petaloid perianth. The extension of B-class gene expression into whorl 4 of carpels might explain the petaloidy observed in the style of  C .  indica  ( Glinos and Cocucci 2011 ).  Two copies of  GLOBOSA  were studied by  Almeida  et al.  (2013) , and both  GLO-1  and  GLO-2  show an expansion in their expression domains.  GLO-1  and  GLO-2  show great similarity to  CiGLO  of our study, but they are only partial CDS, which makes it difficult to address the relationship between them and  CiGLO . Further data are required to see whether  CiGLO  is a new copy due to its divergent expression patterns. Broad expression patterns observed for  ZinGLO1 ,  ZinGLO2 ,  ZinGLO3  and  ZinGLO4  support a combination hypothesis which supports the idea that labellum identity is a result of the combination of multiple  GLO  homologues rather than expression of a single orthologue ( Bartlett and Specht 2010 ). Whether the combination hypothesis is applicable in  Canna  needs broader investigation.  In the canonical BC model, simultaneous expression of B- and C-class MADS-box genes would result in the specification of stamen identity.  CiAG  and  CiGLO  are expressed simultaneously in the labellum, petaloid staminodes and the fertile stamen in the present study. If molecular evidence is sufficient to determine organ identity, one could claim that these results suggest that the three floral organs are of the same identity. However, despite their similar expression patterns, these organs present very different morphologies. The role of B- and C-class genes in determining final organ morphology awaits further studies. Other studies, such as stage-specific  in situ  hybridization, would be necessary for a more complete picture of the expression profiles during development.  In situ  hybridization experiments carried out on a C-class gene  AhMADS6  and two B-class genes  AhMADS5  and  AhMADS8  of  A. hainanensis  ( Song  et al.  2010 ) have shown a case similar to the present study, which has corroborated the hypothesis that the labellum of  A. hainanensis  originated from stamens. Recently,  Miao  et al.  (2014)  showed that the vascular bundle of the labellum of  C. indica  originates from two stamen primordia at an early developmental stage, providing anatomical evidence for the interpretation that the labellum should be regarded as a derivative of staminodes in the inner whorl ( Miao  et al.  2014 ). Although the molecular data presented in this study do not provide sufficient evidence to support that anatomical result, they are also not inconsistent with this interpretation. In accordance with the expression pattern of B- and C-class genes described by  Almeida  et al.  (2013) , our present data do not show differential expression patterns between fertile and sterile elements within the androecial whorl, and neither set of results can explain the observed petaloidy or how, mechanistically, the staminodes and the fertile stamen show distinct morphologies.  Based on the expression patterns of B- and C-class genes, the molecular data presented in this study suggest that petaloid staminodes and the labellum are of androecial identity, in concordance with their position in the floral meristem and in agreement with largely described expression patterns in model species. However, these expression patterns are not sufficient to explain the distinct morphologies observed in staminodes and the fertile stamen. Broader and in-depth exploration of other copies of  GLO  and  AG  genes and sequence evolution, as well as a broader understanding of the involvement of B- and C-class genes in floral organ identity regulatory networks are required for a better understanding of the relationship between B- and C-class gene expression patterns and the floral organ morphology in  Canna .  Funding was provided by the Joint Fund South China Botanical Garden-Shanghai Institute of Plant Physiology &amp; Ecology,  National Natural Science Foundation of China  ( 31200176, 31200246, 30900089 ) and Key Laboratory of Plant Resources Conservation and Sustainable Utilization, SCBG, CAS.  Isolation of the sequences and real-time PCR analyses and data collection were accomplished by Q.F. following supervision by J.P.L. and the laboratory assistance of H.F.L. and P.Z. Phylogenetic analysis was performed by Y.F.K. Writing and editing and comprehensive revision of the manuscript was performed by Y.F.K. and A.M.R.A.  None declared.  Novel sequences have been submitted to NCBI ( http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov ). Accession numbers are  Canna indica AGAMOUS , JQ180191 and  Canna indica GLOBOSA , JQ180192.  We thank Dr Juanjuan Song of South China Botanical Garden, Chinese Academy of Sciences for providing generous assistance in experiment design and Dr YingTong of South China Sea Institute of Oceanology, Chinese Academy of Sciences for help in using the NCBI database and MEGA software. A.M.R.A. would like to thank CAPES for her fellowship support (Bolsa Jovem Talentos, Brazil). We are also grateful to the two anonymous referees and the associate editor of the journal  AoB PLANTS  for their helpful comments. 