Spatial and temporal influences on the physiological condition of invasive silver carpEffects of stress on spawners reproductive performance in female Grass Carp (<italic>Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic>)Connectivity and biocomplexity in waterbodies of riverine floodplainsStress in fishes: a diversity of responses with particular reference to changes in circulating corticosteroidsUnderstanding large river–floodplain ecosystemsDiel pattern of pelagic distribution and feeding in planktivorous fishSeasonal zooplankton dynamics in main channel and backwater habitats of the Upper Mississippi RiverEffects of temperature on growth and metabolism in juvenile turbotModel Selection and Multimodel Inference: A Practical Information-theoric ApproachLinking silver carp habitat selection to flow and phytoplankton in the Mississippi RiverInvasive carp in the Mississippi River BasinMacrophysiology: large-scale patterns in physiological traits and their ecological implicationsMacrophysiology for a changing worldBlood-chemistry indicators of nutritional status in juvenile salmonidsEcological restoration and physiology: an overdue integrationWhat is conservation physiology? Perspectives on an increasingly integrated and essential scienceLinking adult reproduction and larval density of invasive carp in a large riverStatistical comparisons of classifiers over multiple data setsThe impact of cropland cover on river nutrient levels in the Mississippi River BasinIntegrating landscape ecology and conservation physiologySeasonal variations in the physiological status and energy content of somatic and reproductive tissues of chubTemporal changes in plasma thyroid hormone, growth hormone and free fatty acid concentrations, and hepatic 5′-monodeiodinase activity, lipid and protein content during chronic fasting and re-fasting in rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>)Effects of nutritional status on metabolic rate, exercise and recovery in a freshwater fishThe role of progeny quality and male size in the nesting success of smallmouth bass: integrating field and laboratory studiesHow many subjects does it take to do a regression analysis?Multimodel inference in ecology and evolution: challenges and solutionsEffect of temperature and dietary protein/lipid ratio on growth performance and nutrient utilization of juvenile Senegalese sole (<italic>Solea senegalensis</italic>)Long Term Resource Monitoring Program Procedures: Fish MonitoringStress-induced changes in concentrations of plasma sex steroids in black breamNutritional condition and physiology of paternal care in two congeneric species of black bass (<italic>Micropterus</italic> spp.) relative to stage of offspring developmentPhysiological characterization of juvenile Chinook salmon utilizing different habitats during migration through the Columbia River EstuaryOsmoregulatory, metabolic, and nutritional condition of summer-run male Chinook salmon in relation to their fate and migratory behavior in a regulated riverUsing information theory as a substitute for stepwise regression in ecology and behaviorEvaluating habitat quality of vertebrates using conservation physiology toolsNitrogen and phosphorus in the Upper Mississippi River: transport, processing, and effects on the river ecosystemBlood and circulationPhysiological consequences of habitat selectionSeasonal and interannual variation in the allometry of energy allocation in juvenile striped bassMacrostress: do large-scale ecological patterns exist in the glucocorticoid stress response of vertebrates?The when, what and where of freshwater feedingThe When, What and Where of Freshwater Feeding, Atlantic SThe application of electronic computers to factor analysisFish communities of Midwestern rivers: a history of degradationNutrient requirements, supply and utilization in the context of carp cultureEnergy requirements, utilization and dietary supply to salmonidsApplications of a bioenergetics model to yellow perch (<italic>Perca flavescens</italic>) and walleye (<italic>Stizostedion vitreum vitreum</italic>)Bigheaded Carps: A Biological Synopsis and Environmental Risk AssesmentSeasonality of the red blood cell stress response in rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>)Influence of food deprivation and high stocking density on energetic metabolism and stress response in red porgy, <italic>Pagrus pagrus</italic> LCondition and energy reserves of Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic>) during the collapse of the northern Gulf of St. Lawrence stockCan simple condition indices be used to monitor and quantify seasonal changes in the energy reserves of Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic>)?Placing the North American invasion of Asian carp in a spatially explicit contextA Flexible System of Enzymatic AnalysisThe long-term Illinois River fish population monitoring programThe concept of allostasis in biology and biomedicineSeasonal changes in osmoregulation, cortisol, and cortisol receptor activity in the gills of parr/smolt of steelhead trout and steelhead-rainbow trout hybrids, <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>Energy allocation strategy modifies growth-survival trade-offs in juvenile fish across ecological and environmental gradientsCortisol in teleosts: dynamics, mechanisms of action, and metabolic regulationStarvation, energetics, and antioxidant defensesThe effects of 2011 Ohio and Mississippi river valley flooding on Cairo, Illinois, areaOverwinter survival of juvenile lake herring in relation to body size, physiological condition, energy stores, and food rationReproductive condition and occurrence of intersex in bighead carp and silver carp in the Missouri RiverChanges in the concentrations of plasma cortisol and thyroxine during sexual maturation of the hatchery-reared brown trout, Salmo trutta LContrasting seasonal modulation of the stress response in male and female rainbow troutHydrologic alterations in the Wabash River watershed, USAWhole-body cortisol is an indicator of crowding stress in adult zebrafish, Danio rerioMatch and mismatch: conservation physiology, nutritional ecology and the timescales of biological adaptationThe physiology/life-history nexusCollecting baseline corticosterone samples in the field: is under 3 min good enough?A mark-recapture population estimate for invasive silver carp (Hypophthalmichthys molitrix) in the La Grange Reach, Illinois RiverEnvironmental variation, life history attributes, and community structure in stream fishes: implications for environmental management and assessmentStream fish ecology: a landscape perspectiveFish, stress inEffects of stress on fish reproduction, gamete quality, and progenyValidation, use, and disadvantages of enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kits for detection of cortisol in channel catfish, largemouth bass, red pacu, and golden shinersA tutorial on Principal Components AnalysisFeeding behaviour of silver carp Hypophthalmichthys molitrix Val. and its impact on the food web in Lake Kinneret, IsraelThe effect of starvation on growth and plasma growth hormone concentrations of rainbow trout, Oncorhynchus mykissThe influence of environmental temperature and oxygen concentration on the recovery of largemouth bass from exercise: implications for live-release angling tournamentsClimate and body size influence nest survival in a fish with parental careA brief guide to model selection, multimodel inference and model averaging in behavioural ecology using Akaike's information criterionThe Long-term Illinois, Mississippi, Ohio, and Wabash Rivers Fish Population Monitoring Program 2011Assessment of seasonal and polluting effects on the quality of river water by exploratory data analysisBlood chemistry correlates of nutritional condition, tissue damage, and stress in migrating juvenile chinook salmon (<italic>Oncorhynchus tshawytscha</italic>)Spatial and temporal dynamics of lake whitefish (<italic>Coregonus clupeaformis</italic>) health indicators: linking individual-based indicators to a management-relevant endpointExploring riverine zooplankton in three habitats of the Illinois River ecosystem: where do they come from?Blood glucose and lactate, and plasma protein as stress indicators in fishEcology of Teleost Fishes<bold>Editor:</bold> Steven CookeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.This study quantified the nutritional and stress physiology of invasive silver carp across broad spatial and temporal scales to define how these fish interact with their environment. Results demonstrated that nutritional properties varied significantly across rivers and sampling time. Stress levels varied only across time periods.We quantified nutritional and stress parameters (alkaline phosphatase, cholesterol, protein, triglycerides, cortisol, and glucose) in invasive silver carp (<italic>Hypophthalmichthys molitrix</italic>) inhabiting four large rivers throughout three distinct time periods in the Midwestern USA. Examining the basic biology and ecology of an invasive species is crucial to gain an understanding of the interaction between an organism and its environment. Analysis of the physiological condition of wild-caught silver carp across broad spatial and temporal scales is essential because stress and nutritional parameters can link individuals to their habitats and vary among populations across environments. During each time period, we collected blood samples from individual silver carp in the Illinois River and portions of the Mississippi, Ohio, and Wabash rivers in Illinois. We tested for relationships between silver carp nutrition and stress across rivers, reaches within rivers, and time periods. Principal component analyses separated physiological parameters into a stress component (cortisol and glucose) and two nutritional components representative of short-term feeding (alkaline phosphatase, protein, and triglycerides) and body energy reserves (cholesterol and protein). Akaike's information criterion suggested that time period had the greatest influence on stress. Stress levels were consistent in all four rivers, and declined across time periods. Akaike's information criterion also suggested that interactions of time period and river had the greatest influence on short-term feeding and body energy reserves. There was no specific pattern across time periods within each river, nor was there a pattern across rivers. Our results provide a better understanding of nutritional and stress conditions in invasive silver carp across a broad landscape and temporal scale, with implications for managing and predicting the spread of this species.Riverine ecosystems are spatially and temporally dynamic, and this variability may influence habitat quality for fishes. For example, hydrological regimes, nutrient loading, seasonal variation, and human activity can interact, or act independently, to generate lotic habitat characteristics that vary across an extreme range of conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C42">Karr <italic>et al.</italic>, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C64">Pyron and Neumann, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C53">McClelland <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Water temperature may vary spatially or seasonally along environmental gradients caused by channel morphology and location within the river, which may influence the density, diversity, and/or richness of aquatic communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C70">Schlosser, 1990</xref>). Warmer water temperatures may induce growth or spawning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C4">Bayley, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C16">DeGrandchamp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and increase feeding rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C45">Kitchell <italic>et al.</italic>, 1977</xref>), while cooler temperatures may lead to decreased feeding and lower metabolic rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C5">Bohl, 1980</xref>). Seasonal variation in flow rates can cause lotic environments to vary from slow to fast moving, which may also provide suitable environmental conditions for larval production in fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C51">Lohmeyer and Garvey, 2008</xref>). In addition to the influence of broad-scale factors, habitat parameters that operate at smaller scales can also influence resident fish and aquatic communities. Competition for resources (e.g. food availability, thermal habitat, and refuge) may occur within high-quality lotic habitats, with a competitive advantage offered to individuals that obtain access to these preferred habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C36">Huey, 1991</xref>).Access to habitat of varying quality may influence decisions by individual fish that relate to reproduction and/or movement, which may ultimately influence abundance, distribution, and mortality. Resource allocation is often shaped by habitat quality, with high-quality habitat providing sufficient food accessibility (maximizing fitness) and low-quality habitat potentially forcing an animal to disperse and find sufficient resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C36">Huey, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C33">Homyack, 2010</xref>). For example, the energy required for optimal growth and recruitment can be influenced by available resources, including access to food, nutritional status, and the energy expenditure of parents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C20">Encina and Granado-Lorencio, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C33">Homyack, 2010</xref>). Likewise, variation in thermal regimes may reduce foraging activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C7">Burel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>) or prey availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C85">Wahl <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C6">Burdis and Hoxmeier, 2011</xref>), which may restrict food access. Related to habitat quality is the notion of allostasis, and the influence that habitat quality can have on allostatic load, which, in turn, can influence abundance, distribution, and mortality. Essentially, individuals strive to maintain a balance between daily and seasonal environmental variation, and unpredictable events that can affect energy requirements. Higher-quality habitats may provide environmental conditions that minimize an organism's allostatic load and, in turn, can reduce energetic expenditure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C54">McEwen and Wingfield, 2003</xref>). Thus, understanding how fish populations interact with habitat of varying quality at broad temporal and spatial scales can provide insights into population-level trends, including energy use, movement, dispersal, reproduction, and mortality.Physiological tools are an integral way to quantify organism–environment interactions, particularly when considered over broad spatial scales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C11">Chown <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C12">Chown and Gaston, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C33">Homyack, 2010</xref>), and can link individuals to the habitats in which they reside (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C67">Ricklefs and Wikelski, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C14">Cooke and Suski, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C19">Ellis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In particular, aspects of physiology that quantify the stress and nutritional status of individuals are particularly insightful. Stress and nutritional metrics represent how behaviour and physiology interact within dynamic environments to influence individual homeostasis and balance energy requirements that are not reflected in simply quantifying habitat occupancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C19">Ellis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C66">Raubenheimer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). More importantly, changes at the population level (e.g. abundance and distribution) occur in response to changes in individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C67">Ricklefs and Wikelski, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C19">Ellis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), making the quantification of animal health, stress, and condition through blood chemistry valuable for understanding links between physiology, community structure, competition, and movement.Silver carp (<italic>Hypophthalmichthys molitrix</italic>) are relatively recent invaders to North America (early 1970s; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C10">Chick and Pegg, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C46">Kolar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and represent an excellent model organism for asking questions regarding the impacts of broad- and small-scale habitat variation on the stress, condition, and distribution of wild organisms. Silver carp have exhibited rapid population growth and spread since their introduction, making them the dominant species in several riverine ecosystems in the Midwestern USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C46">Kolar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C69">Sass <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). More importantly, silver carp can have multiple spawning bouts per year, have few natural predators as adults, and feed low on the food chain (primarily prioritizing planktonic prey), all of which may be responsible for their success as invaders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C10">Chick and Pegg, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C46">Kolar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Currently, we do not know how various broad- and small-scale parameters influence the health and condition of silver carp, or how these different factors can influence the movement, activity, and spread of this invasive species. Information on stress and condition at broad scales can have important implications for understanding not only how organisms interact with their environments, but also which factors influence their spread and distribution across the landscape. Therefore, our objective was to quantify variation in blood-based nutritional and stress parameters of silver carp across broad spatial and temporal scales.Silver carp (<italic>Hypophthalmichthys molitrix</italic>) sampling at broad temporal and spatial scales across mid-summer, late summer, and early autumn time periods in the Illinois, Mississippi, Ohio, and Wabash rivers during 2011Map of the Illinois River and portions of the Mississippi, Ohio, and Wabash rivers in Illinois, illustrating reaches sampled in 2011. The Illinois River consists of the Alton reach [river mile (RM) 0–70], Meredosia (RM 70–80), La Grange (RM 80–158), and Chillicothe (RM 158–231). The Mississippi River consists of Pool 20 (RM 343–364.5), Pool 25 (RM 242–273.5), Chain of Rocks (RM 165.5–200.5) and Kaskaskia (RM 117–165.5). The Ohio River consists of Smithland Pool (RM 848–918.5), Pool 52 (918.5–939), Pool 53 (RM 939–962.5), and the Confluence (RM 962.5-981). The Wabash River consists of Terre Haute (RM 315.5–351), Palestine (RM 351–385.5), Vincennes (RM 385.5–412), Mt Carmel (RM 412–444.5), and New Harmony (RM 444.5–487).We collected silver carp primarily using pulsed direct current (DC) electrofishing according to methods outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C27">Gutreuter <italic>et al.</italic> (1995)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C81">Tyszko <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>. Some of the silver carp analysed leapt on board the boat prior to being stunned by electricity and were sampled for blood in a manner identical to those that were stunned by electricity and labelled accordingly. Immediately after capturing a fish, we collected blood from the caudal vessel using either a 2.5 or a 3.8 cm needle (BD PrecisionGlide needles; 22 gauge) with a 1 ml syringe (BD Slip Tip Sterile Syringes; volume 1 ml) pre-rinsed in heparin saline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C35">Houston, 1990</xref>). We drew blood from all individuals, regardless of collection method, in &lt;3 min to obtain a baseline value of stress not influenced by sampling procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C68">Romero and Reed, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C19">Ellis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). This also qualifies as baseline nutritional status, because nutritional values have not been shown to change in &lt;3 min (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C13">Congleton and Wagner, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C22">Gingerich <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). One millilitre of whole blood was collected, placed into a microcentrifuge tube, and spun at 5200 <italic>g</italic> for at least 3 min to separate plasma from red cells. Plasma was removed using a transfer pipette and placed into two additional 1.5 ml microcentrifuge tubes. Plasma and red cells were then flash frozen in a dry shipper charged with liquid nitrogen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C78">Suski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Samples were transported to the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and stored in a &lt;− 75°C freezer until processing. We also recorded total length (in millimetres) and weight (in grams) for each fish.We analysed plasma triglycerides (in milligrams per decilitre), cholesterol (in milligrams per decilitre), alkaline phosphatase (ALP; in units per litre), and cortisol (in nanograms per millilitres) using the following commercially available kits: EnzyChrom Triglyceride Assay Kit (ETGA-200), EnzyChrom Cholesterol Assay Kit (ECCH-100), and QuantiChrom Alkaline Phosphatase Assay Kit (DALP-250), respectively (BioAssay Systems, Haywood, CA, USA), and Cortisol EIA Kit (ADI-900-071; Enzo Life Sciences, Plymouth Meeting, PA, USA). Plasma glucose (in milligrams per decilitre) was determined enzymatically with a microplate spectrophotometer (Spectra Max Plus 384 model #05362; Molecular Devices, Union City, CA, USA) following the procedure of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C52">Lowry and Passonneau (1972)</xref>. We measured protein (in grams per decilitre) with a hand-held protein refractometer (AST model 1250; Thomas Scientific, Swedesboro, NJ, USA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C86">Wells and Pankhurst, 1999</xref>), certified for use in the range of 0–12 g dl<sup>−1</sup>. The cortisol EIA kit we used has been identified as accurate and precise when used for fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C74">Sink <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), and has a lower detection limit of 0.0567 ng ml<sup>−1</sup>. Individuals below sensitivity limits were treated as being equal to the lowest detection limit value for the kit (0.0567 ng ml<sup>−1</sup>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C28">Haddy and Pankhurst, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C65">Ramsay <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Cholesterol, ALP, protein, and triglycerides have been shown to represent either a short-term, recent feeding nutritional component or a long-term body energy reserve nutritional component (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C83">Wagner and Congleton, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C13">Congleton and Wagner, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C26">Guerreiro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Cortisol and glucose are associated with the stress response of teleost fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C3">Barton, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C83">Wagner and Congleton, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C13">Congleton and Wagner, 2006</xref>).Model selection results relating predictor variables to variation in principal component scores for wild-caught silver carp (<italic>H. molitrix</italic>)Principal component (PC) scores are as follows: PC1 corresponds to a short-term feeding score; PC2 represents a body energy reserve score; and PC3 represents a stress score. Fish were collected from four rivers across three time periods and sampled for blood immediately following collection. Models are ranked by differences in Akaike's information criterion values (corrected for small sample size; ΔAICc), and the model with the lowest ΔAICc value is the best fit to the data, with AICc weight determining the best approximating model.Competing models were compared using Akaike's information criterion corrected for small sample size (AICc) to quantify and rank the best approximating model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C25">Grueber <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C32">Hegyi and Garamszegi, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C80">Symonds and Moussalli, 2011</xref>). Based on the ΔAICc, a value 0 ≤ ΔAICc ≤ 2 shows substantial support that a model is the best fit to the data, while an ΔAICc &gt;10 shows little support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C8">Burnham and Anderson, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C79">Suski and Ridgway, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C80">Symonds and Moussalli, 2011</xref>). Following best fit model determination for each rotated PC, a mixed-model analysis of variance (ANOVA) for the best-fitting model was compared using a Tukey's multiple comparison <italic>post hoc</italic> analysis to aid with visualization of trends in the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C17">Demsar, 2006</xref>). We performed all statistical analyses using JMP version 10.0 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA). Rejection of the null hypothesis (α) for all tests was 0.05. All values are reported as means ± SEM where appropriate. We used the null hypothesis of no variation in stress or nutrition (i.e. physiological parameters) for silver carp across rivers, across reaches within rivers, or across time periods.Sample size, minimum, maximum, mean, median, and SEM values for several nutritional and stress parameters of silver carp (<italic>H. molitrix</italic>), sampled in the Illinois, Mississippi, Ohio, and Wabash rivers during 2011Ancillary environmental data collected across rivers and time periods sampled in 2011Values shown were averaged across time periods for all reaches. All parameters were measured in real time concurrently with fish sampling, except for river stage. River stage was acquired from the Army Corp of Engineers river gauges website (<uri xlink:href="http://rivergages.mvr.usace.army.mil/WaterControl/new/layout.cfm" xlink:type="simple">http://rivergages.mvr.usace.army.mil/WaterControl/new/layout.cfm</uri>).Principal components summarizing stress and nutritional characteristics for silver carp (<italic>H. molitrix</italic>) sampled from the Illinois, Mississippi, Ohio, and Wabash rivers during 2011Variables were loaded into three principal components (PC1, PC2, and PC3).<sup>a</sup>Characteristics contributing maximally to each principal component are indicated and are &gt;0.4. Positive values for each principal component correlate positively with the stress and nutritional characteristics.Visualization of the best fit Akaike's information criterion (corrected for small sample size; ΔAICc) ranked model linking PC1 (short-term feeding) scores (a) and PC2 (body energy reserves) scores (b) for silver carp (<italic>Hypophthalmichthys molitrix</italic>) by time period, with each river considered independently. PC3 (stress) scores (c) for silver carp are best explained by time period. Results of statistical analysis are reported in the figure, with dissimilar letters indicating significant differences.Understanding the physiology of invasive species is important to address problems facing conservation and management, and how to control these species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C15">Cooke <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Knowledge of nutrition and stress levels can assist in the development of strategies to control the spread of silver carp and help to define predictive relationships between habitat characteristics and individual performance in river basins not yet invaded. For wild-caught silver carp sampled at broad spatial scales, the majority of the variability in the data showed that indices of short-term feeding (PC1; triglycerides, protein, and ALP in plasma) were most strongly influenced by time period, considered independently for each river. Previous research has shown that triglyceride levels in plasma rise following feeding, protein responds to changes in nutritional status (e.g. food consumption, growth, and body condition), and elevated concentrations of ALP are related to the processing of energy substrates by the liver (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C83">Wagner and Congleton, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C13">Congleton and Wagner, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C26">Guerreiro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). More importantly, all three of these metrics vary according to fasting and refeeding patterns in fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C13">Congleton and Wagner, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C30">Hanson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C83">Wagner and Congleton (2004)</xref> demonstrated that plasma ALP and protein concentrations declined in juvenile Chinook salmon (<italic>Oncorhynchus tshawytscha</italic>) during fasting, but recovered after feeding was resumed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C29">Hanson and Cooke (2009)</xref> also showed that triglyceride values in smallmouth bass (<italic>Micropterus dolomieu</italic>) declined because of fasting during the parental care period of spawning. Mechanisms explaining our observed feeding variability across time periods may include changes in food availability, energetic constraints, or both (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C87">Wootton, 1998</xref>).Annually, biotic and abiotic characteristics of rivers can vary significantly. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C85">Wahl <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>, zooplankton densities in the Illinois River peak in late spring, while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C6">Burdis and Hoxmeier (2011)</xref> observed peak zooplankton densities in May and June in the Upper Mississippi River. This variation in zooplankton data may explain trends in the PC1 scores for silver carp from the Illinois River, because scores were greatest in the mid-summer and late summer, potentially during periods of peak zooplankton concentrations. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C81">Tyszko <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>, silver carp catch per unit effort (CPUE; expressed as number per hour) also peaked in the late summer, which may indicate that feeding is optimal for silver carp in the Illinois River during this time period, regardless of density. Silver carp in the Mississippi River showed consistently low PC1 scores across all three time periods sampled, indicating low feeding rates across all seasons. Despite this uniformity, CPUE of silver carp in the Mississippi River varied across time periods, by as much as 3-fold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C81">Tyszko <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). This potentially indicates that feeding levels of silver carp are not influenced by density in this river. The complex morphology of rivers has also been shown to vary seasonally in terms of nutrient loading, species composition, and productivity, all of which may influence food availability in the late summer and, in turn, drive PC1 scores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C2">Amoros and Bornette, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C34">Houser and Richardson, 2010</xref>). For silver carp in the Midwestern USA, variation in prey abundance may explain observed patters in short-term feeding indices.Energetic constraints, related to water temperature and/or reproduction, may be another mechanism explaining patterns in short-term feeding (PC1) across time periods. Optimal metabolic conditions, food intake, growth, and nutrient use for fishes are affected by water temperature; fish generally consume more food during periods of elevated temperatures to balance metabolic costs and optimize growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C44">Kaushik and Médale, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C7">Burel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C26">Guerreiro <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Water temperature also affects metabolic rates and maintenance energy requirements for carp, similar to other teleost fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C76">Spataru and Gophen, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C43">Kaushik, 1995</xref>). For silver carp in the Illinois River, short-term feeding indices were lowest during the early autumn when water temperatures were coolest. In contrast, silver carp in the Ohio and Wabash rivers showed the greatest values for short-term feeding indices during the late summer sampling period, which was the period of highest water temperature for these two locations. Silver carp CPUE was also greatest in the late summer for the Ohio and Wabash rivers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C81">Tyszko <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), which could suggest that feeding is optimal for silver carp in these rivers during this time period, regardless of density. Reproduction may decrease feeding rates, is metabolically expensive, depletes energy stores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C20">Encina and Granado-Lorencio, 1997</xref>), and may result in reductions in short-term feeding indices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C77">Sumpter <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C20">Encina and Granado-Lorencio, 1997</xref>). Asian carp have been shown to use environmental cues, such as elevated flow, temperature, or river stage, to initiate spawning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C16">DeGrandchamp <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), with peak larval production typically occurring in the spring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C51">Lohmeyer and Garvey, 2008</xref>). Silver carp in the Missouri River, for example, have been observed to reproduce as early as March (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C61">Papoulias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Surface velocity was highest across all four rivers during the mid-summer, suggesting that conditions would be suitable for silver carp spawning during this sampling period. This coincides with decreased short-term feeding scores in the Ohio and Wabash rivers during the mid-summer time period. Regardless of the mechanism driving short-term feeding, it was the principal component showing the majority of the variability in silver carp feeding and changed temporally and spatially.Similar to what was observed for indices of short-term feeding, time period considered independently for each river was the strongest predictor of variation in silver carp body energy reserves (cholesterol and protein in plasma; PC2). Previous studies have shown that plasma protein concentrations respond to changes in body condition, with nutritionally deprived individuals showing reduced protein reserves relative to feeding individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C21">Farbridge and Leatherland, 1992</xref>). Cholesterol is a lipid present in animal tissue that is positively correlated with body energy reserves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C13">Congleton and Wagner, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C31">Hasler <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). More importantly, both of these metrics have been shown to vary in response to the feeding history of individual fish. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C50">Lambert and Dutil (1997b)</xref> showed that protein is an energy reserve that can be mobilized during periods of low energy in Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic>), while <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C30">Hanson <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> demonstrated that plasma protein concentrations declined in juvenile Chinook salmon from depletion of energy reserves during smoltification. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C13">Congleton and Wagner (2006)</xref> also suggested that protein and cholesterol responded to body energy reserves rather than directly to food intake, because these metrics declined slowly in fasted fishes and did not recover after refeeding in juvenile Chinook salmon.Seasonal differences in food availability and cyclical changes in energy allocation may explain variation in energy stores in silver carp. River temperature can fluctuate greatly, potentially influencing feeding conditions, food availability and quality, and subsequently fish body composition through the allocation of energy resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C7">Burel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C49">Lambert and Dutil, 1997a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C50">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C56">Mogensen and Post, 2012</xref>). Fishes have the ability to apportion energy to lipid stores to prepare for periods of scarce resources, such as in winter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C56">Mogensen and Post, 2012</xref>). Cooler water temperatures in the autumn and winter can reduce activity and feeding rates of fishes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C7">Burel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C39">Johansen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>), which can minimize energy expenditures and allow for increased energy storage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C58">Morales <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Silver carp have also been observed to situate themselves in positions of low water velocity to conserve energy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C9">Calkins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Body energy reserves for silver carp in the Mississippi and Wabash rivers were greatest during early autumn sampling, which was the period of coolest water temperatures recorded for these two rivers. Interestingly, silver carp CPUE rates were also lowest in the early autumn in the Mississippi River (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C81">Tyszko <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). This may contribute to the reason why body condition was greatest, because fewer organisms were competing for resources, allowing silver carp to store energy during this time period in this river. Likewise, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C76">Spataru and Gophen (1985)</xref> observed that the body condition of silver carp was greatest in autumn and winter relative to other seasons of the year. Analogous to our patterns observed in short-term feeding, high body energy reserves in early autumn may also be related to bioenergetics. The cool water temperatures observed during this time period for all four rivers may have resulted in lower metabolic demands and the absence of energy-consuming spawning events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C7">Burel <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C61">Papoulias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Interestingly, body energy reserves of silver carp in the Illinois and Ohio rivers did not differ across time periods despite changes in water temperature of almost 40 and 30%, respectively, during this study. Irrespective of the mechanism(s) changing body energy reserves, our study provides evidence that body energy reserves in silver carp may peak in the early autumn, as observed by the greatest scores in the Mississippi and Wabash rivers during this time period.Values of PC3 for silver carp (cortisol and glucose in plasma) were highly influenced by time period, independent of river or reach. Given that PC3 was composed exclusively of stress-related variables, our results indicate that stress levels change seasonally, and in synchrony, across broad spatial scales. Plasma corticosteroid (cortisol) is produced during the primary stress response to various physical and psychological stressors for vertebrate animals. Increased plasma glucose levels provide energy as part of the secondary stress response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C3">Barton, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C83">Wagner and Congleton, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C72">Schreck, 2007</xref>). Several types of disturbances may trigger the stress response in fishes, including chemical, physical, or perceived stressors (i.e. temperature, nutrition, and water quality; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C3">Barton, 2002</xref>). For example, season and temperature can exert a strong influence on the hormonal rates of reactions to stress, with higher temperatures causing biological reaction rates to increase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C55">McLeese <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C63">Pottinger and Carrick, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C72">Schreck, 2007</xref>), and potentially elevating cortisol concentrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C73">Schreck <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Stream-dwelling fishes have been observed to undergo shifts in distribution from summer habitats to overwintering areas to avoid metabolic stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C71">Schlosser, 1991</xref>). Stress levels have also been shown to correlate positively with reproductive activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C1">Akar, 2011</xref>) and negatively with nutritional status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C57">Mommsen <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>). Our results showed that the lowest stress levels in silver carp occurred during the early autumn, regardless of river, which was the period of lowest water temperature for all rivers sampled. Similar results were reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C38">Jessop <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>, who showed that both species-specific and environmental variables were important in reptile and bird responses to stressors across broad scales. Reduced stress levels in silver carp may also be caused by favourable water quality and temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C63">Pottinger and Carrick, 2000</xref>), natural, seasonal fluctuations in concentrations of cortisol that are consistent across broad spatial scales, or both (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C62">Pickering and Christie, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C47">Koldkjaer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Elevated indices of stress in the mid-summer and late summer may also be correlated with the general timing of silver carp spawning in these rivers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C61">Papoulias <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C46">Kolar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Additionally, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C81">Tyszko <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref>, CPUE for silver carp was greatest in the late summer in all four rivers sampled, which may have contributed to the higher stress scores. Our results clearly demonstrate that stress in silver carp is driven by time period and is consistent among populations separated across broad spatial scales.Interestingly, variables previously shown to influence fish nutrition and stress were not significant drivers of variation for silver carp in our study. Principal components describing short-term feeding (PC1), body energy reserves (PC2), and stress (PC3), were not affected by total body length or by reaches within rivers. Previous studies have shown that total length can influence short-term feeding and body energy reserves in fish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C37">Hurst and Conover, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C60">Pangle <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C39">Johansen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The capacity for energy storage is often related to body size, where lipid and protein content comprise a greater portion of total body mass in larger individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C60">Pangle <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). In juvenile striped bass (<italic>Morone saxatilis</italic>), lipid reserves were greater in larger individuals, which was attributable to an increase in lipid mass throughout the growing season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C37">Hurst and Conover, 2003</xref>). Direct competition between different age and size classes because of diet overlap may also exist, with larger fish having a greater advantage in accessing food, as observed in Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C40">Johansen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). In response to stressors, previous research has also shown that total length and the ontogenetic stage of silver carp can affect the stress response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C72">Schreck, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C48">Laiz-Carrión <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Total length may not have contributed to a best fit model because of the number of individuals caught (513) and, even though size varied from 252 to 900 mm, the majority of fish sampled were around the same size (mean 577 ± 6 mm). Our findings are in accordance with those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C20">Encina and Granado-Lorencio (1997)</xref>, who suggested that seasonal differences in condition, nutrition, and somatic energy content of juvenile and mature <italic>Leuciscus pyrenaicus</italic> were better explained by variation in the environment (e.g. food quantity and quality) than by size.Likewise, our results also demonstrated that variation in PC scores did not change across reaches within the same river. Previous research has shown that species richness may vary from upstream to downstream locations in rivers, with species richness generally being greater downstream (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C42">Karr <italic>et al.</italic>, 1985</xref>). Earlier studies on the Illinois River showed significant differences in fish communities across reaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C53">McClelland <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), suggesting that reach-scale factors have the potential to impact species assemblages and community structure. However, we did not observe any influence of reach-scale effects on silver carp nutrition and stress. One potential reason may be due to our sampling protocol. Our study was conducted in only 1 year, which was an epic flood year (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C59">Olson and Morton, 2012</xref>), and this single sampling year might not account for potential inter-annual variability influencing silver carp nutrition and stress. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C84">Wagner <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> observed that health indicators of lake whitefish (<italic>Coregonus clupeaformis</italic>) sampled across several locations in Lake Michigan varied across years. Additionally, the rivers we sampled have been greatly altered by anthropogenic influences (i.e. agriculture use, levees, and dams), potentially homogenizing the effects of reach-scale factors at the spatial scales examined.Despite the findings of our study, there are a number of avenues for future studies to explore related to this topic. For example, the influence of fine-scale habitat features, along with community structure and species diversity and richness, on the health and condition of fishes should be investigated. Examining specific, quantifiable habitat and community characteristics and relating them to nutritional and stress parameters may provide a better comprehension of the link between physiology and invasive species, community structure, and competition, and how interacting factors may influence movement. Other prospective research could address inter-annual variability by continuing similar work over several years for a more comprehensive understanding of silver carp nutritional and stress relationships at a broad spatial and temporal scale, similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C53">McClelland <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="COT017C84">Wagner <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>. When combined, results from these future studies could help predict the response of Asian carp to habitats not yet invaded and help to predict how Asian carp will perform in different regions should their distributions spread.The authors thank the staff of the Illinois Natural History Survey's Illinois River Biological Station, National Great Rivers Research and Education Center, and The Long-Term Illinois, Mississippi, Ohio, and Wabash Rivers Fish Population Monitoring Program for assistance with data collection. This work was supported by the Illinois Department of Natural Resources and the United States Fish and Wildlife Service Federal Aid in Sportfish Restoration Project [F-101-R]. This work was also supported by the University of Illinois Graduate College, the College of Agricultural, Consumer and Environmental Sciences, and the Department Of Natural Resources and Environmental Sciences.