 Carbon dioxide stimulation of photosynthesis in  Liquidambar styraciflua  is not sustained during a 12-year field experiment  What have we learned from 15 years of free air CO 2  enrichment (FACE)? A meta-analytic review of the responses of photosynthesis, canopy properties and plant production to rising CO 2   The response of photosynthesis and stomatal conductance to rising [CO 2 ]: mechanisms and environmental interactions  Sustained enhancement of photosynthesis in mature deciduous forest trees after 8 years of free air CO 2  enrichment  Photosynthesis and stomatal conductance responses of poplars to free-air CO 2  enrichment (PopFACE) during the first growth cycle and immediately following coppice  Increased nitrogen-use efficiency of a short-rotation poplar plantation in elevated CO 2  concentration  Rubisco activation state decreases with increasing nitrogen content in apple leaves  Long-term response of nutrient-limited forests to CO 2  enrichment; equilibrium behavior of plant–soil models  Canopy position affects photosynthetic adjustments to long-term elevated CO 2  concentration (FACE) in aging needles in a mature  Pinus taeda  forest  Elevated CO 2  concentration affects leaf photosynthesis–nitrogen relationships in  Pinus taeda  over nine years in FACE  A meta-analysis of elevated CO 2  effects on woody plant mass, form, and physiology  Will photosynthetic capacity of aspen trees acclimate after long-term exposure to elevated CO 2  and O 3 ?  Forest water use and water use efficiency at elevated CO 2 : a model-data intercomparison at two contrasting temperate forest FACE sites  Optimal function explains forest responses to global change  More efficient plants: a consequence of rising atmospheric CO 2 ?  Elevated CO 2  affects photosynthetic responses in canopy pine and subcanopy deciduous trees over 10 years: a synthesis from Duke FACE  Effects of elevated CO 2  concentration on leaf characteristics and photosynthetic capacity of beech ( Fagus sylvatica ) during the growing season  Direct and indirect effects of elevated atmospheric CO 2  on net ecosystem production in a Chesapeake Bay tidal wetland  Moving beyond photosynthesis: from carbon source to sink-driven vegetation modeling  Progressive nitrogen limitation of ecosystem processes under elevated CO 2  in a warm-temperate forest  Increases in nitrogen uptake rather than nitrogen-use efficiency support higher rates of temperate forest productivity under elevated CO 2   Litterfall  15 N abundance indicates declining soil nitrogen availability in a free air CO 2 -enrichment experiment  Photosynthetic responses of two eucalypts to industrial-age changes in atmospheric [CO 2 ] and temperature  Photosynthetic acclimation in trees to rising atmospheric CO 2 : a broader perspective  Foliar gas exchange responses of two deciduous hardwoods during 3 years of growth in elevated CO 2 : no loss of photosynthetic enhancement  Environmental and stomatal control of photosynthetic enhancement in the canopy of a sweetgum ( Liquidambar styraciflua  L) plantation during three years of CO 2  enrichment  A free-air enrichment system for exposing tall forest vegetation to elevated atmospheric CO 2   Effects of CO 2  enrichment on the photosynthetic light response of sun and shade leaves of canopy sweetgum trees ( Liquidambar styraciflua ) in a forest ecosystem  No photosynthetic down-regulation in sweetgum trees ( Liquidambar styraciflua  L.) after three years of CO 2  enrichment at the Duke Forest FACE experiment  Leaf senescence and late-season net photosynthesis of sun and shade leaves of overstory sweetgum ( Liquidambar styraciflua ) grown in elevated and ambient carbon dioxide concentrations  Modelling optimal temperature acclimation of the photosynthetic apparatus in C-3 plants with respect to nitrogen use  Pseudoreplication and the design of ecological field experiments  Extinction coefficients of chlorophyll  a  and  b  in  N , N -dimethylformamide and 80 % acetone  Climate change 2013: the physical science basis  Nitrogen limitation in a sweetgum plantation: implications for carbon allocation and storage  Net mineralization of N at deeper soil depths as a potential mechanism for sustained forest production under elevated [CO 2 ]  Photosynthetic acclimation of overstory  Populus tremuloides  and understory  Acer saccharum  to elevated atmospheric CO 2  concentration: interactions with shade and soil nitrogen  Seasonal response of photosynthesis to elevated CO 2  in loblolly pine ( Pinus taeda  L.) over two growing seasons  Photosynthetic stimulation under long-term CO 2  enrichment and fertilization is sustained across a closed  Populus  canopy profile (EUROFACE)  Progressive nitrogen limitation of ecosystem responses to rising atmospheric carbon dioxide  Forest responses to CO 2  enrichment and climate warming  Effects of growth temperature on the responses of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase, electron transport components, and sucrose synthesis enzymes to leaf nitrogen in rice, and their relationships to photosynthesis  Response of photosynthetic carbon assimilation of Norway spruce exposed to long-term elevation of CO 2  concentration  The optimal allocation of nitrogen within the C 3  photosynthetic system at elevated CO 2   Effects of elevated CO 2  on photosynthesis in European forest species: a meta-analysis of model parameters  Temperature response of parameters of a biochemically based model of photosynthesis. II. A review of experimental data  Reconciling the optimal and empirical approaches to modelling stomatal conductance  Development of a standardized methodology for quantifying total chlorophyll and carotenoids from foliage of hardwood and conifer tree species  Isoprene emission from terrestrial ecosystems in response to global change: minding the gap between models and observations  Elevated CO 2  response of photosynthesis depends on ozone concentration in aspen  Tree responses to rising CO 2 : implications for the future forest  Allometric determination of tree growth in a CO 2 -enriched sweetgum stand  Fine-root production dominates response of a deciduous forest to atmospheric CO 2  enrichment  Forest response to elevated CO 2  is conserved across a broad range of productivity  CO 2  enhancement of forest productivity constrained by limited nitrogen availability  Transient nature of CO 2  fertilization in Arctic tundra  On the complementary relationship between marginal nitrogen and water use efficiencies among  Pinus taeda  leaves grown under ambient and enriched CO 2  environments  Carbon metabolite feedback regulation of leaf photosynthesis and development  The photosynthesis–leaf nitrogen relationship at ambient and elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide: a meta-analysis  Relationships between nutrient supply, nitrogen partitioning and growth in young Sitka spruce ( Picea sitchensis )  Long-term photosynthetic acclimation to increased atmospheric CO 2  concentration in young birch ( Betula pendula ) trees  Photosynthetic acclimation of  Pinus taeda  (loblolly pine) to long-term growth in elevated  p CO 2  (FACE)  Growth and nutrition response of young sweetgum plantations to repeated nitrogen fertilization on two site types  Persistent stimulation of photosynthesis by elevated CO 2  in a sweetgum ( Liquidambar styraciflua  L.) forest stand  Plant respiration and photosynthesis in global-scale vegetation models: incorporating acclimation to temperature and CO 2   Relationships between net photosynthesis and foliar nitrogen concentrations in a loblolly pine forest ecosystem grown in elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide  The interaction between elevated carbon dioxide and nitrogen nutrition: the physiological and molecular background  Physiological and growth response of  Eriophorum vaginatum  to field elevated CO 2  and temperature in the Alaskan tussock tundra  Long-term effects of elevated CO 2  and nutrients on photosynthesis and Rubisco in loblolly pine seedlings  Atmospheric CO 2  enrichment increases growth and photosynthesis of  Pinus taeda : a 4 year experiment in the field  Leaf respiration at different canopy positions in sweetgum  (Liquidambar styraciflua ) grown in ambient and elevated concentrations of carbon dioxide in the field  Comprehensive ecosystem model-data synthesis using multiple data sets at two temperate forest free-air CO 2  enrichment experiments: model performance at ambient CO 2  concentration  Evergreen trees do not maximize instantaneous photosynthesis  Ecohydrologic impact of reduced stomatal conductance in forests exposed to elevated CO 2   Elevated CO 2  enhances premature leaf senescence during extreme climatic events in a temperate forest  Growth and photosynthetic response of nine tropical species with long-term exposure to elevated carbon dioxide   Associate Editor:  Jeffrey S. Dukes  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Atmospheric carbon dioxide levels have increased by∼25% over the last 50 years. While more carbon dioxide can initially stimulate plant photosynthesis, we found that long-term (12 years) exposure of sweetgum trees to elevated carbon dioxide resulted in no stimulation of photosynthesis. The loss of initial increases in photosynthesis was due to low leaf nitrogen levels, which suggests other limiting resources may moderate future impacts of elevated carbon dioxide on photosynthesis.  Elevated atmospheric CO 2  (eCO 2 ) often increases photosynthetic CO 2  assimilation ( A ) in field studies of temperate tree species. However, there is evidence that  A  may decline through time due to biochemical and morphological acclimation, and environmental constraints. Indeed, at the free-air CO 2  enrichment (FACE) study in Oak Ridge, Tennessee,  A  was increased in 12-year-old sweetgum trees following 2 years of ∼40 % enhancement of CO 2 .  A  was re-assessed a decade later to determine if the initial enhancement of photosynthesis by eCO 2  was sustained through time. Measurements were conducted at prevailing CO 2  and temperature on detached, re-hydrated branches using a portable gas exchange system. Photosynthetic CO 2  response curves ( A  versus the CO 2  concentration in the intercellular air space ( C  i ); or  A – C  i  curves) were contrasted with earlier measurements using leaf photosynthesis model equations. Relationships between light-saturated photosynthesis ( A  sat ), maximum electron transport rate ( J  max ), maximum Rubisco activity ( V  cmax ), chlorophyll content and foliar nitrogen (N) were assessed. In 1999,  A  sat  for eCO 2  treatments was 15.4 ± 0.8 μmol m −2  s −1 , 22 % higher than aCO 2  treatments ( P  &lt; 0.01). By 2009,  A  sat  declined to &lt;50 % of 1999 values, and there was no longer a significant effect of eCO 2  ( A  sat  = 6.9 or 5.7 ± 0.7 μmol m −2  s −1  for eCO 2  or aCO 2 , respectively). In 1999, there was no treatment effect on area-based foliar N; however, by 2008, N content in eCO 2  foliage was 17 % less than that in aCO 2  foliage. Photosynthetic N-use efficiency ( A  sat  : N) was greater in eCO 2  in 1999 resulting in greater  A  sat  despite similar N content, but the enhanced efficiency in eCO 2  trees was lost as foliar N declined to sub-optimal levels. There was no treatment difference in the declining linear relationships between  J  max  or  V  cmax  with declining N, or in the ratio of  J  max  :  V  cmax  through time. Results suggest that the initial enhancement of photosynthesis to elevated CO 2  will not be sustained through time if N becomes limited.  In 2013, annual atmospheric CO 2  concentration exceeded 396 ppm at Mauna Loa, 2.6 ppm greater than in 2012 and 25 % greater than the initial measurements in 1959 ( Keeling  et al.  2014 ). Global atmospheric model simulations estimate that this trajectory will continue ( IPCC 2013 ), and thus terrestrial plant communities will remain exposed to increasing CO 2  for the foreseeable future. Atmospheric CO 2  is a potent climate-forcing agent contributing to increased atmospheric temperatures, and ecosystem balance between plant CO 2  uptake through photosynthesis and release through respiratory activity remains a key uncertainty in mechanistic Earth system models that project ecosystem feedbacks to the atmosphere. To address ecosystem response to elevated CO 2  (eCO 2 ), various plant species have been exposed to air enriched with CO 2  in short-term open- or closed-topped field chambers. Results suggested substantial eCO 2  stimulation of photosynthesis ( Luxmoore  et al.  1993 ;  Gunderson and Wullschleger 1994 ;  Medlyn  et al.  1999 ;  Norby  et al.  1999 ) across various woody species (e.g. in oak, yellow poplar ( Gunderson  et al.  1993 ), pine ( Tissue  et al.  1997 ), eucalypts ( Ghannoum  et al.  2010 ) and tropical seedlings ( Ziska  et al.  1991 )). In other studies, eCO 2  induced significant down-regulation and loss of photosynthetic capacity (e.g. in Arctic tundra grasses and shrubs ( Tissue and Oechel 1987 ;  Oechel  et al.  1994 ), beech ( Epron  et al.  1996 ) and spruce ( Marek  et al.  1995 )), indicating that interaction with soil resources, longer term feedbacks and progressive plant acclimation remained a key uncertainty ( Curtis and Wang 1998 ). New, larger experiments using free-air CO 2  enrichment (FACE) technology ( Norby  et al.  2001 ) have allowed field crops, grasses and, in particular, woody forest vegetation to be exposed to eCO 2  over many years. Such studies allow distinction of long-term responses from transient responses due to leaf plasticity, stand development or inter-annual environmental variability.  Similar to the response of plants in chambers, an initial increase in net photosynthesis ( A ) and net primary productivity is common across woody plant species exposed to FACE eCO 2  treatments ( Norby  et al.  2005 ;  Ainsworth and Rogers 2007 ), including in  Liquidambar styraciflua  ( Sholtis  et al.  2004 ),  Pinus taeda  ( Crous and Ellsworth 2004 ),  Populus × euramericana ,  Populus alba ,  P. nigra  ( Bernacchi  et al.  2003 ;  Liberloo  et al.  2007 ),  P. tremuloides  ( Noormets  et al.  2010 ),  Fagus sylvatica ,  Quercus petraea ,  Carpinus betulus ,  Acer campestre  and  Tilia platyphyllos  ( Bader  et al.  2010 ). However, longer term eCO 2  field results are mixed, with some experiments reporting feedbacks such as acclimation and photosynthetic down-regulation through time ( Rey and Jarvis 1998 ;  Medlyn  et al.  1999 ;  Kubiske  et al.  2002 ;  Bernacchi  et al.  2003 ;  Crous  et al.  2008 ) and others not ( Bader  et al.  2010 ;  Darbah  et al.  2010 ).  Leaves typically adjust their Rubisco activity or content to the prevailing CO 2  concentration, i.e. down-regulation by elevated CO 2  ( Tissue  et al.  1993 ;  Drake  et al.  1997 ;  Stitt and Krapp 1999 ;  Rogers and Ellsworth 2002 ). Since eCO 2  increases the efficiency of Rubisco,  A  can be maintained or enhanced despite reductions in enzyme content, activity or maximum photosynthetic capacity. This implies greater photosynthetic N-use efficiency (PNUE) as displayed across C3 woody plant species exposed to elevated CO 2  ( Peterson  et al.  1999 ;  Calfapietra  et al.  2007 ).  Sweetgum ( L. styraciflua ) is a common temperate North American tree species, and is the dominant canopy species at the ORNL-FACE site in TN, USA, and the primary mid-canopy species at the Duke-FACE site in NC, USA. Prior results from these sites indicate a strong and consistent enhancement of light-saturated photosynthesis ( A  sat ) by elevated CO 2 ; the ∼40 % increase in atmospheric CO 2  resulted in 45 % enhancement of  A  sat  at the ORNL-FACE site after 3 years of treatments ( Gunderson  et al.  2002 ;  Sholtis  et al.  2004 ) and consistently &gt;50 % enhancement of  A  sat  at the Duke-FACE site through 6 years of treatments ( Herrick and Thomas 1999 ,  2003 ;  Springer  et al.  2005 ). After 3 years of treatment at ORNL-FACE there was no change in maximum photosynthetic capacity ( A  max ), maximum electron transport rate ( J  max ) or maximum carboxylation rate ( V  cmax ) when foliage from both treatments was measured at the same CO 2  concentrations ( Sholtis  et al.  2004 ). Elevated CO 2  did reduce foliar N content and increase soluble carbohydrates and leaf mass per area (LMA,  Herrick and Thomas 2003 ;  Sholtis  et al.  2004 )—results consistent across time for sweetgum in both FACE studies. After 6 years of eCO 2  treatment at ORNL-FACE, there was still no significant difference in  A  sat  when both treatments were measured at 400 ppm ( Monson  et al.  2007 ), indicating little eCO 2  down-regulation of photosynthesis.  After 12 years of eCO 2  treatment at the ORNL-FACE research study, we re-assessed photosynthetic capacity of the dominant sweetgum trees to determine if the early enhancement of photosynthesis during the years 1–3 ( Gunderson  et al.  2002 ;  Sholtis  et al.  2004 ) was sustained after an additional 9–10 years of treatment.  Over the 12-year study, the canopy spread upward and there was expansion of the stand diameter distribution as dominant individual trees maintained growth, while suppressed individuals stagnated and began to die. In addition, soil N availability decreased across the site, with the greatest rates of decline in the eCO 2  plots ( Garten  et al.  2011 ). Decreased site nutrient availability was reflected by persistent inter-annual reductions in foliar N content and net primary production (NPP) ( Norby  et al.  2010 ), and a shift in carbon (C) allocation belowground to roots ( Norby  et al.  2004 ). The reductions in NPP through time were greatest for eCO 2  plots despite treatment-specific increases or decreases in canopy leaf area in response to inter-annual variability such as drought ( Warren  et al.  2011 b  ), or the substantial reduction in eCO 2  site water use ( Warren  et al.  2011 a  ,   b  ). In addition to increased soil moisture availability in eCO 2  plots, the increase in root production should lead to an enhanced capacity for soil nutrient extraction. Yet canopy N content continued to decline through time at a greater rate for eCO 2  plots than for aCO 2  plots, which correlated with a greater reduction in NPP for eCO 2  plots ( Norby  et al.  2010 ).  The main goal of this project was to determine if the initial enhancement of photosynthesis by eCO 2  was sustained through time, and if responses were linked to the progressive decline in site resource availability ( Garten  et al.  2011 ), foliar N content ( Norby  et al.  2010 ) and shift in internal plant C allocation ( Norby  et al.  2004 ). In 2008–09, we re-measured gas exchange in sweetgum leaves and compared the results with data from previous gas exchange campaigns conducted across seasons from 1998 to 2000 ( Gunderson  et al.  2002 ;  Sholtis  et al.  2004 ); specifically the mid-summer 1999 dataset was used as it was the most comprehensive dataset and overlapped with the same period sampled in 2008–09 (from late July to early August). We hypothesized that (i) declining N availability would be reflected in reduced photosynthetic capacity through time and (ii) when photosynthesis is N-limited, eCO 2  leaves maintain greater RuBP-regeneration capacity, at lower Rubisco carboxylation rates, compared with aCO 2  leaves (e.g. the slope of  J  max  :  V  cmax  is steeper in aCO 2  leaves). Finally, we evaluated treatment effects on coupling between stomatal conductance and C-assimilation.  The study site was a 20-year-old sweetgum ( L. styraciflua  L.) plantation forest in Oak Ridge National Environmental Research Park in eastern TN, USA (35°54′N; 84°20′W). The soil was an Aquic Hapludult with a silty clay-loam texture. A free-air CO 2  enrichment system ( Hendrey  et al.  1999 ) was installed at the site in four 25-m-diameter plots in 1996. The FACE system regulated the release of CO 2  from vertical PVC pipes located in a ring around each plot based on wind speed, wind direction and in-situ measurements of current CO 2  concentration within the canopy. From 1998 to 2009, CO 2  was released into two FACE rings during each growing season to a target [CO 2 ] of 560 ppm. Two FACE rings received ambient [CO 2 ] and one additional ring, without FACE infrastructure, was established to serve as a third control plot. Actual CO 2  enrichment varied through time as ambient concentrations rose incrementally and through modifications in the release regime, which resulted in a mean 40 % increase over ambient CO 2 . In 2008, tree height ranged from 10 to 24 m (mean = 18.2 ± 3.4 m (±1 SD)), median tree diameter was 14.6 ± 4.1 cm (±1 SD) and peak leaf area index (mid-July) was 4.1 ± 0.2. Mean growing season (April–October) temperature was 19.6 °C in 2008 and 19.1 °C in 2009, and growing season precipitation was 440 mm in 2008 and 511 mm in 2009 ( Riggs  et al.  2010 ). The site, experimental design and FACE apparatus have been previously described ( Norby  et al.  2001 ;  Warren  et al.  2011 b  ) and results including micrometeorological data have been archived for public use:  http://cdiac.ornl.gov/ftp/FACE/ornldata .  For each measurement campaign (2008–09), branches were collected early in the morning from mid-canopy (2009) and fully exposed upper canopy (2008, 2009) dominant or co-dominant trees within each treatment plot. Canopy access was achieved via the FACE infrastructure towers, which provided access to trees within ∼8 m from the towers. Trees were selected primarily from within the treatment plots (i.e. &gt;2.5 m from the ring edge); however, in ambient plots, several buffer trees were also sampled. On measurement days, 1–2 m long branches were cut from the mid- and upper canopy of selected trees with a pole pruner and quickly placed into plastic bags with wet paper towels to minimize desiccation. Branches were re-cut under water to remove potential embolism induced during removal from the trees. Most  L. styraciflua  vessel length is &lt;0.3 m, therefore &gt;0.5 m of the branch was removed. Prior measurements of gas exchange on severed or attached branches at the site found no differences in measurements over a 2-h period ( Tissue  et al.  2002 ;  Monson  et al.  2007 ). Gas exchange was measured using four portable photosynthesis systems (LI-6400XT, LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA) during late July 2008 and early August 2009. Measurements were conducted outside under ambient conditions on one or two leaves per branch (total samples  n  = 16–23 (2008);  n  = 29–31 (2009)). Conditions in the gas exchange cuvette were set to approximate ambient outside temperature: relative humidity was ∼50–80 %, photosynthetically active radiation was 1800 µmol m −2  s −1  and CO 2  concentration was initially set at 400 ppm prior to the  A  –C  i  curve measurements (see below). Foliage was retained for the analysis of N, chlorophyll and LMA. Similar raw datasets were available from previous work performed at the site in late July–August 1999 ( Gunderson  et al.  2002 ;  Sholtis  et al.  2004 ). At that time, photosynthesis was measured in situ using vertical man lifts. Upper canopy photosynthetic and biochemical datasets were combined across years (1999, 2008, 2009) to investigate shifts in response through time.  In addition to measurement of the light-saturated photosynthetic rate ( A  sat ) at the CO 2  concentration in which the trees were growing, response curves of assimilation versus the CO 2  concentration within the intercellular spaces of the leaf ( C  i ), or  A–C  i  curves, were measured in all years. These response curves were used to estimate maximum electron transport rate,  J  max , and maximum Rubisco activity,  V  cmax , using a consistent set of leaf photosynthesis model equations ( Medlyn  et al.  2002 ). In 2008 and 2009, curves were conducted through an initially declining, then increasing, reference CO 2  regime (400, 300, 200, 100, 50, 400, 550, 700, 900, 1200, 1600 ppm). This contrasts slightly with curves conducted in 1999 using a declining CO 2  regime (1500, 1200, 960, 760, 560, 360, 250, 175, 100, 50, 0 ppm). To contrast gas exchange responses at growth CO 2 , results were assessed at 400 or 550 ppm for aCO 2  or eCO 2 , respectively. Since those CO 2  concentrations were not part of the 1999 campaigns, values at 400 or 550 ppm were interpolated from the linear portion of each response curve ( R  2  &gt; 0.99) for comparison. Atmospheric CO 2  varied between 1998 and 2008 due to incremental ambient CO 2  increases and FACE performance and management; range (384–405 or 528–560 ppm CO 2 ) for aCO 2  or eCO 2 , respectively. Relationships between  J  max ,  V  cmax , stomatal conductance ( g  s ), foliar N, chlorophyll content and CO 2  treatments were assessed.  To assess foliar chlorophyll and N concentrations, and LMA, nine leaf discs (9 mm diameter) were collected from the same area of each leaf (avoiding midrib) used for gas exchange measurements (2008–09). For chlorophyll analysis, two leaf discs were immediately placed in scintillation vials containing 5 mL of  N , N -dimethylformamide (DMF) and extracted at 4 °C in the dark until analysis. Following extraction total chlorophyll, chlorophyll  a  and chlorophyll  b  were determined based on spectroscopy at 647 and 665 nm ( Inskeep and Bloom 1985 ), and results contrasted with previous chlorophyll analysis in 1999 using an ethanol extraction ( Sholtis  et al.  2004 ). The two extraction solvents have been shown to provide comparable estimates of total chlorophyll in 9 of 11 tree species studied ( Minocha  et al.  2009 ). However, paired comparisons at our lab with sweetgum found that while DMF was able to fully extract chlorophyll within 1 day, 95 % ethanol at room temperature took up to 7 days for full extraction, and even then yielded only 80 % of the total chlorophyll yielded by DMF. Chlorophyll was thus likely underestimated in the earlier studies, and results are discussed in this context. Foliar N concentration was assessed for oven-dry (70 °C) discs using an elemental analyser (Costech Analytical Technologies, Inc., Valencia, CA, USA). In 1999, N content was measured on whole leaves, but not leaf discs, as used in 2008–09. Thus, comparison of N content across years required an LMA adjustment from whole leaf to leaf disc (LMA disk  = 0.9635(LMA total ) + 0.7013 (mg cm −2 );  n  = 28;  R  2  = 0.66; based on 2008 foliage). All N content is provided on a disc basis.  Regression slopes and treatment differences in photosynthesis, chlorophyll content,  V  cmax  and  J  max  were analysed using  t -tests and analysis of variance techniques. There were no significant plot (ring) effects on chlorophyll, N,  J  max  or  V  cmax  measured in 1999 or later years (0.1 &lt;  P  &lt; 0.9). As such, individual leaves were considered as the (pseudo-replicated) experimental unit (df = 37–60 per treatment per year) as opposed to use of treatment rings (df = 1–2). This is common for analyses of these large, expensive studies where true replication is limited, and results should be considered in this context; i.e. there is a greater chance to detect  spurious  treatment effects (Type I errors) ( Hurlbert 1984 ). Data manipulation and statistical procedures were completed using SAS statistical software (ver. 9.1.3, SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) and SigmaPlot (ver. 11.1, Systat Software, Inc., San Jose, CA). Relative differences between treatments and significance levels ( P  values) are presented;  P  &lt; 0.05 indicates statistical significance.  (A) Light-saturated photosynthesis ( A  sat ) at growth CO 2  (400 or 550 ppm for ambient (aCO 2 ) and elevated (eCO 2 ) CO 2  treatments, respectively) for mature upper canopy sweetgum foliage in mid-summer 1999, 2008 and 2009 as derived from  A–C  i  curves. (B)  A  sat  for aCO 2  and eCO 2  foliage at 400 and 550 ppm CO 2 . (C) Foliar N content expressed on a mass (%) or (D) leaf area (mg cm −2 ) basis through time.  Tracking the temporal pattern of  A  sat , foliar N concentration declined by ∼50 % from 1999 to 2009 across both treatments, with values as low as 6.9 or 8.5 mg g −1  for eCO 2  or aCO 2 , respectively, which was not much higher than the seasonal senescent foliar litter (5.8 mg g −1 ). Mass-based foliar N content in eCO 2  leaves was significantly lower than for aCO 2  in 2008 and 2009 ( P  &lt; 0.001), but not in 1999 ( P  = 0.22) (Fig.  1 C). Elevated CO 2  area-based N content was significantly lower than for aCO 2  in 2008 ( P  &lt; 0.05), but not in 2009 ( P  = 0.08) or in 1999 ( P  = 0.47) (Fig.  1 D).  (A) Total foliar chlorophyll (chlorophyll  a  +  b ) for ambient (aCO 2 —solid line) and elevated (eCO 2 —dashed line) treatments in mid-summer 1999, 2008 and 2009 in relation to foliar N content, expressed on a leaf-area basis. Regressions were significant for  N  &lt; 0.2 mg cm −2  ( R  2  = 0.26 or 0.54;  P  &lt; 0.0001), and there was a significant treatment effect on slope ( P  &lt; 0.05;  F  = 4.09; df = 107), but little trend was apparent in 1999 when  N  &gt; 0.2 ( R  2  = 0.02 or 0.08;  P  &gt; 0.05). (B) Light-saturated photosynthesis at growth CO 2  (400 or 550 ppm) in mid-summer across years (1999, 2008, 2009) in relation to foliar N content, expressed on an area basis.  Nitrogen content also had a significant impact on  A  sat , particularly at lower values of N. Values of  A  sat  plateaued as N content increased (Fig.  2 B). The linear regression slope between  A  sat  and N for 1999–2009 was slightly steeper for eCO 2  than for aCO 2  ( P  = 0.055) slopes and coincided at 0.057 mg cm −2 , which is approximately the N content of senescent tissue (regression not shown).  (A) Maximum electron transport rate ( J  max ) and (B) carboxylation rate ( V  cmax ) at 25 °C for ambient (aCO 2 ) and elevated (eCO 2 ) CO 2  treatments by year or (C) across all years in relation to foliar N content on an area basis (as leaf discs). Linear regressions by treatment were generally significant in 2008 and 2009 ( R  2  = 0.14–0.80;  P  = 0.07–0.003) when  N  &lt; 0.2 mg cm −2 , but not significant in 1999 ( R  2  = 0–0.08;  P  = 0.98–0.1). There were no significant treatment effects on the relationships within or across years ( P  = 0.22–0.75). Regression equations are given for combined data across treatments.  Relationships between maximum carboxylation rate ( V  cmax ) and electron transport rate ( J  max ) standardized to 25 °C for ambient (aCO 2 —solid lines) and elevated (eCO 2 —dashed lines) CO 2  treatments through time. Regressions were significant for all treatments and years ( R  2  = 0.45–0.77), but there were no treatment effects on the relationships (in 2009, aCO 2  had a slightly steeper slope,  P  = 0.067).  Light-saturated photosynthesis ( A ) in relation to stomatal conductance ( g  s ) for mature upper canopy foliage exposed to elevated (eCO 2 ; dashed line) or ambient (aCO 2 ; solid line) CO 2  (400 or 550 ppm, respectively) in mid-summer 2008 and 2009. Dotted regression lines represent results of similar measurements conducted across seasons from 1998 to 2000 based on  Gunderson  et al.  (2002) .  Photosynthesis was down-regulated after long-term eCO 2  treatments at the ORNL-FACE research site due to a reduction in foliar N content, a symptom indicative of progressive N limitation as the stand developed ( Norby  et al.  2010 ). Net photosynthesis ( A ) and photosynthetic capacity of sweetgum trees declined through time as the stand matured; these responses were correlated with increased nutrient (N, Ca 2+ , Mg 2+ ) sequestration in long-term biomass or soil organic matter and reduced availability and uptake of N ( Finzi  et al.  2006 ;  Norby  et al.  2010 ;  Iversen  et al.  2011 ; K. Kim  et al. , unpubl. data). Consistent with our first hypothesis, we found a significant reduction in overall photosynthetic capacity across treatments as leaf N content declined. However, in contrast to our second hypothesis, the reduction in foliar N was so acute that the benefit of eCO 2  in generating enhanced photosynthetic efficiency was lost. As such, the initial CO 2  stimulation (∼45 % greater) of net photosynthesis observed after 3 years ( Gunderson  et al.  2002 ;  Sholtis  et al.  2004 ) was not sustained after 12 years.  There was no relationship between foliar N and  A  in 1999, suggesting that foliar N content of upper canopy leaves (2.0–2.1 %) was in excess of photosynthetic requirements during the early years of the experiment. Total canopy N content in aCO 2  plots declined from ∼1.8 % prior to the experiment in 1996 to 1.6 % by 2004 ( Norby  et al.  2010 ). Earlier work in younger 6-year-old sweetgum stands indicated that a leaf N threshold for maximum biomass production was ∼1.9 % ( Scott  et al.  2004 ). In March 2004, part of our sweetgum stand was fertilized (200 kg ha −1  urea), which boosted upper canopy leaf N concentrations from ∼1.65 % (control) to 2.04 % (fertilized) by late July, and substantially increased canopy leaf area and stem growth ( Iversen and Norby 2008 ). The sweetgum trees at the Duke-FACE site indicated no down-regulation of photosynthesis and no change in tissue N content of upper canopy leaves from 1997 to 2004 (N content &gt;1.5 %) ( Herrick and Thomas 1999 ;  Tissue  et al.  2002 ;  Springer  et al.  2005 ;  Ellsworth  et al.  2012 ). Together, these prior studies support our conclusion that upper canopy photosynthesis at ORNL-FACE was not N limited in 1999, but strongly limited by the end of the experiment when the foliar N content had dropped to 1.03 % (eCO 2 ) and 1.16 % (aCO 2 ), which was significantly lower for the eCO 2  treatment.  There was also no relationship between foliar N and chlorophyll in 1999, suggesting that the chlorophyll content was in excess of photosynthetic requirements during the early years of the experiment. However, the chlorophyll values reported for the site in 1999 appear to be too low, suggesting a poor extraction yield occurred with the ethanol solvent as described earlier in the Methods section: ‘Foliar biochemistry and leaf mass per area’. Chlorophyll values ranged from ∼0.020 to 0.043 mg cm −2  in 1999, similar to the values in 2008–09 (0.014–0.041 mg cm −2 ), despite much lower N content. Actual chlorophyll levels at the ORNL-FACE site in 1999 were thus likely significantly higher than indicated here. Indeed, chlorophyll extracted from similar aged sweetgum trees at the Duke-FACE site that were not N limited indicated late season values from 0.047 to 0.071 mg cm −2  ( Herrick and Thomas 2001 ).  The lack of relationship between foliar N content and chlorophyll,  J  max  or  V  cmax  in 1999 suggests that the photosynthetic apparatus in sweetgum was N saturated above ∼0.2 mg cm −2  and that N had accumulated in excess to meet other N requirements (e.g. growth and storage). A similar pattern of N saturation of  V  cmax  has been suggested for pine at the Duke-FACE site, with saturation of the carboxylation rate at tissue contents &gt;1.4 % N ( Palmroth  et al.  2013 ). Nitrogen is most often stored as free amino acids or proteins, especially Rubisco, or as inorganic N within the vacuole ( Proe and Millard 1994 ;  Warren and Adams 2004 ). It is likely that reductions in enzyme activation state in eCO 2  foliage can partially uncouple photosynthetic response from foliar N content, as N is shifted into non-active ‘storage’ components. For example, the activation state of Rubisco has been shown to decline linearly with increasing leaf N in apple ( Cheng and Fuchigami 2000 ). Given that  J  max  and  V  cmax  are often modelled based on N content of the leaf, not on the proportion of N actively used in photosynthesis this may lead to increased uncertainty in estimates of GPP at higher N contents.  While the initial foliar N content of the stand was adequate for photosynthesis, N became progressively more limiting, restricting light harvesting, rates of Rubisco and the electron transport chain. N content for several of the measured leaves in 2008–09 dropped to values as low as 0.075 mg cm −2 , which was not much higher than senescent foliage (0.057 mg cm −2 ). At lower foliar levels of N (0.075–0.2 mg cm −2 ), eCO 2  leaves utilized N more efficiently (greater PNUE) compared with aCO 2  leaves (Fig.  2 B). For leaves operating at greater PNUE, the theoretical photosynthetic N requirement is lower. In our study, this would entail a lower photosynthetic N threshold in eCO 2  leaves. Our results could not determine this threshold, as  J  max  and  V  cmax  became similarly N-restricted below ∼0.2 mg cm −2 , independent of CO 2  availability.  In mature leaves, the optimum N distribution between RuBP carboxylation/regeneration and electron transport may shift as a result of environmental changes (e.g. CO 2  concentration, nutrient availability or thermal acclimation) such that the processes are co-limiting (e.g.  Makino  et al.  1994 ;  Medlyn 1996 ;  Hikosaka 1997 ). Theory predicts that the  J  max  :  V  cmax  ratio should increase under eCO 2  ( Medlyn 1996 ), and simulations with pine seedlings suggest that this optimization may vary seasonally ( Lewis  et al.  1996 ). We found no evidence of a treatment-dependent shift through time (Fig.  4 ). Similar work at the Duke-FACE site with  P. taeda  also found that there was no change in the slope of  J  max  :  V  cmax  due to eCO 2  treatments ( Crous  et al.  2008 ). Other observations have found that  J  max  :  V  cmax  can increase slightly (∼5 %) with eCO 2  ( Medlyn  et al.  1999 ;  Ainsworth and Long 2007 ), although this change is generally smaller than predicted by theory ( Medlyn 1996 ).  After long-term eCO 2  treatment at the Duke-FACE site, there was a decline in the slope of  J  max –N and  V  cmax –N in pine, indicating eCO 2  down-regulation of overall photosynthetic capacity ( Crous  et al.  2008 ). In contrast, at the ORNL-FACE site, there was no treatment effect on the relationships between  J  max –N and  V  cmax –N in sweetgum. Rather, the declining slope of  J  max  :  V  cmax  through time for all treatments suggests a gradual reallocation of N as plants acclimated to reductions in soil N availability.  The decline in photosynthetic capacity and resultant reduction in eCO 2  enhancement of NPP ( Norby  et al.  2010 ), coupled with the demonstrated reduction in N availability for eCO 2  plots ( Garten  et al.  2011 ), is consistent with the progressive N limitation hypothesis ( Comins and McMurtrie 1993 ;  Luo  et al.  2004 ). New root production was stimulated in eCO 2  plots ( Norby  et al.  2004 ) likely as a result of increased internal plant nutrient demand and chemical signalling, including the buildup and translocation of newly fixed sugars. Enhanced root production and exploration at deeper soil depths increased N availability and uptake for eCO 2  trees ( Finzi  et al.  2007 ;  Iversen  et al.  2011 ), but N uptake rates were unable to meet demand and resulted in progressive reductions in photosynthesis. Limitation by other elements could also dampen photosynthetic activity, e.g. Mg, which is the central element in chlorophyll and a key cofactor for Rubisco activation. However, base cation uptake (including Mg and Ca) increased through time in eCO 2  trees based on wood composition (K. Kim  et al. , unpubl. data), likely as a consequence of the enhanced root exploration. Foliar content of other essential mineral nutrients such as P and K did not decline through time in litter collected from 1998 to 2002, nor in wood tissue collected in 2009.  The measurement of gas exchange under fully rehydrated conditions was useful for resolving maximum rates of photosynthesis. Under these hydrated conditions, stomatal conductance remained lower for eCO 2  foliage than for aCO 2  foliage; eCO 2  : aCO 2   g  s  ranged from 0.75 to 0.81. Similarly, under dry field conditions, whole canopy conductance ( g  c ) based on sap flow remained lower for eCO 2  foliage; eCO 2  : aCO 2   g  c  was ∼0.7 and declined to ∼0.4 as stomatal aperture declined during extreme drought ( Warren  et al.  2011 b  ). The relationship between  A  and  g  s  did not change much through time for aCO 2  foliage, but was significantly reduced for eCO 2  foliage (Fig.  5 ). This suggests that the eCO 2  stimulation of photosynthetic WUE declined through time with increasing N limitation. Even so, WUE remained greater for eCO 2  sweetgum trees, and the relationship between stomatal conductance and assimilation was in agreement with predictions of the optimal stomatal model ( Medlyn  et al.  2011 ), independent of leaf N content ( De Kauwe  et al.  2013 ). At the Duke-FACE site, partitioning N either to ‘photosynthetically active’ or ‘storage components’ based on the  N – V  cmax  threshold allowed for linkage of eCO 2 -stimulated WUE to marginal N-use efficiency within the context of optimality theory ( Palmroth  et al.  2013 ). Results from these studies allow predictive capacity of ecosystem level responses to changes in site resources such as CO 2 , water and nutrients.  While shorter-term environmental (e.g. solar radiation, T, CO 2  concentration) regulation of photosynthesis has been studied in detail, knowledge of longer-term shifts in the photosynthetic apparatus in response to eCO 2  has been generally limited to observations at the FACE studies and a few long-term open-top chamber studies (e.g.  Erickson  et al.  2013 ). Long-term dynamics of soil water or nutrient availability ( Finzi  et al.  2006 ;  Palmroth  et al.  2013 ) and growth sink demands ( Paul and Pellny 2003 ;  Fatichi  et al.  2013 ) provide additional regulation of photosynthetic feedback mechanisms and capacity of C uptake in some ecosystems. These processes are not always well represented in global models that depend on scaling mechanistic photosynthetic responses to the land surface ( Smith and Dukes 2013 ). However, it is encouraging that some optimization models do successfully predict biochemical (e.g. reduced foliar N) and mechanistic (e.g. reduced stomatal conductance) process response to eCO 2  and shifts in resource availability ( Dewar  et al.  2009 ). Data from the FACE studies, including this one, are being used in a multi-model comparison to assess land surface model structure and variation in predictive capacity, which will result in future model improvement (e.g.  De Kauwe  et al.  2013 ;  Walker  et al.  2014 ).  Photosynthesis is the predominant mechanism that removes CO 2  from the atmosphere. Therefore, accurate projections of CO 2  feedbacks to climate forcing rely on the correct mechanistic representation of plant photosynthetic C assimilation capacity. At the ORNL-FACE site, the initial stimulation of carbon assimilation by sweetgum trees exposed to eCO 2  was lost over the 12-year study. The loss of stimulation was due to the declining foliar N content, which has been related to lower soil N availability and uptake. Sweetgum foliar N content below a threshold value (∼0.2 mg N cm −2  leaf area) restricted carbon assimilation due to photosynthetic biochemical limitations. This study indicates that atmospheric enrichment of CO 2  may result in an initial ‘fertilization’ effect, directly increasing photosynthesis and productivity, but this may later be offset by the declining soil N availability, which could completely eliminate the initial positive effects of eCO 2 . Overall, we suggest caution in extrapolating shorter-term eCO 2  responses to longer-term ecosystem processes, which are confounded by other controlling factors such as soil nutrient availability, water availability or air temperature that can change through time.  This article is based upon work supported by the  US Department of Energy, Office of Science, Office of Biological and Environmental Research , under contract  DE-AC05-00OR22725 .  J.M.W. designed and conducted the experiment. A.M.J. performed laboratory work. B.E.M. analysed the data. All authors contributed to the writing and editing of the manuscript.  None declared.  The authors appreciate fieldwork and facility maintenance from Joanne Childs (arbornaut), Cassandra Bruno, Jeff Riggs and Danny Sluss, and data from Colleen Iversen and Carla Gunderson. This manuscript has been authored by UT-Battelle, LLC under Contract No. DE-AC05-00OR22725 with the US Department of Energy. The United States Government retains and the publisher, by accepting the article for publication, acknowledges that the United States Government retains a non-exclusive, paid-up, irrevocable, world-wide license to publish or reproduce the published form of this manuscript, or allow others to do so, for United States Government purposes. The Department of Energy will provide public access to these results of federally sponsored research in accordance with the DOE Public Access Plan (http://energy.gov/downloads/doe-public-access-plan). 