How does pea architecture influence light sharing in virtual wheat–pea mixtures? A simulation study based on pea genotypes with contrasting architecturesModelling the effect of wheat canopy architecture as affected by sowing density on <italic>Septoria tritici</italic> epidemics using a coupled epidemic-virtual plant modelLight signals perceived by crop and weed plantsHow good is the turbid medium-based approach for accounting for light partitioning in contrasted grass-legume intercropping systems?Modelling nitrogen distribution in virtual plants, as exemplified by wheat culm during grain fillingGenetic studies of selection criteria for productive and stable peasThe nested radiosity model for the distribution of light within plant canopiesA canopy architectural model to study the competitive ability of chickpea with sowthistleApical dominanceInterspecific competition for soil N and its interaction with N<sub>2</sub> fixation, leaf expansion and crop growth in pea–barley intercropsPlasticity of winter wheat modulated by sowing date, plant population density and nitrogen fertilisation: dimensions and size of leaf blades, sheaths and internodes in relation to their position on a stemFunctional relationships to estimate morphogenetically active radiation (MAR) from PAR and solar broadband irradiance measurements: the case of a sorghum cropAn architectural model of spring wheat: evaluation of the effects of population density and shading on model parameterization and performanceADEL-wheat: a 3D architectural model of wheat developmentRepresenting and encoding plant architecture: a reviewPotential production processesGenetics and genetic modifications of plant architecture in grain legumes: a reviewGrain yield, symbiotic N<sub>2</sub> fixation and interspecific competition for inorganic N in pea-barley intercropsDeveloppement des ramificationsDeveloppement vegetatifExpansion of pea leaves subjected to short water deficit: cell number and cell size are sensitive to stress at different periods of leaf developmentMaximum crop productivity: an estimatePartitioning the apex: the size of the apical meristem and the primordiaMixing plant species in cropping systems: concepts, tools and models. A reviewÜber den Lichtfaktor in den Pflanzengesellschaften und seine Bedeutung für die StoffproduktionIllumination from a non-uniform skyPremiers éléments d'analyse du développement architectural des herbacées cultivéesThe effect of various dynamics of N availability on winter pea-wheat intercrops: Crop growth, N partitioning and symbiotic N<sub>2</sub> fixationPetiole length and biomass investment in support modify light-interception efficiency in dense poplar plantationsConstraints on light interception efficiency due to shoot architecture in broad-leaved <italic>Nothofagus</italic> speciesA theoretical analysis of the frequency of gaps in plant standsCereal-legume intercropping systemsCrown architecture in sun and shade environments: assessing function and trade-offs with a three-dimensional simulation modelOpenAlea: a visual programming and component-based software platform for plant modellingR: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria.A test of a model for light interception by mixturesFoliage area orientation in standsRole of phytometric investigations in the studies of plant stand architecture and radiation regimeHow plant architecture affects light absorption and photosynthesis in tomato: towards an ideotype for plant architecture using a functional-structural plant modelA versatile growth model with statistically stable parametersModelling radiative transfer in heterogeneous canopies and intercropping systemsThe geometrical structure of plant canopy: characterization and direct measurement methodsA theoretical analysis of radiation interception in a two-species plant canopyEstimation of light capture and partitioning in intercropping systemsComparison of models for daily light partitioning in multispecies canopiesBasal branching in field pea cultivars and yield-density relationshipsLeaf primordium initiation and expanded leaf production are co-ordinated through similar response to air temperature in pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.)Spectral modification of light within plant canopies – how to quantify its effects on the architecture of the plant standComparison of architecture among different cultivars of hybrid rice using a spatial light model based on 3-D digitisingThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly citedLight sharing within virtual wheat-pea mixtures was influenced by the variability of pea’s architectural parameters affecting LAI and height. Light capture was affected by the development of leaflets, number of branches and phytomers and internode length.Light interception is a key factor driving the functioning of wheat–pea intercrops. The sharing of light is related to the canopy structure, which results from the architectural parameters of the mixed species. In the present study, we characterized six contrasting pea genotypes and identified architectural parameters whose range of variability leads to various levels of light sharing within virtual wheat–pea mixtures.Virtual plants were derived from magnetic digitizations performed during the growing cycle in a greenhouse experiment. Plant mock-ups were used as inputs of a radiative transfer model in order to estimate light interception in virtual wheat–pea mixtures. The turbid medium approach, extended to well-mixed canopies, was used as a framework for assessing the effects of leaf area index (LAI) and mean leaf inclination on light sharing.Three groups of pea genotypes were distinguished: (i) early and leafy cultivars, (ii) late semi-leafless cultivars and (iii) low-development semi-leafless cultivars. Within open canopies, light sharing was well described by the turbid medium approach and was therefore determined by the architectural parameters that composed LAI and foliage inclination. When canopy closure started, the turbid medium approach was unable to properly infer light partitioning because of the vertical structure of the canopy. This was related to the architectural parameters that determine the height of pea genotypes. Light capture was therefore affected by the development of leaflets, number of branches and phytomers, as well as internode length.This study provides information on pea architecture and identifies parameters whose variability can be used to drive light sharing within wheat–pea mixtures. These results could be used to build up the architecture of pea ideotypes adapted to multi-specific stands towards light competition.Cereal–legume intercropping systems are assumed to provide high and stabilized yields in terms of quantity and quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C31">Ofori and Stern 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C17">Jensen 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C9">Corre-Hellou <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>), allow lower use of fertilizers and pesticides, and enhance biodiversity conservation (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C23">Malézieux <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Intercropping benefits result from a trade-off between complementarity (e.g. separate root and canopy areas) and competition processes (for light, water and nutrients) that occur between the component crops. Among the contested resources, solar radiation, and in particular photosynthetically active radiation (PAR), is an important factor driving plant functioning as it provides the energy required for photosynthesis and thus for plant growth. Light capture also drives biological nitrogen fixation by legume species and therefore the autonomy of the intercropping system towards nitrogen resources. Finally, light determines the potential for crop productivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C21">Loomis and Williams 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C15">Goudriaan 1982</xref>). Therefore, its sharing in multi-specific stands appeared to be a crucial issue for managing the balance between the component species as well as for determining the final yield of the mixture. It has been proposed that increasing the light interception efficiency (LIE) of intercropping systems could be achieved through: (i) maximizing total light interception by improving the spatial and temporal ground cover and (ii) adequately sharing light between component species by improving their spatial and temporal complementarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C42">Sinoquet and Caldwell 1995</xref>).Total radiation interception, as well as its sharing among intercropped species, is highly related to the physical structure of the canopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C36">Ross 1981<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C42">Sinoquet and Caldwell 1995</xref>), which emerges from the architecture of the individuals growing within the stand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C26">Moulia <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Individuals' architecture can be described as a collection of subunits called phytomers. After <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C14">Godin (2000)</xref>, such a description needs to include (i) an inventory of the plant components (decomposition information), (ii) the topological relationships between these components, and (iii) their geometry, given by the organ shape and spatial position (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C14">Godin 2000</xref>). Such a multiscale analysis of the canopy structure reveals the importance of plant architectural parameters as underpinning factors determining light interception and sharing within sole and mixed cropped systems.Contrasting architectural parameters could result from: (i) the genotypic variability of a given species, (ii) the environmental conditions to which plants are exposed during their growth, and (iii) the genotype and environment interactions characterizing the phenotypic plasticity. Architectural plasticity of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) has been described for various cultivars, sowing dates and row orientations, plant densities and nitrogen fertilization regimes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C12">Evers <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C1">Baccar <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C10">Dornbusch <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Plasticity of some architectural components of pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.) has also been studied. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C45">Turc and Lecoeur (1997)</xref> found that leaf primordium initiation and leaf production of several pea cultivars were coordinated and stable in a large range of environmental conditions. Lateral branching of pea appeared to be dependent not only on environmental conditions such as low temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C18">Jeudy and Munier-Jolain 2005</xref>) but also on the genotype and its interactions with plant density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C44">Spies <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Further, the genetic determination of some architectural parameters of pea is now well documented (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C16">Huyghe 1998</xref>). Nevertheless, to our knowledge, the effects of the genetic variability of these architectural parameters on the level of competition for light within cereal–legume intercropping systems have not been reported. Such information would be useful for building up the architecture of pea ideotypes adapted to multi-specific stands.Recently, virtual plant models have been used to study ideotype architectures in order to optimize light interception and photosynthesis in tomato (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C37">Sarlikioti <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) and rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C47">Zheng <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>), and manage light sharing in an integrated legume–weed system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C7">Cici <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Although virtual plant models are able to take into account the multiscale aspect of plant functioning (stand, plant and organ levels), they have not been used to analyse the relationships between species architecture and light sharing within cereal–legume intercropping systems. The present study therefore focused on wheat–pea mixtures and in particular pea architecture, which has been little described. The aim of the present work was to identify the parameters of pea architecture whose genotypic variability leads to various levels of light sharing within wheat–pea canopies. To this end, we combined the virtual plant approach with an explicit description of the above-ground architecture of six pea genotypes. This allowed us to assess the effects of contrasting pea architectures on light sharing within mixtures.<bold>Light sharing in a well-mixed mixture of two species (SP1 and SP2) as a function of their contribution to the total LAI.</bold> Theoretical isolines are shown for different ratios of the species extinction coefficients (<italic>K</italic>). <italic>K</italic><sub>SP1</sub>/<italic>K</italic><sub>SP2</sub> ranged from 0.1 to 10.<bold>Description of pea cultivars.</bold> Contribution of stipules, leaflets and stems to the maximum green area is also indicated for each pea cultivar.<sup>a</sup>Pea cultivars of hr type are not sensitive to photoperiod, whereas cultivar 886/01 shows high response to photoperiod (HR type).<bold>Horizontal views of some reconstructed pea cultivars.</bold> Left: the semi-leafless cultivar 886/01; right: the leafy cultivar US13, both at 1000 DD.Light interception estimates are based on a nested radiosity model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C6">Chelle and Andrieu 1998</xref>). Computations were performed considering only diffuse radiations according to the Uniform Overcast Sky radiation distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C25">Moon and Spencer 1942</xref>). Diffuse radiations were approximated by a set of light sources on a sky vault discretized in 20 solid angle sectors using the spherical coordinates, including 5 zenith angles (18°, 36°, 54°, 72°, 90°) and 4 azimuths. Light interception was computed for each direction and then integrated over the sky vault by summing up the 20 directional values.Light sharing was computed for virtual wheat–pea mixtures at four digitization dates: 300, 600, 1240 and 1560 DD. Wheat (<italic>T. aestivum</italic>) mock-ups were obtained from a dynamic but non-plastic 3D architectural model of wheat development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C13">Fournier <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). The data set was derived from an experiment of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C4">Bertheloot <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref>, where wheat plants (cultivar Caphorn) were grown in field conditions under low-nitrogen fertilization at a density of 250 plants m<sup>−2</sup>. In the present study, wheat mock-ups were generated at the same stages of development as pea and then merged with pea reconstructions in the Openalea platform (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C33">Pradal <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Inter-row spacing of virtual mixtures was 17 cm with a final density of 125 plants m<sup>−2</sup> for wheat and 45 plants m<sup>−2</sup> for pea, i.e. 50 % of each crop optimal density used in local agricultural practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C9">Corre-Hellou <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Species were mixed within each row.Data analyses were performed by using exploratory data analysis and variance analysis. Pea cultivars were compared by using the Tukey's honestly significant difference (HSD) test. The significance threshold was fixed at the 0.05 probability level for all statistical tests. Statistical analyses were performed with SAS 9.2 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) and R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C48">R Development Core Team 2011</xref>).The first derivatives of Schnute adjustments were used in order to estimate the rates of phytomer appearance of the pea cultivars.LAI, foliage inclination and plant height of wheat and pea mock-ups used to simulate light sharing in virtual mixtures.<bold>Light sharing within virtual wheat–pea mixtures at 300, 600, 1240 and 1560 DD.</bold> Relative contributions of the species to the LAI of the mixture and to PAR interception are shown in (A), (C), (E) and (G). Theoretical isolines, based on the ratio of extinction coefficients of the species, are represented by dotted lines. Deviations between the estimated values of light interception of pea and the theoretical isoline are given in (B), (D), (F) and (H) where the equation and coefficient of determination <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> of linear regressions are also shown. For each simulation date (300, 600, 1240 and 1887 DD), computations were performed on eight plants of each pea cultivar.After 1200 DD (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS038F3">3</xref>E and F), LAI of the pea genotypes (1.12–3.44 m<sup>2</sup> m<sup>−2</sup>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS038TB2">2</xref>) was higher than that of wheat (1.00–0.46 m<sup>2</sup> m<sup>−2</sup>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS038TB2">2</xref>). Pea therefore captured &gt;50 % of the radiation intercepted by the mixture. At 1240 DD (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS038F3">3</xref>E), three groups of pea genotypes are distinguishable: (i) the cultivars Lucy and James, which were close to the theoretical isoline, (ii) ‘AOPHA10’ and ‘886/01’ cultivars, vertically distributed around the isoline and (iii) the cultivars China and US13, exhibiting a strong efficiency for light capture. The two last groups, for which the contribution to total LAI exceeded 60 %, showed divergences between computed values of light sharing and the theoretical approach that assumes well-mixed canopies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS038F3">3</xref>F, slope of the linear regression = 0.97, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.42). Thus, at this late stage of development, the architectural parameters that determine the LAI and the foliage inclination of these cultivars do not only determine light sharing between the component species. Similar conclusions could be drawn for the simulations made at 1560 DD (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS038F3">3</xref>G and H). Indeed, the two late semi-leafless cultivars, AOPH10 and 886/01, constituted 81 and 88 % of the whole LAI and intercepted 80 and 75 % of incident light, respectively. These two cultivars were less efficient at capturing light in regard to their relative contribution to the LAI of the mixture. This could be related to a combination of architectural parameters that lead to intra-specific foliage clumping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C30">Nilson 1971</xref>) due to high values of LAI. Indeed at 1560 DD, cultivars AOPH10 and 886/01 exhibited an LAI of 2.03 and 3.44 m<sup>2</sup> m<sup>−2</sup>, respectively, whereas wheat LAI was 0.46 m<sup>2</sup> m<sup>−2</sup>.The above results show that when canopy closure and species interactions begin, the level of light sharing was not only determined by the species LAI and foliage inclination as can be estimated for well-mixed canopies. Light sharing within such mixtures is therefore also related to architectural parameters that lead to heterogeneous canopies such as contrasted vertical profiles of leaf area or height between component species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C42">Sinoquet and Caldwell 1995</xref>).Relationship between the species height ratio and the deviations between computed and theoretical (based on the ratio of extinction coefficients of the species) values of light interception.In the first step of this study, we assessed the impact of the pea genotypes on light sharing within virtual mixtures through basic descriptors, i.e. LAI, foliage inclination and plant height. The second step of this work then consisted in a characterization of the above-ground architecture of the pea genotypes in order to analyse the contribution of the architectural parameters to light interception.<bold>Number of branches and number of phytomers per branch of pea cultivars at each simulation date.</bold> B1, B2 and B3 point out the chronological emission of branches. Mean values are given ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 8 for each cultivar).Parameters (<italic>A</italic>×10<sup>−3</sup>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>y</italic><sub>max</sub>) of Schnute adjustments made on cultivars' kinetics of phytomer emission. Indicated values are the mean ± SD of eight individual adjustments made for each cultivar. Goodness of fit is also given by RMSE values. Cultivars with the same letter are not significantly different (Tukey's HSD test, <italic>α</italic> = 0.05). First derivative of the adjustments provided the maximum rate of phytomer emission.<bold>Phytomer appearance for the pea cultivars during the growing cycle.</bold> Values are indicated for main stems only. The fitting of Schnute's functions is shown by a solid line or by a dotted line when extrapolated (<italic>n</italic> = 8 for each cultivar).The contribution of stipules, leaflets and stems to the maximum green area reached by plants was also estimated for each cultivar (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLS038TB1">1</xref>). Leaves (stipules and leaflets) accounted for &gt;90 % of the green area whatever the cultivar. For leafy cultivars, this area was similarly composed of stipules and leaflets. The contribution of stems to the green area appeared to be constant whatever the genotype (8–11 %), except for the leafy cultivar US13 whose stems constitute 5 % of the cultivar green area.<bold>Vertical distribution of stipule (A) and internode (B) length.</bold> Indicated values are the final lengths reached by organs as a function of the normalized phytomer number of the main stem (<italic>n</italic> = 8 for each pea cultivar).Among the tested cultivars, the vertical distribution of internode length was nearly uniform (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLS038F6">6</xref>B), although maximum values tend to be reached on the upper part of the stem (between normalized phytomer numbers 0.5 and 0.8). Within this interval, the leafy cultivars displayed longer internodes than semi-leafless cultivars; this was particularly the case for ‘China’ whose internodes exceeded 75 mm in length. The cultivars AOPH10 and 886/01 developed the shortest internodes on average (37.0 and 35.0 mm, respectively). ‘Lucy’ and ‘James’ were intermediate cultivars with mean internode length reaching 41.5 and 40.0 mm, respectively. Internode lengths and their spatial distribution are also key parameters of pea architecture determining plant height and leaf area density, and consequently the ability to capture light.<bold>Dynamics of stipule (A) and leaflet (B) inclination during the growing cycle.</bold> Values are indicated for main stems only (<italic>n</italic> = 8 for each pea cultivar).Our results allowed us to distinguish three groups of development among the tested cultivars. The first group is composed of the leafy cultivars (China and US13) which exhibited a rapid vertical and leaf area growth. The second group is constituted by the late cultivars (AOPH10 and 886/10, late hr and HR-type, respectively) which also developed a large leaf area. The third group is composed of cultivars with low developmental rates, ‘Lucy’ and ‘James’, which displayed the smallest leaf area and height.These contrasting pea architectures were then virtually mixed with wheat mock-ups obtained from data where wheat was grown under low nitrogen supply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C4">Bertheloot <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). The level of available nitrogen is obviously a major factor impacting the species growth. However, increasing the nitrogen availability in a cereal–legume mixture enhances the dominance of the cereal species over the legume (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C9">Corre-Hellou <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLS038C27">Naudin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Cereal–legume mixtures are therefore usually grown under low-nitrogen conditions that are close to the data from which the mock-ups were derived. Within open canopies, our results showed that light sharing was mainly related to the architectural parameters that composed the LAI and leaf inclination. Thus, the earliness and the development of leaflets exhibited by the leafy cultivars as well as a large number of phytomers and branches (late semi-leafless cultivars) led to strong competitive abilities for light capture. When canopy closure and competition between component species started, light sharing within the virtual mixtures also appeared to be strongly dependent on the species height ratio. The vertical dominance of pea was due to (i) the rapid development of long internodes for leafy cultivars and (ii) the stack of numerous phytomers on stems for late semi-leafless cultivars. In addition, the dominance of pea genotypes was reinforced by the planophile property of their leaves compared with wheat. However, as very few differences were observed between leaf inclinations of cultivars, this architectural parameter does not appear to be a major factor explaining the contrasting levels of light sharing observed in the different wheat–pea mixtures.In the present study, the virtual plant approach was used as a means to provide a suitable framework for the assessment of the effects of the architectural parameters of pea on light sharing within wheat–pea mixture. Nevertheless, the present approach did not account for plant plasticity, i.e. above and below-ground feedbacks between the mixed species were not taken into account. Moreover, wheat and pea mock-ups were derived from data obtained in mono-specific conditions and pea plants were staked, although this can be representative of the field conditions as wheat plants generally support pea stems. However, these mock-ups were not aimed to be representative of the development of species grown in a field mixture. These virtual plant models were intended to generate a large range of physical structures reflecting contrasting canopies which can be found in multi-specific stands. Therefore, pea plants that exhibited contrasting architectures (stemming from the different cultivars and stages of development) were virtually mixed with a given wheat architecture in order to compare their efficiency for light interception in relation to their architectural features. The present study highlights levers of pea architecture that are determinant parameters driving light sharing. These parameters were mainly involved in the composition of the species LAI and height. Competitive pea ideotypes for light capture therefore exhibited (i) a large foliar area, through the presence of leaflets and/or the development of a larger number of branches and phytomers, and/or (ii) a vertical dominance due to the stack of numerous phytomers and the development of long internodes. To drive the interspecific competition, the developmental dynamics of these architectural parameters must also be taken into account in regard to the other components of the mixture. In addition, we identified contrasting architectural parameters among the tested genotypes, associated to variability in their earliness/lateness that would, in field conditions, lead to different levels of competition for light in the mixture. Further studies should be conducted on supplementary genotypes and growing conditions in order to reveal additional categories of architectural development and assess their effects on light sharing. At the present state-of-the-art, it is still complex to assess the optimal level of light sharing within intercropping systems. However, the present results could help to identify/design suitable cultivars/ideotypes for intercropping systems towards light sharing, in particular because of the genetic progress which has already identified several genes driving pea architecture.This research is supported by ‘<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">La Région Pays de la Loire</grant-sponsor>’, France through a Ph.D. fellowship to R.B. The research of D.C. and A.E.-G. is partially funded by ‘<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">La Région Poitou-Charentes</grant-sponsor>’, France.All the authors contributed to a similar extent overall.None declared.We thank Sylvain Pineau and Pierre Huynh for their great technical assistance and Gaëtan Louarn for his comments on the manuscript. We also thank INRA-Agri-obtentions – URD78 (Orsonville, France) which provided ‘US13’, ‘886/01’ and ‘AOPH10’ pea cultivars and INRA UMRLEG (Dijon, France) for ‘China’ cultivar.