Fine-scale genetic differentiation of a temperate herb: relevance of local environments and demographic changeRobust control of the seasonal expression of the <italic>Arabidopsis FLC</italic> gene in a fluctuating environmentDetecting population expansion and decline using microsatellitesAssignment of 30 microsatellite loci to the linkage map of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Local-scale patterns of genetic variability, outcrossing, and spatial structure in natural stands of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Cross-species microsatellite markers for elucidating population genetic structure in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and <italic>Arabis</italic> (Brassicaeae)Patterns of distribution in Japanese land mammalsDNA extraction by using DTAB-CTAB proceduresSTRUCTURE HARVESTER: a website and program for visualizing STRUCTURE output and implementing the Evanno methodHigh level of genetic differentiation for allelic richness among populations of the argan gree (<italic>Argania spinoda</italic> (L.) Skeels) endemic to MoroccoGenetic diversity and population structure assessed by SSR and SNP markers in a large germplasm collection of grapeDetecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation studyReconstructing origins of loss of self-incompatibility and selfing in north American <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic>: a population genetic contextPhylogeography of Japanese alpine plants: biogeographic importance of alpine region of Central Honshu in JapanSpatial genetic structure of <italic>Aquilegia</italic> taxa endemic to the island of SardiniaInference from iterative simulation using multiple sequencesDNA and RNA extraction for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Genetic divergence in nuclear genomes between populations of <italic>Fagus crenata</italic> along the Japan sea and Pacific sides of JapanPopulation genetic structure of <italic>Fagus japonica</italic> revealed by nuclear microsatellite markersThe genetic legacy of the quaternary ice agesEvolution of the realized climatic niche in the genus: <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Brassicaceae)Application of phylogenetic networks in evolutionary studiesMode of local differentiation in <italic>Arabis lyrata</italic> and <italic>A. gemmifera</italic> (Cruciferae) in JapanPhylogeography of <italic>Carpinus japonica</italic> and <italic>Carpinus tschonoskii</italic> (Betulaceae) growing in Japanese deciduous broad-leaved forests, based on chloroplast DNA variationComparative phylogeography of four component species of deciduous broad-leaved forests in Japan based on chloroplast DNA variationPattern of population genetic structure revealed by nuclear simple sequence repeat markers in the understory perennial <italic>Veratrum album</italic> ssp. <italic>oxysepalum</italic> (Melanthiaceae) with a disjunct pattern of chloroplast DNA haplotypesMicrogeographic genetic structure and gene flow in <italic>Hibiscus moscheutos</italic> (Malvaceae) populationsQuantifying effects of environmental and geographical factors on patterns of genetic differentiationComplex trait divergence contributes to environmental niche differentiation in ecological speciation of <italic>Boechera stricta</italic>High paternal diversity in the self-incompatible herb <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic> despite clonal reproduction and spatially restricted pollen dispersalLength polymorphism and allele structure of trinucleotide microsatellites in natural accessions of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>Ecological reproductive isolation of coast and inland races of <italic>Mimulus guttatus</italic>Patterns of genetic diversity in outcrossing and selfing populations of <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic>Strong differences in genetic structure across disjunct, edge, and core populations of the distylous forest herb <italic>Pulmonaria officinalis</italic> (Boraginaceae)Assessing population structure: <italic>F</italic><sub>st</sub> and related measuresGenotype and Genodive: two programs for the analysis of genetic diversity of asexual organismsAccuracy of estimated phylogenetic trees from molecular dataDivergent selection and heterogeneous genomic divergenceThe scale of population structure in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>CODA: convergence diagnosis and output analysis for MCMCInference of population structure using multilocus genotype dataGENEPOP (version 1.2): population genetics for exact tests and ecumenicismGenetic differentiation and estimation of gene flow from F-statistics under isolation by distanceHow did the exposed seafloor function in postglacial northward range expansion of <italic>Kalopanax septemlobus</italic>? Evidence from ecological niche modellingLineage admixture during postglacial range expansion is responsible for the increased gene diversity of <italic>Kalopanax septemlobus</italic> in a recently colonised territoryGenetic isolation by distance in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: biogeography and postglacial colonization of EuropeThe biology of speciationAn analysis of microsatellite loci in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>: mutational dynamics and applicationPollen-based reconstructions of Japanese biomes at 0, 6000 and 18,000 <sup>14</sup>C yr BPRecent loss of self-incompatibility by degradation of the male component in allotetraploid <italic>Arabidopsis kamchatica</italic>JapanNew insights from fine-scale spatial genetic structure analyses in plant populationsThe relative importance of factors determining genetic drift: mating system, spatial genetic structure, habitat and census size in <italic>Arabidopsis lyrata</italic><bold>Associate Editor:</bold> F. Xavier PicóThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.To examine determinants of geographical patterns in population differentiation, we quantified genetic variation of a temperate herb, <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic>, across the Japanese mainland. We found significant evidence for isolation-by-distance but not for isolation-by-environments. However, at least within the central area, the magnitude of genetic differentiation tended to increase with microhabitat dissimilarity in light conditions and water availability. Furthermore, most populations have been estimated to experience a recent decline in the effective population size. These findings highlight a potential influence of the microhabitat conditions and demographic processes on the local-scale genetic differentiation among natural plant populations.The genetic structure of a plant species is shaped by environmental adaptation and demographic factors, but their relative contributions are still unknown. To examine the environment- or geography-related differentiation, we quantified genetic variation among 41 populations of a temperate herb, <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> (Brassicaceae). We analysed 19 microsatellite loci, which showed a significant population differentiation and a moderate within-population genetic diversity (global <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub> = 0.42 and <italic>H</italic><sub>s</sub> = 0.19). Our structure analysis and phylogenetic network did not detect more than two genetic groups across the Japanese mainland but found fine-scale genetic differentiations and admixed patterns around the central area. Across the Japanese mainland, we found significant evidence for isolation-by-distance but not for isolation-by-environments. However, at least within the central area, the magnitude of genetic differentiation tended to increase with microhabitat dissimilarity under light conditions and water availability. Furthermore, most populations have been estimated to experience a recent decline in the effective population size, indicating a possibility of bottleneck effects on the pattern of genetic variation. These findings highlight a potential influence of the microhabitat conditions and demographic changes on the local-scale genetic differentiation among natural plant populations.Current patterns of genetic structure within a single plant species are shaped by demographic (e.g. genetic drift or gene flow) and ecological (e.g. species' life-history traits or adaptation to local environments) factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C50">Sharbel <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C42">Platt <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C57">Willi and Määttänen 2011</xref>). At a regional scale where current migrations are probably limited (e.g. on a several hundred-kilometre scale), many phylogeographical studies have revealed historical influences on the genetic structure of natural populations (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C13">Fujii and Senni 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C14">Garrido <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C35">Meeus <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). For example, impacts of glacial periods upon temperate flora were prominent in the regional patterns of genetic differentiation, since they have been relevant to latitudinal or altitudinal migrations, population extinction, range expansion and fragmentation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C20">Hewitt 2000</xref>). On the other hand, at a local scale where ongoing migrations and drifts are possible, landscape genetic studies have reported that habitat fragmentations and life-history traits of each plant species can be determinants of within-population genetic diversity and genetic differentiation among proximate populations, because they are involved in limited seed or pollen dispersal and genetic drifts (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C28">Kudoh and Whigham 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C56">Vekemans and Hardy 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C4">Bomblies <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).In addition to ample evidence on the genetic structure of plant populations from phylogeographical and landscape studies, there has also been increasing evidence that local environment and geographic scale exert mutually non-exclusive influences on the pattern of genetic structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C39">Nosil <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C51">Sobel <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C29">Lee and Mitchell-Olds 2011</xref>). For example, environmental factors may contribute to genetic differentiation by mediating local adaptation that can reduce the fitness of immigrants or promote reproductive isolation. These conceptual frameworks, which are termed ‘ecological speciation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C51">Sobel <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) or ‘isolation-by-adaptation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C39">Nosil <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), have been recognized as important. Thus, for a comprehensive understanding of an evolutionary trajectory of plant populations, it is necessary to consider the interaction between ecological and demographic processes.The Japanese archipelago consists of four main islands extending over 2000 km in the southwest–northeast direction and encompassing a wide range of climatic zones, including many floral or vegetation types from warm-temperate, evergreen and broadleaf forests to temperate, deciduous and sub-boreal coniferous forests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C40">Numata 1974</xref>). No major glaciers were present in Japan during the last glacial period, but the temperature and precipitation were significantly lower than that at present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C55">Tsukada 1988</xref>). Reconstruction of past vegetation from palaeoecological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C53">Takahara <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>) and phylogeographical data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C13">Fujii and Senni 2006</xref>) indicates that the main vegetation zones were displaced towards the south and lower altitudes (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C6">Dobson 1994</xref>). In the temperate zone of Japan in particular, the genetic structure of deciduous broadleaved tree species showed a regional genetic differentiation between the coastal areas of the sea of Japan and the Pacific Ocean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C18">Hiraoka and Tomaru 2009<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C25">Iwasaki <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). These regional-scale investigations postulate a phylogeographically unique scenario of recent range expansions from the central region along coastal areas of the Japanese mainland. Accumulated phylogeographical evidence also suggests that historical climate changes have shifted the distribution range, and consequently altered the genetic diversity of Japanese vegetation (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C48">Sakaguchi <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C49">2011</xref>). However, local-scale analyses are still limited regarding the pattern of genetic differentiation and its association with local environments.<italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> (syn. <italic>Arabis gemmifera</italic>) is distributed throughout Japan and the Russian Far East (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C21">Hoffmann 2005</xref>), where regional scales for this subspecies can be considered to be several hundred kilometres or more. <italic>Arabidopsis halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> can reproduce clonally: after flowering, plants produce new rosettes on the main and lateral meristems of flowering stems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C1">Aikawa <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), and these rosettes often establish as clonal offspring once they have rooted and attached themselves to the ground. The flowers are self-incompatible and produce fruits through cross-pollination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C54">Tsuchimatsu <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). The pollinators are small solitary bees and flower flies, and the seeds have no specific structure for long-distance dispersal. This subspecies is often found in somewhat isolated habitats near open gravel sites along valleys or in gaps within vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C23">Ihara 1976</xref>). The sporadic distribution, together with the lack of long-distance dispersal, may therefore enhance the genetic structure formed at a local scale (&lt;10 to a few hundred kilometres). Furthermore, <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> often occurs near human-disturbed habitats such as forest pathways and abandoned mines, whereby artificial dispersals may homogenize the local genetic structure.In this study, we examined genetic differentiation among natural populations of <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera.</italic> In particular, we conducted a fine-scale sampling around the Kinki area, because private genetic groups or admixed populations have often been reported for its coastal regions in temperate plants of Japan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C19">Hiraoka and Tomaru 2009<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C24">Iwasaki <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). We used cross-species microsatellite markers developed for a close relative, <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, to detect genetic structures at a fine resolution. Microsatellite loci are known to be highly polymorphic (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C10">Emanuelli <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>) and consequently provide us with suitable levels of variation for quantifying genetic differentiation at a fine scale. Three specific questions were addressed in this study. Is there any distinct genetic structure among <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> populations? Is the magnitude of genetic differentiation associated with environmental gradients and/or geographical distance? Are demographic processes involved in the genetic differentiation? To answer these questions, we initially generated a Bayesian clustering and phylogenetic network to determine the patterns of genetic differentiation. Secondly, we analysed the isolation-by-distance or -by-environmental differences. Finally, to estimate the demographic processes of each population, declines/expansions of effective population sizes were tested using a coalescence-based method.List of 41 populations of <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> and their genetic characteristics. Site ID, locality name, latitude, longitude and altitude are shown for each sampling site. The number of plants sampled per site (<italic>n</italic>), the number of polymorphic loci (#Poly. loci), the number of private alleles per site (#PA), AR, observed heterozygosity, within-population genetic diversity (<italic>H</italic><sub>o</sub> and <italic>H</italic><sub>s</sub>) and inbreeding coefficient (<italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub>) are shown based on the results from 19 microsatellite loci. Bold values of <italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub> indicate &lt;5 % significant deviation from the Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium values, in which positive and negative values indicate deficit and excess of heterozygotes, respectively. Demographic estimates by the Msvar programme (current and ancient effective population size, <italic>N</italic><sub>0</sub> and <italic>N</italic><sub>1</sub>, and time since the change of the population size, <italic>T</italic><sub>a</sub>) are also given. Mean and 95 % highest posterior density intervals (within square brackets) are presented for the Msvar estimates. Scale bars (---) indicate a study site not analysed due to its limited sample size, and NA means no information available.Map of sampling sites (A and B) and two principal components (PCs) summarizing eight environmental variables (C and D) for 41 populations of <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic>. The site IDs (coloured blue) are mapped on the sampling location. (A) focuses on the Kinki area whereas (B) presents the entire study area. The eight environmental variables include air temperature (°C, daily mean, maximum and minimum), annual precipitation (mm), radiation (h), sunshine (MJ/m<sup>2</sup>), maximum snow cover (cm) and altitude (m). PC1 and PC2 are also shown for the entire study area (C) and the Kinki area (D). Red arrows represent the contributions of each environmental variable to the PCs. Numbers correspond to the site IDs. Note that high-altitude populations (shaded IDs) show outlier values beyond the plot area.Primer information and basic population genetic statistics for microsatellite loci used in this study. Multiplex combinations (comb. 1–3), four types of inflorescent dye, annealing temperature (°C), size range of fragments detected in this study and the number of alleles are shown for each locus. Observed heterozygosity, within-population and total genetic diversity (<italic>H</italic><sub>o</sub>, <italic>H</italic><sub>s</sub> and <italic>H</italic><sub>t</sub>, respectively); inbreeding coefficients (<italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub>: bold values indicate &lt;5 % significant deviations from the Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium); and population differentiation (<italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub>: bold values indicate &lt;5 % significant deviations from no differentiation). See also references for sequence information. Scale bars (---) indicate that the summary for overall loci are not applicable to these information.The primer concentration was 10 μM. The multiplex PCR was performed in a volume of 10 μL, containing 0.5 μL DNA, 5 μL Multiplex PCR Master Mix (QIAGEN) and 1 pmol of each primer. The PCR proceeded as follows: 15 min at 95 °C; 30 cycles of 30 s at 94 °C, 90 s at 53 °C, 1 min at 72 °C for multiplex set 1, or 35 cycles of 30 s at 94 °C, 90 s at 58 °C and 1 min at 72 °C for multiplex sets 2 and 3; and a final extension step of 30 min at 60 °C. The PCR products were loaded on an ABI 3130xl Genetic Analyzer with GS 500 LIZ size standard (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). Genotypes were determined using Gene Mapper version 4.0 software (Applied Biosystems). The genotypic data are provided in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu070/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple"><bold>Supporting Information</bold> as supplementary material</ext-link>.We initially described the basic statistics for the population genetics of each sampling site and locus. We used GenoDive software version 2.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C37">Meirmans and van Tienderen 2004</xref>) to calculate observed heterozygosity (<italic>H</italic><sub>o</sub>), within-population genetic diversity (<italic>H</italic><sub>s</sub>, identical to the expected heterozygosity [<italic>H</italic><sub>e</sub>], calculated using GenoDive), total genetic diversity (<italic>H</italic><sub>t</sub>) and the inbreeding coefficient (<italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub>); and the Fstat version 2.9.3.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C17">Goudet 2002</xref>) to calculate allelic richness (AR; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C9">El Mousadik and Petit 1996</xref>). Deviations of <italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub> from the Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium were analysed with 9999 one-sided permutation tests using GenoDive. We also analysed the number of alleles, genetic diversities and genetic differentiation among populations (<italic>H</italic><sub>o</sub>, <italic>H</italic><sub>s</sub>, <italic>H</italic><sub>t</sub> and <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub>) for each locus by using GenoDive. Significances of the genetic differentiation, <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub>, were analysed for each locus based on the sum of square of the test statistic with 9999 permutations. Linkage disequilibrium among the 19 loci was also tested with 1000 Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) iterations with 100 batches, using GENEPOP software version 4.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C46">Raymond and Rousset 1995</xref>). Because of the possibility of clonality, the number of identical genotypes was checked by the clone assignment implemented in GenoDive.Secondly, we used a Bayesian clustering and population phylogeny to infer patterns of genetic differentiation. We estimated population gene pools and ancestry using Structure software version 2.3.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C44">Pritchard <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>) for all samples. The estimated number of ancestral populations (<italic>K</italic>) was set from 1 to 25 with a 100 000-step burn-in and 300 000 MCMC iterations. Allele frequencies were assumed to be correlated among populations and an admixture model was chosen. This process was repeated 20 times for each <italic>K</italic>. The probable <italic>K</italic> value was determined using the Δ<italic>K</italic> statistic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C11">Evanno <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). The mean log-likelihood and the Δ<italic>K</italic> statistics were calculated using Structure Harvester software version 0.6.93 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C8">Earl 2012</xref>). We repeated this structure analysis using the 30 populations from the Kinki area to further determine the genetic structure at the local scale. Additionally, we estimated the population structure using a phylogenetic network depicted by the SplitsTree4 version 4.13.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C22">Huson and Bryant 2006</xref>). The network was constructed on the basis of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C38">Nei <italic>et al.</italic>'s (1983)</xref> genetic distance (<italic>D</italic><sub>a</sub>; calculated using GenoDive).Thirdly, we analysed the relationships of genetic differentiation and environmental dissimilarity or geographical distance. We selected <italic>G′′</italic><sub>st</sub> as a metric of genetic differentiation to adjust <italic>H</italic><sub>s</sub>-dependent variation in <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub> values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C36">Meirmans and Hedrick 2011</xref>). The data from the entire study area and the Kinki area were separately analysed. According to the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C47">Rousset (1997)</xref>, we converted pairwise <italic>G′′</italic><sub>st</sub> values into <italic>G′′</italic><sub>st</sub>/(1 − <italic>G′′</italic><sub>st</sub>) for each pair of sampling sites. The Mesh Climate 2000 database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C26">Japan Meteorological Agency 2002</xref>) was used to compile the environmental variables. This database provides the information on air temperature (°C; daily mean, maximum and minimum), annual precipitation (mm), radiation (h), sunshine (MJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and maximum snow cover (cm) at a 1-km<sup>2</sup> scale, and is thus suitable for our sampling scale. We added the altitude of each sampling site to these variables. These variables were summarized by a principal component analysis (PCA) to deal with multicollinearity of the environmental variables. The sum of the first and second principal components (PC1 and PC2) explained 78 and 79 % (respectively for the entire area and the Kinki area) of the total variation in habitat environments represented by the eight variables. PC1 explained ∼54 % of the variation, whereas PC2 explained roughly 25 % of the variation for both the entire area and the Kinki area. PC1 was related to the three temperature variables (daily mean, maximum and minimum air temperature) as well as the altitude, whereas PC2 was related to the light conditions (radiation and sunshine) and water availability (precipitation and snow cover). This tendency was consistent between the entire study area and the Kinki area (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU070F1">1</xref>C and D). On the basis of the PCA results, we used PC1 and PC2 as representative indices to analyse genetic differentiation along environmental gradients. We used the Mantel tests to analyse Pearson's correlation between genetic and geographical distances; or partial Mantel tests for the correlation between genetic distance and the difference of principal component values by incorporating the geographical distance as a covariate. <italic>P</italic>-values were determined by 9999 permutations. We utilized the prcomp function for the PCA and the vegan package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C41">Oksanen <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) implemented in the R software version 3.0.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C45">R Core Team 2013</xref>) for the Mantel tests. Additionally, to deal with the exaggerated sampling on the Kinki area, we repeated the Mantel tests (with 999 permutations) for the entire study area by randomly selecting 10 populations from the Kinki area. This subsampling analysis was run 9999 times, where the significance of test statistics (<italic>r</italic> and <italic>P</italic>) was determined by mean and 95 % CI (i.e. 1.96 × SD) of the resampled distribution.Finally, we estimated demographic changes in each studied population using the Msvar programme version 1.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C2">Beaumont 1999</xref>). On the basis of a coalescent simulation by hierarchical Bayesian models with a step-wise mutation assumption, this programme provides multi-locus posterior distribution estimates for current and ancient effective population size (log<sub>10</sub>[<italic>N</italic><sub>0</sub>]) and log<sub>10</sub>[<italic>N</italic><sub>1</sub>]), respectively), mutation rate (log<sub>10</sub>[<italic>μ</italic>]) and the time since populations started to expand/decline (log<sub>10</sub>[<italic>T</italic><sub>a</sub>]). These parameters were allowed to vary among all 19 loci, while their initial values were equal among these loci. The generation time (<italic>g</italic><sub>a</sub>) was set as 2 years because <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> is a perennial herb able to bloom during the first year of its life cycle under cultivated conditions (Y. Sato, pers. obs.). We used uninformative lognormal priors as follows: means of the prior distributions were set to 4, 4, −4 and 5; and SD equal to 4, 4, 1 and 4 for <italic>N</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>N</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>μ</italic> and <italic>T</italic><sub>a</sub>, respectively. Hyper-prior lognormal distributions were set as: mean equal to 6, 6, −4 and 8; SD equal to 2, 2, 0.25 and 2; hyper-prior of mean equal to 0, 0, 0 and 0; hyper-prior of SD equal to 0.5, 0.5, 0.5 and 0.5 for <italic>N</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>N</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>μ</italic> and <italic>T</italic><sub>a</sub>, respectively. Three independent chains of MCMC were run with 40 000 thinned updates and a thinning interval of 20 000 steps (i.e. total number of update steps = 8 × 10<sup>8</sup>). The coda package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C43">Plummer <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>) implemented in R was used to estimate the posterior distribution and to assess convergence among three chains, where the first half of the iterations was discarded as burn-in periods. The convergence was assessed using potential-scale reduction factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C15">Gelman and Rubin 1992</xref>). For the coalescent estimation, we did not analyse populations with less than seven individuals due to their small sample size (total number of populations analysed = 30).The AR ranged from 1.00 to 2.02 in all populations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB1">1</xref>). Within-population genetic diversities were &lt;0.4 for all populations. <italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub> values significantly deviated from zero in 23 of 41 populations (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB1">1</xref>). A few populations were found to have private alleles (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB1">1</xref>). Percentages of null alleles were &lt;5 %, except for 7.5 % in Site 19. Most markers showed significant genetic differentiation among the studied populations (global <italic>G</italic><sub>st</sub> = 0.42; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB2">2</xref>). Sixteen markers showed a significant <italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub>, and six of them had <italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub> values &gt;0.2 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB2">2</xref>). No marker pairs exhibited a significant linkage disequilibrium, except in three cases (ICE12-MHJ24, <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> = 14.4, d<italic>f</italic> = 6, <italic>P</italic> = 0.006; ICE10-AthZEPG, <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> = 6.05, d<italic>f</italic> = 2, <italic>P</italic> = 0.048; ATH-AthCTR1A, <italic>χ</italic><sup>2</sup> = 91.9, d<italic>f</italic> = 34, <italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.0001). Within the entire dataset, there were only five individuals with missing values at more than four loci. Although Site 40 consisted of identical genotypes across the 19 loci, identical genotypes were &lt;10 % in the entire dataset.Genetic groups inferred from the structure analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C44">Pritchard <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). (A) and (B) show results at the number of ancestral populations (<italic>K</italic>) = 2 and 4 for the entire study area and within the Kinki area, respectively. The inset of (B) presents a neighbour-joining tree based on allele-frequency divergence among clusters (the scale bar indicates a 0.01 unit). The site IDs correspond to those in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB1">1</xref> and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU070F1">1</xref>. Note that colours of clusters do not correspond between different values of <italic>K</italic>.A split phylogenetic network between the studied <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> populations based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C38">Nei <italic>et al.</italic>'s (1983)</xref> <italic>D</italic><sub>a</sub> distances. The site IDs correspond to Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB1">1</xref> and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU070F1">1</xref>. The IDs of sites outside the Kinki area are within parentheses. The scale bar indicates a 0.1 unit of the <italic>D</italic><sub>a</sub> distance.Isolation-by-distance or -environmental gradients across the Japanese mainland (A–C) and within the Kinki area (D–F). Pairwise genetic distances (<italic>G′′</italic><sub>st</sub>/[1 − <italic>G′′</italic><sub>st</sub>]) are plotted against geographical distances (km) or the differential values of the first or second principal components (PC1 and 2; see also Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU070F1">1</xref>C and D). Solid and dashed lines indicate significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and marginally significant trends (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.1), respectively. Pearson's correlation coefficient (<italic>r</italic>) is also shown within each panel.The coalescence-based analysis by the Msvar programme indicated that most populations experienced a 10<sup>2</sup> to 10<sup>3</sup> times reduction in the effective population size compared with the ancestral (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB1">1</xref>). The time since the demographic changes was estimated at 10<sup>4</sup>–10<sup>5</sup> years, except for a few populations (&gt;10<sup>8</sup> years for Sites 34 and 41; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU070TB1">1</xref>). Because estimations for four populations did not converge (multivariate potential scale reduction factors &gt;1.1 for Sites 2, 12, 31 and 31), further MCMCs were run with 120 000 thinned updates for these populations. After this additional run, the multivariate potential-scale reduction factors reduced to ≤1.1 for all populations, indicating successful convergence among the MCMC chains.We did not detect more than two genetic groups across the Japanese mainland, but we identified a fine-scale differentiation and admixed pattern within the central area, as indicated by the structure analysis. The magnitude of genetic differentiation depended on geographical distance, but not on the environmental differences across the entire study scale. However, at least within the central area, we found suggestive evidence for environment-related differentiation, although it was marginally significant. Given that the second principal component was related to the light conditions (radiation and sunshine) and water availability (precipitation and snow cover), we hypothesize that microhabitat conditions can be a factor in local adaptation. Moreover, <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> often occurs in transient habitats such as vegetation gaps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C23">Ihara 1976</xref>), and we indeed observed them often growing in gravel along valleys or shady habitats nearby forest margins. Hence, it seems plausible that microhabitat environments rather than meteorological conditions (such as temperature or altitude) influenced the distribution of our studied species and accordingly resulted in the isolation-by-environments.In plants, isolation-by-adaptation has been suggested for micro-environmental regimes, such as salt tolerance in <italic>Mimulus guttatus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C33">Lowry <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) or water availability in <italic>Boechera stricta</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C29">Lee and Mitchell-Olds 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C30">2013</xref>). These examples may agree with our evidence in which microhabitat-related differentiation was observed at a local scale. Furthermore, in the relative <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, the influence of breeding systems on genetic structure has been suggested as relevant even within a scale &lt;50 km (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C4">Bomblies <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). In our studied species, it is possible that the life-history traits can facilitate the formation of the fine-scale differentiation. Specifically, <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> has a potential for clonal growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C1">Aikawa <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and thereby can generate identical genotypes within a population. Despite the fact that such identical genotypes were rare in the entire dataset, similar genotypes easily occurred in our studied clonal species. In addition, seeds of <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> are not specialized for long-distance dispersal. Thus, asexual breeding system may have allowed populations from a small number of founders with low genetic diversity to become established. In total, combinations of microhabitat isolations and negative distance-dispersal relationships may be specific factors facilitating the local-scale differentiation in <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic>.The coalescence-based estimation inferred a decline in the effective population size for most sites. Accompanied with the species' life-history discussed above (clonality and lack of long-distance dispersal), such a decline of population size could account for significantly positive <italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub> and moderate heterozygosity as it might have caused genetic drifts. In Japan, bottlenecks that are associated with positive inbreeding were also reported for a clonal self-incompatible herb <italic>Veratrum album</italic> subsp. <italic>oxysepalum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C27">Kikuchi <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The bottleneck effects exerted by the reduction of effective population size may therefore explain the local-scale genetic differentiation and low levels of within-population genetic diversity in our studied clonal self-incompatible species, <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic>. However, other factors may also be responsible for the within- and among-population patterns of genetic diversity. For example, in a self-incompatible relative <italic>A. lyrata</italic>, selfing has recently evolved in some populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C34">Mable and Adam 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C12">Foxe <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) and has consequently influenced their genetic structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C57">Willi and Määttänen 2011</xref>). Although the evidence for the breakdown of self-incompatibility has not been reported in our studied species yet, this factor remains possible for some populations exhibiting the extremely positive deviation of <italic>G</italic><sub>is</sub> (e.g. Sites 20 and 21).The pattern of genetic structure of <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic> seems comparable with those of the temperate deciduous broadleaved trees in Japan, i.e. admixed pattern in central Japan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C19">Hiraoka and Tomaru 2009<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C24">Iwasaki <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). A comparative phylogeographic study on four species of deciduous broadleaved trees has identified genetic groups specific to the coastal area of the Kinki region; this postulates the presence of multiple refugia within the Kinki area during glacial periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C25">Iwasaki <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). The phylogeographical scenario for the temperate deciduous broadleaved trees may be responsible for the presence of multiple genetic groups that we identified within the Kinki area. Despite the unclear genetic structure across the Japanese mainland, significant isolation-by-distance was detected across the entire study area. This may suggest that the genetic differentiation have been formed gradually along the geographic scale rather than clustered into distinct genetic groups.The present results should be interpreted with caution. Firstly, the sample size per site in several populations was too small to accurately quantify their genetic variation or perform quantitative analysis. Secondly, our structure analysis detected an admixture of multiple genetic groups even within a population (e.g. Sites 7, 23, 29 and 31). The underlying genetic structure made it difficult to accurately estimate the demographic processes of highly admixed populations. Thirdly, we should note that our demographic inference has some limitations due to a simplified assumption. In particular, the Msvar estimates assumed the absence of gene flow among local populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C2">Beaumont 1999</xref>). Thus, this assumption prevented us from excluding a possibility that the decline of population size and the time since the demographic change were overestimated for proximate populations in the Kinki area, while the estimates of regional samples did not differ considerably from those of local ones. These caveats should be taken into account when interpreting the patterns of genetic differentiation reported here.In summary, this study provides suggestive evidence for microhabitat-related differentiations at a local scale despite the lack of isolation-by-environment across the Japanese mainland in <italic>A. halleri</italic> subsp. <italic>gemmifera</italic>. We also suggest the possible effects of population decline on the patterns of genetic variation. Our findings therefore highlight a potential impact of ecological and demographic factors on the genetic differentiation at a fine spatial scale. Further investigations (such as common garden experiments) are required for rigorous testing of isolation-by-adaptation in order to understand how local adaptation and geographic isolation interactively affect the pattern of genetic differentiation within a plant species.This study was supported by funding Programme for <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">Next Generation World-Leading Researchers</grant-sponsor> (NEXT Program, <grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">GS013</grant-num>), JSPS and by <grant-sponsor id="cs2" rid="cn2" xlink:type="simple">Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research</grant-sponsor> (S) <grant-num id="cn2" rid="cs2" xlink:type="simple">26221106</grant-num>, MEXT to H.K.Y.S. performed the experiment and analysed the data. Y.S. and H.K. designed the study and wrote the manuscript.None declared.The following Supporting Information is available in the online version of this article –<bold>Figure S1.</bold> Pictures of the study sites and plants.<bold>Figure S2.</bold> Log-likelihood and Δ<italic>K</italic> values showing the likely number of ancestral populations inferred by the structure analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU070C44">Pritchard <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>).<bold>Figure S3.</bold> Genepop format of raw genotypic data [SatoKudoh_AhSSR_GENEPOP.txt].The authors thank Dr T. Kawagoe for providing the materials analysed in this study and for discussions during the study, and also thank Dr J. Sugisaka, Ms S. Fujii and Dr A. Satake for their help in the sample collection. They also thank Dr T. Iwasaki, Dr T. Tsuchimatsu, two anonymous reviewers, and Dr Xavier Picó, associate editor, for valuable comments on the manuscript; Dr K. S. Araki for technical support in the experiments; and Dr S. I. Morinaga for providing primer information.