 Taxonomic and ecological discrimination of Fagaceae species based on internal transcribed spacer polymerase chain reaction–restriction fragment length polymorphism  The ITS region of nuclear ribosomal DNA: a valuable source of evidence on angiosperm phylogeny  Frequent cytoplasmic exchanges between oak species that are not closely related:  Quercus suber  and  Q. ilex  in Morocco  Utility of ITS sequence data for phylogenetic reconstruction of Italian  Quercus  spp  Genetic diversity among old Portuguese bread wheat cultivars and botanical varieties evaluated by ITS rDNA PCR–RFLP markers  Differential rRNA genes expression in hexaploid wheat related to NOR methylation  Intergenic spacer length variants in old Portuguese bread wheat cultivars  Physical localization of NORs and ITS length variants in old Portuguese durum wheat cultivars  Differential rRNA genes expression in bread wheat and its inheritance  Taxonomic identity of  Quercus coccifera  L. in the Iberian Peninsula is maintained in spite of widespread hybridisation, as revealed by morphological, ISSR and ITS sequence data  Molecular evidence for hybrid origin of  Quercus crenata  Lam. (Fagaceae) from  Q. cerris  L. and  Q. suber  L  Distribution of chloroplast DNA variation in British oaks ( Quercus robur  and  Q. petraea ): the influence of postglacial colonisation and human management  Genetic diversity assessment and estimation of phylogenetic relationships among 26 Fagaceae species using ISSRs  Chloroplast DNA variation of white oaks in the alpine region  Significance of pollen characteristics for infrageneric classification and phylogeny in  Quercus  ( Fagaceae )  The oaks of western Eurasia: traditional classifications and evidence from two nuclear markers  The evolutionary history of  Fagus  in western Eurasia: evidence from genes, morphology and the fossil record  Episodic migration of oaks to Iceland: evidence for a North Atlantic ‘Land Bridge’ in the latest Miocene  Fagaceae from the early Oligocene of Central Europe: persisting new world and emerging old world biogeographic links  Molecular drive: a cohesive mode of species evolution  Molecular drive in multigene families: how biological novelties arise, spread and are assimilated  A rapid DNA isolation procedure for small quantities of fresh leaf tissue  Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap  Chloroplast DNA variation in the  Quercus affinis–Q. laurina  complex in Mexico: geographical structure and associations with nuclear and morphological variation  5.8S motifs for the identification of pseudogenic ITS regions  High variability of chloroplast DNA in three Mediterranean evergreen oaks indicates complex evolutionary history  Phylogeny of  Castanea  (Fagaceae) based on chloroplast  trn T-L-F sequence data  Molecular evidence for an Asian origin and a unique westward migration of species in the genus  Castanea  via Europe to North America  Testing the theory of natural selection  Genetic variability in  Sambucus nigra  L. clones: a preliminary molecular approach  Phylogeographical variation of chloroplast DNA in cork oak ( Quercus suber )  Phylogeny, biogeography, and processes of molecular differentiation in  Quercus  subgenus  Quercus  (Fagaceae)  Systematics of Fagaceae: phylogenetic tests of reproductive trait evolution  Why nuclear ribosomal DNA spacers (ITS) tell different stories in  Quercus   The relationship of a particular chromosomal element to the development of the nucleoli in  Zea mays   Moving beyond single-locus studies to characterize hybridization between oaks ( Quercus  spp.)  Three divergent rDNA clusters predate the species divergence in  Quercus petraea  (Matt.) Liebl. and  Quercus robur  L  Identification and characterization of some ITS variants from hexaploid wheat ( Triticum aestivum  L.)  Chromosomal alterations caused by hybridization and their bearing upon certain general genetic problems  Analysis of gene diversity in subdivided populations  PCR–RFLP of the ribosomal DNA internal transcribed spacers (ITS) provides markers for the A and B genomes in  Musa  L  TREEVIEW: an application to display phylogenetic trees on personal computers   Quercus macranthera  Fisch. &amp; Mey. ex Hohen. And  Quercus iberica  M. Bieb.: Taxonomic definition and systematic relationships with European oaks inferred from nuclear internal transcribed spacer (ITS) data  Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data  Variation in the nuclear ribosomal DNA internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region of  Pinus rzedowskii  revealed by PCR–RFLP  Restriction analysis of PCR-amplified internal transcribed spacers of ribosomal DNA as a tool for species identification in different genera of the order Glomales  Intra-individual and intra-species heterogeneity in nuclear rDNA ITS region of  Vigna  species from subgenus  Ceratotropis   The neighbour-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees  ITS sequences from nuclear rDNA suggest unexpected phylogenetic relationships between Euro-Mediterranean, East Asiatic and North American taxa of  Quercus  ( Fagaceae )  Index Herbariorum: a Global Directory of Public Herbaria and Associated Staff  Amplification and direct sequencing of fungal ribosomal genes for phylogenetics   Associate Editor:  Kermit Ritland  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  In 30 Fagaceae individuals from the  Castanea ,  Fagus  and  Quercus  genera, the internal transcribed spacer region (ITS) of the ribosomal DNA (rDNA) was amplified and digested with four restriction enzymes ( Hae III,  Hpa II,  Sau 96I, and  Taq I), producing ITS PCR-RFLP markers. This technique allowed the discrimination of the Fagaceae species according to genus, infrageneric group and ecological area. This study constitutes the first application of the alternative co-dominant marker system ITS PCR-RFLP in Fagaceae species and proved to be highly suitable for taxonomic and ecological discrimination, constituting a useful molecular tool for taxonomists and forestry researchers.  The internal transcribed spacer (ITS) of ribosomal DNA has been used to confirm taxonomic classifications and define phylogenies in several plant species following sequencing or polymerase chain reaction–restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR–RFLP) techniques. In this study, co-dominant ITS PCR–RFLP molecular markers were produced in 30 Fagaceae individuals belonging to the  Castanea ,  Fagus  and  Quercus  genera in order to assess the potential of this technique for taxonomic discrimination and determination of phylogenies. The complete ITS region (ITS1-5.8S rRNA-ITS2) was amplified in most of the Fagaceae individuals as a single fragment of ∼700 bp. The ITS amplified products were digested with nine restriction enzymes, but only four (HaeIII, HpaII, TaqI and Sau96I) produced polymorphic/discriminative patterns. The total expected heterozygosity ( H  E ) was 20.31 % and the gene diversity ( I ), 32.97 %. The ITS polymorphism was higher within the  Quercus  genus (85.3 %). The ITS PCR–RFLP markers clustered the Fagaceae species according to genus or infrageneric group (in the case of  Quercus  sp. individuals). Five oaks did not cluster in line with the adopted infrageneric classification, but three of these were grouped according to their actual ecological distributions. The ITS PCR–RFLP markers indicated their potential for phylogenetic studies since all Fagaceae individuals were discriminated according to genus, and most of the oaks were clustered according to infrageneric group or ecological area.  Ribosomal DNA (rDNA) is a nuclear multigene family with copies arranged in tandem arrays within the nucleolar organizer regions (NORs) that form the secondary chromosomal constriction, with the centromere being the primary constriction ( McClintock 1934 ;  Navashin 1934 ). Each rDNA unit is composed of the conserved coding regions of the 18S-5.8S-26S rRNA genes, including the variable non-coding intergenic spacer (IGS). The IGS itself consists of a non-transcribed spacer region containing motifs that are designated as sub-repeats and is flanked by external transcribed spacers. The 5.8S rRNA gene is flanked by two non-coding sequences referred to as the internal transcribed spacers (ITS), ITS1 and ITS2, constituting the entire ITS region. Despite being fast-evolving regions, the rDNA spacers experience concerted evolution, and low diversity is expected within and among the rDNA loci. Such sequence uniformity allows the numerous rDNA copies in a genome to be treated as a single gene. Furthermore, the biparental inheritance, universality and orthology/paralogy of the rDNA sequences allow the use of ITS in taxonomic inferences and phylogenetics among diverged taxa ( Baldwin  et al.  1995 ).  As an alternative to sequencing or studies involving the laborious Southern blotting technique ( Carvalho  et al.  2010 ,  2013 ), the polymerase chain reaction–restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR–RFLP) technique has been applied to the ITS or IGS rDNA spacers, resulting in co-dominant molecular marker systems that have proved useful for the detection of length variants, establishment of genetic relationships and assessment of genetic diversity in different plant species ( Quijada  et al.  1998 ;  Nwakanma  et al.  2003 ;  Nalini  et al.  2007 ;  Saini  et al.  2008 ;  Carvalho  et al.  2009 ,  2011 a  ,   b  ;  Lima-Brito  et al.  2011 ). Due to their repetitive nature, the spacers tend to be more variable than the coding regions of the rDNA. In plants, the longer ITS1 seems to evolve more rapidly than ITS2 (in  Pinus  sp.;  Quijada  et al.  1998 ); it also exhibits higher levels of informative phylogenetic information than ITS2 (in oaks;  Bellarosa  et al.  2005 ). Nevertheless, the sequence conservation of rDNA loci has led to an intra-specific degree of polymorphism with &lt;5 % of sequence divergence ( Mayol and Rosselló 2001 ;  Bellarosa  et al.  2005 ). Such slow and consistent mutational behaviour might have increased the utility of ITS in phylogenetics. Despite the concerted evolution of rDNA, intra-individual variability may be found in Fagaceae species when sequence homogenization among paralogues has not yet achieved completion ( Mayol and Rosselló 2001 ;  Muir  et al.  2001 ). However, the identification of paralogues in an individual does not always seem to imply the presence of pseudogenes ( Denk  et al.  2002 ).  Several studies have resorted to ITS sequencing for taxonomic clarification in this family, particularly in the assessment of phylogenetic relations in  Quercus  ( Manos  et al.  1999 ,  2001 ;  Bellarosa  et al.  2005 ;  Casas  et al.  2007 ;  Denk and Grimm 2010 ),  Castanea  ( Manos  et al.  2001 ) and  Fagus  ( Denk  et al.  2002 ). The fact that the RFLP technique is rapid and able to analyse a large number of samples simultaneously has made it useful for studying the chloroplastidial DNA (cpDNA) or mitochondrial DNA in the  Quercus  genus, and has enabled the following: evaluation of the cpDNA variation of  Quercus suber  L. in the Mediterranean basin ( Lumaret  et al.  2005 ); study of the level of cytoplasmic exchange between  Q. suber  and  Q. ilex  L. in Morocco ( Belahbib  et al.  2001 ); investigation of the dynamics of the spread of  Q. robur  L. and  Q. petraea  (Mattuschka) Liebl. throughout England ( Cottrell  et al.  2002 ); retracing of the recolonization routes of white oaks in the Alps ( Csaikl  et al.  2002 ); and inference of the structure of the  Q. affinis  Scheidweiler—  Q. laurina  Humboldt complex in Mexico ( González-Rodriguez  et al.  2004 ).  Subjecting the amplified ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 region to the RFLP technique may allow the evaluation of the ITS polymorphism. Instead of searching for dissimilarities in a nucleotide sequence, the RFLP methodology identifies only the differences associated with the presence/absence of endonuclease recognition sites due to mutations, insertions or deletions. As a result, only highly prevalent ITS differences present in the large rDNA multigene family of an organism will allow the development of a visible band in an agarose gel, thus producing a specific band pattern.  In the current study, our aim was to evaluate the ITS polymorphism in individuals from the genera  Castanea  Mill.,  Fagus  Tourn and  Quercus  L. using PCR–RFLP performed with nine restriction enzymes. We also aimed to investigate the potential of the ITS PCR–RFLP markers for taxonomic discrimination and determination of phylogenies, with a particular focus on the genus  Quercus .  Taxonomical classification, ecological distribution, seed origin and voucher numbers of the Fagaceae individuals studied (HVR designation is in accordance with Index Herbariorum codes;  Thiers 2010 ). *Seeds were provided by the following botanical gardens: Arboretumul Simeria, Hunedoara, Romania; Botanical Garden of the University of Tras-os-Montes and Alto Douro, Vila Real, Portugal; Botanischer Garten der Universität Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany; Botanischer Garten der Westfälische Wilhelms, Universität Münster, Germany; Botanischer Garten Duisburg, Duisburg, Germany; Dubrava Arboretum, Kaunas, Lithuania; Hortus Botanicus Tallinnensis, Tallinn, Estonia; Hortus Botanicus, Universitatis Latviensis, Riga, Latvia; Jardin Botanique de la Ville de Lyon, Lyon, France; Kamigamo Experimental Station, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan; Kanagawa Prefectural Ofuna Botanical Garden, Okamoto, Kamakura, Kanagawa, Japão; Ökologisch Botanischer Garten, Universität Bayreuth, Bayreuth, Germany; Orto Botanico, Universita' di Siena, Siena, Italia; Rivierenhof Park, Deurne, Belgium; Späth-Arboretum, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Berlin, Germany.  Regarding the taxonomy of the genus  Quercus , we adopted (except for  Q. serrata ) the informally unranked infrageneric ‘groups’ proposed by  Denk and Grimm (2009 ,  2010 ). Thus, the oak species used in this study were classified as  Cerris  (cerris oaks; ecologically confined to Eurasia),  Ilex  (ilex oaks; Eurasia),  Quercus  (white oaks; Eurasia and North America) and  Lobatae  (red oaks; Americas). We assumed that the hybrid  Q. crenata  would belong to the  Cerris  group along with the parental  Q. cerris  and  Q. suber . All the studied species have ecological origins that are representative of the natural distributions of the Fagaceae across the northern hemisphere.  To rule out hybridization issues between the mother trees of the plants used for DNA extraction, the seeds were harvested in different botanical gardens (Table  1 ), ensuring that the plants had morphological characters that enabled unambiguous classification. Dormancy was broken at 4 °C, and germination occurred at 7 °C in the dark on moistened cotton. Plantlets were grown in peat moss under greenhouse conditions at the University of Tras-os-Montes and Alto Douro (Vila Real, Portugal).  To avoid fungal contamination in the ITS amplification, young, healthy leaves from one individual per species were collected and thoroughly cleaned with 70 % v/v alcohol and deionized water for further genomic DNA extraction using the cetyl trimethylammonium bromide method ( Doyle and Doyle 1987 ). The integrity evaluation was done by electrophoresis performed in 0.8 % w/v agarose gels and by DNA quantification in a Nanodrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer. DNA stocks were diluted to a concentration of 50 ng μL −1 .  The complete ITS region (ITS1-5.8S-ITS2) was amplified using the primers ITS-5 (5′-GGAAGTAAAAGTCGTAACAAGG-3′) as forward and ITS-4 (5′-TCCTCCGCTTATTGATATGC-3′) as reverse, both from  White  et al.  (1990) . These primers were designed for the highly conserved 5′-end of the 26S rRNA gene and for the 3′-end of the 18S rRNA gene, respectively ( White  et al.  1990 ). Each PCR (final volume of 50 µL) consisted of 50 ng of template DNA, 5μL KCl reaction buffer, 2.5 mM of each dNTP, 62 µM of each primer and 4 units of Dream Taq DNA polymerase (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Ten microlitres of each amplified product were loaded on 1.5 % w/v agarose gels stained with ethidium bromide in order to confirm the ITS amplification.  Nine restriction enzymes were tested for the production of ITS PCR–RFLP markers: AluI, BamHI, DpnI, EcoRI, HaeIII, HpaII, RsaI, Sau96I and TaqI (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The digestion reactions (final volume of 30 µL) followed the manufacturer's instructions. In each digestion reaction, 10 µL of the amplified product were used. The enzymatic reaction was thermally interrupted, and the digested products were separated by electrophoresis performed in 2 % w/v agarose gels stained with ethidium bromide. The sizes of the fragments were estimated by comparison with the molecular weight marker Gene Ruler DNA Ladder 100 bp Plus (Thermo Fisher Scientific) loaded in each agarose gel.  Despite being co-dominant markers, the ITS fragments were scored as presence (1) or absence (0) in order to construct binary matrices for statistical analysis. For each genus and the  Quercus  infrageneric groups, the software POPGENE 1.32 ( Yeh  et al.  1999 ) was used to calculate Nei's expected heterozygosity ( H  E ;  Nei 1973 ) and Shannon's information index ( I ;  Lewontin 1972 ) to measure the level of gene diversity, and the same software was used to estimate Nei's original measures of genetic identity and genetic distance ( Nei 1973 ). To evaluate the phylogenetic relationships, a radial tree and a phylogram were generated with TreeView ( Page 1996 ) based on the genetic distance ( Nei 1987 ) and neighbour-joining method ( Saitou and Nei 1987 ), calculated using POPGENE. A pairwise similarity matrix was calculated using Dice's coefficient, and a dendrogram of genetic similarity was constructed using the unweighted pair group method with arithmetical averages (UPGMA) and the Numerical Taxonomy and Multivariate Analysis System software (NTSYS-PC 2.02) ( Rohlf 1998 ). A bootstrap analysis based on 1000 replications was performed with Winboot ( Yap and Nelson 1996 ) to test the clustering reliability. Only bootstrap values &gt;50 % and common to the consensus trees generated either by Winboot and UPGMA are shown ( Felsenstein 1985 ). The adjustment fitness of the UPGMA dendrogram to the binary matrices was verified using the COPH and MXCOMP modules from the NTSYS software. To certify the NTSYS UPGMA clustering and estimate the genetic structure of the individuals under study, we used STRUCTURE 2.3.4 software ( Pritchard  et al.  2000 ), where several clusters ( K ) were tested with 50 000 generations of burn-in and 100 000 Markov chain Monte Carlo iterations.  The ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 length usually varies from 500 to 750 bp in angiosperms ( Baldwin  et al.  1995 ). Phylogenetic studies based on ITS sequencing often detect, beyond point mutations, short nucleotide insertions/deletions responsible for the variable length of the ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 region. Such an event is related to dissimilarities in the spacers, since the 5.8S gene exhibits high sequence conservation and minimal variation in the length of ∼163−165 bp in several species ( Baldwin  et al.  1995 ;  Manos  et al.  2001 ;  Denk  et al.  2002 ;  Papini  et al.  2011 ).  Regarding the results in the genus  Quercus , a single band of ∼700 bp was amplified in 19 species (data not shown). However, in five oak species, two ITS bands of ∼600 and 700 bp in length were detected. In  Q. cerris  and  Q. fraineto , the two bands exhibited the same intensity in the agarose gel, while in the other three species ( Q. crenata ,  Q. castaneifolia  and  Q. ilex  subsp.  rotundifolia ), the 700-bp band was more intense. Several authors have reported variable ITS lengths for the same oak species. Some examples are described below, and may be attributed to different amplification conditions or primers.  Manos  et al.  (2001)  reported an alignment of 635 bp for 179 Fagaceae taxa.  Muir  et al.  (2001)  detected a single band of ∼720 bp in  Q. petraea  and  Q. robur .  Bellarosa  et al.  (2005)  amplified a single band of ∼600 bp in 11 oak species (some common to this study:  Q. cerris ,  Q. suber ,  Q. fraineto ,  Q. petraea ,  Q. pubescens ,  Q. robur ,  Q. coccifera  and  Q. ilex ).  Casas  et al.  (2007)  reported an ITS length ranging from 599 to 607 bp in six oak species ( Q. pubescens ,  Q. faginea ,  Q. pyrenaica ,  Q. suber ,  Q. ilex  and  Q. coccifera ). Regarding the detailed lengths,  Manos  et al.  (1999)  assumed a size of 614 bp in 44  Quercus  species after detecting different lengths for ITS1 (223−234 bp) and ITS2 (206−214 bp), while 5.8S exhibited a rather stable length of 164 bp.  Papini  et al.  (2011)  reported a 615-bp matrix (indels included), where ITS1 represented 212 bp in  Q. iberica  and 222 bp in  Q. macranthera , while the ITS2 and the 5.8S coding region were 211 and 163 bp, respectively, in both species.  The three  Castanea  species showed bands ∼600 bp in length, but an additional band of ∼700 bp was amplified in  Castanea mollissima  and  C. sativa  (data not shown). Interestingly, the 600-bp band was more intense in  C. mollissima , and the 700-bp band was more intense in  C. sativa . According to  Samuel  et al.  (1998) , the lengths in  Castanea  are 231 bp for ITS1 (U93097) and 183 bp for ITS2 (U93098).   Denk and Grimm (2010)  suggested that the dissimilarities in  Fagus  ITS1 to other Fagaceae may discourage comparisons in phylogenetic studies. Indeed,  Manos  et al.  (2001)  found a 635-bp alignment for 179 Fagaceae taxa, but, in  Fagus , an additional 40-bp insertion occurred in ITS1. Despite this, we decided to include our results in the pooled data to understand how they would stand out from the remaining genera and to survey for intra-specific differences. In the three  Fagus  species studied here, a single band ∼750 bp long was amplified (data not shown), confirming its longer length.  Denk  et al.  (2002)  encountered a total length varying from 644 to 660 bp, average lengths of 259 bp for ITS1, 229 bp for ITS2 and a stable length of 165 bp for the 5.8S gene.  Unweighted pair group method with arithmetical averages dendrogram of genetic similarity based on the pool of ITS PCR–RFLP data achieved with the restriction enzymes HaeIII, HpaII, Sau96I and TaqI. Only bootstrap values &gt;50 are represented. The ecological distribution is indicated after species name (am, North America; as, Asia; eu, Europe; medit, Mediterranean; and af, Africa), and the infrageneric group for each  Quercus  species (C,  Cerris ; I,  Ilex ; L,  Lobatae ; and Q,  Quercus ).  For a preliminary assessment of ITS polymorphism, nine restriction enzymes were tested in  Q. petraea : AluI, BamHI, DpnI, EcoRI, HaeIII, HpaII, RsaI, Sau96I and TaqI. The four enzymes that provided the most clearly visible and polymorphic restriction fragments were selected: HaeIII (5′-GG↓CC-3′), HpaII (C↓CGG), Sau96I (G↓GNCC) and TaqI (T↓CGA).  ITS PCR–RFLP patterns achieved with each restriction enzyme (RE) among the studied Fagaceae species ( Quercus  infrageneric groups in parentheses).  An individual analysis was performed in  Castanea  and  Fagus  genera, and each  Quercus  infrageneric group ( Cerris ,  Ilex ,  Lobatae  and  Quercus ) for the size (bp) of the monomorphic ( M ) and polymorphic ( P ) bands, and the polymorphism percentage (% P ) detected per RE. The unique (U) bands were evaluated among the six studied taxa.  Whenever the RFLP assay returns bands whose summed lengths exceed the uncut product, the presence of dissimilar loci in a genome is implied, reflecting the existence of sequence variants. In fact,  Redecker  et al.  (1997)  suggested that when the restriction patterns indicate the presence of two sets of sequences, because the overall length of the fragments is much larger than the original, uncut PCR product, this must be attributed to sequence heterogeneity.  Genetic diversity analyses based on the pool of the RFLP data produced with the four REs, performed in  Castanea  and  Fagus  genera, and each  Quercus  infrageneric group ( Cerris ,  Ilex ,  Lobatae  and  Quercus ): total number of RFLP bands ( T ); number of polymorphic bands ( P ); percentage of polymorphism (% P ); Nei's expected heterozygosity ( H  E ,  Nei 1973 ); and Shannon's information index ( I ).  The expected heterozygosity ( H  E ) was 0.2031 in the family Fagaceae (Table  4 ), with averages of 0.1512 among the three genera and 0.2013 among the four  Quercus  infrageneric groups (calculations from Table  4  data). The total diversity of the patterns, measured using Shannon's diversity index ( I ), was 0.3297. Despite the low values exhibited for all taxa, Shannon's diversity index varied according to the  H  E . In the  Quercus  infrageneric groups, this index was similar in  Cerris ,  Ilex  and  Quercus  (∼0.34). The much lower value in  Lobatae  (0.2008) was probably due to the geographic isolation of the American oaks. Overall, such relationships were reflected in the dendrogram (Fig.  1 ). These genetic diversity results are also consistent with those presented by  Quijada  et al.  (1998)  and  Carvalho  et al.  (2009)  using the same molecular marker technique with some of the restriction enzymes used here. Such low levels of heterozygosity might be due to the co-dominant nature of these markers.  The pool of the ITS PCR–RFLP data was used to construct an UPGMA dendrogram of genetic similarity among the 30 Fagaceae species under study in order to estimate their phylogenetic relationships based on these alternative co-dominant markers (Fig.  1 ). The high correlation coefficient ( r  = 0.89) ensured that the UPGMA clustering of the 30 Fagaceae species is an accurate representation of the data matrix, with 36 % total genetic similarity. Considering a cut-off value of 0.76, the dendrogram may be divided into six major clusters that correspond to each one of the four  Quercus  infrageneric groups ( Cerris  [Cluster I],  Ilex  [Cluster II],  Quercus  [Cluster III] and  Lobatae  [Cluster IV]) and to  Fagus  (Cluster V) and  Castanea  (Cluster VI) genera (Fig.  1 ). The genetic similarity among the 24  Quercus  species was 0.57, confirming the moderate ITS PCR–RFLP polymorphisms visualized on the agarose gels (data not shown). The bootstrap analysis also corroborated several clusters at different taxonomic levels (Fig.  1 ). Although correctly clustered in the  Quercus  genus along with the other 19 oaks, five oaks ( Q. coccifera ,  Q. phillyraeoides ,  Q. pyrenaica ,  Q. robur , and  Q. suber ) were not clustered according to the taxonomic infrageneric group. All of these oaks amplified a unique ITS1-5.8-ITS2 band and clustered among others with similar distribution areas, suggesting that such ITS PCR–RFLP resemblances could be due to the sharing of earlier ancestors.  Cluster I included oaks from the  Cerris  group, with only  Q. suber  excluded. Hybrids (particularly those occurring in the overlapping limits of the species distribution areas) tend to coexist with the parental species if these new intermediate genotypes have characters more suitable for the environmental circumstances. In fact, a genetic similarity of 96 % was found between  Q. crenata  and the parent  Q. cerris , with only 66 % similarity between  Q. suber  and the former two.  Bellarosa  et al.  (2005)  reported a contradictory result, with higher proximity between  Q. crenata  and  Q. suber . Such a circumstance may be attributed to the molecular markers' potential for the fingerprinting of natural hybrids. With respect to the uniparental inherited cpDNA,  Muir and Schlötterer (2006)  suggested that some areas of the hybrid genome could escape from selection towards species integrity. Despite the biparental inheritance of rDNA, homogenization of the entire rDNA arrays towards one parental type could take place in hybrids. Our results were similar to those of  Conte  et al.  (2007) , who emphasized that despite being auto-allogamous, ‘asymmetrical backcrossing’ of  Q. crenata  in a mixed population could lead the hybrid progeny towards the predominant parental species. Although in a different context, the hypothesis of ‘directed’ introgression was also noted by  Casas  et al.  (2007)  for the difficulties encountered in finding ‘morphologically identifiable hybrids' between  Q. coccifera  and other  Quercus  species (except for  Q. ilex ). In our work,  Q. coccifera  (group  Ilex ) was included in Cluster I, separately from the other oaks of the same group. Taxonomically, this was a surprising clustering. It was also surprising in the molecular sense, since the large number of cpDNA haplotypes shared between  Q. ilex  and  Q. coccifera  led  Jiménez  et al.  (2004)  to suggest that both species might experience incomplete lineage sorting or hybridization.  Denk and Grimm (2010)  found ‘zero distance’ based on complete ITS sequencing, and  Coutinho  et al.  (2014)  found significant genetic similarity between  Q. ilex  and  Q. coccifera  using inter simple sequence repeats (ISSRs). If  Q. coccifera  clustered near  Q. libani  (Group  Cerris ), and since their distribution overlaps in the Mediterranean region, it is possible that both rDNAs experienced the same evolutionary pressures during speciation. In short, even if not in total agreement with the adopted taxonomy, both Clusters I and II are supported by the sharing of morphological (not homoplastic) and ecological features between the  Cerris  and  Ilex  groups.  Cluster II included two species from the  Ilex  group,  Q. ilex  and  Q. ilex  subsp.  rotundifolia , and  Q. robur  from the  Quercus  group, with the three species exhibiting a Mediterranean-based distribution. The proximity between  Q. ilex  and  Q. ilex  subsp.  rotundifolia  may be due to rDNA array homogenization that preceded the speciation event. Nonetheless,  Q. ilex  and  Q. robur  share the natural hybrid  Q. turneri  Willd. A slow ‘molecular drive’ ( Dover 1982 ,  1986 ) could explain such proximity; being Mediterranean species, both might have experienced similar adaptive conditions. Mutations, insertions or deletions are the changes in the recognition sites needed to explain the presence in this cluster of  Q. robur  ( Quercus  group), the oak-type of the ‘roburoid oaks’.  Constituting a single branch in Cluster III, the  Q. phillyraeoides  ( Ilex  group) only shares a Southwest Asia distribution with the  Quercus  group oaks. In a previous study using ISSRs, this species was clustered in the  Ilex g roup ( Coutinho  et al.  2014 ).  Quercus phillyraeoides  exhibited two specific patterns revealed by the HpaII and TaqI enzymes, and shared patterns (produced by HaeIII) with two oaks from the  Quercus  group that dictated its inclusion in this cluster. The remaining species included in Cluster III are oaks from the  Quercus  group, with the exception of  Q. suber  ( Cerris  group). Similar clustering was recently found based on ISSRs ( Coutinho  et al.  2014 ).  Quercus suber  could have originated in the Middle East ( Bellarosa  et al.  2005  and references therein) and expanded westward ( Lumaret  et al.  2005 ). This feature could somehow explain its clustering along with oaks nowadays distributed throughout Eurasia. Regarding the inter-fertile  Q. robur  and  Q. petraea  (the two predominant white oaks in deciduous European forests),  Muir  et al.  (2001)  could not differentiate these based on ITS sequencing, and suggested that the split between the two may be too recent for rDNA to have diverged. Nevertheless, despite being in different clusters, the existing differences in the recognition sites allowed the ITS-RFLP markers to distinguish the two species.  Quercus serrata  was not included in the studies of  Denk and Grimm (2009 ,  2010 ) on the infrageneric classification of the  Quercus  genus. In our work, it clustered along with oaks from the  Quercus  group. This broad-leaved deciduous oak is widespread in the forests of eastern Asia, and was classified as belonging to the  Lepidobalanus  section ( Camus 1938–39 ) along with the following:  Q. faginea  (subsection  Gallifera );  Q. petraea  and  Q. pubescens  (both subsection  Sessiliflorae );  Q. robur  (subsection  Pedunculatae ); and  Q. ilex  (subsection  Ilex ). With the exception of  Q. ilex  ( Ilex  group), all these species were classified as the infrageneric  Quercus  group (based on the taxonomy adopted for this work). In this sense, we included this oak in the  Quercus  group and interpreted the dendrogram result as adequate clustering.  All the American oaks ( Lobatae  group) were grouped in Cluster IV, suggesting that their geographic isolation led the ITS rDNA region in a different evolutionary direction from the European or Asian oaks. Even  Q. kelloggii , which exhibits morphological features distinct from all other lobed-leaf eastern oak species ( Nixon 2002 ), was clustered accordingly. Strangely, the Southern European  Q. pyrenaica  ( Quercus  group) shares four RFLP patterns with North American oaks, and thus appears in this cluster. The molecular similarity in the ITS sequences of some European and North American oaks from the  Quercus  group ( Denk and Grimm 2010 ) and the pollen characteristics found in fossil sediments have highlighted the importance of Iceland as a ‘North Atlantic land bridge’ before and even after the intercontinental disjunctions of northern temperate trees ( Denk  et al.  2010 ). Also, oak migrations between North America and East Asia via the Bering land bridge were suggested due to the presence, in East Asia and Europe, of leaves and pollen fossil records with characteristics similar to the  Lobatae  group oaks ( Denk  et al.  2012 ). Nevertheless, despite depending only on short recognition sites, the ITS PCR–RFLP clustered all the American oaks in a single cluster. The inclusion of  Q. pyrenaica  could be due to mutations in these four or five nucleotide sequences, but it was remarkable that all patterns were shared with American oaks.  The species from the  Castanea  and  Fagus  genera were grouped in independent clusters (Fig.  1 ). The three  Castanea  species belong to the  Eucastanon  section and constitute Cluster V. High similarity was detected between the Chinese and the European chestnuts, resembling the results achieved by  Lang  et al.  (2006 ,  2007 ). Those authors suggested that the Japanese  Castanea crenata  holds a basal position in the genus phylogeny, and that Eastern Asia could have constituted the centre of diversification towards the east (China and Japan), followed later by the invasion heading to the west, promoting Chinese and European species divergence.  The three beeches studied here from the species  Fagus japonica  and  F. sylvatica , belonging to the  Engleriana  and  Fagus  subgenera, respectively, were clustered in Cluster VI and showed 15 % genetic dissimilarity (Fig.  1 ). As expected, the genetic similarity was higher between the two  F. sylvatica  species than among those and  F. japonica . The ITS PCR–RFLP data revealed 34 % of genetic similarity among the  Fagus  species and the remaining Fagaceae. Interestingly, the major differences in the ITS regions among  Fagus  species are located within the shorter ITS2 region (despite the relatively higher GC content that could promote higher sequence stability) ( Denk  et al.  2002 ), while the major differences between the  Fagus  genus and other Fagaceae are located in the larger ITS1 ( Manos  et al.  2001 ;  Denk and Grimm 2010 ).  Bar plot constructed with the software STRUCTURE based on the pool of ITS PCR–RFLP data and inferred by Bayesian clustering analysis. Each coloured segment corresponds to the proportion of individuals assigned to a hypothetical population or cluster. Successive preset  K  values were calculated under the admixture model and the option of correlated allele frequencies, allowing the degree of admixture alpha to be inferred from the data. Only the  K  = 6 clustering (sorted by the original order) is shown, once it was determined as the most likely according to  Pritchard  et al . (2010) .  The genetic structure analysis provided fixation index ( F  ST ) values that suggested high levels of differentiation (&gt;0.50) for five clusters, corresponding to the  Castanea  genus (0.59),  Fagus  genus (0.61),  Cerris  group (0.51),  Lobatae  group (0.76) and  Quercus  group (0.5862). The sixth cluster, corresponding to the infrageneric  Ilex  group, revealed a reduced genetic differentiation value ( F  ST  = 0.26), sustaining the dispersion of these oaks through the dendrogram. The bar plot showed that four oaks of the  Ilex  group and one oak ( Q. robur ) of the  Quercus  group seemed to share some ancient genetic material with the  Castanea  genus. It is assumed that both  Quercus  and  Castanea  genera share an ancient origin, and the fact that these oaks have a narrow distribution area might have contributed to the conservation of such similarities and the lack of higher genetic fixation (as observed for the other species/groups). In the bar plot, it is apparent that three out of four  Ilex  individuals share material with the  Cerris  group, confirming the 0.74 genetic similarity between these groups found in the dendrogram (Fig.  1 ). The high  F  ST  value for  Fagus  species suggested a defined ITS genetic structure and confirmed the ITS divergence from the other taxa. In the dendrogram,  Q. phillyraeoides  and  Q. suber  were clustered along with oaks of the  Quercus  group, and the bar plot suggested their high similarity. The same occurred between  Q. pyrenaica  ( Quercus  group) and oaks from the  Lobatae  group. Also, the  Lobatae  group was found to be the most genetically fixed, which could be explained by their ancient isolation in North America.  The genetic identities and genetic distances (calculated using POPGENE and the ITS PCR–RFLP pool data, data not shown) of the three genera and four  Quercus  infrageneric groups supported most of these results.  Quercus  and  Castanea  genera were evaluated to be more intimately related to each other (0.82) than to  Fagus  (0.69 and 0.64, respectively). The genetic relations in the infrageneric groups seem to resemble their geographical distributions:  Lobatae  exhibited the highest genetic distance relative to  Cerris ,  Ilex  and  Quercus  (0.153, 0.224 and 0.171, respectively);  Cerris  and  Ilex  were the most related (0.962); and  Quercus  revealed similar proximities to both  Cerris  (0.947) and  Ilex  (0.960).  This study of ITS genotaxonomy intended to evaluate the potential of the ITS-PCR–RFLP markers for inferences about the Fagaceae family taxonomy, particularly in the  Quercus  genus. In phylogenetics, given the stability of the sequence of the 5.8S rRNA gene, the main use of the ITS1-5.8S-ITS2 region has been for comparing the sequence of the two spacers. When using restriction enzymes, in which accuracy resides in short recognition sites defined by four or five nucleotides, even a single-nucleotide mutational event may constrain the final result. Nonetheless, the conservation of those enzyme cutting sites in closely related species may allow the use of RFLP patterns to make inferences about phylogenies. Indeed, according to the adopted taxonomy, correct clustering was observed for (i) the 30 individuals per genus, (ii) 19 of the 24 oaks per  Quercus  infrageneric group (almost 80 % accuracy) and (iii) 22 oaks per ecological area of distribution (&gt;91 % accuracy). One must assume that site variability may distort the phylogenetic analysis, but our results and the advantages of cost-effectiveness, time consumption and higher discriminative power (especially between species with morphological similarities) suggest the effectiveness and utility of these markers for taxonomic discrimination in Fagaceae.  This work was supported by the PhD grant  SFRH/BD/42837/2008  awarded by the  Portuguese Foundation for Science and Technology (FCT)  and, partially, by the  Institute of Biotechnology and Bioengineering—Centre of Genomics and Biotechnology of the University of Tras-os-Montes  and  Alto Douro IBB-CGB/UTAD .  J.P.C. performed the practical work at the laboratory and analysed the results; J.P.C., A.C. and J.L.-B. contributed to the analysis and discussion of the results and to the writing of the manuscript.  None declared.  The authors are very grateful to the botanical gardens (Table  1 ) for providing the seeds used in our work. 