 Multiple shoot induction from axillary bud cultures of the medicinal orchid,  Dendrobium longicornu   Orchid diversity in North-East India  Micropropagation of orchids: a review on the potential of different explants   In vitro  propagation and conservation of  Dendrobium lituiflorum  Lindl. through protocorm-like bodies   In vitro  propagation of  Dendrobium  hybrids through shoot tip and axillary bud culture  Conservation of splendid orchids of North-East India  Optimization of nutrient requirements for asymbiotic seed germination of  Dendrobium longicornu  Lindl. and  D. formosum  Roxb  Stem disc culture: development of a rapid mass propagation method of  Dendrobium moschatum  (Buch-Ham) Swartz—an endangered orchid  Hormones in the nutrition of orchid tissues in mericloning  Shoot tip culture of  Dendrobium   Direct shoot regeneration from nodes of  Phalaenopsis  orchids  Propagation of two  Dendrobium  species by  in vitro  culture  Orchids: the world's most wondrous plants  Effects of combinations of growth regulators and some supplements on the growth of  Cattleya  plantlets cultured  in vitro   Micropropagation of  Dendrobium densiflorum  Lindl. ex Wall. through protocorm-like bodies: effects of plant growth regulators and lanthanoids  A survey of medicinal plants of Jajarkot District, Nepal  A revised medium for rapid growth and bio-assays with tobacco tissue cultures  Protocorm like bodies and plantlet regeneration from  Dendrobium formosum  leaf callus  An effective nutrient medium for asymbiotic seed germination and large-scale  in vitro  regeneration of  Dendrobium hookerianum , a threatened orchid of northeast India  Induction of callus and plant regeneration from shoot-tip explants of  Dendrobium fimbriatum  Lindl. var. oculatum Hk. F  Micropropagation of  Dendrobium  Joannie Ostenhault  Regeneration capacity of  in vitro  cultured leaf segments excised from mature  Phalaenopsis  plants  Plantlet regeneration of  Pinus kesiya  Royle ex. Gord. from mature embryos  Micropropagation of  Spathoglottis plicata   Clonal propagation of orchids  Micropropagation of  Phalaenopsis  and  Doritaenopsis  by culturing shoot tips of flower stalk buds  Micropropagation of therapeutically important orchids:  Malaxis acuminata   Micropropagation of  Dendrobium chrysanthum , through pseudobulb segments   In vitro  pseudobulb segment culture—a means for rapid clonal propagation of  Dendrobium moschatum  (Orchidaceae)  Mycorrhizal association in North Indian Orchidaceae: a morphological study  On the regeneration competence of  Coelogyne viscosa  pseudobulb explants  Regeneration competence of  Bulbophyllum careyanum  (Hook.) Spreng. pseudobulb segments  High-frequency shoot regeneration through transverse thin cell layer culture in  Dendrobium candidum  Wall Ex Lindl  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  The present investigation was undertaken to propagate  D. longicornu , a medicinally important orchid using axillary bud segments. This approach could also help in conserving other threatened orchids as well.   Dendrobium longicornu , commonly known as the ‘Long-horned  Dendrobium ’, is an endangered and medicinally important epiphytic orchid. Over-exploitation and habitat destruction seriously threaten this orchid in Northeast India. Our objective was to develop an efficient protocol for the mass propagation of  D. longicornu  using axillary bud segments.  Axillary buds cultured in Murashige and Skoog semi-solid medium supplemented with α-naphthalene acetic acid (NAA), 2,4-dichlorophenoxy acetic acid (2,4-D) and 6-benzylaminopurine (BAP) readily developed into plantlets. These formed either directly from shoot buds or from intermediary protocorm-like bodies (PLBs). The maximum explant response (86.6 %) was obtained in medium supplemented with NAA at 30 µM, while the maximum number of shoots (4.42) and maximum bud-forming capacity (3.51) were observed in medium containing 15 µM BAP and 5 µM NAA in combination. Protocorm-like bodies were obtained when the medium contained 2,4-D. The maximum number of explants forming PLBs (41.48 %) was obtained in medium containing 15 µM BAP and 15 µM 2,4-D. Well-developed plantlets obtained after 20–25 weeks of culture were acclimatized and eventually transferred to the greenhouse. Over 60 % of these survived to form plants ∼3–4 cm tall after 90 days in glasshouse conditions using a substrate of crushed brick and charcoal, shredded bark and moss.  The method described can readily be used for the rapid and large-scale regeneration of  D. longicornu . Its commercial adoption would reduce the collection of this medicinally important and increasingly rare orchid from the wild.    In vitro  propagation of  D. longicornu  from 3- to 4-mm- long nodal explants.  (A) Mature plant in the natural habitat. (B) Initiation of PLBs on explants cultured on MS medium containing 15 µM BAP and 15 µM 2,4-D for 15 days (bar = 1 cm). (C) Initiation of shoots from an axillary bud on medium containing 5 µM BAP and 15 µM NAA in 15 days (bar = 1 cm). (D) As in (C) but after 30 days (bar = 1 cm). (E) Rooted plantlets after 70 days in culture. (F) Hardened plantlets after 90 days.  Nodal explants of  D. longicornu  were obtained from plants maintained in the net house of the Plant Biotechnology Laboratory, Department of Botany, North-Eastern Hill University, Shillong, India. Stem explants (∼1–2 cm long), each comprising a node and axillary bud, were cleaned by gently scrubbing with a soft brush and mild detergent, washed in running tap water for 15–20 min and rinsed with distilled water. The explants were surface sterilized with 10 % (v/v) NaClO solution (4–6 % available chlorine; Merck) for 10 min followed by 0.1 % (w/v) HgCl 2  (HiMedia) for 2 min. After washing 5–6 times with sterilized distilled water, the explants were shortened to 3–4 mm after the removal of leaves, dry sheaths and other external tissues. These were then cultured in Murashige and Skoog (MS) medium ( Murashige and Skoog 1962 ) containing 3 % sucrose (HiMedia), 0.8 % agar (HiMedia) and supplemented with the growth regulators α-naphthalene acetic acid (NAA), 2,4-dichlorophenoxy acetic acid (2,4-D) and 6-benzyl-aminopurine (BAP) using a range of concentrations between 0 and 50 µM, and in various combinations. The aim was to optimize the formation of protocorm-like bodies (PLBs) and shoot buds in the cultured explants. The cultures were incubated at 25 ± 2 °C under a 12-h photoperiod of 50 μmol m −2  s −1  photon flux density. There were 10 replicates of each treatment and all experiments were repeated three times. Observations were made after 45 days of culture. Well-developed plantlets with roots were obtained in the same induction medium on being left undisturbed. After 20–25 weeks of culture these plantlets were transferred to perforated ‘Thermocol’ or propylene plastic pots (10 × 7 cm size) containing a range of composts: (i) crushed brick and charcoal (1 : 1); (ii) crushed brick and charcoal (1 : 1) + a top layer of moss; (iii) crushed brick and charcoal, and decaying litter (1 : 1 : 1); (iv) crushed brick and charcoal, and decaying litter (1 : 1 : 1) + a top layer of moss; (v) crushed brick and charcoal, and shredded bark (1 : 1 : 1); (vi) crushed brick and charcoal chunks, and shredded bark (1 : 1 : 1) + a top layer of moss. Sixty plantlets were grown in each of these composts in the greenhouse, covered with a pierced polythene bag for 3 weeks, and sprayed with water to inhibit dehydration. The temperature was maintained at 24 ± 2 °C, and relative humidity at 70–80 %. Plantlets were irrigated with 1/10 strength MS medium solution every 2 days for 2 weeks. Plants were assessed after 90 days.  The data were subjected to statistical analysis using one-way analysis of variance and comparisons between the mean values of treatments were made by Fisher's least significant difference (LSD) test ( Fisher 1935 ). For a more realistic determination of the efficacy of a given treatment, regeneration of shoot buds from axillary buds was calculated as the bud-forming capacity (BFC) using the formula ( Tandon  et al . 2007 ): BFC = (average number of buds per explant × % of explants forming buds)/100.  Effect of growth regulators incorporated singly in MS medium on formation of shoot buds and PLBs.  *Values are the mean ± SE. Means followed by the same letter in the column are not significantly different as indicated by Fisher's LSD ( P  = 0.05).  Effect of growth regulators in combination in MS medium on formation of shoot buds and PLBs.  *Values are the mean ± SE. Means followed by the same letter in the column are not significantly different as indicated by Fisher's LSD ( P  = 0.05).  Re-establishment of D. longicornu plantlets after 90 days of hardening under the greenhouse conditions.  Values represent the means ± SE.  Means of 60 plantlets per substrate were taken and the experiments were repeated three times.  The supply of growth regulators promoted the production of shoots from the axillary buds of nodal explants cultured on MS medium. This is probably an outcome of the habituated nature and juvenility of axillary buds. The juvenility of tissues is thought to be an important factor controlling cell proliferation in several orchids ( Vij and Pathak 1989 ;  Arditti and Ernst 1993 ;  Vij  et al . 1997 ). The axillary buds of  D. longicornu  explants responded differently to the two auxins NAA and 2,4-D. Shoot buds and PLBs were seen emerging from the explants given 2,4-D. Such a varying response in the form of shoot buds/PLBs has been attributed to the genetic and/or source-related physiological intricacies ( Vij  et al . 2000 ). In  D. longicornu , the maximum number of shoots generated from each explant was recorded in medium supplemented with 30 µM NAA.  Vij and Kaur (1998)  also reported similar results where NAA-enriched medium favoured multiple shoot bud formation in  Malaxis acuminata . Similarly, there are earlier reports on accentuated regeneration potential of  Dendrobium moschatum  pseudobulb explants ( Vij and Sood 1982 ). In the present study, the regeneration pathway to shoot formation was directly through shoot bud formation and also through PLBs. When present, PLB formation was mostly restricted to media containing 2,4-D. The suitability of 2,4-D for both callusing and PLB formation in the case of  Dendrobium  has been reported previously ( Kanjilal  et al . 1999 ;  Nasiruddin  et al . 2003 ;  Das  et al.  2008 ). On the other hand, the incorporation of BAP in the medium promoted only the formation of shoot buds not PLBs. The activation of meristematic activity in explants by BAP has been found by others to be obligatory for the development of multiple shoot buds ( Vij  et al . 2000 ;  Kosir  et al . 2004 ).  In the present study, the response of explants to BAP in combination with auxins (NAA and 2,4-D) differed according to concentration.  Tokuhara and Mii (1993)  reported that the combination of hormones was of key importance for the micropropagation of  Phalaenopsis . A stimulatory effect of BAP and NAA together in the medium has been reported for certain species of orchids before ( Kosir  et al . 2004 ). While some authors have reported reduced induction and regeneration in medium supplemented with NAA ( Arditti and Ernst 1993 ), others reported that an appropriate combination of NAA and BAP stimulated shoot formation ( Tokuhara and Mii 1993 ;  Tisserat and Jones 1999 ;  Roy and Banerjee 2003 ). Similar results were also obtained in our study wherein a maximum number of shoots and BFC were recorded in medium containing a combination of BAP (5 µM) and NAA (15 µM). The interactions of BAP with 2,4-D induced both PLBs and shoot buds from cultured axillary buds.  Kusumoto (1979)  had reported multiple PLB formation in  Cattleya  with kinetin (KN)/BAP in combination with 2,4-D. Although some authors reported the induction of shoot buds without the intervention of callus and PLBs ( Devi  et al.  1998 ), others have reported the formation of PLBs from different explants ( Kim  et al . 1970 ;  Sharon and Vasundhara 1990 ). Since many orchid species require auxins and/or cytokinins for shoot and PLB formation ( Arditti and Ernst 1993 ), the combination, concentrations and the ratio between them are critically important. In the present study, the explant response in terms of PLB induction was highest in the medium supplemented with 2,4-D or NAA in combination with BAP at the same concentrations (15 μM). The response of the explants to PLB formation varies from species to species and from explant to explant used ( Teng  et al . 1997 ). A high ratio (12.2) of NAA to BAP in  Spathoglottis plicata  was reported to be best for the induction of PLBs from nodal explants ( Teng  et al . 1997 ). However, a low ratio of NAA to BAP, 0.12 in the case of  Phalaenopsis amabilis  ( Tanaka and Sakanishi 1985 ) and 0.42 in  Dendrobium antennatum , was reported to be suitable ( Kukulczanka and Wojciechowska 1983 ). Also, in several hybrid species of  Aranda , a ratio of 1.23 for NAA to BAP has been found to be most effective ( Khaw  et al . 1978 ).  The survivability of the micropropagated plantlets on being transferred to pots depends on their proper acclimatization.  Dendrobium longicornu  is epiphytic in nature and the substratum should reflect this by combining water-holding capacity with good drainage. Crushed charcoal and brick pieces were therefore adopted as the basis for the six compost mixes we tested. The highest survival levels (over 60 %) were achieved when this combination was augmented with shredded bark or decaying litter plus a covering layer of moss for water retention ( Dohling  et al . 2008 ).   In vitro  multiplication of orchids makes an effective contribution to saving rare species from extinction. This is the first report of a successful and efficient protocol for  in vitro  propagation of the threatened medicinally useful epiphytic orchid  D. longicornu . The method uses nodal explants with an axillary bud cultured  in vitro  on MS semi-solid medium supplemented with the cytokinin BAP and the auxin 2,4-D, each at 15 μM. Regeneration of viable rooted shoots is mediated by combination of direct shoot bud formation and indirectly via PLBs. The technique is likely to be widely applicable but the growth regulator component may need adjustment depending on the species, and the physiological state and nutrient environment of the source material.  Financial support received from the  Department of Biotechnology, Government of India  vide grant No.  BT/PR2321/SPD/11/199/2001  is gratefully acknowledged.  All the authors contributed to the same extent overall and have seen and agreed to the submitted manuscript.  None declared. 