Effects of a native parasitic plant on an exotic invader decrease with increasing host agePhenotypic plasticity in seedling defense strategies: compensatory growth and chemical inductionOntogenetic patterns in the mechanisms of tolerance to herbivory in <italic>Plantago</italic>The ontogeny of plant defense and herbivory: characterizing general patterns using meta-analysisInfluence of plant ontogeny on compensation to leaf damagePlant quality and predation risk mediated by plant ontogeny: consequences for herbivores and plantsInteractions between woody plants and browsing mammals mediated by secondary metabolitesNitrogen relations of the sorghum-Sfriga hermonthica hostparasite association: growth and photosynthesisAge-dependent effects of jasmonic acid treatment and wind exposure on foliar oxidase activity and insect resistance in tomatoBioactive compounds in <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> L. populations: a key step in the standardization of phytopharmaceutical preparationsCompetition- and resource-mediated tradeoffs between growth and defensive chemistry in trembling aspen (<italic>Populus tremuloides</italic>)Comparative water use and nitrogen relationships in a mistletoe and its hostPlant ontogeny and chemical defence: older seedlings are better defended<italic>Conostegia xalapensis</italic> (Melastomataceae): an aluminum accumulator plantContrasting ontogenetic trajectories for phenolic and terpenoid defences in <italic>Eucalyptus froggattii</italic>Biomass allocation and growth responses of Scots pine saplings to simulated herbivory depend on plant age and light availabilityOntogenetic changes in leaf traits of tropical rainforest trees differing in juvenile light requirementThe content analysis of total alkaloids in a rare and extincted plant <italic>Sinocalycanthus chinensis</italic>Content of total flavonoids and total chlorogenic acid in the endangered plant <italic>Sinocalycanthus chinensis</italic> and their correlations with the environmental factorsDefense response of resistant host <italic>Impatiens balsamina</italic> to the parasitic angiosperm <italic>Cuscuta japonica</italic>Analysis and determination of total saponin content in an endangered plant <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic>Comparison of the total tannin in different organs of <italic>Calycanthus chinensis</italic>Do native parasitic plants cause more damage to exotic invasive hosts than native non-invasive hosts? An implication for biocontrolShort-term parasite-infection alters already the biomass, activity and functional diversity of soil microbial communitiesEffect of nitrogen limitation on foliar antioxidants in relationship to other metabolic characteristicsImpact of eastern dwarf mistletoe (<italic>Arceuthobium pusillum</italic>) on host white spruce (<italic>Picea glauca</italic>) development, growth and performance across multiple scalesDefoliation increases carbon limitation in ectomycorrhizal symbiosis of <italic>Betula pubescens</italic>Ontogenetic differences of herbivory on woody and herbaceous plants: a meta-analysis demonstrating unique effects of herbivory on the young and the old, the slow and the fastIntegrated responses of hydraulic architecture, water and carbon relations of western hemlock to dwarf mistletoe infectionLimited by the host: host age hampers establishment of holoparasite <italic>Cuscuta epithymum</italic>Relative tolerance of rainy season crops to field dodder (<italic>Cuscuta campestris</italic>) and its management in niger (<italic>Guizotia abyssinica</italic>)Optimal defense theory predicts the ontogeny of an induced nicotine defenseGrowth and chemical defense in willow seedlings: trade-offs are transientOpposing effects of native and exotic herbivores on plant invasionsDracula or Robin Hood? A functional role for root hemiparasites in nutrient poor ecosystemsEffects of insect herbivory on induced chemical defences and compensation during early plant development in <italic>Penstemon virgatus</italic>De novo assembly and characterization of the transcriptome of the parasitic weed dodder identifies genes associated with plant parasitismThe effect of tree height and light availability on photosynthetic leaf traits of four neotropical species differing in shade toleranceDevelopmental variation in resistance and tolerance in a multi-host-parasite systemVolatile chemical cues guide host location and host selection by parasitic plantsParasitism by <italic>Cuscuta pentagona</italic> sequentially induces JA and SA defence pathways in tomatoCyanogenesis in <italic>Turnera ulmifolia</italic> L. (Turneraceae). II. Developmental expression, heritability and cost of cyanogenesisBasal area growth impacts of dwarf mistletoe on western hemlock in an old-growth forestGrowth but not photosynthesis response of a host plant to infection by a holoparasitic plant depends on nitrogen supplyThe influence of plant age on tolerance of rice to injury by the rice water weevil, <italic>Lissorhoptrus oryzophilus</italic> (Coleoptera: Curculionidae)The evolutionary ecology of tolerance to consumer damageEffects of the parasite plant (<italic>Cistanche deserticola</italic>) on growth and biomass of the host plant (<italic>Haloxylon ammodendron</italic>)Compensation for herbivory by <italic>Cucumis sativus</italic> through increased photosynthetic capacity and efficiencyOntogenetic changes in tolerance to herbivory in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Specificity of induced plant responses to specialist herbivores of the common milkweed <italic>Asclepias syriaca</italic>Effect of the parasitic <italic>Cuscuta australis</italic> on the community diversity and the growth of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>Chemical and physical plant defence across multiple ontogenetic stages in a tropical rain forest understorey treeFactors restraining parasitism of the invasive vine <italic>Mikania micrantha</italic> by the holoparasitic plant <italic>Cuscuta campestris</italic>Host plant resistance to parasitic weeds; recent progress and bottlenecksHoloparasitic <italic>Cuscuta campestris</italic> suppresses invasive <italic>Mikania micrantha</italic> and contributes to native community recoveryNative <italic>Cuscuta campestris</italic> restrains exotic <italic>Mikania micrantha</italic> and enhances soil resources beneficial to natives in the invaded communities<italic>Cuscuta australis</italic> restrains three exotic invasive plants and benefits native speciesEffect of differing levels parasitism from native <italic>Cuscuta australis</italic> on invasive <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> growthEffects of nutrients on the growth of the parasitic plant <italic>Cuscuta australis</italic> R.Br.<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> James F. CahillThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Infection by parasitic plants has been considered as an effective method for controlling invasive plants because the parasites partially or completely absorb water, nutrients, and carbohydrates from their host plants, suppressing the vitality of the host. Our study verified that younger and smaller <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> plants suffer from higher levels of damage and are less likely to recover from infection by the parasitic plant <italic>Cuscuta australis</italic> than relatively older and larger plants, suggesting that <italic>Cuscuta australis</italic> is only a viable biocontrol agent for younger <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> plants.Understanding changes in the interactions between parasitic plants and their hosts in relation to ontogenetic changes in the hosts is crucial for successful use of parasitic plants as biological controls. We investigated growth, photosynthesis and chemical defences in different-aged <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> plants in response to infection by <italic>Cuscuta australis</italic>. We were particularly interested in whether plant responses to parasite infection change with changes in the host plant age. Compared with the non-infected <italic>B. pilosa</italic>, parasite infection reduced total host biomass and net photosynthetic rates, but these deleterious effects decreased with increasing host age. Parasite infection reduced the concentrations of total phenolics, total flavonoids and saponins in the younger <italic>B. pilosa</italic> but not in the older <italic>B. pilosa</italic>. Compared with the relatively older and larger plants, younger and smaller plants suffered from more severe damage and are likely less to recover from the infection, suggesting that <italic>C. australis</italic> is only a viable biocontrol agent for younger <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants.A parasitic plant is a type of angiosperm (flowering plant) that directly attaches to another plant via a haustorium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C58">Press 1998</xref>). Over 4500 known plant species are parasitic to some extent and acquire some or all of their water, carbon and nutrients from a host (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C58">Press 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C23">Li <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). Parasitic plants are classified as stem or root parasites including facultative, hemiparasitic and holoparasitic forms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C52">Yoder and Scholes 2010</xref>).Infection by parasitic plants has been considered as an effective method for controlling invasive plants because the parasites partially (hemiparasites) or completely (holoparasites) absorb water, nutrients and carbohydrates from their host plants, suppressing the vitality of the host (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C33">Parker <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C53">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C54">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C22">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). For example, the holoparasite <italic>Cuscuta australis</italic>, native to China, can inhibit the growth of <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic>, an invasive plant in China, and thus serve as an effective biological control agent for controlling the invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C56">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C57">2013</xref>). Compared with the effects of feeding by herbivores, the defence responses of plants infected by parasitic plants have rarely been studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C38">Runyon <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C35">Ranjan <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>), even though such knowledge is important for the successful use of parasitic plants as enemies against invasive plants.It has been documented that plant defences to herbivore or pathogen damage vary with a plant's ontogenetic stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C5">Boege and Marquis 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C3">Barton and Koricheva 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C47">Tucker and Avila-Sakar 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C2">Barton 2013</xref>). The ontogenetic patterns of plant defences were found to differ with plant life form (woody, herbaceous and grass, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C3">Barton and Koricheva 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C27">Massad 2013</xref>), growth stage (seedlings, juveniles, mature plants, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C3">Barton and Koricheva 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C16">Houter and Pons 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C2">Barton 2013</xref>), development stage (flowering stage, fruiting stage, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C47">Tucker and Avila-Sakar 2010</xref>) and growth rate (slow-growing plant and fast-growing plant, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C27">Massad 2013</xref>). For herbaceous plants, for example, young plants are normally more heavily chemically defended than older ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C8">Cipollini and Redman 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C3">Barton and Koricheva 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C27">Massad 2013</xref>). However, as expected from the resource limitation hypothesis, the smaller reserves of resources stored in younger plants may negatively influence secondary metabolites in comparison with the larger resource reserves stored in mature plants, as expected from the resource limitation hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C6">Bryant <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>). Thus, younger plants may be less defended and less able to recover after herbivory or parasitic infestation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C15">Hódar <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>).Similar to those defence reaction induced by herbivores and pathogens infection, plants may increase their chemical complexes to defend against parasitic infection through plant hormones, salicylic acid and jasmonic acid pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C39">Runyon <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). Little attention has been paid to the ontogenetic changes of invasive plants inresponse to holoparasites. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C51">Wu <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> found that <italic>Cuscuta campestris</italic> seedlings cannot parasitize the invasive <italic>Mikania micrantha</italic> if the stem diameter of the host is ≥0.3 cm. Our field investigation found that the infestation rate of plants, such as <italic>B. pilosa</italic>, <italic>Solidago canadensis</italic> and <italic>Phytolacca americana</italic>, by <italic>C. australis</italic> decreased with increasing host age (data not shown). Accordingly, we conducted an experiment to understand the host defences in relation to host age in a holoparasite–host system. The growth characteristics and the concentrations of the main chemical defences were determined in different-aged invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants infected by <italic>C. australis</italic> to test the hypothesis that younger hosts are more easily damaged and less able to recover than the older ones because the younger plants with limited resource reserves have less capacity to produce chemical defences and to promote compensatory growth. We aimed to answer the following questions: (i) Do younger and older <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants differ in their responses to infection by <italic>C. australis</italic>? (ii) Are these differences in responses are correlated with the growth of different-aged invasive host plants? The answers to these questions could provide basic scientific knowledge for using <italic>C. australis</italic> to manage the invasive plant <italic>B. pilosa</italic>.<italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> is native to the tropical America and has widely spread throughout China. It is an annual forb and can grow up to 1 m in height and produces numerous seeds every year, and it grows both in nutrient-rich and -poor soils. In November, 2009, seeds of <italic>B. pilosa</italic> were collected near Sanfeng temple (121°16′E, 28°88′N) in Linhai City, Zhejiang Province, China, and stored in a low-humidity storage cabinet (HZM-600, Beijing Biofuture Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology Development) until use.<italic>Cuscuta australis</italic>, a native annual holoparasitic plant species to South China, and is considered a noxious weed of agriculture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C55">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). It can infect a wide range of herbs and shrubs (e.g. plants in the families of Fabaceae and Asteraceae), including the invasive plants <italic>M. micrantha</italic>, <italic>Ipomoea cairica</italic>, <italic>Wedelia trilobata</italic>, <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> and <italic>Bidens</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C55">Yu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C49">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C56">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>).We conducted a greenhouse experiment at Taizhou University (121°17′E, 28°87′N) in Linhai City, Zhejiang Province, China. We sowed <italic>B. pilosa</italic> seeds in trays with sand to germinate in a greenhouse on 13 March, 22 March and 6 April 2011, to create three different-aged <italic>B. pilosa</italic> seedlings of three different ages. Approximately 20 days after sowing, <italic>B. pilosa</italic> seedlings (∼10 cm in height) were transplanted into pots (28 cm in inner diameter and 38 cm deep; 1 seedling per pot) filled with 2.5 kg yellow clay soil mixed with sand in a 2 : 1 ratio (v : v). Plant materials and stones were removed from the yellow clay soil collected from fields in Linhai. The soil mixture had a pH of 6.64 ± 0.01, with an organic matter content of 15.74 ± 2.65 g kg<sup>−1</sup>, available nitrogen of 0.27 ± 0.10 g kg<sup>−1</sup>, available phosphorus of 0.026 ± 0.004 g kg<sup>−1</sup> and available potassium of 0.049 ± 0.003 g kg<sup>−1</sup>.The pots were randomly placed in a greenhouse and irrigated with tap water twice daily. One week after transplantation, 2 g slow release fertilizer (Scotts Osmocote, N : P : K = 20 : 20 : 20, The Scotts Miracle-Gro Company, Marysville, OH, USA) was added to each pot.On 5 June, when <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants were of ages 59 days (mean height 32.0 cm and mean diameter 2.7 mm), 74 days (mean height 62.6 cm and mean diameter 5.1 mm) and 83 days old (mean height 93.3 cm and mean diameter 5.7 mm), plants were infected by <italic>C. australis</italic> manually. Three 15-cm long segments of parasitic <italic>C. australis</italic> stems collected from fields in Linhai were twined onto the stems of a <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plant to induce infection. After 24 h, most of <italic>C. australis</italic> successfully parasitized the host and died segments were substituted by new ones. For each age class, six individuals were infected and six plants were left intact as controls (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Six individuals were harvested, separated into shoots and roots, and then dried at 70 °C for 72 h, to determine the initial plant biomass (<italic>W</italic><sub>1</sub>) at the beginning of infection (<italic>t</italic><sub>1</sub>, i.e. 5 June).On 30 June 2011, i.e. after 26 days of infection, the net photosynthetic rate (<italic>P</italic><sub>n</sub>) of <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants was determined on fully expanded, mature sun leaves in the upper canopy between 10:00 and 11:30 am, using a portable photosynthesis system (LI-6400/XT, LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE, USA). For each measurement, three leaves per plant were chosen, and six consecutive measurements were performed.On 9 July 2011 (<italic>t</italic><sub>2</sub>), i.e. 35 days after infection, when <italic>C. australis</italic> was flowering and the host plants were 94, 109 and 118 days old, respectively, all plants were harvested. <italic>Cuscuta australis</italic> plants were separated from their hosts and dried at 70 °C for 72 h to determine the <italic>C. australis</italic>' biomass (<italic>B</italic><sub>c</sub>). The host plants were separated into leaves, stems and roots. Leaves, stems and roots of the host plants were dried at 70 °C for 72 h to determine their biomass (<italic>W</italic><sub>2</sub>). The relative growth rate (RGR) of biomass was calculated with the equation RGR = (ln <italic>W</italic><sub>2</sub> − ln <italic>W</italic><sub>1</sub>)/(<italic>t</italic><sub>2</sub> − <italic>t</italic><sub>1</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C13">González-Santana <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C22">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>).The dried stems of the host plants were ground using a universal high-speed grinder (F80, Xinkang Medical Instrument Co. Ltd, Jiangyan, Jiangsu). The powder was filtered through a 20-mesh sieve and stored in a drier until chemical analysis.Approximately 0.1 g of powder was extracted three times with 70 % ethanol (v/v) under reflux at 90 °C and the aqueous extract was used to measure the concentration of total phenolics and total flavonoids. The concentration of total phenolics and total flavonoids was determined using the Folin–Denis method and AlCl<sub>3</sub> reaction method according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C9">Cortés-Rojas <italic>et al</italic>. (2013)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C18">Jin <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>. Absorbance at 750 nm for total phenolics and 420 nm for total flavonoids was determined with a T6 UV–VIS spectrophotometer (Beijing Purkinje General Instrument Co. Ltd, Beijing, China). Gallic acid and rutin (purchased from National Institutes for Food and Drug Control, Beijing, China) were used as the standard for total phenolics and total flavonoids, respectively.Approximately 0.1 g of powder was extracted three times with 70 % methanol under reflux at 70 °C, and the aqueous extract was used to measure the concentration of saponins and alkaloids. The concentration of total saponins and alkaloids was determined by a colourimetric method and bromocresol green reaction method, respectively, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C20">Li <italic>et al</italic>. (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C17">Jin <italic>et al</italic>. (2006)</xref>. Absorbance at 560 nm (saponins) and 470 nm (alkaloids) was determined with a T6 UV–VIS spectrophotometer (Beijing Purkinje General Instrument Co. Ltd, Beijing, China). Ginsenosides-Re and berberin HCl (purchased from National Institutes for Food and Drug Control, Beijing, China) were used as the standard for saponins and alkaloids, respectively.Approximately 0.1 g of powder was extracted three times with boiled water and the aqueous extract was used to measure the concentration of soluble tannin via the potassium permanganate redox titrations method according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C21">Li <italic>et al</italic>. (2007)</xref>. Gallic acid (purchased from National Institutes for Food and Drug Control, Beijing, China) was used as the standard.The plastic responses (PR) of the host plants to parasite infection were calculated for all plant traits studied, using the equation PR = (VPP − MVC)/MVC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C1">Barton 2008</xref>), where VPP is the value of a trait in a parasite-infected plant and MVC is the mean value of that trait in the same-aged controls. For example, if the mean biomass of the non-parasitized <italic>B. pilosa</italic> is <italic>A</italic> and the biomass of the parasitized <italic>B. pilosa</italic> is <italic>B</italic>, then PR = (<italic>B</italic> − <italic>A</italic>)/<italic>A</italic>. Such PR values reflect the relative changes in the host traits caused by parasites. A value of PR = 0 indicates no response. A value of PR &lt; 0 indicates a negative response, whereas a value of PR &gt; 0 indicates a positive response of the host to parasite infection.The normality of the distribution and the homogeneity of the data were checked (Kolmogorov–Smirnov test) before any further statistical analysis. A two-way ANOVA was used to analyse the effects of parasitism and host age on the host traits studied, followed by a one-way ANOVA and Tukey's HSD analysis to test the difference in means within a parasite treatment and between the infected and non-infected plants. All tests were conducted at a significance level of <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 using SPSS (version 16.0).The root (A), stem (B), leaf (C) and total plant biomass (D) of different-aged invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants infected and not infected by <italic>C. australis</italic>, and the PR of the stem (E), root (F), leaf (G) and total plant biomass (H) of the infected <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants. Values are given as means +1 SD (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Asterisks in the upper panel indicate significant difference in means between non-infected and infected plants within the same age class at *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 and ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively. Different letters in the lower panel indicate significant difference between PRs (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).The biomass of parasites (A) of different-aged invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants, and the ratio of parasite biomass to host biomass (B). Values are given as means +1 SD (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Different letters indicate significant difference between host plants of different ages at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. <italic>F</italic>-value and significance levels are given. ***Significant difference in means between plants within the same age class at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.Two-way ANOVA analysis of age and parasitism on the growth of invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic>. Bold values indicate significant effects on the growth of <italic>B. pilosa</italic>.The RGR (A), net photosynthetic rate of leaves (B) and root/shoot ratio (C) of different-aged invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants infected and not infected by <italic>C. australis</italic>, and the PR of RGR of plant biomass (D), net photosynthetic rate of leaves (E) and ratio of root biomass to shoot biomass (F) of different-aged invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic> to the parasitic <italic>C. australis</italic>. Values are given as means +1 SD (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Different letters indicate significant difference between host plants of different ages at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. <italic>F</italic>-value and significance levels are given. Asterisks indicate significant difference in means between plants within the same age class at ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.The concentrations (mean values + 1 SD, <italic>n</italic> = 6) of tannin (A), total phenolics (C), total flavonoids (E), saponins (G) and alkaloids (I) in different-aged invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants infected and not infected by <italic>C. australis</italic>, and the PR of tannin (B), total phenolics (D), total flavonoids (F), saponins (H) and alkaloids (J) in stems of the different-aged <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants to the parasitic <italic>C. australis</italic>. Different letters indicate significant difference between host plants of different ages at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. <italic>F</italic>-value and significance levels are given. Asterisks indicate significant difference in means between plants within the same age class at *<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt;0.01 and ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively.The present study found that the deleterious effects of parasite infection on the older <italic>B. pilosa</italic> were significantly less severe than on the younger plants, indicating that the younger plants were more sensitive to parasite infection than the older ones. These results supported our hypothesis that the damage to younger <italic>B. pilosa</italic> caused by <italic>C. australis</italic> infection is greater than the damage to older <italic>B. pilosa</italic>.Previous studies have shown that older hosts exhibit a defence mechanism that hampers the development of haustoria and thus mitigates parasite infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C38">Runyon <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C29">Meulebrouck <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C19">Lee and Jernstedt 2013</xref>). However, this conclusion was not supported by the present study because the parasite biomass did not decrease but increased with increasing host age in association with host size. Older hosts, with larger size and greater resource storage, could support greater growth of the attached parasites, leading to a mean increase in parasite biomass by 142 % for the 74-day-old hosts and 248 % for the 83-day-old hosts compared with that for the 59-day-old hosts.Our study found that root, stem, leaf and total biomass, RGR and photosynthetic ability were significantly negatively affected by parasite infection in the younger plants (59 and 74 days old) but not in the older plants (83 days old), indicating that the young plants fail to compensate whereas the older plants do (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C45">Tan <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C56">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Herbivory can induce compensatory growth by stimulating photosynthesis, altering mass allocation and increasing growth rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C26">Markkola <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C15">Hódar <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Therefore, the responses of younger <italic>B. pilosa</italic> to parasite infection is not similar to the responses of plants to damage by herbivores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C3">Barton and Koricheva 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C2">Barton 2013</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C43">Stout <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref> have found that younger rice plants appeared to be less tolerant to herbivory than older rice plants, though <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C12">Elger <italic>et al.</italic> (2009)</xref> have reported a higher sensitivity to herbivore attacks in young seedlings of British grassland species than in older conspecifics.Parasite infection had no effects on the root/shoot ratio in different-aged hosts, i.e. parasite infection did not alter the mass allocation to roots and shoots. This result may be due primarily to changes in the light conditions caused by the attack behaviour of the parasite. Herbivores destroy parts of plants, resulting in increases in light quality and quantity within a plant and thus leading to increases in photosynthesis and growth rates. In contrast, parasite infection may shade a host and decrease the light intensity within a host plant, especially if the hosts plants are small or young, thus leading to decreases in photosynthesis and growth rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C36">Rijkers <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>).The decreases in photosynthesis induced by parasitic infection led to a limited availability of resources, which further resulted in lower growth rates in smaller and younger hosts. These results indicated that the resistance of hosts to parasitic infection is negatively correlated with the availability of the resources stored in a host plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C42">Shen <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). For woody forest plants, negative effects of mistletoe infection on host tree growth and mortality have been consistently and extensively reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C41">Shaw <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C25">Logan <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>), and those negative growth effects have widely been considered to result from decreased photosynthetic production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C28">Meinzer <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>) caused by decreased leaf size and leaf N content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C11">Ehleringer <italic>et al.</italic> 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C7">Cechin and Press 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C24">Logan <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C30">Mishra <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>).Little attention has been paid to changes in chemical defences, such as alkaloids, phenolics, flavonoids, cyanogenic glycosides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C12">Elger <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C34">Quintero and Bowers 2013</xref>), induced by parasitic infection, whereas ontogenetic changes in chemical defences against herbivory are well documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C48">Van Zandt and Agrawal 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C1">Barton 2008</xref>). The concentrations of cyanogenic glycoside (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C40">Schappert and Shore 2000</xref>), nicotine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C31">Ohnmeiss and Baldwin 2000</xref>), alkaloids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C31">Ohnmeiss and Baldwin 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C12">Elger <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>) and phenolics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C10">Donaldson <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C12">Elger <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>) have been found to be higher in older tissues/plants than in younger tissues/plants exposed to herbivory. The present study found that the concentrations of total phenolics, total flavonoids and saponins were significantly negatively affected by <italic>C. australis</italic> infection in younger <italic>B. pilosa</italic> but not in older plants. A positive response of total phenolics was found only in the 83-day-old plants; a positive response of total flavonoids and saponins occurred in both 74- and 83-day-old plants. These results supported our initial hypothesis that the younger plants with limited resource reserves have less leeway to produce chemical defences. Similarly, it has been reported that older plants that had accumulated resources over a long period were better able to maintain anti-herbivore defences than younger plants with limited resources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C4">Boege 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C12">Elger <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>).However, other studies have reported opposite or neutral responses of chemical defences to herbivory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C46">Thomson <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C3">Barton and Koricheva 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C14">Goodger <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref> demonstrated that the levels of phenolics produced in response to herbivory were highest in seedlings compared with those in juveniles and mature trees. A meta-analysis based on data from 36 published studies also did not find any clear relationships between ontogenetic stage and chemical defences induced by herbivory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C3">Barton and Koricheva 2010</xref>). Ontogenetic patterns of plant chemical responses to herbivory or parasite infection might vary with plant species, chemical compounds and disturbance (e.g. parasite or insect infection) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C50">Webber and Woodrow 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C37">Rohr <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). Further studies are needed to identify, clarify and quantify the chemical defences in different hosts and different-aged hosts infected by different parasites.Plant resistance traits, including physical defences traits and chemical secondary compounds, and tolerance traits such as compensatory re-growth are detectable, when plants are damaged by insect, pathogen or parasite infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C44">Stowe <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C34">Quintero and Bowers 2013</xref>). Previous studies prove that trade-offs between resistance and tolerance traits of plants do occur following damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C32">Orians <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C34">Quintero and Bowers 2013</xref>). However, several studies reported that the trade-offs between resistance and tolerance traits are not detectable for all development stages (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C34">Quintero and Bowers 2013</xref>), for example, during the seedling development stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C1">Barton 2008</xref>). Our results showed that younger hosts had higher concentrations of tannin and alkaloids but lower concentrations of flavonoids, phenolics and terpenoids, as well as a lower re-growth ability; conversely, older hosts had lower concentration of tannin and alkaloids, but higher concentrations of flavonoids, phenolics and terpenoids, as well as a higher capability of compensatory growth. These results provided an indirect evidence for supporting the above-mentioned viewpoints that younger hosts with lower biomass invest fewer resources in growth but more resources in higher concentrations of tannin and alkaloids, whereas the older hosts have a higher biomass and higher concentrations of flavonoids, phenolics and terpenoids, but lower concentrations of tannin and alkaloids. Accordingly, the overall pattern of response might depend on the age or size of the host and even on the diversity of damage.In conclusion, the intensity of damage caused by the parasite <italic>C. australis</italic> was dependent on the host age or size associated with the host biomass, showing that younger and smaller hosts were more easily damaged and less able to recover. This result supported the resource limitation hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C6">Bryant <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>) because hosts with increasing host age (or size) have more resources available to defend against or limit the establishment of haustoria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C39">Runyon <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Our field investigation found that <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants with a height &gt;90 cm were resistant because they were less infected by <italic>C. australis</italic>, whereas <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants with a height &lt;30 cm were effectively and successfully controlled by <italic>C. australis</italic>. Our results, therefore, indicate that the parasite <italic>C. australis</italic> could be successfully used as a potential biological agent in the control of invasive <italic>B. pilosa</italic> plants only in the early stages of development. However, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV031C4">Boege (2005)</xref> indicated, further studies are needed to better and fully understand the mechanisms underlying the effects of host ontogeny on the responses of the host plants to herbivores or (holo) parasites.This work was financially supported by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">National Natural Science Foundation of China</grant-sponsor> (No. <grant-num xlink:type="simple">31270461</grant-num>; No. <grant-num xlink:type="simple">30800133</grant-num>) and <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">National Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province</grant-sponsor> (No. <grant-num xlink:type="simple">Y5110227</grant-num>).J.L. and M.Y. conceived and designed research. B.Y., Q.Y. and J.Z. conducted experiments. J.L. analysed data. J.L. and M.L. wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.None declared.