Plant performance on Mediterranean green roofs: interaction of species-specific hydraulic strategies and substrate water relationsSalicylic acid may be involved in the regulation of drought-induced leaf senescence in perennials: a case study in field-grown <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> L. plantsDifferences in stomatal responses and root to shoot signalling between two grapevine varieties subjected to droughtWildflower green roofs for urban landscaping, ecological sustainability and biodiversityInitial agronomic performances of Mediterranean xerophytes in simulated dry green roofsGreen roof performance towards management of runoff water quantity and quality: a reviewAlternatives to <italic>Sedum</italic> on green roofs: can broad leaf perennial plants offer better ‘cooling service’?Urban greening to cool towns and cities: a systematic review of the empirical evidenceSpace for urban wildlife: designing green roofs as habitats in SwitzerlandVegetated roofs for stormwater management at multiple spatial scalesWater relations, gas exchange and growth of dominant and suppressed shoots of <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> LPerformance evaluation and development strategies for green roofs in Taiwan: a reviewPotential benefits of plant diversity on vegetated roofs: a literature reviewWater-use strategies in two co-occurring Mediterranean evergreen oaks: surviving the summer droughtGreen roof vegetation for North American ecoregions: a literature reviewPlant establishment on unirrigated green roof modules in a subtropical climateGreen roofs for hot and dry climates: interacting effects of plant water use, succulence and substrateWater-retention additives increase plant available water in green roof substratesPartitioning of water and nitrogen in co-occurring Mediterranean woody shrub species of different evolutionary historyGreen roof energy and water related performance in the Mediterranean climateIsohydric and anisohydric strategies of wheat genotypes under osmotic stress: biosynthesis and function of ABA in stress responsesMedia depth influences Sedum green roof establishmentSubstrate depth influences <italic>Sedum</italic> plant community on a green roofQuantifying the effect of slope on extensive green roof stormwater retentionCarbon sequestration potential of extensive green roofsAdapting cities for climate change: the role of the green infrastructureAdaptive strategy at the leaf level of <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> L. to cope with Mediterranean climateThe variability of stomatal sensitivity to leaf water potential across tree species indicates a continuum between isohydric and anisohydric behavioursEffect of green roof on ambient CO<sub>2</sub> concentrationDrought tolerance and thermal effect measurements for plants suitable for extensive green roof planting in humid subtropical climatesPlant species and functional group combinations affect green roof ecosystem functionsInsect species composition and diversity on intensive green roofs and adjacent level-ground habitatsRemotely sensing the cooling effects of city scale efforts to reduce urban heat islandRegulation of photosynthesis of C<sub>3</sub> plants in response to progressive drought: stomatal conductance as a reference parameterLaboratory study on the potential use of recycled inert construction waste material in the substrate mix for extensive green roofsDrought-induced oxidative stress in strawberry tree (<italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> L.) growing in Mediterranean field conditionsDrought-induced senescence is characterized by a loss of antioxidant defences in chloroplastsWater relations and hydraulic characteristics of three woody species co-occurring in the same habitatInfluence of substrate depth and vegetation type on temperature and water runoff mitigation by extensive green roofs: shrubs versus herbaceous plantsTrade-offs between leaf hydraulic capacity and drought vulnerability: morpho-anatomical bases, carbon costs and ecological consequencesThe challenge of the Mediterranean climate to plant hydraulics: responses and adaptationsGreen roofs as urban ecosystems: ecological structures, functions, and servicesGrowth of native aromatic xerophytes in an extensive Mediterranean green roof as affected by substrate type and depth and irrigation frequencyImpact of green roofs on stormwater quality in a South Australian urban environmentWater relations of plants in the field: some comments on the measurement of selected parametersGreen roofs as a means of pollution abatementEffect of green roof media depth on Crassulacean plant succession over seven yearsComparison of irrigation efficiency and plant health of overhead, drip, and sub-irrigation for extensive green roofsThermal property measurements for ecoroof soils common in the western U.SPerformance of seedlings of Mediterranean woody species under experimental gradients of irradiance and water availability: trade-offs and evidence for niche differentiationImpact of different green roof layering on plant water status and drought survivalGreen roofs for a drier world: effects of hydrogel amendment on substrate and plant water statusDifferences in hydraulic architecture account for near-isohydric and anisohydric behaviour of two field-grown <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. cultivars during droughtEvaluation of the energy performance and irrigation requirements of extensive green roofs in a water-scarce Mediterranean climateSequestering zinc from recycled crumb rubber in extensive green roof mediaSurface heat budget on green roof and high reflection roof for mitigation of urban heat islandVariability among species of stomatal control under fluctuating soil water status and evaporative demand: modelling isohydric and anisohydric behavioursSummer period analysis of the performance of a planted roof as a passive cooling techniqueRelationships between stomatal behavior, xylem vulnerability to cavitation and leaf water relations in two cultivars of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>The measurement of the turgor pressure and the water relations of plants by the pressure-bomb techniqueMediterranean open habitat vegetation offers great potential for extensive green roof designNumerical evaluation of sound propagating over green roofsReducing the acoustical façade load from road traffic with green roofsWatering regime and green roof substrate design affect <italic>Sedum</italic> plant growthPhysiological differences explain the co-existence of different regeneration strategies in Mediterranean ecosystemsMeasurement of the matric potential of soil water in the rhizosphereGreen roofs for a wide brown land: opportunities and barriers for rooftop greening in AustraliaResponses of leaf stomatal density to water status and its relationship with photosynthesis in a grass<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Astrid VolderThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Mediterranean native shrubs can be very useful for green roofs in hot and arid regions. Our data show that both <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> L. and <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> L. could be successfully utilized, although the choice of species should be based on the drought-resistant strategy relative to the desired technical performance of the green roof. Moreover, substrate selection was found to have a crucial role in the success of green roof installations in the Mediterranean area.Recent studies have highlighted the ecological, economic and social benefits assured by green roof technology to urban areas. However, green roofs are very hostile environments for plant growth because of shallow substrate depths, high temperatures and irradiance and wind exposure. This study provides experimental evidence for the importance of accurate selection of plant species and substrates for implementing green roofs in hot and arid regions, like the Mediterranean area. Experiments were performed on two shrub species (<italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> L. and <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> L.) grown in green roof experimental modules with two substrates slightly differing in their water retention properties, as derived from moisture release curves. Physiological measurements were performed on both well-watered and drought-stressed plants. Gas exchange, leaf and xylem water potential and also plant hydraulic conductance were measured at different time intervals following the last irrigation. The substrate type significantly affected water status. <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> and <italic>S. officinalis</italic> showed different hydraulic responses to drought stress, with the former species being substantially isohydric and the latter one anisohydric. Both <italic>A. unedo</italic> and <italic>S. officinalis</italic> were found to be suitable species for green roofs in the Mediterranean area. However, our data suggest that appropriate choice of substrate is key to the success of green roof installations in arid environments, especially if anisohydric species are employed.Green roofs are engineered ecosystems designed to favour plant establishment on manufactured layers installed over rooftops, and typically comprise lightweight mineral substrate, drainage and moisture retention layers and a root-resistant waterproofing barrier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C65">VanWoert <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C5">Berndtsson 2010</xref>). Modern green roofs were first developed in the 1960s in Germany and, over the last 15 years, this technology has received increasing attention in several countries of Northern and Central Europe, North America, Australia, Japan and China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C7">Bowler <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C14">Dvorak and Volder 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C68">Williams <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C11">Chen 2013</xref>). This renewed interest for green roofs is a consequence of recent experimental evidence highlighting the ecological, economic and social benefits provided by this technology to urban areas. In fact, green roofs have been reported to improve urban management of water runoff (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C23">Getter <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C30">Lundholm <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C31">MacIvor and Lundholm 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C38">Nardini <italic>et al</italic>. 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>), reduce the consumption of energy for thermal comfort of buildings (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C59">Theodosiou 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C49">Sailor <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C6">Blanusa <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>), mitigate the ‘urban heat island’ effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C25">Gill <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C57">Takebayashi and Moriyama 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C32">Mackey <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>), improve acoustic insulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C63">Van Renterghem and Botteldooren 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C64">2009</xref>), improve air (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C46">Rowe 2011</xref>) and water quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C9">Carter and Jackson 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C5">Berndtsson 2010</xref>) and sequester CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C24">Getter <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C28">Li <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>). Moreover, this technology could prove useful for recycling of waste materials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C56">Solano <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C34">Mickovski <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) and might provide effective instruments to ameliorate the urban appeal, increase the number of recreational spaces and improve urban biodiversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C8">Brenneisen 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C31">MacIvor and Lundholm 2011</xref>).Green roofs are rather hostile environments for plant growth, because of shallow substrate, high temperatures and irradiance and wind exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C21">Getter and Rowe 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C29">Liu <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). In particular, structural features of buildings frequently require the use of reduced substrate depths, with predictable impacts on water availability to vegetation. This, in turn, limits the number of species that can thrive over green roofs, especially in hot and arid regions like Mediterranean countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C19">Fioretti <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C39">Nardini <italic>et al</italic>. 2012<italic>b</italic></xref>), where drought, high irradiance and temperatures are common stress factors even for natural vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C50">Sánchez-Gómez <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C13">David <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C40">Nardini <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). Under these environmental conditions, the plants' growth over green roofs is particularly challenging and thus requires specific technological and ecophysiological strategies to improve plant survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C15">Dvorak and Volder 2013</xref>).In particular, the selection of substrates with high water holding capacity and high amounts of water available to plants is apparently a key requirement to improve the performance of green roofs in arid climates. As an example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C16">Farrell <italic>et al</italic>. (2012)</xref> reported a correlation between the survival rate of different succulent species under drought stress and the water holding capacity of different substrates. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C44">Razzaghmanesh <italic>et al</italic>. (2014)</xref> reported significant effects of substrate type on growth and survival of different grass species native to the Australian flora. Moreover, improving water holding capacity of the substrate, amended with different materials, has been reported to be effective in increasing plant survival rates and ameliorating plant water status under drought conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C17">Farrell <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C42">Papafotiou <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C52">Savi <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>).The selection of drought-resistant plant species is as important as substrate features in order to assure the success of green roofs in arid environments. Specific studies addressing the relative suitability of different plant species for green roof development have appeared in recent years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C14">Dvorak and Volder 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C31">MacIvor and Lundholm 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C12">Cook-Patton and Bauerle 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C42">Papafotiou <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C62">Van Mechelen <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>), but the most commonly used species are still small succulents, mainly belonging to the genus <italic>Sedum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C55">Snodgrass and Snodgrass 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C41">Oberndorfer <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C47">Rowe <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). These are characterized by shallow roots, high drought tolerance and relatively fast propagation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C55">Snodgrass and Snodgrass 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C22">Getter and Rowe 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C16">Farrell <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). In contrast, only few studies have explored the possibility to use alternative plant species over green roofs in arid regions, despite the high number (and drought adaptation) of species native to the Mediterranean region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C4">Benvenuti and Bacci 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C42">Papafotiou <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C3">Benvenuti 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C62">Van Mechelen <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). In particular, the impressive heterogeneity in plant hydraulic strategies and water relations displayed by Mediterranean plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C40">Nardini <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C66">Vilagrosa <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>) might represent an important resource for designing green roofs with specifically requested technical features. As an example, isohydric species that display tight stomatal control of transpiration might help to design green roofs with high resistance against drought, as well as with low irrigation requirements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C48">Rowe <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). On the other hand, anisohydric species that maximize transpiration and photosynthesis while tolerating very negative water potential values might represent a more interesting choice in order to favour transpirational cooling of buildings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C54">Schweitzer and Erell 2014</xref>) and/or improve the capacity of green roofs to intercept water during intense albeit sporadic rainfall events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C38">Nardini <italic>et al</italic>. 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>).In the present study, we provide experimental evidence for the importance of substrate characteristics, with special reference to water retention properties, to assure sufficient water availability to plants over green roofs under drought stress conditions. Moreover, we provide insights into the importance of species-specific drought-resistance strategies and hydraulic properties for selecting Mediterranean native species best suited for specific technical functions and ecological requirements of green roofs. To this aim, experiments were performed using two Mediterranean shrub species: <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> L. and <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> L. <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> (sage) is a perennial, evergreen, sub-shrub species widely naturalized even outside its original habitat. <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> (arbutus) is an evergreen shrub or small tree widely distributed in the Mediterranean Basin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C43">Pignatti 2002</xref>). Both species are well known for their drought tolerance, although a specific comparison of their hydraulic strategies has not been previously performed.Experiments were performed between May and July 2012 on 36 plants of <italic>A. unedo</italic> and 36 plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic>. Plants were provided at the end of April 2012 by a local nursery and planted in 24 experimental green roof modules with dimensions 75 × 23 × 27 cm (i.e. 12 modules per species, 3 plants per module <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv007/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold>). The modules were assembled with the SEIC<sup>®</sup> extensive system (Harpo Spa, Trieste, Italy). The layering included a water retention geotextile (MediPro MP), a drainage and aeration element (MediDrain MD), a filtering layer (MediFilter MF 1) and 18 cm of one of the two different experimental substrates provided by SEIC. Species-specific modules were divided into two main categories on the basis of substrate type tested: substrate A and substrate B. In summary, six modules per species contained substrate A and six modules were filled with substrate B <bold>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv007/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">see Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold>.Percentage of different grain sizes, organic matter, porosity and values of electrical conductivity and pH of the two substrate types utilized (i.e. A and B). Data are kindly provided by SEIC.The water retention properties of the two substrates were preliminarily measured using a dewpoint potentiameter (WP4, Decagon Devices, Pullman, WA, USA). In particular, the relationships between water content (WC) and water potential (pressure–volume curve) of the two substrates were measured to estimate the amount of water available to plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C67">Whalley <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Samples of the two substrates were watered to saturation. After complete drainage of excess water, small samples (a few grams each) were collected and placed in dedicated WP4 sample-holders. Water potential of substrate (Ψ<sub>s</sub>) was measured in the continuous mode and after each reading, samples were weighed with an electronic balance (Basic BA110S, Sar-torius AG, Göttingen, Germany) to obtain their fresh weight (FW), and then oven-dried at 70 °C for 24 h. Samples were weighed again to get their dry weight (DW). Water content of samples was calculated as (FW − DW)/DW. Measurements were performed on fully hydrated samples as well as on samples air-dehydrated for increasing time intervals.Green roof modules were randomly located over the flat rooftop of the Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, University of Messina. On the basis of irrigation regime, experimental modules were further divided in four experimental groups per species <bold>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plv007/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">see Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold>: three modules per substrate type category were regularly watered to field capacity (well-watered plants: WA and WB), while the other three modules per substrate-type category received irrigation up to 75 % field capacity (stressed plants: SA and SB). Irrigation was supplied at 48 h intervals for 10 weeks. At the end of the treatment, all plants were irrigated to field capacity and physiological measurements were performed again 24 and 48 h after irrigation.During the study period, mean air temperatures and relative humidity in the area were 19 ± 1 °C and 74 ± 7 % in May, 24 ± 2 °C and 75 ± 5 % in June and 28 ± 1 °C and 74 ± 5 % in July, respectively. The total rainfall was 13 mm only. Climatic data were obtained from the weather station of Torre Faro, Messina, Italy.At the beginning and at the end of the experiment (i.e. beginning of May and end of July, respectively), two plants within each module of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> and two plants within each module of <italic>A. unedo</italic> per each experimental group (i.e. WA, SA, WB and SB) were selected and the following parameters were measured: plant height (H), trunk diameter at the root-stem transition zone (Ø) and total number of leaves per plant (<italic>N</italic> leaves/plant). During the study period, substrate water status (Ψ<sub>s</sub>) of both W and S-modules was estimated by measuring the pre-dawn water potential (Ψ<sub>pd</sub>) of six leaves wrapped in cling-film the day before measurements (two leaves per species and per module) and sampled at 0500 hours (solar time). Measurements were performed with a pressure chamber (3005 Plant Water Status Console, Soilmoisture Equipment Corp., Goleta, CA, USA), assuming that under nocturnal low transpiration conditions leaf water potential equilibrated with Ψ<sub>s</sub>, so that Ψ<sub>pd</sub> ∼ Ψ<sub>s</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C45">Richter 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C37">Nardini <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>). The indirect estimation of Ψ<sub>s</sub> was preferred to direct sampling of the substrate, in order to avoid the risk of damage to the root system. Measurements of Ψ<sub>pd</sub> were performed on the same days selected for gas exchange and midday leaf water potential measurements (see below).At the end of the 10-week treatment period, both 24 and 48 h after irrigation, maximum leaf stomatal conductance to water vapour (<italic>g</italic><sub>L</sub>) and transpiration rate (<italic>E</italic><sub>L</sub>) were measured between 1200 and 1400 hours on leaves of at least one plant per module per experimental group and species using a steady-state porometer (LI-1600, LICor Inc., Lincoln, NE, USA). At the same time, midday diurnal leaf water potential (Ψ<sub>midday</sub>) was estimated using a portable pressure chamber (3005 Plant Water Status Console, Soilmoisture Equipment Corp.).In order to quantify eventual acclimation of water relation parameters in terms of leaf water potential at the turgor loss point (Ψ<sub>tlp</sub>), osmotic potential at full turgor (<italic>π</italic><sub>0</sub>) and bulk modulus of elasticity (<italic>ɛ</italic><sub>max</sub>), leaf water potential isotherms of leaves of at least one plant per module per experimental group were determined from pressure–volume (P–V) curves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C61">Tyree and Hammel 1972</xref>). Measurements were performed before starting the treatment and repeated at the end of the 10-week period, respectively.Whole-plant hydraulic conductance (<italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub>) was estimated <italic>in planta</italic> using the Evaporative Flux Method on at least one plant per module per species and per experimental group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C37">Nardini <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>). <italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub> was calculated as: <italic>E</italic><sub>L</sub>/(Ψ<sub>midday</sub> − Ψ<sub>s</sub>), where <italic>E</italic><sub>L</sub>, Ψ<sub>midday</sub> and Ψ<sub>s</sub> were measured as described above. All hydraulic conductance values were corrected to a temperature of 20 °C, to take into account changes in water viscosity.Data were analysed with the SigmaStat 2.0 (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) statistics package. To test the differences among substrate type and the effects of both irrigation regimes and time after last irrigation on Ψ<sub>s</sub>, <italic>g</italic><sub>L</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub>, a three-way ANOVA was performed (soil, irrigation and time as factors) with Type III sums of squares. The same test was used to check the significance of the differences among substrate type and the effects of irrigation regime and time (i.e. May and July) on H, Ø and N leaves/plant. To test the differences among substrate type and effects of irrigation regime on Ψ<sub>tlp</sub>, <italic>π</italic><sub>o</sub> and <italic>ɛ</italic><sub>max</sub> a two-way ANOVA test was performed. Data have been analysed by nesting the plant observations within each module (<italic>n</italic> = 3).When the difference was significant, a post hoc Tukey's test was carried out. Relationships between the studied characteristics and independent variables were assessed by Pearson's correlations.Means ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3) of plant height (H), trunk diameter (Ø) and number of leaves per plant (<italic>N</italic> leaves/plant) as recorded in May and in July (i.e. at the beginning and at the end of treatment irrigation regimes) in plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> and <italic>A. unedo</italic> growing in two types of substrate (A and B) and irrigation regimes (W: plants irrigated to field capacity; S: plants irrigated to 75 % field capacity) (for details, see text). Different letters indicate, for each measured parameter, statistically different mean values for Tukey pairwise comparison, after performing a three-way ANOVA test.Relationships between water potential (−Ψ<sub>s</sub>) and water content (WC) as measured for the substrate A (A) and B (B). Regression curves are expressed by the following function: <italic>f</italic> = <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> + (<italic>a</italic>/<italic>x</italic>) + (<italic>b</italic>/<italic>x</italic><sup>2</sup>) + (<italic>c</italic>/<italic>x</italic><sup>3</sup>). Coefficient values and correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>) are reported.Substrate water potential (Ψ<sub>s</sub>) as recorded 24 and 48 h after irrigation of experimental modules with <italic>S. officinalis</italic> (A) and <italic>A. unedo</italic> (B) plants subjected to two irrigation regimes (W: plants irrigated to field capacity; S: plants irrigated to 75 % field capacity). Two substrates were tested (A and B, for details, see text). Means are given ±SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Different letters indicate statistically different mean values for Tukey pairwise comparison.Leaf conductance to water vapour (<italic>g</italic><sub>L</sub>, A and B) and leaf water potential (Ψ<sub>midday</sub>, C and D) as recorded in plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> and <italic>A. unedo</italic> growing in the two types of substrate (A and B) and under different irrigation regimes (W: plants irrigated to field capacity; S: plants irrigated to 75 % field capacity, for details, see text). Means are given ±SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Different letters indicate statistically significant differences for Tukey pairwise comparison.Leaf water potential at turgor loss point (Ψ<sub>tlp</sub>), osmotic potential at full turgor (<italic>π</italic><sub>0</sub>) and bulk modulus of elasticity (<italic>ɛ</italic><sub>max</sub>) as recorded in plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> and <italic>A. unedo</italic> growing in two types of substrate (A and B) and irrigation regimes (W: plants irrigated to field capacity; S: plants irrigated to 75 % field capacity) (for details, see text). Means are given ±SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Different letters indicate, for each measured parameter, statistically different mean values for Tukey pairwise comparison, after performing a three-way ANOVA test.Results of: (A) a three-way ANOVA of different measured parameters by soil type, <italic>S</italic> (i.e. A and B), irrigation regime, <italic>I</italic> (i.e. samples regularly watered to field capacity and samples watered to 75 % field capacity) and time, <italic>T</italic> (i.e. time after last irrigation for soil water potential Ψ<sub>s</sub>, maximum diurnal leaf conductance to water vapour <italic>g</italic><sub>L</sub>, minimum diurnal leaf water potential Ψ<sub>min</sub> and plant hydraulic conductance <italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub>, and time of year for plant height <italic>H</italic>, stem diameter Ø and number of leaves per plant <italic>N</italic> leaves/plant) treatments; (B) a two-way ANOVA of parameters determined from P–V curves by soil type, S (i.e. A and B) and irrigation treatment, I (i.e. time of the year) recorded in <italic>S. officinalis</italic> and in <italic>A. unedo</italic>. For details, see the text. Numbers represent <italic>F</italic> values, *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001.Plant hydraulic conductance (<italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub>) as recorded in plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> (A) and <italic>A. unedo</italic> (B) growing in two types of substrate (A and B) and under different irrigation regimes (W: plants irrigated to field capacity; S: plants irrigated to 75 % field capacity, for details, see text). Means are given ±SD (<italic>n</italic> = 3). Different letters indicate statistically significant differences for Tukey pairwise comparison.Relationship between maximum leaf stomatal conductance to water vapour (<italic>g</italic><sub>L</sub>) values and substrate water content (Ψ<sub>s</sub>) values recorded in plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> (A) and <italic>A. unedo</italic> (B) growing in two types of substrate and under different irrigation regimes. Regression equation, coefficient values, <italic>P</italic>-values and correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>) are also reported.Relationship between plant hydraulic conductance (<italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub>) values and corresponding substrate water status (Ψ<sub>s</sub>) recorded in plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> (A) and <italic>A. unedo</italic> (B) growing in the two types of substrate and subjected to different irrigation regimes. Regression equation, coefficient values, <italic>P</italic>-values and correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>) are also reported.Our data suggest that the use of species selected from the native flora of the Mediterranean region might be a valuable strategy for implementation of green roof systems in hot and arid areas. On the other hand, our findings reveal that even subtle differences in terms of substrate properties, with special reference to water relation parameters, can have very important consequences for the performance and persistence of vegetation over green roofs.Substrate A was more suitable than substrate B for installation of efficient and fully functional green roofs in arid-prone areas. This was mainly due to the higher water retention capability related to the particle size, and especially to the higher amounts of water potentially available to plants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F1">1</xref>). This feature resulted in the maintenance of higher soil water potential values over 48 h after the last irrigation in plants growing in modules containing substrate A than in samples growing in modules filled with substrate B, as observed in both species, despite their different water relations strategies (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F3">3</xref>).Arbutus and sage plants apparently adopted contrasting strategies to cope with drought stress. On the basis of relationships between <italic>g</italic><sub>L</sub> and leaf water potential, it can be suggested that <italic>A. unedo</italic> adopted a rather typical isohydric behaviour, while <italic>S. officinalis</italic> displayed a significant level of anisohydry, although a recent study has highlighted the fact that there might be a continuum of water relations strategies along these two ideal extremes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C27">Klein 2014</xref>). Values of <italic>g</italic><sub>L</sub> were lower in arbutus than in sage, even in well-watered samples (∼130 versus 300 mmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, respectively, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F3">3</xref>A and B), and a further reduction of stomatal conductance was observed in arbutus plants under water stress (∼70 mmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>). Progressive stomatal closure apparently allowed arbutus plants to limit water loss and maintain relatively stable leaf water potential values both under well-watered and drought stress conditions, especially in samples growing in modules filled with substrate type A (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F3">3</xref>D and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F5">5</xref>B). In contrast, <italic>S. officinalis</italic> plants maintained values of <italic>g</italic><sub>L</sub> as high as ∼300 mmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> as long as soil water potential remained above a critical value of about −0.6 MPa (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F3">3</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F5">5</xref>A). Below this threshold, gas exchange rates were reduced by ∼50 % (from 300 to 150 mmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, as recorded in SB samples 48 h after last irrigation Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F3">3</xref>A). This, in turn, induced statistically significant differences in leaf water potential values as a function of the time after the last irrigation, regime of irrigation and the type of substrate (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F3">3</xref>C, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV007TB4">4</xref>). The different water use strategies adopted by arbutus and sage plants to face drought stress were also confirmed by the analysis of leaf water potential isotherms. In fact, water-stressed plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> lowered the leaf water potential at the turgor loss point by osmotic adjustment. In the case of arbutus, water stress induced a significant increase of the bulk modulus of elasticity (<italic>ɛ</italic><sub>max</sub>, Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV007TB3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLV007TB4">4</xref>).Isohydric and anisohydric behaviour of different species/genotypes could arise from different stomatal sensitivity to xylem-born ABA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C58">Tardieu and Simonneau 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C2">Beis and Patakas 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C20">Gallè <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) and/or to different levels of xylem hydraulic safety/efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C53">Schultz 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C60">Tombesi <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>). Different levels of stomatal control of transpiration under drought stress are known to affect photosynthetic productivity and plant growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C33">Medrano <italic>et al</italic>. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C69">Xu and Zhou 2008</xref>). In the present study, the anisohydric behaviour recorded in sage plants was coupled to a strong reduction of the number of leaves per plant as recorded in July in stressed versus watered samples (i.e. ∼100 % versus ∼40 %). Isohydric and anisohydric behaviours of the two study species were further supported by estimates of plant hydraulic conductance (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F5">5</xref>). In fact, arbutus plants (isohydric) showed three times lower <italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub> than sage plants (anisohydric, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F4">4</xref>), and this parameter remained quite constant up to 48 h after the last irrigation in samples growing in modules filled with substrate B, despite wide variations in terms of soil water availability (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F2">2</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F4">4</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F5">5</xref>B). In contrast, <italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub> of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> strongly changed as a function of Ψ<sub>s</sub> (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F4">4</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV007F5">5</xref>A). In other words, the isohydric behaviour of arbutus allowed to maintain stable <italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub> values, while anisohydry in sage implied a drop of <italic>K</italic><sub>plant</sub> as drought progressed.Data recorded in the present study suggest that arbutus plants could overcome intense drought conditions and, then, might be more suitable for Mediterranean green roofs than to sage plants. In fact, the higher water use of the latter species might imply the need of additional irrigation to prevent foliage damage and/or desiccation under prolonged drought. In the literature, <italic>A. unedo</italic> is frequently reported to be able to survive even severe drought stress (i.e. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C10">Castell and Terradas 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C26">Gratani and Ghia 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C35">Munné-Bosch and Peñuelas 2004</xref>), as it apparently maintains a positive carbon balance until pre-dawn leaf water potential values of −4 MPa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C18">Filella and Peñuelas 2003</xref>). In contrast, sage plants are known to show leaf senescence symptoms when exposed to severe drought conditions (i.e. Ψ<sub>pd</sub> &lt; −1 MPa, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C36">Munné-Bosch <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C1">Abreu and Munné-Bosch 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C51">Savi <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Hence, while arbutus might represent a suitable species for green roofs with very low input of additional irrigation, sage might be more recommendable in order to maximize the transpirational cooling of buildings and/or to favour fast water depletion from substrates, thus improving the effectiveness of green roofs to mitigate water runoff during occasional storms, although the use of this species would probably be possible only when regular albeit low irrigation inputs are guaranteed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLV007C51">Savi <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). Additional studies focussed on testing the physiological performance and water requirements of a large number of Mediterranean species over green roofs are required to conclude about possible relationships between plant hydraulic strategies and green roof performance under drought.This work was supported by <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">University of Messina (Atheneum Research Project)</grant-sponsor>. Materials of set up of green roof experimental modules were kindly provided by Harpo Spa (Trieste, Italy).P.T., M.A.L.G., S.A. and A.N. designed the experiment and planned the measurements. F.R., P.T., S.A. and T.S. carried out experiments. F.R. and P.T. analysed the data. P.T. wrote the manuscript. M.A.L.G., A.N. and T.S. revised and finalized the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.None declared.The following additional information is available in the online version of this article –<bold>Figure S1.</bold> Schematic representation of the experimental design. Twenty-four modules (75 × 23 × 27 cm) were divided in two groups of 12 modules in which 36 plants of <italic>A. unedo</italic> and 36 plants of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> were planted, respectively (i.e. 3 plants per module). Two types of substrate (A and B) and two irrigation regimes (well watered, W and stressed, S) were tested. More in detail, 12 modules per species were divided in two categories on the basis of substrate type tested: 6 modules per species contained substrate A and the other 6 modules contained substrate B. These modules were further divided in four experimental groups on the basis of irrigation regime: 3 modules per substrate type category were regularly watered to field capacity (i.e. WA and WB modules), and 3 modules per substrate type category received irrigation up to 75 % field capacity (i.e. SA and SB modules).