Bulk elastic moduli and solute potentials in leaves of freshwater, coastal and marine hydrophytes. Are marine plants more rigid?Drought and salt tolerance in plantsThe determinants of leaf turgor loss point and prediction of drought tolerance of species and biomes: a global meta-analysisSalinity effects on water potential components and bulk elastic modulus of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> (Mart.) GrisebSeasonal changes in tissue elasticity in chaparral shrubsWater relations parameters on single leaves obtained in a pressure bomb and some ecological interpretationsThe role of solute accumulation, osmotic adjustment, and changes in cell wall elasticity in drought tolerance in <italic>Ziziphus mauritiana</italic> (Lamk.)Physical and biotic drivers of plant distribution across estuarine salinity gradientsA study of transcellular osmosis and the kinetics of swelling and shrinking in cells of <italic>Chara corallina</italic>Photosynthetic production and biomass of the subtropical seagrass <italic>Halodule wrightii</italic> along an estuarine gradientIon transport studies and determination of the cell wall elastic modulus in the marine alga <italic>Halicystis parvula</italic>Position of water in vitrified plants visualised by NMR imagingA beneficial gas transport system in <italic>Nymphoides peltata</italic>Ca<sup>2+</sup> dependent cessation of cytoplasmic streaming induced by hypertonic treatment in <italic>Vallisneria</italic> mesophyll cells: possible role of cell wall–plasma membrane adhesionTurgor pressure changes trigger characteristics changes in the electrical conductance of the tonoplast and the plasmalemma of the marine alga <italic>Valonia utricularis</italic>Osmotic adjustment in indoor cassava in response to water stressFormation of aerenchyma and the processes of plant ventilation in relation to soil flooding and submergenceAlteration of cell-wall water content and elasticity in Douglas-Fir during periods of water deficitPhotosynthesis by thin leaf slices in solution II. Osmotic stress and is effects on photosynthesisCurrent topics in drought physiologyLeaf–water relations and ion concentrations of the halophyte <italic>Atriplex hortensis</italic> in response to salinity and water stressGraphical evaluation and partitioning of turgor responses to drought in leaves of durum wheatSalinity tolerance of eukaryotic marine algaeDetermination of the volumetric modulus of elasticity of wheat leaves by pressure–volume relations and the effect of drought conditioningPlasma membrane–cell wall adhesion is required for expression of plant defense responses during fungal penetrationContrasting physiological responses of six <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> species to water deficitDevelopmental changes in cell and tissues water relations parameters in storage parenchyma of sugarcaneOsmoregulation and water stress in higher plantsEffects of sodium chloride on growth, tissue elasticity, and solute adjustment in two <italic>Acacia nilotica</italic> subspeciesViscoelastic versus plastic cell wall extensibility in growing seedling organs: a contribution to avoid some misconceptionsNational list of plant species that occur in wetlands: national summaryMorphological adjustments promote drought avoidance in the wetland plant <italic>Acorus americanus</italic>Reversible decreases in bulk elastic modulus of mature leaves of deciduous <italic>Quercus</italic> species subjected to two drought treatmentsDelayed modifications in plant–water relations in the coastal marsh halophyte <italic>Spartina patens</italic> following sudden increases in soil salinitySap pressure in vascular plantsBiomechanics of plant growthEffect of turgor pressure and cell size on the wall elasticity of plant cellsSalt tolerance in a <italic>Juncus roemerianus</italic> brackish marsh: spacial variations in plant water relationsSeagrass–salinity interactions: physiological mechanisms used by submerged marine angiosperms for life at seaGrowth and water relations in a central North Carolina population of <italic>Microstegium vimineum</italic> (Trin.) A. CamusDrought tolerance versus drought avoidance: a comparison of plant–water relations in herbaceous wetland plants subjected to water withdrawal and repletionTolerance and avoidance: two contrasting physiological responses to salt stress in mature marsh halophytes <italic>Juncus roemerianus</italic> Scheele and <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> LoiselSalt spray induces osmotic adjustment and tissue rigidity in smooth cordgrass, <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> (Loisel.)Ecophysiological responses of five emergent-wetland plants to diminished water supply: an experimental microcosm studyRidge crest versus swale: contrasting plant–water relations and performance indexes in two understory plant species in a coastal maritime forestComparison of water potentials measured by in situ psychrometry and pressure chamber in morphologically different speciesStationary volumetric elastic modulus and osmotic pressure of the leaf cells of <italic>Halophila ovalis</italic>, <italic>Zostera capricorni</italic>, and <italic>Posidonia australis</italic>Plant water relations in a San Francisco Bay salt marshHydrologic variability and the application of index of biotic integrity metrics to wetlands: a Great Lakes evaluationSeagrass leaves in 3-D: using computed tomography and low frequency acoustics to investigate the material properties of seagrass tissueEffect of salinity on water relations of two growth forms of <italic>Suaeda calceoliformis</italic><bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Tim J. BrodribbThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.The flexibility of plant cell walls is characterized by bulk modulus of elasticity (<italic>ϵ</italic>); which is an important component of how plants maintain adequate water continent. For example, plants with rigid tissues (high <italic>ϵ</italic>) that accumulate solutes may better tolerate drought or saline soils. This concept is termed the ‘cell water conservation hypothesis.’ While it is generally held that marine plants have higher <italic>ϵ</italic>, no study has considered that notion across a number of species residing in marine and coastal habitats. The finding from this study show that aquatic marine plants do maintain rigid tissues with lower osmotic potentials (relative to freshwater plants), and support the tenets of the cell water conservation hypothesisBulk modulus of elasticity (<italic>ɛ</italic>), depicting the flexibility of plant tissues, is recognized as an important component in maintaining internal water balance. Elevated <italic>ɛ</italic> and comparatively low osmotic potential (<italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>) may work in concert to effectively maintain vital cellular water content. This concept, termed the ‘cell water conservation hypothesis’, may foster tolerance for lower soil-water potentials in plants while minimizing cell dehydration and shrinkage. Therefore, the accumulation of solutes in marine plants, causing decreases in <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>, play an important role in plant–water relations and likely works with higher <italic>ɛ</italic> to achieve favourable cell volumes. While it is generally held that plants residing in marine systems have higher leaf tissue <italic>ɛ</italic>, to our knowledge no study has specifically addressed this notion in aquatic and wetland plants residing in marine and freshwater systems. Therefore, we compared <italic>ɛ</italic> and <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> in leaf tissues of 38 freshwater, coastal and marine plant species using data collected in our laboratory, with additional values from the literature. Overall, 8 of the 10 highest <italic>ɛ</italic> values were observed in marine plants, and 20 of the lowest 25 <italic>ɛ</italic> values were recorded in freshwater plants. As expected, marine plants often had lower <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>, wherein the majority of marine plants were below −1.0 MPa and the majority of freshwater plants were above −1.0 MPa. While there were no differences among habitat type and symplastic water content (<italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub>), we did observe higher <italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub> in shrubs when compared with graminoids, and believe that the comparatively low <italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub> observed in aquatic grasses may be attributed to their tendency to develop aerenchyma that hold apoplastic water. These results, with few exceptions, support the premise that leaf tissues of plants acclimated to marine environments tend to have higher <italic>ɛ</italic> and lower <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>, and agree with the general tenets of the cell water conservation hypothesis.The flexibility of plant tissues, as characterized by bulk modulus of elasticity (<italic>ɛ</italic>), is an important component of plant–water relations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C40">Steudle <italic>et al.</italic> 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C19">Joly and Zaerr 1987</xref>). Plants with relatively flexible cell walls (low <italic>ɛ</italic>) can maintain adequate turgor during periods of tissue-water decline (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C7">Clifford <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). In contrast, rigid tissues restrict appreciable changes in cell size, and it has been suggested that limiting cellular water flux could help maintain intermolecular distances within cell fluids supporting optimal metabolic function (e.g. maintaining appropriate cellular pH or preventing ‘salting out’ of important metabolites; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C20">Jones 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C21">Jones and Corlett 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C7">Clifford <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). Cell wall elasticity and osmotic potentials (<italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>) are closely linked to changes in cell volume (e.g. Δ<italic>V</italic>/Δ<italic>Ψ</italic> = <italic>V</italic>/(<italic>ɛ</italic> + <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C50">Tyerman 1982</xref>), and it is possible that rigid tissues can limit dehydration as both low <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> and high <italic>ɛ</italic> together are effective means of maintaining vital cellular water content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C6">Cheung <italic>et al.</italic> 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C3">Bartlett <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). This concept, termed the ‘cell water conservation hypothesis’, likely plays an important role in marine and coastal plants that accumulate ions or other solutes as an osmoregulatory response to elevated environmental salts.Although plants with comparatively rigid tissues tend to lose turgor faster than plants with more flexible tissues (given comparable decreases in cell volume), loss in turgor may promote other important water-stress responses including stomatal closure, wilting and leaf rolling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C1">Barker <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>). Changes in <italic>ɛ</italic> may be induced by developmental and/or environmental factors including plant or tissue age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C5">Bowman and Roberts 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C30">Moore and Cosgrove 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C29">Merchant <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>), hysteresis from water stress altering cell wall viscoelastic properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C33">Nolte and Schopfer 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C39">Schopfer 2006</xref>), drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C19">Joly and Zaerr 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C7">Clifford <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C44">Touchette <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>) and salinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C4">Bolaños and Longstreth 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C32">Nabil and Coudret 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C45">Touchette <italic>et al.</italic> 2009<italic>a</italic></xref>). Indeed, these factors often work in concert, wherein the specific response of <italic>ɛ</italic> to water stress may depend on, for example, the age of the tissue during drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C36">Saito and Terashima 2004</xref>). While salinity- and drought-strain are physiologically similar in plants (both fostering cellular dehydration, ion accumulation, formation of reactive oxygen species and diminished photosynthetic capacity), the ratio of accumulated ions will be markedly different due to selective ion uptake during salinity stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C24">Kirst 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C2">Bartels and Sunkar 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C42">Touchette 2007</xref>). Moreover, it would appear that salt stress promotes a disproportionally higher <italic>ɛ</italic> and lower <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> in coastal–marine plants in comparison to drought stress which fosters smaller increases or even decreases in tissue elasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C44">Touchette <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C45">2009<italic>a</italic></xref>). In some plant tissues, higher salinities can promote up to a 30-fold increase in <italic>ɛ</italic> along with a concomitant accumulation of compatible osmolytes that lower <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C4">Bolaños and Longstreth 1984</xref>). In contrast, one study found that three of five freshwater perennials receiving drought had decreased <italic>ɛ</italic> and/or increased <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C44">Touchette <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>).As mentioned, several studies have shown strong associations between elevated environmental salinities and increased tissue rigidities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C4">Bolaños and Longstreth 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C37">Salpeter <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). These findings, in general, suggest that marine halophytes should have higher <italic>ɛ</italic> values compared with freshwater or terrestrial plant species. To our knowledge, however, no study has been conducted to fully consider this relationship in hydrophytic angiosperms. Therefore, the purpose of this investigation was to test the hypothesis that coastal or marine aquatic and wetland plants (exposed to natural and/or artificial salinities) will have higher <italic>ɛ</italic> relative to plants residing in freshwater systems. We also wanted to consider how <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> and symplastic water content (<italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub>) interact with <italic>ɛ</italic> in promoting optimal water relations in plants from different aquatic systems. We intentionally focused on aquatic and wetland plants residing in relatively stable hydrologies as plants previously exposed to low soil moistures may have altered physiological properties (e.g. tissue elasticity and solute content) that would promote greater tolerances towards future soil-water deficits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C31">Morgan 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C44">Touchette <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Therefore, as prevailing water conditions may be an important determinant for <italic>ɛ</italic>, we wanted to avoid using plants from natural systems with unknown water histories (e.g. terrestrial or upland environments) and perhaps prior drought exposure.List of plant species use in this assessment. Data include species, taxonomic family, habitat (freshwater, coastal or marine), growth form (forb-herb, graminoid or shrub), environmental conditions at the time of collection (including salinity for marine plants; in practical salinity units [psu]) and the reference or source of the data.Plants were selected either from natural populations where hydrology was expected to be fairly static (e.g. lake or perennial stream populations) or from greenhouse-maintained hydrophytes grown in flooded or soil-saturated containers (20-L microcosms as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C47">Touchette <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) for more than 12 months. For the most part, collected plants were restricted to Atlantic coastal regions of North America, including Maryland, North Carolina and Vermont. During the collection of coastal and marine plants, ambient environmental salinities were recorded in surface or soil pore-waters located near the plant. Pressure–volume measurements were restricted to young fully expanded leaves to minimize differences attributed to the tissue developmental stage.To complement data obtained on our cultured/collected samples and to expand the number of species used in this evaluation, we also incorporated values from other studies reported in the literature. For the most part, the data used were from known aquatic species (emergent or submersed plants) that were either collected or maintained in water-saturated environments (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU014TB1">1</xref>).A Scholander pressure chamber (model no. 1000; PMS Instrument Co., Albany, OR, USA; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C38">Scholander <italic>et al.</italic> 1965</xref>) was used to determine leaf-water potentials (<italic>Ψ</italic><sub>leaf</sub>) on 5–10 plants per species (samples collected from different individuals with the quantity depending on the abundance or rarity of the species being considered). Prior to conducting pressure–volume analyses, leaves were fully submerged in deionized water and allowed to reach full turgor in darkness. During analysis, water deficits were established by exposing the samples to transpirational water loss on a laboratory bench. This process was favoured by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C49">Turner <italic>et al.</italic> (1984)</xref> as it minimized possible disequilibria of <italic>Ψ</italic> between apoplastic and symplastic tissues.For comparing species physiological characteristics (both data collected from our laboratory and values obtained from the literature), we used the mean value reported for each species with the exception of three seagrasses (<italic>Halophila ovalis</italic>, <italic>Posidonia australis</italic> and <italic>Zostera capricorni</italic>). For those exceptions, the reported values were maxima and <italic>ɛ</italic> were stationary volumetric elastic moduli (<italic>ɛ</italic><sub>s</sub>) and not the more commonly reported instantaneous volumetric elastic moduli (<italic>ɛ</italic><sub>i</sub>). Note, for comparative purposes, <italic>ɛ</italic><sub>i</sub> values tend to be higher than <italic>ɛ</italic><sub>s</sub> when recorded on the same plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C50">Tyerman 1982</xref>). Regression analyses were performed using Pearson product moment to identify correlates among physiological traits. Species-specific data were then combined into habitat types (i.e. freshwater, coastal or marine) to derive an overall grand mean. Because of the small sample sizes for coastal and marine plants, unequal replication and frequent occurrence of unequal variances, we elected to compare values classified within each habitat using a non-parametric Kruskal–Wallis one-way analysis of variance (KW one-way ANOVA) followed by Dunn's multiple comparisons test for <italic>post hoc</italic> evaluations. To further consider relationships between habitat type and physiological characteristics, we employed principal components analysis (PCA) as a reduction tool for plant physiological traits (i.e. <italic>ɛ</italic>, <italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub>, <inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm sat}} $</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm tlp}} $</tex-math></inline-formula>) specific to each habitat. Initial observations also indicated that growth form (graminoid, forb and shrub) may explain some physiological traits. Therefore, grand mean values classified by plant form were also compared using KW one-way ANOVAs followed by Dunn's multiple comparisons test. All comparisons were considered significant at <italic>α</italic> = 0.05.Pearson correlation matrix for plant–water relation parameters, bulk modulus of elasticity (<italic>ɛ</italic>), osmotic potential at full saturation (<italic>Ψ</italic><sub>π</sub><sup>sat</sup>), osmotic potential at turgor loss point (<italic>Ψ</italic><sub>π</sub><sup>tlp</sup>) and symplastic water content (<italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub>). Data from all species (the number of species was between 30 and 34, depending on data availability) were used regardless of habitat designation. The matrix includes correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic>), probability values (<italic>P</italic> values) and number of comparisons made (<italic>n</italic>).Bulk elastic moduli (<italic>ɛ</italic>) of aquatic and wetland plants considered in this study. Data include values reported for different species and their respective environmental conditions including freshwater (white bars), coastal (grey bars) and marine (black bars). Data, where applicable, are presented as means ± 1 standard error (SE).Solute potentials at full saturation (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm sat}} $</tex-math></inline-formula>) of aquatic and wetland plants considered in this study. Data include values reported for different species and their respective environmental conditions including freshwater (white bars), coastal (grey bars) and marine (black bars). Data, where applicable, are presented as means ± 1 SE.Solute potentials at turgor loss point (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm tlp}} $</tex-math></inline-formula>) of aquatic and wetland plants considered in this study. Data include values reported for different species and their respective environmental conditions including freshwater (white bars), coastal (grey bars) and marine (black bars). Note that data were not available for a few marine plant species. Data, where applicable, are presented as means ± 1 SE.Bulk elastic moduli (<italic>ɛ</italic>; A), solute potentials at full saturation (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm sat}} $</tex-math></inline-formula>; B), symplastic water content (<italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub>; C) and solute potential at turgor loss point (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm tlp}} $</tex-math></inline-formula>; D) for plants categorized as freshwater (white bars), coastal (grey bars) and marine (black bars). Statistical differences are indicated by the letters above the bars, wherein different letters identify significant differences among the three habitat types. Data are presented as means (grand means for each category as described in the Methods section) ± 1 SE.Symplastic water content (<italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub>) of aquatic and wetland plants considered in this study. Data include values reported for different species and their respective environmental conditions including freshwater (white bars), coastal (grey bars) and marine (black bars). Note that data were not available for a few marine plant species. Data, where applicable, are presented as means ± 1 SE.Bulk elastic moduli (<italic>ɛ</italic>; A), solute potentials at full saturation (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm sat}} $</tex-math></inline-formula>; B), symplastic water content (<italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub>; C) and solute potential at turgor loss point (<inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm tlp}} $</tex-math></inline-formula>; D) for plants categorized by form including graminoids (white bars), forbs (grey bars) and shrubs (black bars). Statistical differences are indicated by the letters above the bars, wherein different letters identify significant differences among the three habitat types. Data are presented as means (grand means for each category as described in the Methods section) ± 1 SE.Matrix of eigenvector loadings for physiological predictors for freshwater, coastal and marine plants. Most of the variance was explained by the first four principal components (97.1 %; 77.3 % was explained by the first two principal components).Principal components analysis of physiological traits (<italic>ɛ</italic>, <italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub>, <inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm sat}} $</tex-math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">${\it \Psi} _\pi ^{{\rm tlp}} $</tex-math></inline-formula>) measured in different aquatic and wetland plant species including freshwater (white circles), coastal (grey circles) and marine (black circles). Percentages of explained variances for the first and second principal components (PC) are in parentheses. Note the pronounced horizontal tendencies between freshwater and marine species.In response to sudden changes in plant-water status (e.g. water availability and/or environmental salinity), turgor pressure in tissues may increase or decrease as water moves in the direction of the osmotic gradient. The degree of water flux is largely dependent on hydraulic conductivity of cell membranes, intracellular osmotic pressure, cell volume and elastic properties of cell walls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C50">Tyerman 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C26">Kramer and Boyer 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C42">Touchette 2007</xref>). Cell wall elasticity can vary greatly among plant species, with reported ranges of <italic>ɛ</italic> from 0.06 MPa in <italic>Halicystis parvula</italic> to 70 MPa in <italic>Chara corrallina</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C10">Dainty <italic>et al.</italic> 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C12">Graves and Gutknecht 1976</xref>). In some instances, flexible cell walls (low <italic>ɛ</italic>) can benefit plants inhabiting systems with dynamic salinity fluctuations, as cell walls expand or contract in order to maintain osmotic equilibrium with the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C24">Kirst 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C41">Touchette 2006</xref>). In hyperosmotic conditions, for example, lower <italic>ɛ</italic> can foster positive turgor pressures during periods of water efflux. These physiological processes are sometimes employed in estuarine macroalgae, where changes in osmolyte levels (i.e. <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>) and cell volume are important mechanisms for osmotic adjustment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C24">Kirst 1989</xref>). For these algae, sudden changes in water salinity may be balanced by expanding or shrinking of comparatively thin cell walls.Based on observations from this study, however, only a few marine angiosperms actually have relatively flexible cell walls (<italic>ɛ</italic> &lt; 10 MPa). This response may be explained, in part, by the saline dynamics within the particular system. <italic>Schoenoplectus robustus</italic>, for example, had the eighth lowest <italic>ɛ</italic> of the 38 species considered. Although classified as a salt marsh plant, <italic>S. robustus</italic> resides along the mid-to-upper boundaries of salt marsh systems where salinities tend to be relatively low (sometimes freshwater) with sporadic inundations of higher saline waters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C51">Ustin <italic>et al.</italic> 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C9">Crain <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Indeed, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C51">Ustin <italic>et al.</italic> (1982)</xref> were able to demonstrate that among the different salt marsh zones, the regions dominated by <italic>S. robustus</italic> maintained the greatest seasonal fluctuations in salinity. Not only would having comparatively flexible tissues benefit <italic>S. robustus</italic> in this osmotically dynamic environment, but apparently <italic>S. robustus</italic> can lie dormant as tubers for up to 2 years to avoid extended periods of hypersalinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C51">Ustin <italic>et al.</italic> 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C9">Crain <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). Furthermore, <italic>S. robustus</italic> had comparatively high <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> (the third highest among all species in this study); thus any substantial decline in cell volume may not confine existing solutes to levels where metabolic functions are compromised (e.g. salting out metabolites). <italic>Spartina patens</italic>, which also has relatively flexible tissues, is common along the upper reaches of salt marshes where it is fed by shallow freshwater systems. Unlike <italic>S. robustus</italic>, <italic>S. patens</italic> can have comparatively low <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> (−2.14 MPa), although highly variable with some reported potentials as high as −0.25 MPa. Apparently, <italic>S. patens</italic> can undergo extended periods of salt avoidance when exposed to hypersaline conditions, and perhaps these delays in modifying plant–water relations may contribute to a greater range in both <italic>ɛ</italic> and <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C37">Salpeter <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). That is, <italic>S. patens</italic> will likely maintain low <italic>ɛ</italic> and high <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> when exposed to short periods of high salinity, but longer exposures (&gt;5 weeks) may foster physiological alterations that include higher <italic>ɛ</italic> and lower <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C37">Salpeter <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). The seagrass <italic>H. wrightii</italic> had the sixth most flexible tissue of the 38 species considered and, as with the other 2 species, resides in osmotically dynamic systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C41">Touchette 2006</xref>). That is, <italic>H. wrightii</italic> has been shown to thrive in the Guadalupe estuary where salinities can fluctuate from 5 to 25 practical salinity units (psu) over a few months, with periodic spikes in salinities up to 55 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C11">Dunton 1996</xref>). We argue that for <italic>S. robustus</italic>, <italic>S. patens</italic> and <italic>H. wrightii</italic> to survive in these highly dynamic euryhaline environments, like estuarine macroalgae, maintaining flexible cell walls could be advantageous provided cytoplasmic ion content remains low and/or <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> remains high (including osmotic adjustments attributed to compatible solutes and/or vacuolar sequestration of ions; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C24">Kirst 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C42">Touchette 2007</xref>).While a few marine plants have relatively flexible cell walls, most studies indicate that plants residing in saline environments will have rigid tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C17">Ike and Thurtell 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C27">Melkonian <italic>et al.</italic> 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C4">Bolaños and Longstreth 1984</xref>). The results from this study, with the aforementioned exceptions, support this previously untested assertion. Here 9 of the 10 species with the highest <italic>ɛ</italic> values were either marine or coastal plants. For plants with comparatively high <italic>ɛ</italic>, a corresponding reduction in osmotic potentials could help prevent dehydration and shrinkage during periods of lower <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>soil</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C6">Cheung <italic>et al.</italic> 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C3">Bartlett <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Rigid cells may also be advantageous in marine plants that tend to sequester ions for osmotic balance, as diminishing cell volume would confine existing solutes and ions to a level that could disrupt cellular processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C42">Touchette 2007</xref>). This notion is supported by the tendency for plants with high <italic>ɛ</italic> to also have low <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> (suggesting high cellular solute content). Therefore, plants residing in more stable marine environments (including lower salt marsh areas or open coastal waters) would benefit from having thicker cell walls with relatively low elasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C24">Kirst 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C42">Touchette 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C3">Bartlett <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>).In contrast to marine species, freshwater plants generally have lower <italic>ɛ</italic> and higher <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>. Although we intentionally focused on plants from areas with more stable hydrologies, freshwater wetlands are transitional areas between terrestrial and deep-water habitats and therefore many of the resident species are physiologically adapted to periodic water deprivation from water-table drawdown and/or drought (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C8">Cowardin <italic>et al.</italic> 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C52">Wilcox <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). For these plants, a small <italic>ɛ</italic> can facilitate turgor maintenance in cells as tissue water declines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C25">Kozlowski <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>). Indeed water stress may promote greater turgor in some plants following water repletion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C23">Kikuta and Richter 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C36">Saito and Terashima 2004</xref>). Maintaining turgor and avoiding plasmolysis are important in plants as high turgor pressure has been shown to enhance membrane transport, plant defence responses, cytoskeleton stability and cytoplasmic streaming (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C28">Mellersh and Heath 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C15">Hayashi and Takagi 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C16">Heidecker <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Therefore, with higher <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic> limiting the likelihood of confining solutes to the point of metabolic disruption (as in marine species), freshwater species tend to maintain flexible cells that minimize the likelihood of zero turgor or plasmolysis.Finally, although there were no significant differences in <italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub> among the three habitats considered in this study, we did observe that growth form may be an important component in determining the level of <italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub> in wetland plants. In this case, graminoids had significantly lower <italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub> than shrubs. One possible explanation for this difference, as well as the overall low <italic>θ</italic><sub>sym</sub> reported in aquatic grasses and forbs, is the predominance of aerenchyma that often develops in grasses and forbs in response to reduced anaerobic substratums (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C18">Jackson and Armstrong 1999</xref>). In this case, the substantial increase in apoplastic volume (due to aerenchyma development) within tissues could act, in part, as reservoirs for maintaining comparatively higher apoplastic water and consequently a proportionally lower symplastic water content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C13">Gribble <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). The use of aerenchyma as a possible apoplastic water reservoir, along with other roles (e.g. a lacunar system that provides oxygen to roots residing in hypoxic/anoxic sediments; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU014C14">Grosse and Mevi-Schütz 1987</xref>), could benefit emergent wetland plants by providing water to the cells during periods of soil-water deficit or drought.In this study, we were able to demonstrate that marine plants, by and large, do have higher <italic>ɛ</italic> and lower <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>. By maintaining rigid tissues and lower <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>, marine plants may be able to both prevent dangerous dehydration and achieve tolerance of lower <italic>Ψ</italic><sub>soil</sub> (i.e. the ‘cell water conservation hypothesis’). Maintaining higher cellular water content could help minimize metabolic disruptions that may develop when existing solutes, already in high concentrations, are confined into smaller spaces during water efflux. In contrast, freshwater plants tend to have lower <italic>ɛ</italic> and higher <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>. Flexible tissues would allow for appreciable water loss while maintaining positive turgor pressure. In this case, because cellular solute content is low (i.e. high <italic>Ψ<sub>π</sub></italic>) there may be greater probability that physiological disruptions will occur due to plasmolysis rather than to solute confinement.This study was supported by the North Carolina Sea Grant (NCSG), UNC Water Resources Research Institute (WRRI) and the Japheth E. Rawls Foundation.Experiments were carried out by all three authors. Compilation of data from previous published studies was conducted by B.W.T. and S.E.M. Data and statistical analyses were performed by all authors. The manuscript was written by B.W.T. and S.E.M.None declared.We are grateful for the continued support from the North Carolina Sea Grant and the UNC Water Resources Research Institute. Laboratory space and consumable materials were generously provided by the Departments of Biology and Environmental Studies at Elon University. We greatly appreciate the thoughtful and constructive comments from the managing editor T. Brodribb and two anonymous reviewers.