Light–dark O<sub>2</sub> dynamics in submerged leaves of C<sub>3</sub> and C<sub>4</sub> halophytes under increased dissolved CO<sub>2</sub>: clues for saltmarsh response to climate changeInteractions between light and CO<sub>2</sub> enhance the growth of <italic>Riccia fluitans</italic>Flooding stress: acclimations and genetic diversityThe use of pulse amplitude modulated (PAM) fluorometry for <italic>in situ</italic> measurements of photosynthesis in two Red Sea Faviid coralsMeasuring photosynthesis in seagrasses by pulse amplitude modulated (PAM) fluorometryEnzymes as biochemical reagentsFacing the inevitable: plants and increasing atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantification of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye-bindingSpecies zonation in Corroios salt marsh in the Tagus estuary (Portugal) and its dynamics in the past fifty yearsStock and losses of trace metals from salt marsh plantsDevelopment of an angiosperm quality assessment index (AQuA—index) for ecological quality evaluation of Portuguese water bodies—a multi-metric approachUnderwater photosynthesis and respiration in leaves of submerged wetland plants: gas films improve CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> exchangeFlooding tolerance: suites of plant traits in variable environments<italic>Spartina maritima</italic> (cordgrass) rhizosediment extracellular enzymatic activity and its role on organic matter decomposition and metal speciation processesAccumulation and biological cycling of heavy metal in the root–sediment system of four salt marsh species, from Tagus estuary (Portugal)Hexavalent chromium reduction, uptake and oxidative biomarkers in <italic>Halimione portulacoides</italic>Ecophysiological adaptations of two halophytes to salt stress: photosynthesis, PS II photochemistry and anti-oxidant feedback—implications for resilience in climate changeAbiotic modulation of <italic>Spartina maritima</italic> photosynthetic ecotypic variations in different latitudinal populationsPhotochemical and biophysical feedbacks of C3 and C4 Mediterranean halophytes to atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment confirmed by their stable isotope signaturesBiophysical probing of <italic>Spartina maritima</italic> photosystem II changes during increased submersion periods: possible adaptation to sea level riseHeavy metal distribution and partitioning in the vicinity of the discharge areas of Lisbon drainage basins (Tagus Estuary, Portugal)C4 pathwayElevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration ameliorates effects of NaCl salinity on photosynthesis and leaf structure of <italic>Aster tripolium</italic> LThe relationship between the quantum yield of photosynthetic electron transport and quenching of chlorophyll fluorescenceLong-chain (C<sub>19</sub>–C<sub>29</sub>) 1-chloro-<italic>n</italic>-alkanes in leaf waxes of halophytes of the ChenopodiaceaePhotosynthetic pathway diversity in a seasonal pool communityThe carboxylation and oxygenation of ribulose-1,5-biphosphate carboxylase: the primary event in photosynthesis and photorespirationInvolvement of superoxide anion radical in the autoxidation of pyrogallol and a convenient assay for superoxide dismutaseA mechanistic model of photoinhibitionSubmergence-induced leaf acclimation in terrestrial species varying in flooding toleranceSubmergence effects on rice genotypes during seedling stage: probing of submergence driven changes of photosystem 2 by chlorophyll a fluorescence induction O–J–I–P transientsOxygen dynamics during submergence in the halophytic stem succulent <italic>Halosarcia pergranulata</italic>Surviving floods: leaf gas films improve O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> exchange, root aeration, and growth of completely submerged riceSubmergence tolerance of <italic>Hordeum marinum</italic>: dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> determines underwater photosynthesis and growthPhotoinhibition of photosynthesis in natural assemblages of marine phytoplanktonEnvironmental characterization of floodwater in Eastern India: relevance to submergence tolerance of lowland riceExogenous inorganic carbon sources in plant photosynthesisEndogenous inorganic carbon sources in plant photosynthesis. II. Comparison of total CO<sub>2</sub> production in the light with measured CO<sub>2</sub> evolution in the lightAmong-shoot variability and leaf-specific absorbance characteristics affect diel estimates of <italic>in situ</italic> electron transport of <italic>Posidonia australis</italic>Environmental variables and their effect on photosynthesis of aquatic plant communities. General features to aquatic photosynthesisPhotosynthetic use of inorganic carbon among primary and secondary water plants in streamsModelling the primary production of intertidal microphytobenthos: time scales of variability and effects of migratory rhythmsSubmergence of rice I. Growth and photosynthetic response to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment of floodwaterPhotosynthesis by aquatic plants: effects of unstirred layers in relation to assimilation of CO<sub>2</sub> and HCO<sup>−</sup><sub>3</sub> and to carbon isotopic discriminationEstimation of the energetic connectivity of PS II centres in plants using the fluorescence rise O–J–I–P. Fitting of experimental data to three different PS II modelsCatalase activities of hydrocarbon-utilizing <italic>Candida yeast</italic>Antioxidant defence system and cadmium uptake in barley genotypes differing in cadmium tolerance‘Omics’ analyses of regulatory networks in plant abiotic stress responsesPlant hormones regulate fast shoot elongation under water: from genes to communitiesEmerging concept for the role of photorespiration as an important part of abiotic stress responseQuantitative assessment to the structural basis of water repellency in natural and technical surfacesDiurnal changes in radial oxygen loss and ethanol metabolism in roots of submerged and non-submerged rice seedlingsTranscriptional regulatory networks in cellular responses and tolerance to dehydration and cold stressesChlorophyll a fluorescence induction kinetics in leaves predicted from a model describing each discrete step of excitation energy and electron transfer associated with Photosystem IIGuest Editor: Tim J. FlowersThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Global warming and climate change, as driving forces of sea level rise, tend to increase marsh submersion periods and also modify the carbonate chemistry of the water column due to the increased concentration of CO2 in the atmosphere. Photosynthetic enhancement due to increased dissolved CO2 was confirmed for both C3 and C4 halophytes. Transposing these findings to the ecosystem, and assuming increased dissolved CO2 concentration scenarios, the halophyte community displays a new ecosystem function, increasing the water column oxygenation and thus reinforcing their role as principal primary producers of the estuarine systemWaterlogging and submergence are the major constraints to which wetland plants are subjected, with inevitable impacts on their physiology and productivity. Global warming and climate change, as driving forces of sea level rise, tend to increase such submersion periods and also modify the carbonate chemistry of the water column due to the increased concentration of CO<sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere. In the present work, the underwater O<sub>2</sub> fluxes in the leaves of two abundant Mediterranean halophytes were evaluated at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub>. Photosynthetic enhancement due to increased dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> was confirmed for both <italic>Halimione portulacoides</italic> and <italic>Spartina maritima</italic>, probably due to high tissue porosity, formation of leaf gas films and reduction of the oxygenase activity of Rubisco. Enhancement of the photosynthetic rates in <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> and <italic>S. maritima</italic> was concomitant with an increase in energy trapping and transfer, mostly due to enhancement of the carboxylation reaction of Rubisco, leading to a reduction of the energy costs for carbon fixation. Transposing these findings to the ecosystem, and assuming increased dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> concentration scenarios, the halophyte community displays a new ecosystem function, increasing the water column oxygenation and thus reinforcing their role as principal primary producers of the estuarine system.Wetlands are among the most productive ecosystems of the planet, retaining about one-half to one-third of the carbon fixed and providing important ecosystem services to the estuarine system, namely nutrient regeneration, primary production and shoreline stabilization as well as a habitat for wildlife (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C9">Caçador <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Estuarine wetlands are known for their high productivity, which has been attributed to the high degree of halophyte coverage and diversity, with specific zonation, resulting from inter-specific relationships between species and competition for specific optimal habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C30">Mendelssohn and Morris 2000</xref>). Another key factor defining species expansion, growth and productivity is their exposure to abiotic stresses, both environmental (for example, climate driven) and anthropogenic (for example, pollution with heavy metals). If the future of these ecosystems is to be predicted in the face of climate change, it is of great importance to understand plant stress responses and adaptations at the molecular, biochemical, cellular and physiological levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C55">Yamaguchi-Shinozaki and Shinozaki 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C50">Urano <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>).Waterlogging and submergence are two major features to which wetland plants, especially salt marsh halophytes, are subjected with severe impacts on their survival and productivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C2">Bailey-Serres and Voesenek 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C35">Pedersen <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Due to tidal flooding, shoots and leaves can become completely submerged, restricting gas exchange and light harvesting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C12">Colmer and Voesenek 2009</xref>). The frequency, duration and depth of tidal flooding can influence species distribution in salt marshes, this being determined by, for example, their ecophysiological tolerance to flooding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C51">Voesenek <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C33">Pedersen and Colmer 2006</xref>). Not only does the slow diffusion of CO<sub>2</sub> in the aquatic environment limit its uptake by leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C45">Smith and Walker 1980</xref>), but also the decreased light availability, due to attenuation down the water column, impairs photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C41">Sand-Jensen 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C33">Pedersen and Colmer 2006</xref>). Several plant species have developed leaf adaptations to these constraints in order to enhance underwater CO<sub>2</sub> uptake by reducing morphologically the boundary layer and cuticle resistance or by acquiring HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> directly from the water column (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C11">Colmer and Pedersen 2008</xref>). In submerged leaves of halophytes, CO<sub>2</sub> limitation becomes severe when concentrations are near air equilibrium, due to the elevated saturation point of underwater photosynthesis (20–75 times the water–air equilibrium conditions; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C35">Pedersen <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Taking into account the present projections made by the Intergovernmental Panel for Climate Change (IPCC), it is expected that the increased levels of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> will lead to an inevitable increase in the dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> in water bodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C25">IPCC 2002</xref>), in this way altering the availability of CO<sub>2</sub> underwater.<italic>Spartina maritima</italic> (L.) Loisel (Poaceae) and <italic>Halimione portulacoides</italic> (L.) Allen (Amaranthaceae) are two of the most abundant and productive halophytic plants present in the Mediterranean estuaries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C14">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C10">Caçador <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). These species typically colonize the lower marsh mudflats and the sides of the network of channels within the marshes, being subjected to tidal flooding twice per day (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C13">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C18">2014<italic>a</italic></xref>). Nevertheless, these are photosynthetically different species: <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> utilizes C<sub>3</sub> photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C15">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19">2014<italic>b</italic></xref>), while <italic>S. maritima</italic> is a C<sub>4</sub> plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C16">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2013<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C17"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). Previous work has shown that these species present very different dynamics under atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment as well as under submersion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C18">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19"><italic>b</italic></xref>).In the present paper, we report the O<sub>2</sub> dynamics in both light-exposed and dark-incubated leaves of C<sub>3</sub> <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> and C<sub>4</sub> <italic>S. maritima</italic> under different dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations. This has provided insights not only on the species tolerance to submersion but also how CO<sub>2</sub> can ameliorate the imposed submersion stress and its consequences in the ecosystem services provided, namely in terms of water column oxygenation.Intact turfs of the target species were collected at the end of the growing season (October), 1 day before the experiments started, from the Tagus estuary (Alcochete, 38°45′38.78″N, 8°56′7.37″W). All the turfs of the same species were of similar height to ensure similar ages. The intact turfs and their rhizosediment were transported to the laboratory of Marine Botany of the Centre of Oceanography, in air-exposed trays and placed in a FytoScope Chamber (Photon Systems Instruments, Czech Republic), in a photoperiod (16/8 h light/dark) at 20 °C, until the beginning of the experiments. Sediment was supplemented with one-fourth strength Hoagland solution with the salinity adjusted to 20 ‰ (estuarine salinity) to maintain moisture conditions from the field.The experimental set-up was based on that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C11">Colmer and Pedersen (2008)</xref> for similar experiments. Fully expanded leaves (<italic>n</italic> = 3) were excised from the base of the stem. In the case of <italic>S. maritima</italic> leaves, samples were sliced into similar rectangular segments (∼5 cm) by cutting their extremities. For <italic>H. portulacoides</italic>, intact excised leaves were used, as their approximate length was 5 cm. The segments were immediately placed in 50-mL plastic gas-tight bottles with rubber stoppers (three bottles containing three leaf segments each, per treatment). The Hoagland solution (¼ strength) was used as the incubation medium with salinity adjusted to 20 ‰ (estuarine salinity) with sea salt mixture and supplemented with KHCO<sub>3</sub> in order to attain the desired dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> levels (0.05, 0.5, 1.0 and 2.0 mM) and the pH adjusted to 6 with KOH, according to field measurements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C20">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>c</italic></xref>). These four dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations correspond to 5.0, 50.0, 100 and 200 μM of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>, respectively. Three replicate bottles per treatment were maintained in the light (PAR 400 μmol photons m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> inside the bottle), while the remaining three replicate bottles were darkened. Both groups were maintained at 25 °C. Bottles containing only the incubation medium were placed under the same conditions to confirm that the O<sub>2</sub> concentrations were maintained constant in the absence of leaves. Underwater net photosynthesis (<italic>P</italic><sub>N</sub>) and respiration (<italic>R</italic><sub>N</sub>) were measured using a dissolved oxygen electrode (WTW Oxi 330i/SET) after 2 h. All tubes were gently stirred every 30 min to allow a homogeneous distribution of oxygen on the incubation medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C11">Colmer and Pedersen 2008</xref>), as confirmed by the constant O<sub>2</sub> values verified in the blank tubes (only Hoagland solution at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> without leaves) during the time course. The lack of headspace prevented the escape of gaseous CO<sub>2</sub>. Due to differences in the morphology and succulence of the leaves of the two species, O<sub>2</sub> fluxes were expressed on the basis of dry weight. To determine the dry weight (DW) of the leaves, 20 samples per species, from the same intact turfs used in the experiments, were collected and dried at 60 °C until constant weight and re-weighted. This normalization was adopted instead of using chlorophyll since during stress conditions chlorophyll content can be affected and thus affect the normalization.In order to achieve a projection of the O<sub>2</sub> production/consumption rates in the Tagus estuarine system, the rates determined in this work were combined with the known biomasses and areas colonized by each of the studied species in the Tagus estuary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C9">Caçador <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C14">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C10">Caçador <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). The computed values were expressed on a daily basis, considering two high tides per day (one in daytime and another during the night) with a maximum period of plant submersion of 3 h (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C43">Serôdio and Catarino 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). The calculations were made for the four dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> scenarios tested in the present work and the O<sub>2</sub> production/consumption rates obtained experimentally.Summary of fluorometric analysis parameters and their description. NPQ, non-photochemical quenching.All enzyme extraction procedures were performed at 4 °C. Briefly, fresh leaves were homogenized in sodium phosphate buffer (50 mM, pH 7.6) with Na-EDTA (0.1 mM) at a ratio of 8 mL per 500 mg fresh weight. The homogenate was centrifuged at 8923 rpm for 20 min, at 4 °C, and the supernatant was used for the enzymatic assays. Enzymatic activity measurements were performed at room temperature (18 °C).Catalase (CAT) activity was measured according to the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C48">Teranishi <italic>et al.</italic> (1974)</xref> by monitoring the consumption of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and consequent decrease in absorbance at 240 nm. (<italic>ɛ</italic> = 39.4 mM<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−1</sup>). The reaction mixture contained sodium phosphate buffer (50 mM, pH 7.6), Na-EDTA (0.1 mM) and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (100 mM). The reaction was started with the addition of the extract. Ascorbate peroxidase was assayed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C49">Tiryakioglu <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>. The reaction mixture contained sodium phosphate buffer (50 mM, pH 7.0), H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (12 mM) and <sc>l</sc>-ascorbate (0.25 mM). The reaction was initiated with the addition of 100 µL of the enzyme extract. The activity was recorded as the decrease in absorbance at 290 nm, and the amount of ascorbate oxidized was calculated from the molar extinction coefficient of 2.8 mM<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−1</sup>.Guaiacol peroxidase was measured by the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C5">Bergmeyer <italic>et al.</italic> (1974)</xref> with a reaction mixture consisting of sodium phosphate buffer (50 mM, pH 7.0), H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (2 mM) and guaiacol (20 mM). The reaction was initiated with the addition of 100 µL of the enzyme extract. The enzymatic activity was measured by monitoring the increase in absorbance at 470 nm (<italic>ɛ</italic> = 26.6 mM<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−1</sup>).Superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity was assayed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C28">Marklund and Marklund (1974)</xref> by monitoring the reduction of pyrogallol at 325 nm. The reaction mixture contained sodium phosphate buffer (50 mM, pH 7.6), Na-EDTA (0.1 mM), pyrogallol (3 mM) and Milli-Q water. The reaction was started with the addition of 10 µL of the enzyme extract. Control assays were done in the absence of a substrate in order to evaluate the auto-oxidation of the substrates.All enzymatic activities were expressed as U μg<sup>−1</sup> of protein, where U, a unit, is the amount of enzyme that catalyses the conversion of 1 μmol of substrate per second. Proteins were determined according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C7">Bradford (1976)</xref>, using bovine serum albumin as the standard protein.In order to compare the results of the different ecophysiological parameters between species at different treatments, the Kruskal–Wallis test was employed. Statistical analyses were carried out using the Statistica Software version 10 (StatSoft).Oxygen production and consumption by the two tested species under light and dark conditions, at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> (average ± standard deviation, <italic>n</italic> = 9. Letters indicate significant differences among CO<sub>2</sub> treatments at <italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05).Photosystem II variable fluorescence and quantum efficiencies (operational and maximum) by the two tested species under light and dark conditions, at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> (average ± standard deviation, <italic>n</italic> = 9. Letters indicate significant differences among CO<sub>2</sub> treatments at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Kautsky OJIP curves of the two tested species under light and dark conditions, at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> (average, <italic>n</italic> = 9).OJIP-driven photochemical parameters in the two tested species under light and dark conditions, at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> (average ± standard deviation, <italic>n</italic> = 9. Letters indicate significant differences among CO<sub>2</sub> treatments at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Photochemical reactions driving forces in the two tested species under light and dark conditions, at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> (average, <italic>n</italic> = 9).Photosystem II antennae connectivity (PG) and energy fluxes on a leaf cross-section basis, in the leaves of the two tested species under light and dark conditions, at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> (average ± standard deviation, <italic>n</italic> = 9. Letters indicate significant differences among CO<sub>2</sub> treatments at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Peroxidase (CAT, APx and GPx) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity in the leaves of the two tested species under light and dark conditions, at different levels of dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> (average ± standard deviation, <italic>n</italic> = 9. Letters indicate significant differences among CO<sub>2</sub> treatments at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).O<sub>2</sub> (mol) produced (+)/consumed (−) by each halophyte (considering all the coverage area in the Tagus estuary) at the four considered scenarios per day (including light and dark fluxes).Aquatic plants submerged in different coastal ecosystems are often flooded by water with CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations above the air–water equilibrium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C42">Sand-Jensen <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C26">Keeley 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C37">Ram <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C35">Pedersen <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). The dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> concentration is a key factor, as its availability controls underwater net photosynthesis, in both terrestrial and aquatic plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C42">Sand-Jensen <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C11">Colmer and Pedersen 2008</xref>). In estuaries populated with halophytes, not only is their growth controlled by dissolved CO<sub>2</sub>, but also their function as oxygen providers/consumers. The tolerance of these plants to submersion has often been described on the basis of a quiescence response—the lack of shoot elongation conserves carbohydrates during submersion periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C2">Bailey-Serres and Voesenek 2008</xref>). At night-time an increased O<sub>2</sub> deficit arises as another stressor in submerged conditions, due to the plants' dependency on dissolved O<sub>2</sub> entry from floodwaters for night respiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C54">Waters <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C33">Pedersen and Colmer 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C34">Pedersen <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).In the present study, two of the more abundant halophytic species in the Portuguese estuarine ecosystems showed very different feedbacks to increases in dissolved CO<sub>2</sub>. The photosynthetic enhancement due to increased dissolved CO<sub>2</sub>, verified for <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> and <italic>S. maritima</italic>, has already been described for rice and for <italic>Hordeum marinum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C44">Setter <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C35">Pedersen <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). These authors suggested that enhancement was driven by the presence of gas films on the leaf surface and high tissue porosity, allowing higher rates of gas exchange according to CO<sub>2</sub> availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C35">Pedersen <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Also, an increase in [CO<sub>2</sub>]/[O<sub>2</sub>] ratio can improve CO<sub>2</sub>-use efficiency, due to a reduction in Rubisco oxygenase activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C27">Lorimer 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C6">Bowes 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C1">Andersen and Pedersen 2002</xref>). Although this enhancement was detected even at low dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations in <italic>H. portulacoides</italic>, for <italic>S. maritima</italic> it was only achieved at high CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations. <italic>Spartina maritima</italic> proved to be highly adapted to submersion, in line with a recent study that also demonstrated the plasticity of <italic>S. maritima</italic> as an efficient adaptation to flooding, allowing plants to recover quickly from the stress imposed by this condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). Being a C<sub>4</sub> species, these results for <italic>S. maritima</italic> point to a reduction in the oxygenase activity of Rubisco as a consequence of the extremely high internal [CO<sub>2</sub>]/[O<sub>2</sub>]; this, together with a high resistance to CO<sub>2</sub> entry, restricts underwater photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C27">Lorimer 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C6">Bowes 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C1">Andersen and Pedersen 2002</xref>). Although <italic>S. maritima</italic> has a high specific leaf area compared with <italic>H. portulacoides</italic>, the presence of a thicker cuticle is probably the factor responsible for this reduced diffusion underwater (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C31">Mommer <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). In <italic>S. maritima</italic>, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration mechanism occurs in the mesophyll cells catalysed by PEPc supplying the bundle sheath with C4 organic acids, independently of the O<sub>2</sub> concentration. In sum, C<sub>4</sub> plants with their Kranz anatomy rely on the preferential assimilation of HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C38">Raven 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C39">1972</xref>). Additionally, it should be noted that, under submersion in turbid water, mitochondrial respiration must be included as a possible contributor for O<sub>2</sub> budgets. Nevertheless, under these conditions, <italic>S. maritima</italic> HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>-pump allowed an enhancement of the photosynthetic O<sub>2</sub> production at HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> concentrations as low as 200 μM. Thus, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration mechanism in <italic>S. maritima</italic> is apparently highly adapted to underwater conditions, as shown previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>), needing comparatively low HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> concentrations to efficiently supply the bundle sheath cells with the required CO<sub>2</sub> concentration for restarting the Calvin cycle. On the other hand, C<sub>3</sub> plants depend on the availability of CO<sub>2</sub>, and therefore on the leaf gas film formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C38">Raven 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C39">1972</xref>). The presence of wax-rich cuticles has been reported in hydrophobic leaves of <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C24">Grossi and Raphel 2003</xref>) and can result in an improvement in gas film formation at the leaf surface, thus promoting gas exchange (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C44">Setter <italic>et al.</italic> 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C53">Wagner <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C11">Colmer and Pedersen 2008</xref>). Nevertheless, the C<sub>3</sub> mechanism of <italic>H. portulacoides</italic>, dependent on the CO<sub>2</sub> acquisition, only showed a significant enhancement at 0.5 mM CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, making it less efficient than the C<sub>4</sub> of <italic>S. maritima</italic>. All these facts indicate that, while underwater, these species are C<sub>i</sub>-limited at normal inorganic carbon concentration in estuarine water.Alongside the anatomical differences, the photosynthetic and electronic processes showed marked differences in light-harvesting and processing mechanisms. One important fluorescence parameter, normally associated with stress conditions is the variable fluorescence (<italic>F</italic><sub>v</sub>). The maximum photosynthetic O<sub>2</sub> production in <italic>H. portulacoides</italic>, verified at 0.5 mM dissolved CO<sub>2</sub>, also showed the highest value of <italic>F</italic>′<sub>v</sub>, an indicator of low stress conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C15">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). The same was true, but to a smaller extent, for the operational quantum yield of this species.Since CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> compete for the same Rubisco active sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C47">Taiz and Zeiger 2002</xref>), favouring the carboxylation process and reduction of the oxygenation capacity of Rubisco also implies a decrease in the energy costs for CO<sub>2</sub> fixation and a consequent increase in PSII quantum yield for photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C21">Furbank 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C47">Taiz and Zeiger 2002</xref>). This was confirmed by analysing the principal driving forces underlying the electronic photosynthetic processes. In <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> and <italic>S. maritima</italic> there was not only an increase in the driving forces related to the trapping of excitation energy, but also in transfer of this energy to the electron transport chain. Both these increases lead to an enhancement in total driving force for photosynthesis. It was also interesting to note that, in both species, there were no changes in the light energy absorption ability, confirming the above-mentioned hypothesis (increased PSII efficiency induced by higher Rubisco carboxylation rates) and pointing to an increase in photosynthetic activity due to higher CO<sub>2</sub> availability. In fact, in <italic>S. maritima</italic> this was related to an increase in the probability of a PSII trapped electron being transferred from QA to QB (<italic>ψ</italic>0) as well as for the quantum yield of this transport between quinones (<italic>φ</italic>Eo).All these findings are confirmed by the analysis of the energy fluxes on a cross-sectional area basis. Both species maintained their number of available PSII RC constants and thus the absorbed and trapped energy fluxes did not suffer any changes. Differences arise if the integrity of the PSII antennae is observed and are the basis of the increased energy processing efficiency observed in <italic>S. maritima</italic> leaves. This parameter accounts for all the energetic communication pathways between neighbour PSII antennae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C46">Strasser and Stirbet 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C32">Panda <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). On the contrary to what has been observed in other terrestrial plants, there was no loss of connectivity between the antennae of the PSII units during submersion, indicating an improved survival strategy for underwater conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C32">Panda <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). The increased PSII antennae integrity in <italic>S. maritima</italic> leads to an enhanced efficiency in transporting energy and thus reduction of the dissipated energy. Although this was also noticed in <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> leaves subjected to the highest dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations tested, it did not result in a significant improvement of the energy fluxes use efficiency, indicating that the increasing dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations do not affect <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> leaves at the energy processing but in deeper processes.Comparing the data on antioxidant enzymatic activities with the data from the oxygen production, <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> showed a maximum photosynthetic O<sub>2</sub> production at 0.5 mM CO<sub>2</sub> decreasing towards higher CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations, concomitantly with an increase in CAT activity. This O<sub>2</sub> production decreased or increased consumption during daytime conditions as well as increased CAT activity, which is in agreement with photorespiratory activation. It is known that activation of photorespiration is an important part of the abiotic stress feedback as a means to dissipate the excessive energy trapped (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C52">Voss <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). With the activation of this mechanism, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is generated and scavenged by the increased CAT activity. In fact, looking at the data from the principal driving forces, the increase in CAT activity appears simultaneously with a decrease in the driving forces for trapping excitation energy and for photosynthesis. In the C<sub>4</sub> <italic>S. maritima</italic>, peroxidase activity (APx and GPx) showed a concomitant decrease along with the increase in O<sub>2</sub> production. On the other hand, SOD showed two marked peaks driven by distinct and opposite mechanisms. The first peak at 0.05 mM CO<sub>2</sub> is concomitant with high respiratory activity and increased non-photochemical activity, indicating a need to dissipate excessive photon energy, due to the Ci limitation, similar to that observed in plants exposed to increased atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C22">Geissler <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C18">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>a</italic></xref>). The second observed SOD peak, observed in individuals exposed to 2 mM dissolved CO<sub>2</sub>, is coincident with the increase in the photosynthetic activity, and consequent superoxide radical production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C47">Taiz and Zeiger 2002</xref>).Nevertheless, previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C18">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>a</italic></xref>) with CO<sub>2</sub>-enriched air showed a very different trend, pointing to different stress mechanisms, occurring during submersion. While the C<sub>3</sub> <italic>H. portulacoides</italic> showed an enhancement of the photosynthetic rates while exposed to atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment, the same was not observed for the C<sub>4</sub> <italic>S. maritima</italic>. In the present study, this grass showed a very significant improvement in its photosynthetic rates upon dissolved CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization that was not observed in immersed conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C19">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). This points to two interesting aspects: (i) <italic>S. maritima</italic> is probably <italic>C<sub>i</sub></italic> limited under submersed conditions and (ii) CO<sub>2</sub> in fact ameliorates the stress imposed by submersion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C18">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2014<italic>a</italic></xref>).All these ecophysiological responses have their repercussions for the ecosystem services provided by the salt marshes, namely in terms of O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> production for the water column. Considering the average temperature used in these experiments and the biomass production drawn from the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C9">Caçador <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C14">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) as well as the species coverage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C10">Caçador <italic>et al.</italic> 2013</xref>), a very simple and basic extrapolation was made for the Tagus estuary salt marshes. It was possible to calculate that there is a general trend for increasing water column oxygenation during the daily tidal cycle (two tides, one in the daytime and another during the night-time), driven by plant underwater photosynthesis. This becomes of great importance if we consider salt marshes as one of the most important primary producers in an estuarine system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C8">Caçador <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C10">2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU067C14">Duarte <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Oxygen production by the halophytes becomes a key player overcoming the low rates of air–water O<sub>2</sub> diffusion, and thus introduces important amounts of oxygen required for the heterotrophic species (fishes, macro-invertebrates and bacteria). According to this conclusion, a new saltmarsh service arises as a crucial O<sub>2</sub> producer for the estuarine aquatic community to accompany the role of these marshes as important carbon-harvesting primary producers.The diurnal tidal flooding imposes on the halophyte community an underwater environment where gas concentrations are very different from the atmospheric ones. The predicted atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> increase will have consequences not only on the atmospheric composition, but also on the carbonate chemistry of estuarine water. It is important to consider the physiology of each species, and the consequences that their adaptations to altered CO<sub>2</sub> concentration have in terms of the ecosystem they inhabit. The presence of leaf gas films, lack of tissue porosity or other morphological traits of the leaf, as well as photochemical differences and biochemical responses to the imposed condition, are very important characteristics that from a holistic point of view have enormous impacts on the estuarine water column chemistry as a habitat for heterotrophic species. Salt marshes will play a crucial role in counterbalancing the effects of climate change, in terms of water column oxygenation and in buffering its acidification by withdrawing excess CO<sub>2</sub>.The work was funded by ‘<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia (FCT)</grant-sponsor>’ at the <grant-sponsor id="cs1" rid="cn1" xlink:type="simple">Centre of Oceanography (CO)</grant-sponsor> throughout the project <grant-num id="cn1" rid="cs1" xlink:type="simple">PEst-OE/MAR/UI0199/2011</grant-num>, the <grant-sponsor id="cs2" rid="cn2" xlink:type="simple">Institute of Marine Research (IMAR)</grant-sponsor> throughout the project <grant-num id="cn2" rid="cs2" xlink:type="simple">PEst-C/MAR/UI0284/2011 and this specific work throughout the ECOSAM project (PTDC/AAC-CLI/104085/2008). The investigation of B.D. was supported by FCT through a PhD grant (SFRH/BD/75951/2011</grant-num>).In the present work, all the authors were involved according to their area of expertise. B.D. was responsible for the biophysical and photochemical analyses and D.S. for the antioxidant enzymatic assays. I.C. and J.C.M. were responsible for the supervision of the work and for the final corrections and suggestions in data interpretation. H.S. and N.S. supervised the work and introduced their expertise in terms of halophyte ecology.None declared.The authors thank the ‘Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia (FCT)’ for funding the research at the Centre of Oceanography (CO) throughout the project PEst-OE/MAR/UI0199/2011, the Institute of Marine Research (IMAR) throughout the project PEst-C/MAR/UI0284/2011 and this specific work throughout the ECOSAM project (PTDC/AAC-CLI/104085/2008).