  Prosopis : a global assessment of the biogeography, benefits, impacts and management of one of the world's worst woody invasive plant taxa  Problems posed by  Prosopis  in Yemen  Have southern Texas savannas been converted to woodlands in recent history?  Mesquite ( Prosopis  spp.) in Sudan: history, distribution and control  Influence of mesquite control on soil erosion on a depleted range site  The human dimensions of invasive woody plants  The ecological and socio-economic role of Prosopis juliflora in Eritrea: an analytical assessment within the context of rural development in the Horn of Africa  Woody plant invasion grassland: establishment of honey mesquite ( Prosopis glandulosa  var.  glandulosa ) on sites differing in herbaceous biomass and grazing history  A monograph of the genus  Prosopis  (Leguminosae subfam. Mimosoideae). Part 1 and 2. Catalogue of the recognised species of  Prosopis    Prosopis glandulosa  Torry (Leguminosae-Mimosoidae) at Swang'oma, Lake Chilwa plain: a blessing in disguise  Experiences of  Prosopis  utilization and management from outside Kenya  Status report on commercialization of Prosopis tree resources in Kenya  Establishment of  Neltumius arizonensis  (Coleoptera: Burchidae) on  Prosopis  ( Prosopis  species: Mimosaceae) in South Africa  Avian assemblages in native  Acacia  and alien  Prosopis  drainage line woodland in the Kalahari, South Africa  Conflicts of interest over beneficial and undesirable aspects of  Prosopis  ( Prosopis  spp.) in the United States as related to biological control.  Sixth International Symposium on Biological Control   First report in Egypt of two seed-beetles (Coleoptera: Burchidae) noxious to  Prosopis  spp  Conflicts of interest in environmental management: estimating the costs and benefits of a tree invasion  Once there was a lake: vulnerability to environmental changes in northern Mali  Long-term dynamics of 2 populations of  Prosopis caldenia  Burkart  Water relations and the effects of clearing invasive  Prosopis  trees on groundwater in an arid environment in the Northern Cape, South Africa  Field studies on ecological strategies of  Prosopis juliflora  in a dry land ecosystem  Impacts of the invasive exotic  Prosopis juliflora  (Sw.) D.C. on the native flora and soils of the UAE  Mesquite: an all-purpose leguminous arid land tree  The prioritization of invasive alien plant control projects using multi-criteria decision model informed by stakeholder impute and special data  Management of introduced  Prosopis  species: can economic exploitation control and invasive species?  Invasive  Prosopis  in Sultanate of Oman  Land degradation situation in Bangladesh and the role of agroforestry  Biological invasions: winning the science battles but losing the conservation war?  Community impacts of  Prosopis juliflora  invasion: biogeographic and congeneric comparisons  Adoption, use and perception of Australian acacias around the world  Is  Prosopis  a curse or a blessing? An ecological and economic analysis of an invasive alien tree species in Sudan  The impact of invading alien plants on surface water resources in South Africa: a preliminary assessment  In denial about dangerous aid  Global plant dispersal, naturalization, and invasion: pathways, modes and circumstances  Value for money? Investment in weed management in Australian rangelands  Impacts of  Prosopis juliflora  on Kenya's semi-arid and arid ecosystems and local livelihoods  Global indicators of biological invasion: species numbers, biodiversity impact and policy responses  A global strategy on invasive alien species: synthesis and ten strategic elements  Selection of the best chemical pretreatment for lignocellulosic substrate  Prosopis juliflora   Impact of  Prosopis  (mesquite) invasion and clearing on the grazing capacity of semiarid Nama Karoo rangeland, South Africa  Hydrological impacts of mesquite encroachment in the upper San Pedro watershed  Diurnal and seasonal water relations of the desert phreatophyte  Prosopis glandulosa  (honey mesquite) in the Sonoran Desert of California  Preference and adoption of farmer field school (FFS)  Prosopis juliflora  management practices: experiences in Baringo District, Kenya  Biological invasions in developing and developed countries: does one model fit all?  Identification of threats on mangrove forests in Gabrik International Wetland for sustainable management   Prosopis —pest or providence, weed or wonder tree?  Cinderella species and what happens after midnight?  Safeguarding valued old world native  Prosopis  species from biocontrol introductions  Implications of uncertain  Prosopis  taxonomy for biocontrol  Updated world map of the Köppen-Geiger climate classification  Economics and environmental threats of alien plant, animal and microbe invasions  Alien plants in checklists and floras: towards better communication between taxonomists and ecologists  Geographical and taxonomic biases in invasion ecology  Hitting the right target: taxonomic challenges for, and of, plant invasions  Trees and shrubs as invasive alien species—2013 update of the global database  Commercial forestry and agroforestry as sources of invasive alien trees and shrubs  Forestry trees as invasive aliens  Conifers as invasive aliens: a global survey and predictive framework  Trees and shrubs as invasive alien species—a global review  Comparison of alternative strategies for invasive species distribution modelling  Mapping potential ranges of major plant invaders in South Africa, Lesotho and Swaziland using climatic suitability  Assessing the effects of invasive alien species on rural livelihoods: case examples and a framework from South Africa  Some biological characteristics that foster the invasion of  Prosopis juliflora  (Sw.) DC. at Middle Awash Rift Valley Area, north-eastern Ethiopia  Influence of dense stands of an exotic tree  Prosopis glandulosa  Benson, on a savanna dung beetle (Coleoptera: Scarabeidae) assemblage in southern Africa  Exotic weed  Prosopis juliflora  in Gujarat and Rajasthan, India—boon or bane?  Detection, quantification and monitoring Prosopis spp. in the Northern Cape Province of South Africa using Remote Sensing and GIS   Prosopis  spp.—mesquite  Australian weeds series:  Prosopis  species  Targeting biological control across diverse landscapes: the release, establishment and early success of two insects on mesquite ( Prosopis  spp.) insects in Australian rangelands  Population ecology of hybrid mesquite ( Prosopis  species) in Western Australia: how does it differ from native range invasions and what are the implications for impacts and management?  Challenges and trade-offs in the management of invasive alien trees  National-scale strategic approaches for managing introduced plants: insights from Australian acacias in South Africa  An assessment of the effectiveness of a large, national-scale invasive alien plant control strategy in South Africa  Alien invading plants and water resources in South Africa  Human domination of Earth's ecosystems  Risk assessment, eradication, and biological control: global efforts to limit Australian acacia invasions  A standardized set of metrics to assess and monitor tree invasions  Costs, benefits and management options for an invasive alien tree species: the case of mesquite in the Northern Cape, South Africa  Biofuels and invasive species from an African perspective—a review  Biological control of mesquite  (Prosopis  species) (Fabaceae) in South Africa  Biological control of Prosopis,  Prosopis  spp. (Fabaceae), in South Africa  A South African perspective on  Prosopis   Associate Editor: Jeffrey S. Dukes  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Taxa from the genus  Prosopis  are widespread invasive aliens across the globe. Numerous species have contentious issues surrounding them as they provide both benefits and harm.  Prosopis  taxa are currently naturalised or invasive in 103 countries and are bioclimatically suitable for many more. There are numerous management practices available to control  Prosopis  invasions, each with their benefits and costs, however, in most areas management has had only limited success. There is need for more research to improve understanding and management success and for countries to develop strategic plants to guide managed in the future.  Invasive species cause ecological, economic and social impacts and are key drivers of global change. This is the case for the genus  Prosopis  (mesquite; Fabaceae) where several taxa are among the world's most damaging invasive species. Many contentious issues (‘conflicts of interest’) surround these taxa, and management interventions have not yet sustainably reduced the negative impacts. There is an urgent need to better understand the factors that drive invasions and shape management actions, and to compare the effectiveness of different management approaches. This paper presents a global review of  Prosopis , focusing on its distribution, impacts, benefits and approaches to management.  Prosopis  was found to occur in a 129 countries globally and many more countries are climatically suitable. All areas with naturalized or invasive  Prosopis  species at present are suitable for more taxa and many Asian and Mediterranean countries with no records of  Prosopis  are bioclimatically suitable. Several  Prosopis  species have substantial impacts on biodiversity, ecosystem services, and local and regional economies in their native and even more so in their invasive ranges; others provide multiple benefits to local communities. Management efforts are underway in only a small part of the invaded range. Countries where more research has been done are more likely to implement formal management than those where little published research is available. Management strategies differ among countries; developed nations use mainly mechanical and chemical control whereas developing nations tend to apply control through utilization approaches. A range of countries are also using biological control. Key gaps in knowledge and promising options for management are highlighted.  The increased movement of humans around the world has facilitated transportation of many species to environments far from their native ranges. This has been done purposefully—to introduce new crops and horticultural and forestry species—and accidentally, for example as weed seed in grain shipments ( Mack 2003 ). These introductions have led to the rise of biological invasions that cause substantial ecological, social and economic impacts, and they are one of the key drivers of global change ( Vitousek  et al . 1997 ;  Pimentel  et al . 2000 ). However, many alien species have been embraced by humans and are crucial for local livelihoods and national economies through the goods and services they provide ( Shackleton  et al . 2007 ;  Kull  et al . 2011 ;  van Wilgen  et al . 2011 ).  It is important to understand the dynamics of invasive species to reduce their negative impacts and maximize their benefits, but frameworks linking theory and management for biological invasions are lacking ( Hulme 2003 ;  Wilson  et al . 2014 ). Management is inefficient in many areas due to lack of knowledge on key aspects of the invasive species. It is crucial to understand the reasons for introductions, uses (benefits), costs, ecology and scales of invasions and to elucidate perceptions and potential contentious issues when creating sustainable management plans ( Kull  et al . 2011 ;  van Wilgen and Richardson 2014 ;  Wilson  et al . 2014 ). This is true for invasive species in the genus  Prosopis .  Taxa of  Prosopis  (mesquite; Fabaceae) occur in most of the world's hot arid and semi-arid regions as native or introduced species ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ). The genus  Prosopis  as described by  Burkart (1976)  consists of 44 species. They have been introduced globally and have become naturalized or invasive in many places ( Rejmánek and Richardson 2013 ). Several  Prosopis  species are also ‘weedy’ in parts of their native ranges ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ). In this paper we define native species as those whose presence in an area is not attributable to introduction by humans (this includes species that have spread into areas without assistance from humans by overcoming biogeographic barriers). Alien taxa are those whose presence in an area is attributable to introduction by humans. Naturalized taxa are alien taxa that are self-sustaining. Invasive taxa are naturalized taxa that have spread substantially from introduction sites (further details in  Pyšek  et al . 2004 ). We define ‘weedy’ taxa as native taxa that have increased in abundance and/or geographic range in their native ranges.  Numerous  Prosopis  taxa are recognized as major invaders across large parts of the world ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ;  Brown  et al . 2004 ). ‘ Prosopis ’ is listed as one of the 20 weeds of national significance in Australia and taxa in the genus are declared as major invasive species in Ethiopia, India, Kenya and South Africa, and Sudan is advocating for its eradication ( FAO 2006 ;  Australian Weeds Committee 2012 ;  Low 2012 ;  van Wilgen  et al . 2012 ). Factors that make many  Prosopis  species successful invaders include the production of large numbers of seeds that remain viable for decades, rapid growth rates, an ability to coppice after damage ( Felker 1979 ;  Shiferaw  et al . 2004 ), root systems that allow them to efficiently utilize both surface and ground water (to depths of &gt;50 m) ( Nilsen  et al . 1983 ;  Dzikiti  et al . 2013 ), and allelopathic and allelochemical effects on other plant species ( Elfadl and Luukkanen 2006 ). Many  Prosopis  species can also withstand climatic extremes such as very high temperatures and low rainfall, and they are not limited by alkaline, saline or unfertile soils ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ;  Shiferaw  et al . 2004 ). Interspecific hybridization also enhances invasiveness in many introduced regions ( Zimmermann 1991 ).   Prosopis  invasions generate environmental, social and economic benefits as well as harm ( Chikuni  et al . 2004 ;  Geesing  et al . 2004 ;  Wise  et al . 2012 ). This has led to contentious issues surrounding the genus ( Richardson 1998 b  ;  van Wilgen and Richardson 2014 ). Some advocates promote it as a ‘wonder plant’ while others call for its eradication, or contrast its positive and negative aspects, e.g. ‘Boon or bane’ ( Tiwari 1999 ), ‘Pest or providence, weed or wonder tree?’ ( Pasiecznik 1999 ), ‘Invasive weed or valuable forest resource?’ ( Pasiecznik 2002 ). Contrasting views, contradictory perceptions and unclear policies are limiting options for constructive dialogue between different parties. This is exacerbated by problems in identifying and differentiating morphologically similar species, and by a general lack of knowledge on the distribution, scale of invasion, benefits, impacts and effective management approaches. Furthermore, many different approaches for managing  Prosopis  have been tried in different situations, without a thorough evaluation of the relative effectiveness of the methods. The Food and Agricultural Organization has called for a sound, unbiased global overview of  Prosopis  to act as a prerequisite for the holistic management of the genus ( FAO 2006 ). Such reviews have been useful for guiding and prioritizing management and improving knowledge in other groups of woody invasive plants ( Richardson and Rejmánek 2004 ,  2011 ;  Kull  et al . 2011 ;  Wilson  et al . 2011 ).  The aims of this paper are thus to (i) contrast benefits and costs of invasive  Prosopis , (ii) update knowledge on  Prosopis  occurrence and introductions globally and highlight the potential range expansion of  Prosopis , (iii) elucidate ecological, economic and social factors that shape attempts at managing  Prosopis , (iv) compare and contrast the effectiveness of different management approaches in different regions, and (v) identify priorities for research and policy development. We review the literature and collate data from many sources. Details on the approach for the literature review, approaches used for statistical analyses and climate matching are provided in   Supporting Information  .  Costs and benefits of introduced  Prosopis  species: (A) invasive  Prosopis  stand altering hydrology in Loeriesfontein, South Africa; (B) cleared  Prosopis  in the foreground and uncleared in the background illustrating impenetrable thickets, loss of land, loss of grazing potential and the effort needed for its control in Kenhardt, South Africa; (C) loss of access to a barn and encroachment of fields in Calvinia, South Africa; (D) death of a native tree ( Searsia lancea ) due to competition from  Prosopis  in Kenhardt, South Africa; (E) effects of  Prosopis  pods on a goat's teeth in Kenya; (F)  Prosopis  thorns that cause tyre damage and injure humans and livestock; (G)  Prosopis  causing loss of topsoil and erosion in Prieska, South Africa; (H) ‘manna’—a blood sugar medicine made from  Prosopis  in South Africa ( www.mannaplus.co.za ); (I) food products made from  Prosopis  in Peru; (J) timber from  Prosopis  used to make furniture in Kenya; (K) a young boy collecting  Prosopis  pods to feed livestock in Askham, South Africa; (L)  Prosopis  used for shade and ornamentation in Askham, South Africa; (M)  Prosopis  used as a fuel in Kenhardt, South Africa; (N) a bee hive placed in an invasive  Prosopis  stand Calvinia, South Africa. Photos: S. Choge (J), G. Cruz (I), P. Manudu (E, F), R. Shackleton (A–D, G, K–N).  Several species are also weedy and thus provide both benefits and costs in their native ranges ( P. affinis ,  P. caldenia ,  P. campestris ,  P. chilensis ,  P. cineraria ,  P. farcta ,  P. glandulosa ,  P. hassleri ,  P. humilis ,  P. juliflora ,  P. kuntzei ,  P. nigra ,  P. pubescens ,  P. ruscifolia ,  P. strombulifera ,  P. tamarugo ,  P. velutina )  [see  Supporting Information ] . At least 19 (invasive and weedy) of the 44 species in the genus are known to generate benefits and costs, with the rest being only beneficial. The invasiveness and potential negative impacts of many  Prosopis  species are still unknown as only a handful have been introduced.   Prosopis  species have been used for a variety of products for more than 5000 years in their native ranges ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ). The numerous goods and services provided by  Prosopis  have led to global introductions and have made some species important for local communities.  Prosopis  is commonly used for fuel, fodder, windbreaks, shade, construction materials and soil stabilization through its invasive ranges in Africa and Asia ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ;  Wise  et al.  2012 ). In some areas the benefits from  Prosopis  are, or were, regarded as a key income source for many households. In one village in Malawi, 44 % of people relied on  Prosopis  products as a primary or supplementary source of income ( Chikuni  et al . 2004 ). Communities in Kenya have benefited greatly from the sale of charcoal and  Prosopis  pods for fodder, boosting the local economy in some areas by US$1.5 million per year ( Choge  et al . 2012 ). In India,  Prosopis  provides up to 70 % of fuelwood needs for local households in some dry region villages ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ).  Although utilization is most common in rural settings to sustain local livelihoods,  Prosopis  products are also exploited on a large scale by private companies. In South Africa, pods are collected to produce organic medicines (‘manna’) that are said to have properties that stabilize blood sugar levels in humans. This company is making profits of US$100 000 per annum and has the potential to increase profits 10-fold if the product is marketed internationally ( Wise  et al . 2012 ). A company in Brazil, Riocon, has an annual turnover of US$6 million a year from the sale of  Prosopis  pod flour for animal feeds (A. Davi, Ricocon, pers. comm.).  Cause-and-effect network diagram showing the negative effects of  Prosopis  invasions and management options that can be used to target each stage of invasion.  Local communities in Kenya, Sudan, Eritrea, Malawi and Pakistan noted a range of negative consequences arising from invasive  Prosopis  ( Choge  et al . 2002 ;  Chikuni  et al . 2004 ;  Mwangi and Swallow 2005 ;  Laxén 2007 ;  Bokrezion 2008 ;  Kazmi  et al . 2009 ) .  These included effects on livestock health,  Prosopis  thorns causing tyre punctures and flesh wounds, dense thickets reducing access to water points, roads, infrastructure and agricultural and range lands, drying up of water sources, reducing natural forest cover and the services from these forests, as well as providing refuge for thieves.  In many parts of Africa  Prosopis  invasions are a leading cause of detrimental impacts on local community structure and functioning, leading to an increase in their vulnerability. This includes the potential loss of land rights for local livestock herders in Mali and violent conflict over limited natural resources between neighbouring communities in Ethiopia and Kenya ( Centre for Sustainable Development Initiatives 2009 ;  Djoudi  et al . 2011 ;  Stark  et al . 2011 ). One Kenyan community has even taken the Food and Agricultural Organization (FAO) and the Kenyan government to court over the harm created by the introduction of  Prosopis  ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2006 a  ).  Native weedy  Prosopis  taxa are also estimated to cause a loss of US$200–500 million per annum to the livestock industry in the USA ( DeLoach 1984 ). In South Africa costs of managing  Prosopis  invasions are substantial, averaging $35.5 million per annum ( van Wilgen  et al . 2012 ).  Perceptions on the benefits and costs of invasive alien species are strongly influenced by invasion abundance ( Binggeli 2001 ;  Shackleton  et al . 2007 ). As abundance increases, associated costs rise and benefits fall due to issues such as resource accessibility ( Wise  et al . 2012 ). In India,  Prosopis  was initially seen as beneficial, but over time the negative consequences became more apparent, leading to increasingly negative perceptions of the plant from some quarters ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ). A similar situation arose in Kenya where, as  Prosopis  became invasive, it was described as a ‘bad omen’ by some local people ( Choge and Chikamai 2004 ) and more than 65 % of people in three villages mentioned that their lives would have been better off if  Prosopis  was never introduced ( Maundu  et al . 2009 ). In Sudan, over 90 % of livestock farmers viewed  Prosopis  as a problem as it became more widespread ( Elsidig  et al . 1998 ).  In many areas, invasive  Prosopis  trees do not sustain their full use potential due to intraspecific competition in dense stands which, generally, form over time. In such cases relatively few pods are produced for fodder and human consumption and dense invasive stands become impenetrable for humans and livestock making utilization of resources difficult ( Chikuni  et al . 2004 ;  Mwangi and Swallow 2005 ).  Wise  et al . (2012)  show that net economic benefits decrease as invasion densities increase in South Africa. They predict that the net cost of having  Prosopis  in the country will become negative in 4–20 years depending on future rates of spread. A framework by  Shackleton  et al . (2007)  also shows that useful invasive aliens initially have high benefits, but as invasion densities increase, costs rise which lead to an increase in human vulnerability. This raises questions about the introduction of ‘miracle’ species in the past such as  Acacia ,  Leucaena  and  Prosopis  because the adverse impacts tend to exceed the benefits as the invasions progress, if left unmanaged ( de Wit  et al . 2001 ;  Pasiecznik 2004 ;  Wise  et al.  2012 ;  Low 2012 ), as well as the continued promotion of invasive alien species like  Prosopis  for biofuels today ( Witt 2010 ;  Naseeruddin  et al . 2013 ).  The fact that the detrimental effects emerge only after invasions have reached unmanageable levels exacerbates contentious issues surrounding invasive species and may delay management decisions, in many cases restricting the implementation of effective management. There have also been conflicts of interest regarding which form of management to implement—how best to preserve, exploit and even enhance benefits while reducing negative impacts of  Prosopis  invasions ( Zimmermann 1991 ).  Time scale of all  Prosopis  introductions globally ( n  = 82 known species–country introduction dates).  Seed introductions have come both from native populations and from naturalized and invasive populations in countries where  Prosopis  was introduced previously. However, the original sources of seed and dates for introductions to many countries are poorly documented. Seed introduced to Hawaii came from a tree in France with a speculated provenance in Brazil ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ) and  P. pallida  introduced to Australia came from Hawaii ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ). South Africa had multiple introductions of many species and seed was most likely introduced from native ranges in Chile, Honduras, Mexico and USA ( Zimmermann 1991 ). Seed from naturalized populations in South Africa was introduced into Egypt and seed introduced into Sudan came from South Africa and Egypt ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ). The provenance of early  Prosopis  introductions to India is uncertain (likely Mexico or Jamaica); later introductions came from Argentina, Australia, Mexico, Peru and Uruguay ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ).  Most introductions of  Prosopis  were intentional, although there have been accidental cross-border introductions between neighbouring counties.  Prosopis  was introduced for many reasons: to provide fodder and shade in the arid areas of South Africa and Australia; for dune stabilization, afforestation and fuel wood supply in Sudan; for live fencing in Malawi; initially to rehabilitate old quarries and later for afforestation and the provision of fuelwood and fodder in Kenya; for fuelwood production and rehabilitating degraded soil in India; for local greening, ornamental cultivation and soil stabilization in many Middle Eastern countries; and for vegetation trials in Spain ( Zimmermann 1991 ;  Ghazanfar 1996 ;  Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ;  Choge  et al . 2002 ;  Chikuni  et al . 2004 ;  Elfadl and Luukkanen 2006 ;  van Klinken  et al . 2006 ;  Laxén 2007 ; N. Pasiecznik and E. Peñalvo López, unpubl. res.).  Prosopis  was possibly first introduced unintentionally into Botswana, Nigeria and Yemen through livestock trading with neighbouring countries ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ;  Geesing  et al . 2004 ).  Classification of all records of introduced  Prosopis  species (236 introductions in 103 countries); classification of ‘naturalized’ and ‘invasive’ follows the criteria of  Pyšek  et al . (2004) .  Global distribution of  Prosopis  species: (A) species diversity in countries with native taxa; (B) species diversity of taxa recognized as being weedy within their native ranges; (C) species richness of introduced  Prosopis  taxa that have either naturalized or become invasive (following the criteria of  Pyšek  et al . 2004 ); and (D) potential  Prosopis  species richness based on climatic suitability.  The last comprehensive global review of  Prosopis  distribution listed the presence of taxa in 93 mainland and island/attol countries ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2001 ). It is unlikely that  Prosopis  has been introduced into more places in the 13 years since that review was undertaken, but rather that data availability has increased in the intervening period or that there has been unintentional spread e.g. into Tanzania. Of the 129 countries, 26 have only native species, 64 have only introduced  Prosopis  species, and 39 have both native and introduced species.  Prosopis  is weedy in 38 % of countries where it occurs naturally and 38 % of species in the genus are currently categorized as weedy in their native ranges. The distribution and scale of invasions in countries with invasive  Prosopis  are not well known, with only 13 % of countries having detailed distribution or percentage cover data and not just records of occurrence.  Climate matching was used to assess areas of potential naturalization and invasion ( Peel  et al . 2007 ). We identified many regions that are climatically suitable for  Prosopis  where there are currently no records of any taxa (Fig.  5 D).This includes countries in Europe (Greece, Italy, Portugal, Romania, etc.), South America (Guyana and Suriname), Asia (China, Japan, Nepal, South Korea, etc.) and numerous island/atoll countries and overseas territories (Comoros, Malta, Solomon Islands, Timor-Leste, etc.) (Fig.  5 D;   Supporting Information  ). All countries where at least one  Prosopis  species has been introduced and has established have the potential for the naturalization of additional  Prosopis  species. For example, there are currently seven naturalized and invasive  Prosopis  species recorded in South Africa, but the country is climatically suitable for many more species  [see  Supporting Information ] .  Maundu  et al . (2009)  also illustrated a high climatic suitability for  Prosopis  in southern and eastern Africa and showed that there are many areas that could have invasions but currently do not.  Naturalized and/or weedy  Prosopis  are reported in 112 countries. Currently 23 countries with weedy or invasive  Prosopis  (21 %) implement some form of formal management. No countries rely exclusively on biological control, 6 (26 %) use only mechanical or chemical control, 5 (22 %) use control through utilization and 11 (48 %) apply an integrated approach (three or more methods, including biological control, mechanical control, chemical control, control through utilization and cultural control) (Table  2 ).  Countries that use only chemical and mechanical control are mainly found in the Middle East and have small isolated invasions and are usually wealthier nations, whereas control through utilization is applied in poorer countries such as Kenya and Ethiopia. Biological control is driven by Australia and South Africa; however, there are also areas where ‘biological control agents’ are present but were not deliberately introduced, for example, Egypt (seed-feeding beetles—Coleoptera and Burchidae), Sudan and Yemen ( Algarobis prosopis ) ( Delobel and Fediere 2002 ;  Al-Shurai and Labrada 2006 ;  Babiker 2006 ). In Yemen there is no evidence that the non-native  A. prosopis  feeds on the native  Prosopis cineraria  ( Al-Shurai and Labrada 2006 ). There are concerns, however, that introduced insects could affect less invasive  P. pallida  populations in these areas that are utilized by local communities ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2006 a  ,   b  ). Another view is that any effect of such insects could improve the usefulness of less invasive taxa by reducing seed production and therefore potential invasiveness and could lead to less dense stands with larger trees and greater pod production ( Zachariades  et al . 2011 ).  Logistic regression highlighting the importance of different ecological, economical and social factors in determining management of  Prosopis  within a country.  Simple socioeconomic variables are poor predictors of the existence of management strategies as there is evidence of management in countries at all levels of development (Table  1 ). Many of the poorer countries receive foreign aid to implement and run management programmes, at least at the outset.  The findings of this review contradict previous publications that have argued that less developed countries have conducted less research and management of invasive alien species ( McNeely  et al . 2005 ;  Pyšek  et al . 2008 ;  Nuñez and Pauchard 2009 ;  McGeoch  et al . 2010 ). Some developing countries are at the forefront of  Prosopis  research and management such as Kenya (control through utilization, social impacts) and South Africa (biological control), along with developed countries such as Australia and the USA.  Witt (2010)  noted that the prominence and severity of the impacts of  Prosopis  in developing countries has motivated this investment in research and understanding. However, there may be a lack of research for less prominent invasive alien species in poorer regions of the world.  A classification and regression tree model using social, ecological and economic variables to explore the drivers of different types of  Prosopis  management globally.  A comparison of techniques for managing  Prosopis  and their advantages and disadvantages.  The benefits and impacts and choice of different management approaches of  Prosopis  have led to contentious issues regarding management. Control through utilization is advocated by some as a management technique that enables benefit of invasive  Prosopis  to be utilized while simultaneously reducing the negative impacts of invasions and promoting local development ( Choge and Chikamai 2004 ). However, many believe that this approach is inefficient at reducing invasions and leads to other problems such as dependencies (Table  2 ) ( van Wilgen  et al . 2011 ) and that other approaches such as chemical and mechanical clearing should be prioritized, although they are costly ( Witt 2010 ). To date, there is no evidence of the success of control through utilization as a management technique (Table  2 ). The control through utilization approach is motivated around local development (which is needed) more so than managing invasions at large spatial and temporal scales.  There are conflicting views on best management approaches (eradication vs. control through utilization) in different villages in Kenya ( Mwangi and Swallow 2005 ;  Njoroge  et al . 2012 ). Similar cases of contentious issues and conflicts of interest have been seen for other management approaches such as biological control. In South Africa only seed-feeding beetles were introduced so that neither the  Prosopis  trees themselves nor the production of pods would be harmed ( Richardson 1998 a  )—even though better biological control agents have been identified that would harm trees and be more effective in reducing invasions ( Zachariades  et al . 2011 ).  Despite the growing body of research on management options for weedy and invasive  Prosopis  stands ( van Klinken  et al . 2006 ), there is an ongoing debate on how to effectively manage large-scale invasions. Different approaches are currently being used to manage  Prosopis , each with their own set of advantages and disadvantages (Table  2 ). The following case studies were selected as being representative of different management strategies and also encompass the approaches most commonly employed in countries with different levels of socioeconomic development (developed—Australia; emerging economies—South Africa; developing—Kenya). The case studies are also characteristic of management strategies driven and implemented by different stakeholders, e.g. government driven with mainly private implementation (Australia), mainly government driven and implemented (South Africa) and government driven with some non-government organization (NGO) and international support (Kenya).   Prosopis  has invaded over one million hectares and could potentially spread over 70 % of Australia's land area ( Osmond 2003 ).  Prosopis  taxa are considered as one of the 20 worst invasives in Australia, and in accordance with the  Weeds Management Act  2001, a strategic plan has been developed to guide management ( Australian Weeds Committee 2012 ).  Prosopis  is a declared weed in all the mainland states and one territory in Australia and has been categorized in accordance with the threats it poses and the corresponding management responses that need to be implemented ( van Klinken and Campbell 2009 ). This includes preventing introductions, trade, sale or movements of  Prosopis  taxa and the eradication of small populations and control of large populations ( Australian Weeds Committee 2012 ). In general, most landowners use mechanical and chemical control measures to manage  Prosopis . Although control and eradication programmes are primarily funded by the state, many private landowners also fund management operations. For example, in Queensland $A4 million was allocated for  Prosopis  management by the government, which was supplemented further by over $A600 000 by landholders between 1995 and 1999 and over $A2 million was spent on clearing between 2001 and 2005 ( Martin and van Klinken 2006 ).  Control of  Prosopis  first started in 1954 at Mardie Station, Western Australia, and by 1962 a major reduction in  Prosopis  density had been achieved. Populations increased again when funding diminished, but in the mid-1970s the allocation of government funding led to substantial progress with clearing ( van Klinken and Campbell 2009 ). In other areas of Western Australia control was improving, but after funding lapsed many infestations returned in the 1990s with the exception of some areas such as Yeeda Station where control had been successful due to annual monitoring and clearing ( van Klinken and Campbell 2009 ). In Queensland substantial funding was invested for clearing in the area around Comongin Station, and by 2005 over 4000 ha of dense  Prosopis  stands had been removed ( van Klinken and Campbell 2009 ). In northern Queensland research concluded that eradication was feasible in the region and significant steps have been made towards this goal ( van Klinken and Campbell 2009 ). New South Wales and South Australia have similar examples of good control efforts and others that have had limited success due to a lapse in control and monitoring ( van Klinken and Campbell 2009 ).  Four biological control agents have been released in Australia:  Algarobius bottimeri  and  A. prosopis  (seed-feeding bruchids),  Evippe  species (a leaf-tying moth) and  Prosopidopsylla flava  (a sap sucker) ( van Klinken  et al . 2003 ;  van Klinken 2012 ). Two have established widely ( A. prosopis ,  Evippe  species), and the latter has had noticeable impacts on  Prosopis  populations through reducing long-term growth rates ( van Klinken 2012 ). Biological control in Australia has been more successful than in other places like South Africa and the benefit-to-cost ratios are positive (0.5), with expectations to increase in the future ( Page and Lacey 2006 ). The release of more agents is recommended to further improve control ( van Klinken  et al . 2003 ;  van Klinken 2012 ).  Experiments have shown that some species are highly fire tolerant (especially the hybrids), which reduces the potential for using fire as a control method in many areas ( van Klinken  et al . 2006 ). Grazing control has also been advised to help prevent establishment and further spread of  Prosopis  ( Csurhes 1996 ), although this approach has had limited success in Argentina and the USA ( Dussart  et al . 1998 ;  Brown and Archer 1989 ). There are also regulations on the transport of livestock in areas infested with  Prosopis  to prevent its spread and accidental introduction elsewhere in Australia ( Australian Weeds Committee 2012 ). Management policy is backed up by good legislation; Australia is one of two countries with a national management strategy. The government has also published many easily accessible documents on  Prosopis  management methods to inform landowners on control measures, and the  Prosopis  strategic plan places a lot of emphasis on educating and making stakeholders aware of  Prosopis  invasions and how to manage them ( Australian Weeds Committee 2012 ). There have been rewarding examples of control success ( van Klinken and Campbell 2009 ); however,  Prosopis  populations continue to spread in many areas and further management is needed.   Prosopis  invasions in South Africa cover an estimated 1.8 million hectares, and are increasing at 8 % per annum ( Versfeld  et al . 1998 ;  Van den Berg 2010 ). They have the potential to invade between 5 and 32 million hectares of South Africa based on climatic suitability—about a third of the area of the country ( Rouget  et al . 2004 ).  Prosopis  is declared as a category 2 invasive alien species because it provides benefits and causes harm; this status means that it is legal to grow  Prosopis  in demarcated areas once a permit has been issued. A combination of mechanical, chemical and biological control methods is used to control  Prosopis , mainly by the government-managed Working for Water programme. Three seed-feeding beetles ( A. prosopis ,  A. bottimeri  and  Neltumius arizonensis ) were introduced as biological control agents to try and reduce spread while maintaining its benefits ( Zimmermann 1991 ;  Coetzer and Hoffmann 1997 ).  Neltumius arizonensis  failed to establish ( Zachariades  et al . 2011 ). Although biological control is considered the most cost-effective way of managing large-scale invasions of many species, there are many cases where the agents fail to make a significant impact and  Prosopis  is one of them ( van Wilgen  et al . 2012 ). The overall return on investment is low compared with biological control programmes for  Opuntia  species and Australian  Acacia  species in South Africa ( van Wilgen  et al . 2012 ). There is potential to release more agents, such as the  Evippe  species which is already successful in Australia (see above), should the contentious issues surrounding the benefits and costs of  Prosopis  be resolved ( Zachariades  et al . 2011 ).  Prosopis  cover increased by ∼35 % between 1996 and 2008, despite the expenditure of R435.5 million (US$42.7 million) on control over this period. Only 15 100 ha were cleared using mechanical and chemical control with this substantial budget ( van Wilgen  et al . 2012 ), which makes the cost/ha very expensive (US$2828). The limited success to date may be due to lack of a management strategy and of prioritization of management projects ( Forsyth  et al . 2012 ). There is a need for researchers, managers and policy-makers to agree on new strategies for prioritizing areas for interventions to curb the spread of  Prosopis  and to ensure that the limited resources are used effectively ( Forsyth  et al . 2012 ). There have been some attempts at controlling  Prosopis  through utilization, but they had no noticeable impacts on invasions, and these initiatives failed as input and transport costs were too high and financial returns were low ( Zimmermann  et al . 2006 ). South Africa also has many particularly aggressive hybrids that form dense shrub-dominated stands, which makes the utilization approach difficult ( Zimmermann  et al . 2006 ).   Prosopis  is estimated to have invaded one million hectares and has the potential to invade nearly half of Kenya's surface ( Maundu  et al . 2009 ;  Witt 2010 ). It was declared a noxious weed in 2008 ( Low 2012 ). Biological and mechanical control was initially proposed as the management approach to combat  Prosopis  invasions, but the government later opted for a control-by-utilization approach ( FAO 2006 ;  Pasiecznik and Felker 2006 ). The FAO, with support from several NGOs, initiated programmes to manage  Prosopis  through utilization. These efforts were continued by the government's forestry department and forestry research organization (KEFRI) following the end of these projects. Considerable time and effort was taken to build capacity, formulate good policies and educate communities to utilize the goods and services from  Prosopis  ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2006 a  ). For example, small-scale utilization projects were established and a cookbook using  Prosopis  flour was created and supplied to communities to promote its use ( Choge  et al . 2006 ;  Pasiecznik  et al . 2006 a  ). Although initial costs for training and purchasing appropriate small-scale processing machinery are high, they are considered to be lower than other control approaches ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2006 a  ). In 2002, trade in  Prosopis  goods and services was worth US$2122 per household per year in some villages ( Choge  et al . 2002 ). Ten years later, trade in  Prosopis  products in four selected areas was estimated to exceed US$1.5 million ( Choge  et al . 2012 ). Each tonne of pods that are collected and milled into flour is estimated to remove approximately two million viable seeds ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2006 a  ). Changes in legislation, and the promotion of  Prosopis  use, helped drive the substantial rise in use and led to 100 % of the locals in one village supporting control through utilization as the most preferred management method to adopt in Kenya ( Njoroge  et al . 2012 ). However, in other villages 85–90 % of people surveyed considered complete eradication of  Prosopis  to be the best option ( Mwangi and Swallow 2005 ). There are still, however, contentious issues surrounding the benefits and costs of the species and management approaches in Kenya ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2006 a  ). There are many publications on the profits that are being made through utilization, but there is no evidence that these utilization programmes have contained or reduced the extent of  Prosopis  invasions. There is, therefore, a need for further investigation of the successes and failure of control through utilization programmes ( Geesing  et al . 2004 ). A common problem with trying to promote  Prosopis  utilization is that it is seen as an inferior resource in many communities, with people preferring to use native species ( Geesing  et al . 2004 ). Recently, a new utilization approach to increase invasive  Prosopis  use has been adopted in Kenya—a power station (based on technology from India) is currently being built in the Kenyan Rift Valley which aims to produce electricity for the local area from burning  Prosopis  biomass (S. Choge, pers. comm.).  Requirements for research and management needs regarding  Prosopis  and factors limiting success.  National strategies and management/action plans need to be created and adopted to guide the coordinated control of  Prosopis  (Fig.  7 ) .  Such national strategies and plans are important to set up frameworks on how to guide  Prosopis  management and research .  Numerous organizations and national governments globally have undertaken projects to control  Prosopis , and planning and prioritization from the outset would ensure greater success. Country-specific strategic plans need to be created as there are large differences in invasion rates and scales and socio-economic situations within different areas of the world.  Introductions of known invasive  Prosopis  species to climatically suitable countries where it does not already exist should be undertaken such as in China, European countries along the Mediterranean and North East Asia, and spread of  Prosopis  into new areas within countries where it is invasive should be prevented. Risk assessments for purposeful introductions need to be conducted in the future. Pathways of accidental introductions between neighbouring countries and into new areas in countries with invasive  Prosopis  need to be managed. This could include regulations on livestock and fodder transport which is currently implemented in Australia ( Australian Weeds Committee 2012 ). This is done by holding livestock in feed lots for a week before they are transported to ensure that all  Prosopis  seeds have excreted.  Countries need to eradicate small naturalized populations before they become invasive. Early detection and rapid response is a cost-effective way of preventing invasive species from getting out of hand and causing devastating, irreversible impacts in the future. For example, in Spain,  Prosopis  has started to show signs of naturalization at a single location where it was planted for experiments and eradication attempts now would be most cost effective in the long run (N. Pasiecznik and E. Peñalvo López, unpubl. res.).  There is also an urgent need for managers and researchers to monitor the effectiveness of control measures. Adaptive management needs to be promoted and applied for controlling  Prosopis  invasions where operational success is so far limited, so that the causes of the failures can be identified and addressed to improve overall control. Managers and researchers need to collaborate in research to design from the outset successful adaptive management strategies to be implemented.  There are many research questions regarding  Prosopis  invasions in many parts of the world that need to be answered to improve management (Fig.  7 ).  These include correctly identifying  Prosopis  species present and gaining consensus on the status introduced and weedy species (e.g. following the criteria proposed by  Pyšek  et al . 2013 ). There have been numerous misidentifications of introduced  Prosopis  species, especially in Africa. This has caused much taxonomic confusion and contradictions between different sources of information that are only starting to be clarified. There are also hybridized populations in many areas where  Prosopis  has been introduced, further hindering identification ( Zimmermann 1991 . It was recently recognized that  P. pallida , which was seen as not being as invasive as other species, is more widespread than originally thought as it was misidentified as  P. juliflora  in Africa ( Pasiecznik  et al . 2006 b  ). Most species introduced to Africa were described as  P. chilensis , but this is not the case, and accurate species lists are not available for many African countries such as Angola. Molecular methods are useful for clarifying taxonomic issues, especially in areas where hybridization has taken place. It is important to know which taxa are present for management, e.g. when looking for biological control agents and understanding ecology and rates of spread ( Pyšek  et al . 2013 ).  There is a need to improve the understanding of  Prosopis  distribution and population sizes in introduced ranges to guide management planning ( Wilson  et al . 2014 ). As indicated earlier, only 13 % of countries with naturalized and invasive  Prosopis  have maps or detailed records of occurrence and scale of invasion. No information is available on the scale of  Prosopis  invasions on any of the Pacific (besides Hawaii), Indian Ocean or Caribbean Islands. Only a few African countries have a good understanding of the scale of invasions and, in Asia, information on the distribution of invasive  Prosopis  is only available for India and Pakistan. Such knowledge is essential for planning and implementing management. Bioclimatic mapping at board local scales is useful for understanding potential spread and occurrence of invasive species. However, bioclimatic models can be of limited value at very local scales as other biotic and abiotic factors come into play ( Robinson  et al . 2011 ). On a global scale, bioclimatic modelling is useful for highlighting which countries and species need risk assessments for purposeful introductions, and where introduction pathways need to be monitored to prevent unintentional introductions, e.g. between India and China or Iran and Turkmenistan.  Further knowledge on the ecology, local perceptions, and the ecological, economic and social benefits and impacts of  Prosopis  is needed to guide management ( Wilson  et al . 2014 ). Our study has highlighted that knowledge on  Prosopis  invasions is essential for management (Table  1 ; Fig.  6 ). Most of the literature comes from a handful of countries (Australia, India, Kenya, South Africa, USA), and research in other areas is needed since each region has its own set of factors that drive invasions and complicate management. There is also a need for research to better predict trends such as future densities, extent and impacts which is particularly important when it comes down to developing strategic responses. Drivers of weediness in areas where it is native such as Argentina, Mexico, Middle East and the USA require further study to improve understanding of what drives native plants to become invasive and provide insight into how to manage them.  The issue of the lack of knowledge is also present for research on the effectiveness of controlling populations using different methods. Utilization as a control method is becoming popular in many areas such as Djibouti, Ethiopia and Kenya. However, despite many reports showing how much monetary benefit  Prosopis  has provided, there is no information on how successful this approach is for controlling  Prosopis  invasions. There are also conflicting ideas on the role and success of biological control in Australia and South Africa and further work is needed ( Zachariades  et al . 2011 ). There is scope for identifying and potentially releasing additional biological control agents to improve control success in areas where this has been limited until now, such as in South Africa ( Zachariades  et al . 2011 ). Research is needed to identify novel solutions to aid the dilemma of management and contentious issues regarding invasive  Prosopis  globally. These include methods that retain the benefits, but reduce the impacts substantially.  Risk assessments need to be run for  Prosopis  species that have not been introduced yet to determine whether they might be better candidates for introduction, by providing benefits with fewer costs associated with invasiveness.  Organizations involved in addressing land degradation and invasions should promote the dissemination of knowledge and awareness of both the impacts and benefits of  Prosopis  to prevent unwise introductions and promote management (Fig.  7 ). Some people still advocate the introduction of  Prosopis  species long after the severe impacts caused by invasions of these species were widely publicized; this has been described as ‘dangerous aid’ ( Low 2012 ). Having regular multidisciplinary international meetings or workshops on  Prosopis  invasions may help to spread knowledge and create dialogue between parties, which could help to reduce contentious issues surrounding many invasive  Prosopis  species. The creation of management strategies using transdisciplinary approaches would also help to provide solutions acceptable to all stakeholders in situations where conflicting goals exist.   Prosopis  species are among the most widespread and damaging invasive woody plants in semi-arid and arid regions of the world and there is much potential for taxa to spread further. The detrimental effects on the environment and human livelihoods are escalating rapidly and there is an urgent need to devise more effective management approaches to drastically reduce adverse impacts and enhance benefits. However, there are still critical gaps in our knowledge of its ecology, impacts and how to retain benefits and reduce costs, and a lack of management capacity in many countries. Clearly focused research and strategic planning is needed to improve management, reduce costs and improve benefit flows.  The DST-NRF Centre of Excellence for Invasion Biology and Working for Water Programme through their collaborative research project on ‘Integrated management of invasive alien species in South Africa’ –  National Research Foundation  (grant  85417 ).  R.T.S. and D.M.R. conceived the idea. R.T.S., D.C.L. and N.M.P. collected the data. N.M.P. provided specialist taxonomic advice and management information. R.T.S. ran the statistics and R.T.S. and D.C.L. undertook the climate matching. R.T.S. led the writing with assistance from the others.  None declared.  The following  Supporting Information  is available in the online version of this article –   File 1.  Methods for literature review, climate matching, regression analysis, classification and regression tree.   File 2.  Global distribution of  Prosopis  species. Status codes ( sensu   Pyšek  et al . 2004 ) are given in brackets: N, naturalized; I, invasive; NA, native; W, weedy; U, unknown. Countries partaking in management of  Prosopis  species are marked with an asterisk.   File 3.  Climate matching output—list of climatically suitable countries and the associated species (excluding known native species).   File 4.  Underlying information on  Prosopis  invasions worldwide.  We thank the many researchers and managers who were consulted about the occurrence and management of  Prosopis . 