Pollinator scarcity drives the shift to delayed selfing in Himalayan mayapple <italic>Podophyllum hexandrum</italic> (Berberidaceae)Evolution of Asian monsoons and phased uplift of the Himalaya–Tibetan plateau since late Miocene timesCommunity studies in pollination ecology in the high temperate Andes of central Chile. I. Pollination mechanisms and altitudinal variationSelf-compatibility and establishment after ‘long-distance’ dispersalPollination and the weatherPollination and pollen limitation in mayapple (<italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> L.), a nectarless spring ephemeralPollen-ovule ratios: a conservative indicator of breeding systems in flowering plantsFacultative xenogamy: examination of a mixed mating systemRole of corolla abscission in delayed self-pollination of <italic>Mimulus guttatus</italic> (Scrophulariaceae)Does self-pollination provide reproductive assurance in <italic>Aquilegia canadensis</italic> (Ranunculaceae)?Genetic structure and breeding system of a rare understory herb, <italic>Dysosma versipellis</italic> (Berberidaceae), from temperate deciduous forests in ChinaPalaeovegetation: diversity of temperate plants in East AsiaPollination in <italic>Lupinus nanus</italic> subsp. <italic>latifolius</italic> (Leguminosae)The mechanism of delayed selfing in <italic>Collinsia verna</italic> (Scrophulariaceae)Outcrossing rates of individual <italic>Mimulus ringens</italic> genets are correlated with anther-stigma separationDelayed autonomous self-pollination in <italic>Hibiscus laevis</italic> (Malvaceae)Fruit and seed set in mayapple (<italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic>): influence of intraspecific factors and local enhancement near <italic>Pedicularis canadensis</italic>Glacial survival east and west of the ‘Mekong–Salween Divide’ in the Himalaya–Hengduan Mountains region as revealed by AFLPs and cpDNA sequence variation in <italic>Sinopodophyllum hexandrum</italic> (Berberidaceae)Molecular evidence for the sister relationship of the eastern Asia-North American intercontinental species pair in the <italic>Podophyllum</italic> group (Berberidaceae)Self- and cross-fertilization in plants. II. The selection of self-fertilizationSelf- and cross-fertilization in plants. I. Functional dimensionsA contribution to the reproductive biology of <italic>Sinopodophyllum hexandrum</italic> (Royle) Ying (Berberidaceae)The evolution of self-pollination in <italic>Clarkia xantiana</italic>Pollination ecology of the spring wild flower community of a temperate deciduous forestPatches, clones, and self-fertility of mayapples (<italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> L.)Plant molecular phylogeography in China and adjacent regions: tracing the genetic imprints of quaternary climate and environmental change in the world's most diverse temperate floraDevelopmental adaptation of leaves in <italic>Podophyllum hexandrum</italic> for effective pollination and dispersalAutogamy and inbreeding depression in mountain laurel, <italic>Kalmia latifolia</italic> (Ericaceae)Adaptive significance of floral movementSeed production and seedling establishment in the mayapple, <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> LThe evolution of self-fertilization and inbreeding depression in plants. II. Empirical observationsThe genus <italic>Podophyllum</italic>New combinations for the varieties of <italic>Sinopodophyllum hexandrum</italic>Indian <italic>Podophyllum</italic>: is it <italic>Podophyllum emodi</italic> or <italic>Podophyllum hexandrum</italic>?Self fertilization and population variability in the higher plantsCorolla wilting facilitates delayed autonomous self-pollination in <italic>Pedicularis dunniana</italic> (Orobanchaceae)The biology of <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> L. (Berberidaceae), the mayapple. II. The transfer of pollen and success of sexual reproductionPhylogenetic and biogeographic diversification of Berberidaceae in the northern hemisphereElevational distribution of insect pollinatorsEvolution of eastern Asian and eastern North American disjunct distributions in flowering plantsPotential for the loss of self-incompatibility in pollen-limited populations of mayapple (<italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic>)Pollinator-plant interactions and the evolution of breeding systemsTiming the eastern Asian-eastern North American floristic disjunction: molecular clock corroborates paleontological dataAFLP analysis of genetic diversity of the endangered species <italic>Sinopodophyllum hexandrum</italic> in the Tibetan region of Sichuan Province, ChinaThe floral biology and its evolutionary significance of <italic>Sinopodophyllum hexandrum</italic> (Royle) Ying (Berberidaceae)BerberidaceaeOn <italic>Dysosma</italic> Woodson and <italic>Sinopodophyllum</italic> Ying gen. nov. of the BerberidaceaeThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.American mayapple and Himalayan mayapple are a pair of sister species with disjunct distribution between eastern Asia and eastern North America, which the former was considered to be self-incompatible but the later to be self-compatible. We are interested in the diversification of breeding systems in the two species, particularly a usual mode of self pollination in Himalayan mayapple (<italic>Podophyllum hexandrum</italic>) which is achieved by movement of the pistil as a previous study suggested. By contrast, our observations and flower manipulations show that delayed selfing was facilitated by petals closing and stamens moving simultaneously to contact the stigma, and bees were effective pollinators although they were few.Recent molecular phylogenetics have indicated that American mayapple (mainly self-incompatible, SI) and Himalayan mayapple, which was considered to be self-compatible (SC), are sister species with disjunct distribution between eastern Asia and eastern North America. We test a hypothesis that the persistence of this early spring flowering herb in the Himalayan region is attributable to the transition from SI to SC, the capacity for selfing in an unpredictable pollination environment. Pollinator observations were conducted in an alpine meadow with hundreds of Himalayan mayapple (<italic>Podophyllum hexandrum</italic> Royle) individuals over 2 years. To examine autogamy, seed set under different pollination treatments was compared. To clarify whether automatic self-pollination is achieved by movement of the pistil as a previous study suggested, we measured incline angles of the pistil and observed flower movement during anthesis using video. Floral visitors to the nectarless flowers were very rare, but solitary bees and honeybees could be potential pollinators. Seed set of bagged flowers was not significantly different from that of open-pollinated, self- or cross-pollinated flowers. However, removal of petals or stamens lowered seed yield. The angles of inclination of pistils did not change during the process of pollination. Automatic self-pollination was facilitated by petals closing and stamens moving simultaneously to contact the stigma. Stigmatic pollen load increased little during the day time, in contrast to a sharp increase when the flowers closed during the night-time. These observations indicated that Himalayan mayapple was SC and delayed self-pollination was facilitated by the movement of petals rather than the pistil. Compared with SI American mayapple, no obvious inbreeding depression in SC Himalayan mayapple may contribute its existence in the uplifting zone. A scarcity of pollinators may have driven the shift to delayed selfing in <italic>P. hexandrum</italic>.The transition of the breeding system from outcrossing to selfing has been considered to be a widespread evolutionary trend in flowering plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C36">Stebbins 1957</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C3">Baker (1955)</xref> noted that, unlike the situation in self-incompatible (SI) species, self-compatibility permits a species to colonize in a new habitat after long-distance dispersal. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C8">Darwin (1862)</xref> realized that autonomous self-pollination could be an adaptation to reproduction if pollinator service was lost or extremely unpredictable. For example, he illustrated that a nectarless orchid (<italic>Ophrys apifera</italic>) could be favoured by deceit pollination by bees, but was capable of self-fertilization by curving of the caudicles that delivered pollinia directly onto the stigma. Autonomous self-pollination has been classified into three types, termed ‘prior’, ‘competing’ and ‘delayed’, according to the timing of self-pollination relative to cross-pollination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C21">Lloyd and Schoen 1992</xref>). Only the last situation, in which self-pollination is delayed until the opportunity for outcrossing has passed, is considered to provide reproductive assurance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C20">Lloyd 1992</xref>).Phylogenetic analysis indicated that the two mayapple species represent an outstanding example of disjunct distribution between eastern Asia and eastern North America (EA-ENA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C19">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C39">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Himalayan mayapple, <italic>Podophyllum hexandrum</italic> Royle (Berberidaceae), is an alpine herb occurring in the eastern Himalayas, including southwest China and nearby countries. It was once treated as <italic>Sinopodophyllum hexandrum</italic> (Royle) Ying, a monotypic genus, based on morphological characteristics (e.g. pollen in tetrads) and breeding systems different from American mayapple (<italic>P. peltatum</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C47">Ying 1979</xref>), and it is sometimes regarded as a separate family Podophyllaceae (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C19">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>). However, molecular phylogeny on Berberidaceae and its relatives showed that Himalayan and American mayapple are sister species and its diversification evolved around 7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C19">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>) or 6 million years ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C39">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). The time of diversification coincides with the rapid uplift of the Himalayas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C1">An <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>), suggesting that extant populations of Himalayan mayapple were elevated to the alpine zone, unlike American mayapple. Given that <italic>Dysosma</italic>, a sister to the clade containing American and Himalayan mayapple (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C19">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C39">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C11">Guan <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), is basically SI, it is safe to deduce that the capacity for self-fertilization in Himalayan mayapple evolved recently from SI ancestors. Meanwhile, a shift from SI to self-compatible (SC) was also observed in a few populations of American mayapple where pollinators were extremely rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C25">Policansk 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C42">Whilser and Snow 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C5">Crants 2008</xref>). This parallel evolutionary transition in the two species of EA-ENA disjunct distribution suggests an ideal group to address the causes of diversification in breeding systems.In general, the degree of self-pollination within a flower is modified either by spatial or temporal separation of the mature anthers and stigmas or by combinations of these (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C23">Moore and Lewis 1965</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C15">Karron <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C14">Kalisz <italic>et al.</italic> 1999</xref>). Previous studies on Himalayan mayapple showed that no pollinators visited it, and flowers were capable of automatic self-pollination by inclining the pistil, pushing the stigma into contact with the anthers, after which the pistil returns to its normal upright position at the centre of the flower (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C46">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>). It remains unclear in this species whether autogamy is delayed selfing or whether there are any pollinators. The movement of the pistil could involve much higher energetic cost than stamen (or petal) movement, given that stamens are much smaller and more flexible. If this type of self-pollination is really facilitated by the pistil inclining, it suggests that the stigma contacts only one or two anthers in this monogynous flower, leaving other anthers untouched. This mode of pistil movement resulting in selfing is questionable, but is often cited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C22">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C32">Shaw 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C39">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C18">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C29">Ruan and Teixeira da Silva 2011</xref>).To better understand diversification of the breeding system of sister species with a disjunct distribution between EA-ENA, we conducted a study of the pollination ecology and breeding system of Himalayan mayapple (<italic>P. hexandrum</italic>). We address the following questions: (i) Are there potential pollinators for this nectarless early spring flowering herb in the Himalayan region? (ii) When and how does the autogamy take place? In particular, we try to quantify whether the selfing is caused by the pistil inclining, as previous studies suggested. We examined pollen loads on stigmas at different times of anthesis and movement of flower components, including the petals, stamens and pistil. This investigation permits us to compare breeding systems between the two mayapples and trace diversification of the species under geological disjunction.Flowers of Himalayan mayapple (<italic>P. hexandrum</italic>) and pollinators. (A) One plant with two stems each with a terminal flower. (B) Two dehisced anthers touching the stigma in a second-day flower in the late afternoon. (C) A halictid bee collecting pollen<italic>.</italic> (D) A red mature fruit in summer.Flower-visiting insects were observed along transects among four patches, taking 50 min per round. We also observed a fixed sample of about 20 flowers for a period of 30 min at a time. At total of 60 h on 18 sunny days during May 2010 and 2011 were spent watching flower-visiting insects.To examine the breeding system in <italic>P. hexandrum</italic>, we randomly selected 100 flower buds, labelled them in five groups (20 buds for each group) and bagged each one with a fine nylon mesh net to exclude flower visitors before treatments. The five treatments were as follows: (i) flowers were bagged during anthesis to exclude pollinators, to examine possible automatic self-pollination; (ii) flowers were hand-pollinated with self-pollen to examine self-compatibility; (iii) flowers were hand-pollinated with pollen from other plants at least 5 m away (outcrossing); (iv) stamens were removed from open-pollinated flowers; (v) petals were removed from open-pollinated flowers. These treatments permit us to examine the role of pollinators, and the role of petal closing and stamens in facilitating self-pollination. We compared seed set, which was the ratio of seeds to ovules per flower, among different treatments and from 20 randomly collected open-pollinated individuals (controls) using one-way ANOVA and least significant difference (LSD) post hoc tests.To quantify whether autogamy in <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> is accomplished through inclining of the pistil, which is then erected again after pollination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C46">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>), we took photographs of 20 flowers from when they had just opened (unpollinated) until the day after they had been pollinated. Using Image-Pro Plus software (Media Cybernetics, Silver Springs, MD, USA), we could obtain the angle of inclination of the pistil before and after pollination. The angle of inclination was measured between the central axis of the ovary and a horizontal line through the base of the ovary. One-way ANOVA was performed to compare the angles per flower pre- and post-pollination. Meanwhile, we used a video focusing on five flowers to record flowering behaviour.To describe movement of the sexual organs, we introduced an opening index of petals and stamens. We measured the distance between the tips of two opposite petals and stamens, and the diameter of flower buds, using a digital calliper. The distance divided by the diameter was defined as the opening index of petals and stamens. The distances were measured from 10:00 to 16:00 h every half an hour in 15 newly opened flowers and corresponding diameters were measured in the early morning.To examine when automatic self-pollination occurs during anthesis, pollen grains deposited on stigmas were counted at different flowering stages. We observed that flowers of <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> opened in the morning (around 10:00 h) and closed in late afternoon (after 16:00 h) every day during anthesis. Sixty unopened flowers were divided into four groups, and then we collected the stigmas at four different flowering times, i.e. 17:00 h on the first day, 9:00 h on the second day, 17:00 h on the second day and 9:00 h on the third day. Fifteen stigmas from each collection were fixed in standard FAA solution (formalin : acetic acid : alcohol = 90 : 5 : 5 by volume) in separate microcentrifuge tubes, and pollen grains on each stigma were counted under a microscope. Because stigmatic pollen counts were not normally distributed, they were analysed using non-parametric statistics (Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test) for pairwise comparisons among four times of collection at the 0.05 level of significance. All data analysis was conducted in SPSS, version 17.0. All means are presented with standard errors (±SE).Floral visitors to Himalayan mayapple were very rare. Our 60-h observation recorded only a total of 27 visits by solitary bees (<italic>Halictus</italic>, nine visits), honeybees (<italic>Apis cerana</italic>, four visits), sepsid flies (Sepsidae, six visits), soldier flies (Stratiomyidae, four visits) and heteropteran bugs (Coreidae, Lygaeus and Miridae, four visits). Except for <italic>Halictus</italic> and honeybees, flies and other small insects could not serve as pollinators, because no pollen grains were seen on their bodies. In addition, we also noted 19 visits by tiny insects (thrips) foraging pollen, but they did not touch the stigmas. These observations indicated that bees were potential pollinators, but they rarely visited this nectarless herb (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLT037F1">1</xref>).Comparison of seed set per fruit (mean ± SE) under six pollination treatments (open pollination, hand cross-pollination, hand self-pollination, flower bagged, all petals removed and all stamens removed). One-way ANOVA, <italic>F</italic><sub>5,109</sub> = 16.549, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, significant differences between means are indicated by the letters that differ by LSD's multiple comparison test.In contrast to previous observations, we observed that the pistils did not move during anthesis. The angle of inclination of the pistils at flower opening (71.27 ± 7.76°) was not significantly different from that at a late stage of anthesis (71.45 ± 7.32°) (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,41</sub> = 0.006, <italic>P</italic> = 0.937). The pistils did not move during flowering, being inclined from the beginning.Diagram of the petal opening index (A, mean ± SE) and the stamen opening index (B, mean ± SE) on the first day (open circles) and second day (solid circles) in <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> flowers. The time interval is 30 min.Stigmatic pollen load (mean ± SE) on three consecutive days. Measurement was at 17:00 h on the first day, 9:00 h on the second day, 17:00 h on the second day and 9:00 h on the third day. Significant differences between means are indicated by different letters (Mann–Whitney <italic>U</italic> test). The grey areas mark periods of flower closure.Our pollination treatments confirmed that Himalayan mayapple is SC and capable of autogamy. Our observations of flower behaviours and manipulations indicated that autogamy in <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> was facilitated by petal closure, rather than by pistil movement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C22">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C46">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>). The pistil was indeed inclined at flower opening, but it did not move towards the anthers during anthesis. Furthermore, we observed that bees were potential effective pollinators for this early flowering herb in the alpine area. Wind pollination is unlikely in the species, given that the showy flowers release sticky pollen in tetrads. Self- and cross-pollination yielded similar seed production, suggesting no pre-seedling inbreeding depression. Automatic self-pollination occurred when the petals were closed, indicating that it was delayed selfing rather than prior selfing as previously thought. Emasculated flowers yielded some seeds, suggesting that pollinator-mediated cross-pollination existed.Local solitary bees were occasionally seen visiting Himalayan mayapple during observations in two flowering seasons. Although terminal flowers are visible with a dark, pigmented shrunken leaf providing a contrasting background suitable for attracting pollinators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C27">Rajkumar and Ahuja 2010</xref>), previous investigators did not observe pollinators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C22">Ma <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C46">Xu <italic>et al.</italic> 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C27">Rajkumar and Ahuja 2010</xref>). As an early flowering herb in the high-altitude Himalayas, nectarless <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> may have experienced a scarcity of pollinators. Delayed selfing is a reproductive strategy responsive to the scarcity of pollinators, i.e. plants allow earlier cross-pollination to predominate when pollinators are available (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C6">Cruden 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C43">Wyatt 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C7">Cruden and Lyon 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C21">Lloyd and Schoen 1992</xref>). Delayed self-pollination is often accomplished through the movement of sexual organs in various species. For example, delayed self-pollination in <italic>Hibiscus laevis</italic> was accomplished through the progressive curling of the style branches down towards the anthers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C16">Klips and Snow 1997</xref>). In <italic>Aquilegia canadensis</italic>, delayed self-pollination resulted from progressive elongation of stigmas up towards the stamens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C10">Eckert and Schaeffer 1998</xref>). However, anthers collapsed onto stigmas in late anthesis to achieve self-pollination in <italic>Kalmia latifolia</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C28">Rathcke and Real 1993</xref>). In <italic>Lupinus nanus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C13">Juncosa and Webster 1989</xref>) and <italic>Mimulus guttatus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C9">Dole 1990</xref>), a pronounced curling of the lower stigmatic lobe facilitated self-pollination by corolla abscission. Corolla wilting has also been reported to achieve autogamy in <italic>Pedicularis dunniana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C37">Sun <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Flower closure in late anthesis or in unfavourable weather may bring delayed selfing in many species, but quantitative data on the process are few (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C13">Juncosa and Webster 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C4">Corbet 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C9">Dole 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C37">Sun <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>). Our measurements of flower movement and stigmatic pollen loads in Himalayan mayapple indicated that delayed selfing was facilitated by petals closing in the evening rather than by pistil movement. Consistent with the breeding system, low genetic diversity and remarkable population differentiation have been found in various populations of <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C45">Xiao <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C18">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).There is a growing body of evidence from phylogeographic study for allopatric speciation in sister species with a disjunct distribution between EA-ENA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C41">Wen 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C44">Xiang <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C12">Harrison <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C26">Qiu <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). A recent molecular phylogeographic study on Himalayan mayapple suggested the role of mountain glaciers in driving allopatric speciation by causing vicariant lineage divergence and acting as barriers to post-divergence gene flow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C18">Li <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). It is interesting to know the process and driver of species diversification. The sister group of the two mayapples is <italic>Dysosma</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C19">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C39">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Flowers bagged or self-pollinated in the Asian species <italic>D. versipellis</italic> did not produce seeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C11">Guan <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), suggesting that it was SI and incapable of automatic self-pollination. Compared with Himalayan mayapple, which is SC and in which no SI populations have been reported, American mayapple is mainly SI and for which 74 % of patches in central and northeastern Ohio were completely SI, while the rest could set fruits from selfing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C42">Whilser and Snow 1992</xref>), and seed production depends on occasional visits by honeybees and bumblebees and is pollen limited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C38">Swanson and Sohmer 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C30">Rust and Roth 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C24">Motten 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C17">Laverty and Plowright 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C5">Crants 2008</xref>). It is also one of the first plants to flower in spring, but it mainly occurs in the understory of the deciduous woodlands of eastern North America at 1400 m a.s.l. in the southern Appalachians, where some patches of SC individuals have been found in Oak Ridge and Tennessee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C25">Policansk 1983</xref>), across central and northeastern Ohio (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C42">Whilser and Snow 1992</xref>) and in southeastern Michigan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C5">Crants 2008</xref>). If populations frequently experience severe pollinator limitation, which often happens in high altitudes (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C2">Arroyo <italic>et al.</italic> 1982</xref>), SC individuals may have higher fitness than those that are SI. This difference may favour the spread of self-compatibility, particularly in isolated populations or in newly established habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C3">Baker 1955</xref>). Why does American mayapple not evolve from SI to SC and self-pollination as in Himalayan mayapple?The origin and spread of SC genotypes largely depend on the relative effects of inbreeding depression and fecundity differences between SC and SI genotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C31">Schemske and Lande 1985</xref>). Phylogenetic analysis suggested that extant mayapples (SC) arose from SI ancestors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C19">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C39">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). Self-pollination yielded a similar high seed set (86.5 %) compared with cross-pollination in Himalayan mayapple, suggesting no inbreeding depression at least at the pre-seedling stage. Genotypes with high fecundity of SC and a capability for selfing may spread in Himalayan mayapple in the elevated alpine area, resulting in a transition from SI to SC. In American mayapple, seed set from putative SC genotypes was only 10 % of the seed set from hand-outcrossing, preventing them from replacing SI genotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C42">Whisler and Snow 1992</xref>). Low seed set in American mayapples was due to severe inbreeding depression, i.e. selective ovule abortion after self-pollination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C5">Crants 2008</xref>).A comparison of breeding systems in the two mayapples and their relatives (<italic>Dysosma</italic>) documented a shift from SI to SC in Himalayan mayapple (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C19">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C39">Wang <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). The last rapid uprising of the Himalayas began about 4–3 million years ago in the late Miocene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C34">Shi <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). The divergence time estimated for the mayapple pairs (7 million years ago) pre-dated or almost co-occurred with the uplift of the Himalayas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C19">Liu <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>), suggesting that the shift from SI to delayed selfing occurred in the vicariant process. The pollinator fauna, in terms of the number of species and individuals, are generally depauperate with increasing elevation (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C2">Arroyo <italic>et al.</italic> 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C40">Warren <italic>et al.</italic> 1988</xref>). The uplifted habit of Himalayan mayapple may result in the scarcity of pollinators in early spring. Large variations in morphology and population genetics have been recorded in Himalayan mayapple, for example several species or varieties have been proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C35">Soejarto <italic>et al.</italic> 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C33">Shaw 2009</xref>). Population differentiation of <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> in the Himalayan region, like the differentiation of the two mayapple species, may be attributed to geological isolation and delayed selfing. Our analysis in the two mayapples suggests that the loss of pollinators could drive the shift of breeding systems from SI to SC, consistent with the model that self-compatibility permits a species to colonize in a new habitat after long-distance dispersal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT037C3">Baker 1955</xref>).This work was supported by the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">National Science Foundation of China</grant-sponsor> (<grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">NSFC</grant-sponsor>, no. <grant-num xlink:type="simple">31030016</grant-num>).Y.-Z.X. conducted 2-year field work and Q.F. joined in 1 year. Y.-Z.X. and S.-Q.H. wrote the manuscript. All authors contributed in experimental design, data analysis and commented on the manuscript.None declared.We thank M. Xie, J. Gao, Y.-B. Gong and X.-X. Tang for help in the field, Z.-D. Fang and staff from Shangri-La Alpine Botanical Garden for support, B. Montgomery and J. Crants for helpful discussions, and S. Corbet for comments on the manuscript.