 Constitutive and herbivore-induced systemic volatiles differentially attract an omnivorous biocontrol agent to contrasting  Salix  clones  Effects of leaf beetle damage on stem wood production in coppicing willow  Generalist natural enemies of a willow leaf beetle ( Phratora vulgatissima ): abundance and feeding habits  On the ecology of  Anthocoris nemorum  (L.) (Hemiptera-Heteroptera)  Predator foraging strategy influences prey population dynamics: arthropods predating a gregarious leaf beetle  Behavioural and community ecology of plants that cry for help  The evolutionary context for herbivore-induced plant volatiles: beyond the ‘cry for help  Airborne interactions between undamaged plants of different cultivars affect insect herbivores and natural enemies  Willow genotype, but not drought treatment, affects foliar phenolic concentrations and leaf-beetle resistance  The importance of specialist natural enemies for  Chrysomela lapponica  in pioneering for a new host plant  Ecophysiological comparison of direct and indirect defenses in  Nicotiana attenuata   Shared signals—‘alarm calls’ from plants increase apparency to herbivores and their enemies in nature  Within-plant signalling by volatiles triggers systemic defences  Olfactory versus contact cues in host plant recognition of a monophagous chrysomelid beetle  Comparison of volatile leaf compounds and herbivorous insect communities on three willow species  Plant odor analysis of potato: response of Guatemalan moth to above- and belowground potato volatiles  Susceptibility of willow clones ( Salix  spp.) to herbivory by  Phyllodecta vulgatissima  (L.) and  Garelucella lineola  (Fab.) (Coleoptera, Chrysomelidae)  Plant-feeding by the predaceous bug  Anthocoris nemorum  Hem: Heteroptera  Green leaf volatiles: hydroperoxide lyase pathway of oxylipin metabolism  Variation in natural plant products and the attraction of bodyguards involved in indirect plant defense  Volatile compounds from  Salix  spp. varieties differing in susceptibility to three willow beetle species  Effects of host variety on blue willow beetle  Phratora vulgatissima  performance  An aphid sex attractant. I. Biological studies  Host preference and larval performance of the salicylate-using leaf beetle  Phratora vitellinae   Retention index database for identification of general green leaf volatiles in plants by coupled capillary gas chromatography-mass spectrometry  Presence of  Lythrum salicaria  enhances the bodyguard effects of the parasitoid  Asecodes mento  for  Filipendula ulmaria   Uncoupling direct and indirect plant defences: novel opportunities for improving crop security in willow plantations  Host-plant genotype mediates supply and demand of animal food in an omnivorous insect  Plant–carnivore mutualism through herbivore-induced carnivore attractants  Induction of indirect defence against spider-mites in uninfested lima bean leaves  Systemic release of chemical signals by herbivore-injured corn  Olfactory responses of  Neoseiulus cucumeris  (Acari: Phytoseiidae) to odors of host plants and  Frankliniella occidentalis  (Thysanoptera: Thripidae)–plant complexes  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  Little is known about how herbivore-induced plant volatiles affect omnivorous predators. Here we show that the key predator  Anthocoris nemorum  is differentially attracted to three  Salix  clones when these are damaged by the detrimental blue willow beetle ( Phratora vulgatissima ). At least two volatile plant compounds were induced by the herbivore, and these were antennal active in the predator. The results elucidate how plants may recruit omnivorous predators when damaged. These findings could be utilized in crop breeding for increased resistance against herbivores.  While carnivores are known to be attracted to herbivore-induced plant volatiles, little is known about how such volatiles may affect the behaviour of omnivorous predators that may use both plants and herbivores as food. Here, we examine how systemically produced plant volatiles, in response to local herbivore damage, differentially attract a key omnivorous predator,  Anthocoris nemorum  (Heteroptera: Anthocoridae), to single clones of three species of  Salix :  S. viminalis ,  S. dasyclados  and  S. cinerea . The profiles of the plant volatiles produced were found to vary among  Salix  clones and between herbivore-damaged and intact plants.  Anthocoris nemorum  was attracted to the volatiles released from undamaged plants of all three species, but most strongly to a native  S. cinerea  clone. Plants damaged by the herbivorous leaf beetle  Phratora vulgatissima  (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae) were generally more attractive than undamaged plants, with  A. nemorum  responding to systemic changes in the damaged plants where the experimental design specifically excluded volatiles released from the actual site of damage. When comparing damaged plants, the  S. dasyclados  clone was more attractive to  A. nemorum  than the  S. viminalis  clone—a somewhat surprising result since this  Salix  clone is considered relatively resistant to  P. vulgatissima , and hence offers a limited amount of prey. Our experiments highlight that both constitutive and induced plant volatiles play a role in omnivore attraction, and this emphasizes the importance of considering odours of released volatiles when cropping and breeding  Salix  for increased resistance to herbivores.  The abundance of herbivores on a plant is determined directly by plant traits (bottom-up) and natural enemies (top-down), and indirectly by the effects of plant traits on the natural enemies of the herbivore ( Takabayashi  et al.  1991 ;  Halitschke  et al . 2000 ;  Dicke 2009 ). The importance of indirect effects is currently receiving increased attention as evidence accumulates concerning the exploitation of plant volatiles, especially herbivore-induced plant volatiles (HIPVs), by natural enemies when locating their prey ( Mumm and Dicke 2010 ). Herbivore-induced plant volatiles are released both locally, at the site of damage, and/or systemically in non-damaged leaves ( Turlings and Tumlinson 1992 ;  Halitschke  et al.  2000 ). Importantly, the blend of volatiles can vary according to plant species, plant cultivar and the developmental stage of the plant, and this blend can alter the behavioural response of some natural enemies ( Takabayashi and Dicke 1996 ). Thus, in order to make use of a herbivore's natural enemies in a biocontrol programme, it is necessary to know how the enemies respond to the volatiles released by a specific plant species or cultivar. An additional factor that may confound indirect effects is that some enemies are omnivorous. While most studies have focused on pure carnivores (e.g.  Stenberg  et al.  2007 ;  Halitschke  et al.  2008 ), recent studies have also shown that omnivorous predatory mites ( Zhong  et al.  2011 ) and ladybirds ( Glinwood  et al.  2009 ), which also gain nutrition from various plant products, respond to plant volatiles in their search for prey. Omnivores are likely to respond to both constitutive and herbivore-induced plant volatiles since, in the absence of prey, they can in some cases survive by feeding solely on plant food ( Stenberg  et al.  2010 ). Given the unpredictability of prey abundance, the ability of omnivores to survive on the plant even when no prey are present may make omnivores particularly suitable for biological control, provided they do not become pests themselves. Under favourable conditions, omnivorous plant ‘bodyguards’ can trigger top-down effects by suppressing herbivore populations, thereby increasing the production of plant biomass. For example, some well-studied omnivorous bugs in the genus  Geocoris  can consume lepidopteran eggs from wild tobacco, which would otherwise develop into larvae, a single one of which can consume the entire plant before any seeds are produced ( Halitschke  et al.  2008 ).  Willow ( Salix  spp.) is an ideal system in which to study plant–herbivore–omnivore interactions. In northern Europe the herbivorous blue willow beetle,  Phratora vulgatissima , causes extensive damage to the native  Salix cinerea  and to exotic willows used in bioenergy production: a decrease in production of biomass by up to 40 % has been recorded ( Björkman  et al.  2000 ). One important predator that contributes to the regulation of this pest is the omnivorous bug  Anthocoris nemorum  ( Björkman  et al.  2003 ;  Dalin  et al.  2006 ). It is a generalist predator that is found on several plant species ( Collyer 1967 ) and which feeds on a variety of prey including the eggs and larvae of  P. vulgatissima . This anthocorid has also been proven capable of surviving and reproducing on  Salix  plant fluid alone ( Stenberg  et al.  2010 ), and previous investigators have indicated that its consumption of sap and extra-floral nectar does not compromise plant growth (e.g.  Lauenstein 1979 ). The anthocorid can also feed on pollen and floral nectar. Thus, altogether it can utilize a wide range of plant-provided foods without damaging the plant, which makes this generalist predator interesting for biocontrol purposes. Two of the most common  Salix  species grown and bred for bioenergy in northern Europe are  S. viminalis  and  S. dasyclados  (for heritage see  Kendall  et al.  1996 ), of which the latter is considered to be resistant to  P. vulgatissima  and the former susceptible. The preference that  P. vulgatissima  exhibits for volatiles from different  Salix  species has been evaluated previously ( Peacock  et al.  2001 ).  In  Salix , volatiles are well known to alter the composition of insect communities ( Inui  et al.  2003 ) and are correlated with the performance of  P. vulgatissima  ( Peacock  et al.  2001 ). To date, the role of plant volatiles for natural enemies of this pest has not been addressed.  In this study, we examined the attraction of  A. nemorum , an omnivorous anthocorid predator, to plant volatiles released from three contrasting  Salix  clones that differ in suitability to  P. vulgatissima . We used single representative clones of three species of  Salix: S. viminalis ,  S. dasyclados  and  S. cinerea . We expected the preference to mimic the preference of  P. vulgatissima , since this would hypothetically increase the omnivore's likelihood of finding animal food. We also examined whether induced volatiles (HIPVs) altered anthocorid preferences. Overall, we addressed the following specific questions: (i) Is  A. nemorum  attracted to constitutively produced  Salix  volatiles? (ii) Can  A. nemorum  differentiate between these  Salix  clones? (iii) Do HIPVs in  Salix  affect  A. nemorum 's preference for particular  Salix  clones? (iv) Do the volatile profiles of damaged and undamaged  Salix  plants differ?  We used three  Salix  clones: the commercial clones ‘Jorunn’ ( S. viminalis ) and SW901290 ( S. dasyclados ), and one haphazardly selected clone of the native  S. cinerea . The two commercial clones were chosen because they, like other clones of these species (I. Åhman, unpubl. data), are known to differ in their susceptibility to  P. vulgatissima . About 6 weeks before the tests were conducted, winter cuttings (10 cm) of each clone were planted in 11-cm pots containing Hasselfors (Örebro, Sweden) planting soil. The plants were grown in greenhouses under natural light, at 18–24 °C, and continuously provided with water containing fertilizer in solution (N–P–K : 51–10–43).   Four-arm olfactometer (without odour sources shown) after an original design that was first presented in   Pettersson (1970) . Air is sucked from the centre, thereby drawing air up the arms from odour sources, which may include isolated plants, a pot with soil or untreated air.  The out-flow pipe was temporarily removed from the apparatus to allow individual specimens of  A. nemorum  to be released at the centre of the olfactometer. The olfactometer was divided into four choice zones and a neutral central zone in which the presence of an animal was defined as it exhibiting no choice. The location of each  A. nemorum  was recorded every third minute over a period of 30 min. The ‘visitation rate’ for each of the four choice zones was defined as ‘the number of recorded insect observations in the choice zone divided by the total number of observations’. Between each test the olfactometer was washed in detergent and 70 % ethanol, and the position of the treatments randomly re-allocated. After seven insects had been tested the plants were exchanged for new ones.  We performed three sets of experiments. In the first set, we tested whether the anthocorid was attracted to  Salix  at all, and if so, whether it could discriminate between the three contrasting clones. This was accomplished by comparing the anthocorids' attraction to airflow from undamaged  S. viminalis ,  S. dasyclados  and  S. cinerea  clones placed at the three olfactometer arms, with ambient air supplied at the fourth arm as a control.  The second set of experiments comprised two parts focusing on the  S. viminalis  and  S. dasyclados  clones. The reason why we excluded one plant was that we wanted to include both air and soil volatiles as independent controls. Therefore, the four-armed olfactometer only allowed for two more odour sources, and the  S. viminalis  and  S. dasyclados  clones were chosen because they are used in commercial plantations, and included in several ongoing research projects throughout Europe. First, we tested  A. nemorum 's attraction to volatiles from undamaged plants and then to plants damaged by herbivory. The two plant treatments occupied two of the olfactometer's arms, with the third arm supplying airflow from a pot containing only moist soil, and the fourth supplying only ambient air. When testing plants damaged by herbivores, three starved adult  P. vulgatissima  were isolated in a 10 cm × 5 cm frying bag (Toppits ® , Melitta, Germany) at the top of one of the shoots of the plants within the larger bag. All plants were checked to ensure that the beetles had started to feed on the leaves 1h prior to the test. The beetles were kept isolated on the shoots throughout the test. The bag enclosing the beetles prevented any volatiles from being emitted, thus ensuring that the anthocorid could only respond to systemically induced changes in the host plant. Finally, we directly compared damaged and undamaged plants within each species to determine the relative attraction of anthocorids to volatiles released from damaged and undamaged individuals (damaged plants were fed on by  P. vulgatissima  as described above). This test used only ambient air as the control because the previous results had already demonstrated that there was no significant difference between soil and air controls.  Odour collection was performed over a period of 24 h using the same general set-up as for the olfactometer test, except that bags did not include pots, i.e. there were no soil volatiles, and inflowing air was pushed through activated charcoal at 600 mL min −1  at the base of the plants. The volatiles were collected in (Porapak Q filters, Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO) placed at the top of the bags connected to a pump pulling at 300 mL min −1 . The positive-pressure venting prevented any contamination by volatiles from external sources. Three collections from the different clones and treatments were made in parallel. Every sample was replicated six times. Six control samples, using just the bag, were also collected. Porapak Q filters were baked at 180 °C and charcoal filters and tubes were baked at 150 °C overnight under a constant stream of nitrogen before every collection. The frying bags were also baked overnight. Volatiles were extracted from filters by washing with 500 µL of hexane (high-performance liquid chromatography grade) and stored at −20 °C until analysed.  The collected odours were analysed with a gas chromatograph coupled to a mass spectrometer (GC-MS; 6890GC and 5975MS, Agilent, Santa Clara, CA). The GC-MS was equipped with a DB-wax (PEG) column and used helium as a carrier gas. A 2-µL sub-sample from each collected odour sample was injected either manually or by the autoinjector (7683B Series injector, Agilent) (for more details see  Karlsson  et al . 2009 ). The inlet temperature was 200 °C and the oven temperature was set to 30 °C for 3 min, and then increased by 8 °C per minute until 225 °C was reached and held for 3 min. The protocol was terminated by a 1-min post-run at 250 °C. Compounds were tentatively identified by comparing the mass spectra and retention times of the peaks in the odour collections with those from synthetic and authentic standards, and comparing with published Kovats retention indices from the same type of column or a column with similar properties.  All behavioural data were analysed using SAS 9.1. Friedman analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to test for differences in preference in each experiment. Because the variables were related (i.e. the number of observed visitations to a specific choice zone depended on the number of visitations to other choice zones), a new variable was created from the difference between the number of visits (1–10) for each individual insect and pair-wise comparison (for example  S. viminalis  vs.  S. dasyclados ) which was then tested for deviation from zero (cf.  Heisswolf  et al . 2007 ). These data were not normally distributed and were therefore analysed with the non-parametric Wilcoxon signed tests. The released amounts of compounds 1–5 from undamaged and damaged  S. dasyclados  were compared using a two-sample  t -test.   Results from the Friedman ANOVA tests on  A. nemorum:  plant preference, herbivore-induced effects between  Salix  clones and herbivore-induced effects within  Salix  clones . Statistically significant  P  values are in bold.   Visitation rates (mean ± SE) of  A. nemorum  to each of four choice zones in an olfactometer during a 30-min observation period . The four odour sources infiltrating the choice zones were volatiles from undamaged  S. viminalis ,  S. dasyclados  and  S. cinerea , and ambient air. Different letters indicate significant differences (Wilcoxon's signed test,  P  &lt; 0.05).   Visitation rates (mean ± SE) of  A. nemorum  to each of four choice zones in an olfactometer during a 30-min observation period . The four odour sources infiltrating the choice zones were (A)  n  = 40 undamaged  S. viminalis  and  S. dasyclados  with ambient air and soil as negative controls; (B)  n  = 15  S. viminalis  and  S. dasyclados  plants subjected to herbivory by  P. vulgatissima , with ambient air and soil as negative controls. Different letters indicate significant differences (Wilcoxon's signed test,  P  &lt; 0.05).   Visitation rates (mean ± SE) of  A. nemorum  to each of four choice zones in an olfactometer during a 30-min observation period . The four odour sources infiltrating the choice zones were: (A) herbivore ( P. vulgatissima )-damaged  S. viminalis  and undamaged  S. viminalis , and two ambient air zones; (B) herbivore-damaged  S. dasyclados  and undamaged  S. dasyclados , and two ambient air zones. Different letters indicate significant difference (Wilcoxon's signed test,  P  &lt; 0.05).   (A) Odour profiles of undamaged and herbivore ( P. vulgatissima )-damaged  S. dasyclados  . (B) Odour profiles of undamaged and damaged  S. viminalis . (C) The system for odour collection without plants (control collections). The following compounds were tentatively identified from the headspace of damaged SW901290: (1) 3-carene; (2) E-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonatriene; (3) Z-3-hexenyl acetate; (4) Z-3-hexen-ol; (5) Z-3-hexenyl isovalerate.  Overall, we have shown that  A. nemorum , an important omnivorous biocontrol agent in  Salix  plantations, is differentially attracted to several clones of undamaged  Salix , and that, furthermore,  A. nemorum 's preferences for different clones changed when there was a genotype-specific systemic change in the volatile profile induced by  P. vulgatissima  feeding on the plants. In contrast to our predictions, the host plant preference of  A. nemorum  did not mirror the preference of its main prey, the pest insect  P. vulgatissima . While the latter is less attracted to, and performs worse on,  S. dasyclados  relative to other  Salix  species ( Kendall  et al.  1996 ;  Glynn  et al.  2004 ;  Peacock  et al.  2004 ),  A. nemorum  was attracted to volatiles emitted by the  S. dasyclados  clone, both when damaged and when undamaged.  More specifically, the three  Salix  clones differed in their attraction to  A. nemorum ; the  S. cinerea  clone was significantly more attractive than the  S. viminalis  clone while the  S. dasyclados  clone did not differ from the other two. Interestingly, when the plants suffered feeding damage by  P. vulgatissima , the  S. dasyclados  clone was preferred. This pattern may result in attraction to a host that supports a few herbivores and thus could be a maladapted response to  S. dasyclados , which is not native to Sweden. On the other hand,  Stenberg  et al.  (2010 ,  2011)  have recently shown that  S. dasyclados  provides high-quality plant food to  A. nemorum , and propose a plant-centred hypothesis suggesting that the high-quality plant food provided by  S. dasyclados  may be important in supporting  A. nemorum  as part of an indirect defence against detrimental  P. vulgatissima  herbivores. Using the same plant-centred perspective we find it intriguing that the  S. dasyclados  clone used here is also highly attractive to  A. nemorum  when herbivore damaged.  Herbivore-induced volatiles are known to differ in both quality and quantity among plant genotypes ( Dicke and Baldwin 2010 ). We found that  P. vulgatissima  feeding induced changes in the odour profile of both  S. dasyclados  and  S. viminalis . The compounds released from damaged  S. dasyclados  headspace are common plant compounds ( Ruther 2000 ;  Matsui 2006 ) known to be involved in plant–insect interactions ( Heil 2010 ).  A pilot GC electro-antennogram study on  A. nemorum  antennal responses has demonstrated that three of the compounds released from damaged  S. dasyclados  (3-carene, E-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonatriene and Z-3-hexenyl acetate) were antennally active (J. A. Stenberg  et al ., unpubl. data). Predatory bugs have previously been shown to utilize terpenoids and ‘green leaf volatiles’ to locate their prey on herbivore-attacked plants ( Halitschke  et al.  2008 ). These compounds are known to be emitted in response to herbivore attack ( Takabayashi  et al.  1991 ) and are attractive to both generalist and specialist predators.  There is an impending risk for pest insects to overcome plants' resistance to them if, or when, plants with strong resistance become more common in plantations (cf.  Panda and Khush 1995 ). This makes natural enemies especially important, not only for their direct ability to regulate pest numbers, but also for their role in preventing the evolution of new resistant pest populations. Previous studies have shown that  A. nemorum  is relatively insensitive to phenolic glycosides that constitute a cornerstone in the direct defence in  Salix  ( Rank  et al . 1998 ;  Stenberg  et al.  2010 ,  2011 ). Thus, potential conflicts between direct and indirect defences seem to be minimal in  Salix . The fact that the omnivorous predator  A. nemorum  is a widespread and common species makes it an especially important player in the  Salix  system, even though its importance varies between sites ( Gross  et al.  2004 ). The fact that resistant and moderately resistant  Salix  clones are more efficient in attracting  A. nemorum  than the susceptible clone strengthens our plant-centred defence theory and opens up novel opportunities for improved breeding. The fact that  S. dasyclados  is both more resistant to the herbivorous beetles and more attractive to the predator suggests that species such as these are likely to be highly suitable for bioenergy production. In summary, the results presented here lead us one step closer towards understanding the bottom-up and top-down regulators of  P. vulgatissima  populations in  Salix  plantations. How these two regulators interact to shape the overall pest resistance of plants constitutes an important question for future research.  The following additional information is available in the online version of this article –  File 1: Table showing the relative amounts (ion intensities) of the compounds released from undamaged and damaged  S. dasyclados .  This work was funded by  The Swedish Energy Agency, The Faculty of Natural Resources and Agricultural Sciences at SLU , and  Lantmännen Agroenergi AB  through the SAMBA project.  All authors planned the study and wrote the manuscript. A.L. carried out the behavioural assays and analysed the resulting data. T.B. carried out the volatile profiling and analysed the resulting data.  None declared.  We thank Anna-Sara Liman and Karin Eklund for collecting insects and for raising plants. Thanks are due to Professor Jan Pettersson, Dr Robert Glinwood and Dr Velemir Ninkovic for help with experimental design and statistics. 