 Stress physiology of migrant birds during stopover in natural and anthropogenic woodland habitats of the Northern Prairie region  Interaction of corticosterone with feeding, activity and metabolism in passerine birds  A compilation and synthesis of avian research completed in South Dakota. South Dakota Department of Game, Fish and Parks, Wildlife Division Report 2003-09  Role of glucocorticoids in the regulation of lipogenesis  Response of testosterone and corticosterone plasma levels to the challenge of sibling competition: a study in common terns  Landbird migration in the American West: recent progress and future research directions  Forest area in eastern South Dakota, 1980  Dietary effects on prediction of body mass changes in birds by plasma metabolites  An integrative assessment of the effects of tamarisk on stopover ecology of a long-distance migrant along the San Pedro River, Arizona  Balancing food and predator pressure induces chronic stress in songbirds  Sight of a predator can stimulate a corticosterone response in the great tit ( Parus major )  Statistical Power Analysis for The Behavioral Sciences  Reproductive correlates of spring arrival date in the Eastern Kingbird  Tyrannus tyrannus   Stopover ecology of Neotropical migrant songbirds in riparian corridors in the northern Great Plains  Age structure of Neotropical migrants during fall migration in South Dakota: is the northern Great Plains region an inland ‘coast’?  Stress and cognition: are corticosteroids good or bad guys?  Dynamics of plains cottonwood ( Populus deltoides ) forests and historical landscape change along unchannelized segments of the Missouri River, USA  Variation in local-scale edge effects: mechanisms and landscape contest  Corticosterone and migratory fueling in Northern wheatears facing different barrier crossings  Corticosterone, food intake and refueling rate in a long-distance migrant  Speed of migration and migratory flight lengths of passerine birds ringed during autumn migration in Sweden  Integrating landscape ecology and conservation physiology  Recent advances in understanding migration systems of New World land birds  Corticosterone in migrating songbirds during endurance flight  Effects of captivity and body condition on plasma corticosterone, locomotor behavior, and plasma metabolites in Curve-billed Thrashers  Corticotropin-releasing factor in the dorsal raphe nucleus increases medial prefrontal cortical serotonin via type 2 receptors and median raphe nucleus activity  Timing and speed of migration in North and West European populations of  Sylvia  warblers  Spring migration in the western Mediterranean and NW Africa the Piccole Isole project  Species richness and nesting success of migrant forest birds in natural river corridors and anthropogenic woodlands in southeastern South Dakota  Fitness consequences of timing of migration and breeding in cormorants  Extrinsic and intrinsic sources of variation in plasma lipid metabolites of free-living Western Sandpipers ( Calidris mauri )  A field validation of plasma metabolite profiling to assess refueling performance of migratory birds  Ecology and physiology of en route Nearctic-Neotropical migratory birds: a call for collaboration  Age-related differences in foraging efficiency, molt, and fat deposition of gray catbirds prior to autumn migration  Winter and migratory weight and fat field studies on some North American buntings  Floral and faunal trends in the middle Missouri River  Changes in patterns of corticosterone secretion concurrent with migratory fattening in a Neotropical migratory bird  Modulation of the adrenocortical stress response in Neotropical migrants during autumn migration  The role of corticosterone in supporting migratory lipogenesis in the Dark-Eyed Junco,  Junco hyemalis : a model for central and peripheral regulation  Circulating prolactin and corticosterone concentrations during the development of migratory condition in the Dark-eyed Junco,  Junco hyemalis   The adrenal cortex of birds . In    Chester-Jones  I    Henderson  I   , eds,  General and Comparative Endocrinology of the Adrenal Cortex  Regulation of protein breakdown and adrenocortical response to stress in birds during migratory flight  Are birds stressed during long-term flights? A wind-tunnel study on circulating corticosterone in the red knot  Forest overstory vegetation and environment on the Missouri River floodplain in North Dakota  Can wind help explain seasonal differences in avian migration speed?  Dynamics of food availability, body condition and physiological stress response in breeding Black-legged Kittiwakes  Stress hormones link food availability and population in seabirds  Role of the low-affinity glucocorticoid receptor in the regulation of behavior and energy metabolism in the migratory Red Knot  Calidris canutus islandica   Action of glucocorticoids at a seasonal baseline as compared to stress-related levels in the regulation of periodic life processes  Baseline and stress-induced plasma corticosterone during long-distance migration in the Bar-tailed Godwit,  Limosa lapponica   Effects of predation danger on migration strategies of sandpipers  Turnover rates of fall-migrating pectoral sandpipers in the lower Mississippi alluvial valley  Physiological evidence that anthropogenic woodlots can substitute for native riparian woodlands as stopover habitat for migrant birds  Non-invasive corticosterone treatment changes foraging intensity in red-eyed vireos  Vireo olivaceus   Corticosterone secretion, energetic condition, and a test of the migration modulation hypothesis in the Hermit Thrush ( Catharus guttatus ), a short-distance migrant  Energy demands of migration on Red-eyed Vireos  Physiological costs and carry-over effects of avian interspecific brood parasitism influence reproductive tradeoffs  Corticosterone levels as indicators of habitat quality: effects of habitat segregation in a migratory bird during the non-breeding season  Diversity and abundance of spring migratory birds using habitat islands on the Great Plains  Ecology and Management of Neotropical Migratory Birds  Early programming of the hypothalamo–pituitary–adrenal axis  Patterns of corticosterone secretion in migrating Semipalmated Sandpipers at a major spring stopover site  Mechanisms of  en route  habitat selection: how do migrants make habitat decisions during stopover?  Stopover habitat and its importance in the conservation of landbird migrants  Priority access to food in migratory birds: age, sex and motivational asymmetries  Short-term and projected long-term responses of floodplain bird communities to the 2011 flood on the Missouri River  Stress in the wild: chronic predator pressure and acute restraint affect plasma DHEA and corticosterone levels in a songbird  Stress hormone dynamics: an adaptation to migration?  Winter adaptations in chickadees and titmice and the added effect of habitat fragmentation  The relationship of metabolic performance and distribution in black-capped and Carolina chickadees  Baseline corticosterone in wintering marine birds: methodological considerations and ecological patterns  Migration patterns and habitat use by passerine and near-passerine migrant birds in eastern Africa  Multiple Regressions in Behavioral Research: Explanation and Prediction  Baseline corticosterone peaks in shorebirds with maximal energy stores for migration: a general preparatory mechanism for rapid behavioral and metabolic transitions?  Tradeoffs between food abundance and predation danger in spatial usage of a stopover site by western sandpipers,  Calidris mauri   Long-term unpredictable foraging conditions and physiological stress response in Mountain Chickadees ( Poecile gambeli )  Identification Guide to North American Birds. Slate Creek Press  Body condition is associated with adrenocortical response in the Barn Swallow ( Hirundo rustica  L.) during early stages of autumn migration  Plasma corticosterone, adrenal mass, winter weather, and season in nonbreeding populations of Dark-eyed Juncos ( Junco hyemallis hyemalis )  Season and migration alters the corticosterone response to capture and handling in an arctic migrant, the white-crowned sparrow ( Zonotrichia leucophrys gambelii )  Effects of weather on corticosterone response in wild free-living passerine birds  Endocrinology of the stress-response  Variation of fuelling rates among sites, days, and individuals in migrating passerine birds  Basal and stress-induced corticosterone levels of garden warblers,  Sylvia borin , during migration  Effects of physiological state, mass change and diet on plasma metabolite profiles in western sandpiper  Calidris mauri   Plasma metabolites and mass changes of migratory landbirds indicate adequate stopover refueling in a heavily urbanized landscape  Stopover refueling rate underlies protandry and seasonal variation in migration timing of songbirds  Patterns of fuel use and storage in migrating passerines in relation to fruit resources at autumn stopover sites  Arrival timing and seasonal reproductive performance in a long-distance migratory landbird  Seasonal variation in thermogenic capacity in migratory warbling vireos  Migration-induced variation in thermogenic capacity in migratory passerines  Abundance and richness of Neotropical migrants during stopover at farmstead woodlots and associated habitats in southeastern South Dakota  Riparian and woodlot landscape patterns and migration of Neotropical migrants in riparian forests of eastern South Dakota  Relationship between stopover site choice of migrating sandpipers, their population status, and environmental stressors  Tests of landscape influence: nest predation and brood parasitism in fragmented ecosystems  Stopover biology of shorebirds at small natural and large managed wetland sites in eastern South Dakota and western Minnesota  A hard look at blood sampling of birds  Avian metabolism: costs of migration in free-flying songbirds  Endocrine responses to inclement weather in naturally breeding populations of White-Crowned Sparrows ( Zonotrichia leucophrys pugetensis )  Seasonal changes of the adrenocortical response to stress in birds of the Sonoran Desert  Modulation of the adrenocortical responses to acute stress in Arctic birds: a possible ecological basis  Environmental stress, field endocrinology and conservation biology  Spring stopover of intercontinental migratory thrushes along the northern coast of the Gulf of Mexico  Stopover ecology and habitat use of migratory Wilson's Warblers  Editor: Steven Cooke  This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License ( http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ ), which permits unrestricted reuse distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.  This study addresses the question of whether increased anthropogenic influence on migration stopover sites/migration corridors affects the stress physiology of migratory landbirds. Our data suggest that the reduction of natural riparian corridor habitats and subsequent increased reliance of woodland migrants on anthropogenic woodlots for stopover is not detrimental to the stress physiology of these birds in a region with limited woodland habitats.  Anthropogenic alterations of woodland habitat may influence stopover biology, which in turn could alter the stress physiology of migratory landbirds. Woodland stopover habitats are scarce in the Northern Prairie region of North America and consist of native riparian corridor woodlands (corridors) and smaller, more isolated woodlots of anthropogenic origin around farmsteads (woodlots). Corridor habitats have been greatly reduced since the time of European settlement, but woodlot habitats have appeared over this same time period. In this study, we compared stopover biology and stress physiology of migratory landbirds using natural and anthropogenic woodland habitats. We first tested for differences between birds in the two habitats for baseline corticosterone (CORT B ) and the magnitude of the stress response for individual species, taxonomic families and foraging guilds. Plasma corticosterone increased significantly for all bird groups in both habitats following 30 min of restraint stress (CORT 30 ), and neither CORT B  nor the magnitude of the stress response (CORT 30  − CORT B ) differed significantly between birds in the two habitats. Secondly, because CORT B  levels are often elevated and CORT secretion following a stressor is often suppressed for birds in poor body condition, we hypothesized that woodland migrants with higher fattening rates would show reduced CORT B  and a robust stress response. We tested this hypothesis by assessing the relationships between plasma corticosterone and plasma metabolites associated with refuelling. We found that CORT B  was negatively associated and the magnitude of the stress response positively associated with plasma triglycerides (an indicator of fat deposition), with opposite patterns for corticosterone and plasma β-hydroxybutyrate (an indicator of fat catabolism). These data suggest that both corridor and woodlot habitats serve as effective stopover habitat and that the reduction of corridor habitat and increased reliance on anthropogenic woodlots is not detrimental to the stress physiology of migrants in a region with limited woodland habitats.  Migration is energetically expensive, and woodland migrant birds must refuel at stopover habitats along the migratory route ( Moore and Woodrey, 1993 ;  Yong and Moore, 1997 ;  Moore and Aborn, 2000 ;  Wikelski  et al. , 2003 ;  Faaborg  et al. , 2010 ). Woodland habitats are scarce in the Northern Prairie region of North America and consist of natural riparian corridor woodlands (hereafter corridors) and small anthropogenic woodlots (hereafter woodlots;  Castonguay, 1982 ;  Swanson  et al. , 2005 ;  Gentry  et al. , 2006 ). These natural corridors have been greatly reduced and degraded since the time of European settlement ( Johnson  et al. , 1976 ;  Hesse, 1996 ;  Dixon  et al. , 2012 ). The reduction of corridor habitats, however, has occurred simultaneously with an increase in the number of small woodlots of anthropogenic origin ( Bakker, 2003 ;  Swanson  et al. , 2005 ). Given that woodland migrants occupy both corridor and woodlot habitats in this region during migratory stopover ( Martin, 1980 ;  Dean, 1999 ;  Bakker, 2003 ;  Swanson  et al. , 2003 ,  2005 ), these woodlots have the potential to provide a partial substitute for lost and degraded riparian woodlands as stopover habitat for woodland migrant birds.  One aspect of the biology of migratory birds that may be influenced by anthropogenic alterations to the natural landscape is their stress physiology, which can impact the timely and successful completion of migration, with potential fitness consequences ( Heglund and Skagen, 2005 ;  Carlisle  et al. , 2009 ;  Eikenaar  et al. , 2014 ). Corticosterone (CORT) is the major glucocorticoid secreted in birds ( Holmes and Phillips, 1976 ) and is a primary component of the stress response ( Wingfield  et al. , 1997 ). In general, plasma CORT levels are low prior to a stressor and increase rapidly (within minutes) in response to stress, reaching a peak after 30–60 min (e.g.  Holberton  et al. , 1996 ). The increase in plasma CORT in response to a stressor is known as the stress response and acts to direct the organism away from energetically costly activities, such as migration, breeding or courtship, to focus on activities that will promote immediate condition improvement and enhance the probability of survival, such as foraging ( Wingfield  et al. , 1992 ,  1995 ). Indeed, high plasma CORT may enhance fattening during migration ( Astheimer  et al. , 1992 ;  Long and Holberton, 2004 ;  Landys  et al. , 2006 ;  Lõhmus  et al. , 2006 ;  Holberton  et al. , 2007 ,  2008 ; but see  Eikenaar  et al. , 2013 ,  2014 ). However, plasma CORT levels and stopover duration may show a U-shaped relationship, with migrants potentially having higher baseline CORT (CORT B ) upon arrival at stopover sites, showing a decline as their body condition improves and an increase shortly before their departure, when fat stores are high ( Piersma  et al. , 2000 ;  Landys-Ciannelli  et al. , 2002 ;  Eikenaar  et al. , 2013 ). Such a U-shaped relationship between stopover duration and plasma CORT may still be consistent with CORT promoting fattening if fat migrants decrease foraging and fattening rate prior to departure (e.g.  Loria and Moore, 1990 ), concurrent with elevated plasma CORT concentrations to stimulate departure. The elevated plasma CORT concentrations upon departure may function in relationship to other hormones as the cue to induce migratory flight ( Schwabl  et al. , 1991 ;  Landys-Ciannelli  et al. , 2002 ;  Eikenaar  et al. , 2013 ).  Plasma CORT levels in birds may be related to body condition, and many studies suggest that fat birds may show lower levels of CORT B  and a greater stress response than lean birds ( Schwabl  et al. , 1991 ;  Marra and Holberton, 1998 ;  Holberton, 1999 ;  Jenni  et al. , 2000 ;  Piersma  et al. , 2000 ;  Mizrahi  et al. , 2001 ;  Landys-Ciannelli  et al. , 2002 ;  Long and Holberton, 2004 ;  Raja-aho  et al. , 2010 ;  Fokidis  et al. , 2011 ). Migrants in corridor and woodlot sites in the present study showed similar refuelling rates, as indicated by plasma metabolite analyses ( Liu and Swanson, 2014 ), but whether the foraging effort required to achieve similar refuelling rates differs between corridors and woodlots is unknown. Highly fragmented landscapes, such as the woodlots in the present study, often reduce food availability and require increased foraging effort in comparison to more contiguous habitats, such as the corridor habitats in the present study ( Ellis  et al. , 2012 ). If differences in foraging effort exist between corridor and woodlot habitats, such differences could influence the stress physiology of migrants ( Kitaysky  et al. , 1999 ;  Pravosudov  et al. , 2001 ;  Mark and Rubenstein, 2013 ), despite similar refuelling rates.  Differences in the size and structure of corridor and woodlot habitats could also affect other ecological factors, which could, in turn, influence stress physiology of migrant birds. In southeastern South Dakota, the average size of corridor woodlands is more than three times larger than woodlots, which results in much greater amounts of woodland edge for woodlot habitats, and corridors also harbour more diverse vegetation than woodlots ( Castonguay, 1982 ;  Gentry  et al. , 2006 ;  Liu and Swanson, 2014 ). These differences in size, structure and vegetative diversity of corridors and woodlots may produce differences in predation pressure, competition among migrants and thermal microclimates ( Ellis  et al. , 2012 ), all of which could potentially influence stress physiology. Predation pressure can alter the stopover biology of migrants ( Lank  et al. , 2003 ;  Pomeroy, 2006 ;  Taylor  et al. , 2007 ) and influence the stress response ( Cockrem and Silverin, 2002 ;  Clinchy  et al. , 2004 ;  Newman  et al. , 2013 ). Smaller woodland parcel size and increased edge facilitate the access of predators to smaller woodlands ( Donovan  et al. , 1997 ;  Tewksbury  et al. , 2006 ), so predation pressure is expected to be higher in woodlots than in corridors in our study area. Such differences in predation pressure could result in differences in stress physiology between migrants in corridors and woodlots in the present study.  Competition may also influence stress physiology, and better competitors, such as birds with better body condition or of larger size, may show lower CORT B  and a greater magnitude of the stress response ( Lehnen and Krementz, 2005 ;  Braasch  et al. , 2014 ). Hatch-year birds are usually socially subordinate to adults, which may restrict the former's access to limited resources due to competitive interactions with adults ( Moore  et al. , 2003 ;  Faaborg  et al. , 2010 ). In addition, because juveniles in autumn are experiencing their first migration, foraging efficiency during stopover may be lower than that of experienced adults ( Yong  et al. , 1998 ;  Heise and Moore, 2003 ). Consequently, the stress response might differ between ages, with higher CORT B  and a lower stress response in juveniles than in adults. The age ratios of migrants at woodlot and corridor study sites differ, with higher proportions of juveniles at woodlot sites, perhaps resulting from competition with adults ( Dean  et al. , 2004 ;  Liu and Swanson, 2014 ); therefore, differences in stress physiology between birds in corridors and woodlots as a function of differing competitive interactions or differing age ratios might be expected.  Finally, the smaller size and increased edge of woodlots relative to corridors could affect thermal microclimates of birds in the two habitats. These changes would be likely to contribute to increased penetration of wind into woodlot habitats, which would function to reduce operative temperatures for birds in woodlots relative to corridors ( Olson and Grubb, 2007 ). Such reduced temperatures may have metabolic consequences for woodland birds ( Olson  et al. , 2010 ), and thermal stress can influence the stress response in birds, particularly during periods of inclement weather ( Wingfield  et al. , 1983 ;  Rogers  et al. , 1993 ;  Romero  et al. , 2000 ). Thus, differences in microclimate could also contribute to differences in stress physiology for migrants in corridor and woodlot study sites.  In the present study, therefore, we tested for differences between birds in corridors and woodlots for CORT B  and the magnitude of the stress response for individual species, taxonomic families and foraging guilds to determine whether migrants in anthropogenic habitats demonstrate different stress physiology from those in natural riparian corridor habitats. As an additional objective, we also examined whether stress physiology in migrants was correlated with refuelling rates in the two habitats, as measured by plasma metabolites ( Liu and Swanson, 2014 ).  Study sites in Clay County, SD, USA. Open circles denote corridor sites and filled circles woodlot sites. Contiguous woodland areas for the study sites ranged from 1 to 1.6 km 2  for corridor sites and from 0.17 to 0.2 km 2  for woodlot sites.  Migrants were captured with 9 m, 36-mm-mesh, nylon mist nets. Each of the six study sites was sampled once per week, and we rotated through the sites in the same order, with woodlot and corridor sites sampled on alternating days during spring (mid-April to early June, 2010–2012) and autumn (mid-August to mid-October, 2010–2011) migration periods. Mist nets were operated for a few hours, beginning at sunrise, and during similar weather conditions, i.e. no rain and relatively low wind speed (&lt;30 kph). We erected up to three nets per individual field worker at each site, and monitored nets continuously so that we could extract birds from the nets immediately upon capture. The initial blood samples for CORT B  determination were collected within 3 min of birds hitting the net. We collected blood samples with 50 µl heparinized capillary tubes via venipuncture from the brachial vein on the underside of the wing ( Schwabl  et al. , 1991 ;  Wingfield  et al. , 1992 ;  Palm  et al. , 2013 ). A second sample was taken 30 min after capture (CORT 30 ), with birds held in cloth bags during the 30 min restraint stress ( Wingfield  et al. , 1992 ). Depending on bird body mass, a maximum of 100–200 µl blood was sampled from each individual bird ( Voss  et al. , 2010 ). After collection, blood samples were transferred into microcentrifuge tubes and stored on ice while in the field. Upon return to the laboratory, blood samples were centrifuged for 10 min at 4°C and 3000  g  . The plasma was then removed to new microtubes and immediately stored at −60°C until later measurement of plasma CORT.  Prior to release following blood sampling, we banded birds with United States Geological Survey aluminum leg bands, identified each bird to species, and aged birds (autumn only; using skull ossification,  Pyle, 1997 ) as after hatch year (AHY) or hatch year (HY). The date and time of capture were recorded for each bird. Unflattened wing chord and tarsus length were measured with a wing ruler to the nearest 0.5 mm or with callipers to the nearest 0.1 mm. We measured body mass to the nearest 0.1 g with an electronic scale (Ohaus Model LS200) and scored visible fat in the furculum and abdomen on a 0–5 scale ( Helms and Drury, 1960 ). Following blood sampling and morphometric measurements, birds were released at the site of capture. Bird capture, blood sampling and banding were carried out under a Master Banding Permit from the United States Geological Survey Bird Banding Laboratory to D.L.S. All methods in the study were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at the University of South Dakota (protocol # 84-03-11-14B).  Plasma metabolite data are from  Liu and Swanson (2014) , who measured plasma concentrations of triglycerides (TRIG), glycerol and β-hydroxybutyrate (BUTY) from the same individual birds for which CORT was measured in the present study. We measured plasma metabolites with commercially available spectrophotometric assay kits (Sigma-Aldrich Corp., St Louis, MO, USA) using a Beckman DU-7400 spectrophotometer ( Liu and Swanson, 2014 ). We did not obtain sufficient volumes of blood from all individuals for all plasma metabolite and CORT measurements, so we determined the relationships between plasma CORT and plasma metabolites from a subset of individuals, for which we had measurements of both CORT and plasma metabolites.  We measured plasma CORT concentrations with commercially available microplate spectrophotometric end-point assay kits (Enzo Life Sciences ADI-901-097; Assay Designs Inc., Ann Arbor, MI, USA), according to the manufacturer's instructions ( Forster  et al. , 2008 ). We distributed samples across assay plates evenly with respect to season and species to minimize effects of inter-assay variation on subsequent analyses. All samples, controls and corticosterone standards (0–2000 ng/ml) were run in duplicate. Plasma corticosterone levels were detected by absorbance of samples at 405 nm using an automated plate reader and KineticCalc Jr software (Bio-Tek Instruments, Wonooski, VT, USA). Absorbance values from samples were applied to the standard curve generated ( r  2  = 0.99), and CORT levels were expressed as nanograms per millilitre. Absorbance values were also used to calculate the percentage of maximal binding, which ranged from 17.94 to 23.56% ( n  = 21), and the percentage of non-specific binding, which ranged from 2.11 to 2.98% ( n  = 21). The minimal detection limit was 27.0 pg/ml. Inter-assay samples (pooled from blood plasma of multiple species) were included in each of the plasma CORT assays to calibrate measured CORT levels and to monitor variation among assays. Inter-assay variance (average variation among assays) was 6.28% and intra-assay variance (average variation between duplicates) 9.15%.  Classification of foraging guild and taxa of migratory landbird species at our study sites  Abbreviations: FGG, foliage-gleaning guild; FLY, flycatchers; GFG, ground-foraging guild; SPA, sparrows; THR, thrushes; VIR, vireos.  To adjust for individual differences in body size, we used principal component analysis to incorporate structural measurements (wing chord and tarsus length) to produce a principal component (PC1) for each individual species describing body size ( Pedhazur, 1997 ;  Guglielmo  et al. , 2005 ). We used a backward stepwise multiple regression approach to generate predictors with CORT B , CORT 30  or the magnitude of the stress response as the dependent variable. Independent variables in the model included the principal component for body size, fat score (the average of furcular and abdominal fat scores), age (autumn only), season (foraging guilds only), capture time, capture date and year, with variables retained in the model at  P  &lt; 0.10. The variables retained after multiple regressions were maintained as covariates in an analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) to test for differences between birds from corridors and woodlots. We applied ANCOVA (for CORT B  and CORT 30 ) or repeated-measures ANCOVA (for the magnitude of the stress response) to test for differences between habitat types and ages (autumn only) in both spring and autumn. If no covariates were generated by multiple regressions, we used analysis of variance (ANOVA; for CORT B  and CORT 30 ) or repeated-measures ANOVA (for the magnitude of the stress response) to test for differences between birds from corridors and woodlots. Repeated-measures ANOVA or ANCOVA also allowed us to test whether CORT B  and CORT 30  differed significantly for all species, taxa and foraging guilds.  To control for possible individual species effects on plasma CORT levels in analyses of foraging guilds and taxa, we included species and habitat type as categorical independent variables, along with the species × habitat type interaction term, in the general linear model ANCOVA. The rationale behind this correction for species effects is that different species may show varying raw plasma CORT concentrations, so significant biases could exist in pooled species comparisons if species are combined without controlling for species differences. For individual species with sample sizes ≥10 in both corridors and woodlots, we also applied unpaired Student's  t -tests to compare fat scores.  Finally, for correlation analyses between CORT (CORT B , magnitude of the stress response) and plasma metabolites (TRIG and BUTY) and between CORT B  and the magnitude of the stress response, we normalized data for individual birds to species averages (for species with  n  ≥ 10), so that we could pool data from individual birds in our comparisons. To normalize the CORT and plasma metabolite data for each individual bird, the individual values for CORT B , the magnitude of the stress response and plasma TRIG and BUTY levels were divided by the mean value for that species. These normalized data from individual birds were then used for correlation analyses of CORT B  and the magnitude of the stress response against TRIG and BUTY concentrations and of the magnitude of the stress response against CORT B .  No species showed significant between-habitat differences in fat scores, although the difference in fat scores for yellow-rumped warblers ( Setophaga coronata ) in autumn approached significance ( F  1,51  = 6.37,  P  = 0.08), with greater fat scores from corridors than from woodlots. We obtained sufficient sample sizes for comparisons between juveniles and adults only for warbling vireos ( Vireo gilvus ) and dark-eyed juncos ( Junco hyemalis ) in autumn, and fat scores were not statistically different between ages for these species.  Mean (±SEM) baseline corticosterone (CORT B , in nanograms per millilitre) for spring and autumn individual species, taxa and foraging guilds. Abbreviations are as in Tables 1 and 2.  Mean (±SEM) magnitude of the stress response (CORT 30  − CORT B , in nanograms per millilitre) for spring and autumn individual species, taxa and foraging guilds. Abbreviations are as in Tables  1  and  2 .  We found no significant species effects for between-habitat comparisons for either foraging guilds or taxa in spring. In autumn, a significant species effect occurred for CORT B  only for the sparrow group ( F  5,50  = 3.32,  P  = 0.01) and for the magnitude of the stress response only for the foliage-gleaning guild ( F  5,60  = 3.21,  P  = 0.02). A significant species effect indicates a strong influence of particular species on plasma CORT values for the taxon or foraging group as a whole. After between-habitat comparisons were adjusted statistically for these significant species effects, between-habitat comparisons of CORT B , CORT 30  and the magnitude of the stress response remained non-significant for these bird groups. The interaction between species and habitat type for comparisons of plasma CORT was not significant for any foraging guild or taxon in either season.  Variables retained in backward stepwise multiple regression models for plasma corticosterone at the  P  &lt; 0.10 level for individual species, taxa and foraging guilds  Positive or negative symbols indicate direction of effect. ‘None’ means that no covariate showed significant effects on plasma corticosterone levels. Abbreviations are as in Table  1 , plus the following: D, capture date; F, fat score; PC, principal component for body size; REVI, red-eyed vireo,  Vireo olivaceus ; SWTH, Swainson's thrush,  Catharus ustulatus ; T, capture time; TRFL, complex of  Empidonax alnorum  and  Empidonax traillii ; WAVI, warbling vireo,  Vireo gilvus ; Y, year.  Relationship of baseline corticosterone (CORT B ) and the magnitude of the stress response (CORT 30  − CORT B ) with plasma triglycerides (TRIG). The dashed line represents autumn migrants and the continuous line spring migrants. The CORT B  showed a significant negative correlation with TRIG in both seasons [spring, CORT B  = 0.44 − 0.62(TRIG); and autumn, CORT B  = 0.53 − 0.73(TRIG)]. The magnitude of the stress response showed a significant positive correlation with TRIG in both seasons [spring, CORT 30  − CORT B  = 0.18 + 0.54(TRIG); and autumn, CORT 30  − CORT B  = 0.17 + 0.46(TRIG)].  Relationship between baseline corticosterone (CORT B ) and the magnitude of the stress response (CORT 30  − CORT B ). The dashed line represents autumn migrants and the continuous line spring migrants. Significant negative correlations occurred between these variables in both seasons [spring, CORT 30  − CORT B  = 0.46 − 0.09(CORT B ); and autumn, CORT 30  − CORT B  = 0.42 − 0.11(CORT B )].  Anthropogenic woodlots might be expected to provide less favourable stopover habitats for landbird migrants than natural riparian corridor woodlands because of their smaller size, increased isolation, increased edge and lower vegetative diversity ( Castonguay, 1982 ;  Swanson  et al. , 2003 ;  Gentry  et al. , 2006 ). As a consequence of these differences, migrants stopping over in woodlots could be exposed to different levels of food availability, competition intensity, predation pressure and thermal microclimates than migrants stopping over in corridors, and these factors might lead to differences in stress physiology for birds in woodlots and corridors ( Clinchy  et al. , 2004 ;  Kitaysky  et al. , 2007 ;  Olson and Grubb, 2007 ;  Olson  et al. , 2010 ;  Braasch  et al. , 2014 ). In the present study, however, we found no significant differences for any CORT variables (CORT B , CORT 30  or the magnitude of the stress response) between birds captured in corridors and woodlots, suggesting that the stress physiology of migrant birds in both corridors and woodlots is generally similar. In addition, all individual species, taxa and foraging guilds from both spring and autumn migration showed a significant stress response after a 30 min restraint stress, which suggests that birds were in sufficient body condition in both woodland habitats to mount a robust stress response (i.e. a significant increase in plasma CORT with restraint stress). These data suggest that the increased reliance of migrating birds on anthropogenic woodlands with the loss and degradation of natural riparian corridor habitats in the Northern Prairie region, where woodland habitat is scarce, does not negatively impact their stress physiology. This result is consistent with the finding of similar refuelling rates and body condition between birds in the two habitat types at these same study sites ( Liu and Swanson, 2014 ). Collectively, these data suggest similar habitat quality in the two habitat types and support the idea that anthropogenic woodlot habitats can, at least partly, substitute for lost and degraded riparian corridor woodlands as stopover habitat for migrant birds in the Northern Prairie region of North America.  Among the covariates influencing plasma CORT levels in our study, sampling year significantly affected CORT B  for several bird groups in autumn, and CORT B  levels were higher in 2011 than in 2010 for all of these groups. This result suggests that ecological or environmental conditions (e.g. food availability, predation pressure, intensity of competition, weather) may vary among years at our study sites in a manner that influences stress physiology of migrants. Defining which, if any, of these factors might be associated with the elevated CORT B  levels in 2011 relative to 2010 will require further study, but two factors potentially related to this pattern bear mentioning. First, a large and prolonged flood impacted the Missouri River throughout the summer and early autumn of 2011 ( Munes, 2014 ). In addition, autumn 2011 was considerably drier than autumn 2010 near Vermillion, Clay County, southeastern South Dakota, with precipitation in September and October of 2011 only 39% of that during the same months in 2010 (US Climate data,  http://www.usclimatedata.com/ ).  Liu and Swanson (2014)  detected lower plasma TRIG levels in autumn 2011 than in autumn 2010 for several migrant bird groups at these same study sites, suggesting that conditions in autumn 2011 resulted in lower refuelling rates than in autumn 2010, which is consistent with relatively lower quality stopover habitat resulting in elevated CORT B  levels in autumn 2011.  Body size may also be related to plasma CORT B  levels in birds, with smaller birds exhibiting higher baseline levels than larger birds ( Lehnen and Krementz, 2005 ). In the present study, the principal component describing body size had a significant effect on plasma CORT levels for only a few bird groups. The general absence of an effect of body size on plasma CORT in migrating birds is consistent with the findings of  Thomas (2008) , who documented that the body size of migrating shorebirds did not influence the overall CORT response. However, for those bird groups in our study where body size was significantly related to plasma CORT levels (ground-foraging guild in spring and foliage-gleaning guild and vireos in autumn), body size was negatively related to CORT B  and positively related to the magnitude of the stress response. This result is consistent with the relationship documented by  Lehnen and Krementz (2005)  and suggests that larger birds are in better condition than and/or outcompete smaller individuals for resources in these bird groups. We have no obvious explanation for why such a relationship occurs for only some bird groups and not for others, but perhaps differential use of or access to resources is involved.  Hatch-year migrants are undertaking their first migration in autumn, so they are less experienced foragers than adults, which could result in lower refuelling rates, although age-related differences in body condition and refuelling rates are seldom detected at stopover sites (e.g.  Seewagen  et al. , 2013 ;  Liu and Swanson, 2014 ). Moreover, juvenile migrants are usually socially subordinate to adults, which may restrict the former's access to limited resources due to competitive interactions with experienced adults ( Yong  et al. , 1998 ;  Heise and Moore, 2003 ;  Moore  et al. , 2003 ;  Faaborg  et al. , 2010 ). As a consequence, the stress response may differ between age classes, with higher CORT B  and a lower stress response in juveniles than in adults. In the present study, we did not detect significant differences in CORT B , CORT 30  or the magnitude of the stress response between adults and juveniles. This is similar to the results of  Thomas (2008) , who found little difference in plasma CORT levels between adult and juvenile least ( Calidris minutilla ) and semipalmated sandpipers ( Calidris pusilla ). This suggests that ecological and environmental conditions at our stopover sites provided effective stopover habitat for both adults and juvenile birds such that age-related differences in stress physiology were not evident.  We obtained sufficient samples sizes for between-season comparisons only for foliage-gleaning and ground-foraging guilds and found that both groups had higher CORT B  and a greater magnitude of the stress response in the spring compared with autumn migration. Spring migration is potentially more urgent than autumn, because early arrival on the breeding grounds generally shows a positive correlation with fitness (e.g.  Smith and Moore, 2005 ;  Cooper  et al. , 2011 ;  Gargallo  et al. , 2011 ;  Gienapp and Bregnballe, 2012 ). Spring migrants typically migrate at a faster pace than autumn migrants ( Pearson and Lack, 1992 ;  Ellegren, 1993 ;  Fransson, 1995 ;  Kemp  et al. , 2010 ), which may reflect differences in their physiological capacities ( Swanson, 1995 ;  Swanson and Dean, 1999 ). These differences might result in higher CORT B  in spring than in autumn migrants and promote greater foraging intensity and better refuelling performance than for birds during the more leisurely autumn migration. Such an explanation is consistent with our previous study suggesting better refuelling performance in spring migrants than in autumn migrants at these same study sites ( Liu and Swanson, 2014 ).  The migration modulation hypothesis proposes that migrants maintain elevated CORT B  levels during migration and show a suppressed stress response when faced with additional acute stressors ( Holberton  et al. , 1996 ), thereby facilitating fattening while sparing muscle protein. Consistent with this hypothesis, elevated CORT B  levels, a suppressed stress response, or both, occur in a number of wild migrant or photostimulated, migratory-ready captive birds ( Holberton  et al. , 1996 ,  2007 ;  Piersma  et al. , 2000 ;  Landys-Ciannelli  et al. , 2002 ;  Long and Holberton, 2004 ). However, numerous studies also document significant stress responses in wild migrant or photostimulated captive birds ( Romero  et al. , 1997 ;  Piersma  et al. , 2000 ;  Landys-Ciannelli  et al. , 2002 ;  Falsone  et al. , 2009 ;  Nilsson and Sandell, 2009 ), suggesting that full suppression of the stress response does not occur in most migrants or that the degree of suppression changes with the stage of migratory stopover. However, the magnitude of the stress response in these birds may sometimes be influenced by body condition ( Mizrahi  et al. , 2001 ;  Jenni-Eiermann  et al. , 2009 ;  Raja-aho  et al. , 2010 ), so energetic condition could influence the modulation of the stress response during migration. A corollary prediction of the migration modulation hypothesis is that CORT B  and the magnitude of the stress response should be inversely related, even if the stress response is not fully suppressed. The suppressed stress response when facing additional acute stressors might result from negative feedback of elevated CORT B  during migration ( Raja-aho  et al. , 2010 ). In the present study, we found a significant negative relationship between CORT B  and the magnitude of the stress response, despite robust stress responses for all bird groups studied, which is consistent with this corollary prediction of the migration modulation hypothesis.  High plasma CORT concentrations may promote elevated levels of gluconeogenesis and lipogenesis, leading to fat deposition, while also stimulating protein catabolism ( Holmes and Phillips, 1976 ;  Berdanier, 1989 ; but see  Eikenaar  et al. , 2013 ,  2014 ). Plasma levels of TRIG and BUTY are considered the best metabolites for plasma metabolite profiling in birds ( Guglielmo  et al. , 2002 ,  2005 ;  Smith and McWilliams, 2010 ;  Seewagen  et al. , 2011 ) and they are now routinely used to measure fattening rates of birds during migration because plasma TRIG increases during fat deposition and plasma BUTY increases during fat catabolism ( Schaub and Jenni, 2001 ;  Seaman  et al. , 2005 ;  Cerasale and Guglielmo, 2006 ,  2010 ). We found a significant negative correlation of CORT B  and a significant positive correlation of the magnitude of the stress response with plasma TRIG for birds in the present study. Plasma BUTY showed significant opposite patterns of correlations with CORT B  and the magnitude of the stress response in comparison to plasma TRIG. These data support our hypotheses that high-quality habitat promotes effective fattening and reduced CORT B , while allowing a robust stress response.  Furthermore, CORT measures can potentially provide additional information regarding the relationships among the stress response, fattening, body condition and stopover biology in migrants. Plasma CORT shows a U-shaped relationship with fat stores in shorebirds ( Piersma  et al. , 2000 ), and  Eikenaar  et al.  (2013)  found a positive correlation between plasma CORT and fat stores before departure for a passerine bird, the northern wheatear ( Oenanthe oenanthe ). If landbird migrants also show a U-shaped relationship between plasma CORT and fat stores during stopover, but a linear relationship with plasma metabolites (present study), analyses including CORT, plasma metabolites and fat stores might allow teasing apart of the effects of different stopover durations prior to capture on plasma metabolite comparisons. The U-shaped relationship between plasma CORT B  with stopover duration in shorebirds ( Piersma  et al. , 2000 ) suggests that migrants have high CORT B  levels upon arrival at a stopover site and then show a decline as their body condition improves, only to increase CORT again before departure, when fat stores are high (e.g.  Eikenaar  et al. , 2013 ). Such a pattern might be driven by differential sensitivity of receptors to CORT at different CORT levels or by regulation of the hypothalamo–pituitary–adrenal axis at the brain level (e.g.  de Kloet  et al. , 1999 ;  Matthews, 2002 ;  Sapolsky, 2002 ). As a consequence, migrating birds may show considerable variation in the relationship between CORT B  and fat stores. Indeed, negative relationships ( Long and Holberton, 2004 ;  Raja-aho  et al. , 2010 ), positive relationships ( Romero  et al. , 1997 ;  Holberton, 1999 ,  Landys-Ciannelli  et al. , 2002 ;  Landys  et al. , 2004 ;  Eikenaar  et al. , 2013 ) and no relationship ( Holberton  et al. , 1996 ;  Mizrahi  et al. , 2001 ) between CORT B  and fat stores or energetic condition have been documented among migratory birds. We found no significant relationships between fat scores and CORT B  for any individual species, taxon or foraging guild during spring migration. During autumn migration, fat score was a significant covariate in multiple regression models for several bird groups and showed a consistent positive relationship with CORT B  and negative relationship with the magnitude of the stress response in these groups. One possible explanation for these results is that fat birds within these groups were ready to migrate, and elevated CORT B  levels and a smaller stress response prior to departure served to prepare them for upcoming behavioural and metabolic transitions during migratory flights, similar to the suggestion of  Piersma  et al.  (2000)  for shorebirds and  Eikenaar  et al.  (2013)  for northern wheatears. Tracking these variables concurrently during stopover might allow more precise estimation of the stage of migratory stopover from a single blood sample than has been possible to date. However, validation of the potential for this method will require much additional research and larger sample sizes for individual species than those in the present study.   Supplementary material is available at  Conservation Physiology  online.   This study was funded by grants from the US Fish and Wildlife Service (Award Number F10AC00572), University of South Dakota and South Dakota Ornithologists' Union (Nathaniel R. Whitney Jr. Memorial Research Grant).  We thank Eric Dressing, Michael Moxnes, Marisa King, Yufeng Zhang, Zach Orr and Caitlin Crandall for assistance in the field. We thank Kathy Beard, John Davidson and Ken Renner for access to woodlots during our study and Michael Watt, Gina Forster and Jamie Scholl for assistance with the CORT assays. Finally, we thank Marisa King and two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on an earlier version of this manuscript. 