Vegetative growth and cluster development in Shiraz grapevines subjected to partial root-zone coolingA study of the differentiation and the development of floral parts in grapes (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.)Water and solute fluxes through pruned Muscadine grape spursDiurnal and temporal changes in the chemical profile of xylem exudate from <italic>Vitis rotundifolia</italic>Temperature and temperature preconditioning on flux and chemical composition of xylem exudate from Muscadine grapevinesEffects of partial root-zone drying on yield, ripening and berry ABA in potted Tempranillo grapevines with split rootsEffect of root-growing temperature on growth substances in xylem exudate of <italic>Zea mays</italic>pH-regulated leaf cell expansion in droughted plants is abscisic acid-dependentTemperature-dependent water and ion transport properties of barley and sorghum roots. I. Relationship to leaf growthInfluence of plant water status on the production of C<sub>13</sub>-norisoprenoid precursors in <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. cv. Cabernet Sauvignon grape berriesInfluence of partial rootzone drying on the composition and accumulation of anthocyanins in grape berries (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Cabernet Sauvignon)Variation in vine vigour, grape yield and vineyard soils and topography as indicators of variation in the chemical composition of grapes, wine and wine sensory attributesEffects of soil temperature on parameters of a coupled photosynthesis–stomatal conductance modelSeasonal variation in pH, carbohydrate and nitrogen of xylem exudation of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>Retranslocation of carbon reserves from the woody storage tissues into the fruit as a response to defoliation stress during the ripening period in <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> LEffects of girdling and leaf removal on fruit set and vegetative growth in grapeTemperature effects on hydraulic conductance and water relations of <italic>Quercus robur</italic> LAcceleration of global warming due to carbon-cycle feedbacks in a coupled climate modelClimate change and the flowering time of annual cropsEffects of partial root-zone drying on grapevine vigour, yield composition of fruit and use of waterPartial drying of the rootzone of grape. I. Transient changes in shoot growth and gas exchangePhaenologische Entwicklungstadiender RebeRoot growth and carbohydrate responses in bearing citrus trees following partial canopy removalCytokinin-gibberellin regulation of shoot development and leaf form in tobacco plantletsEffect of elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, temperature and drought on photosynthesis of nodulated alfalfa during a cutting regrowth cycleGrapevine response to soil temperature: xylem cytokinins and carbohydrate reserve mobilization from budbreak to anthesisRelation of applied crop stress to inflorescence development, shoot growth characteristics and cane starch reserves in ‘Concord’ grapevineMulti-scale phenotyping of leaf expansion in response to environmental changes: the whole is more than the sum of partsEffects of fruiting on vegetative growth and development dynamics of grapevines (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Semillon) can be traced back to events at or before budbreakRoot-zone temperatures affect phenology of bud break, flower cluster development, shoot extension growth and gas exchange of ‘Braeburn’ (<italic>Malus domestica</italic>) apple treesReductions in biomass accumulation, photosynthesis <italic>in situ</italic> and net carbon balance are the costs of protecting <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> ‘Semillon’ grapevines from heat stress with shade coveringCarbohydrate allocationUsing soil surface temperature to assess soil evaporation in a drip irrigated vineyardEffect of root temperature on budbreak, shoot growth and fruit-set of ‘Cabernet Sauvignon’ grapevinesSugars and flowering in the grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.)Role of abscisic acid in chilling tolerance of rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) seedlings. I. Endogenous abscisic acid levelsRoot hydraulic conductivity of two cactus species in relation to root age, temperature, and soil water statusInteraction between potassium concentration and root-zone temperature on growth and photosynthesis of temperate lettuce grown in the tropicsReducing inflorescence formation by shading individual Sultana budsOptimal leaf size in relation to environmentResponses of tree fine roots to temperatureOvary starch reserves and flower development in apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic>)Nocturnal and daytime stomatal conductance respond to root-zone temperature in ‘Shiraz’ grapevinesSoil temperature moderates grapevine carbohydrate reserves after bud-break and conditions fruit set responses to photoassimilatory stressDistribution of gibberellins in <italic>Lathyrus odoratus</italic> L. and their role in leaf growthPartial rootzone drying: effects on growth and fruit quality of field-grown grapevines (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>)The rise of sap in tall grapevinesAn empirical model for the simulation of leaf appearance and leaf area development of primary shoots of several grapevine (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L.) canopy-systemsThe effects of air and root temperatures on the development of flower clusters on forced lateral shoots of Muscat of Alexandria grapevinesEffect of root temperature on cytokinin activity in root exudate of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> LCumulative responses of Semillon grapevines to late season perturbation of carbohydrate reserve statusFlower bud formation in the Concord grapePartial rootzone drying: regulation of stomatal aperture and carbon assimilation in field-grown grapevines (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cv. Moscatel)Spring filling of xylem vessels in wild grapevinePhysiology of flowering in the grapevine—a reviewHormonal changes induced by partial rootzone drying of irrigated grapevineCytokinin concentrations in roots and root xylem exudate of cucumber and figleaf gourd as affected by root temperatureThe New Zealand Terroir: Sources of variation in fruit composition in New Zealand vineyardsRoot water flow and growth of aspen (<italic>Populus tremuloides</italic>) at low root temperaturesHydraulic conductance in aspen (<italic>Populus tremuloides</italic>) seedlings exposed to low root temperaturesStomatal conductance and xylem sap properties of aspen (<italic>Populus tremuloides</italic>) in response to low soil temperatureCytokinin-deficient transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants show multiple developmental alterations indicating opposite functions of cytokinins in the regulation of shoot and root meristem activityFruit bud and flower formation in the Sultanina grapeThe effect of root temperature on development of small fruiting sultana vinesStudies on retranslocation of accumulated assimilates in ‘Delaware’ grapevines. I. Retranslocation of C-assimilates in the following spring after <sup>14</sup>C feeding in summer and autumnStudies on retranslocation of accumulated assimilates in ‘Delaware’ grapevines. II. Retranslocation of assimilates accumulated during the previous growing seasonInfluence of root temperature and rootstock on budbreak, shoot growth, and fruit composition of Cabernet Sauvignon grapevines grown under controlled conditionsEffect of root temperature, rootstock and fertilization on bud-break, shoot growth and composition of ‘Cabernet Sauvignon’ grapevinesEffects of root temperature on leaf gas exchange and xylem sap abscisic acid concentrations in six Cucurbitaceae speciesChill-induced decrease in capacity of RuBP carboxylation and associated H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> accumulation in cucumber leaves are alleviated by grafting onto figleaf gourdThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Grapevine roots can be exposed to a range of temperatures at any particular moment because the root system can explore large volumes of soil over great depths and distances. A split-pot experiment was designed to assess how vegetative and reproductive development respond to partial and whole root-zone warming following winter dormancy. Simultaneous cooling and warming of parts of the root system slowed shoot elongation, leaf expansion and berry development compared to plants with a fully warmed root-zone, but not to the same extent as those with a fully cooled root-zone.Heterogeneity in root-zone temperature both vertically and horizontally may contribute to the uneven vegetative and reproductive growth often observed across vineyards. An experiment was designed to assess whether the warmed half of a grapevine root zone could compensate for the cooled half in terms of vegetative growth and reproductive development. We divided the root system of potted Shiraz grapevines bilaterally and applied either a cool or a warm treatment to each half from budburst to fruit set. Shoot growth and inflorescence development were monitored over the season. Simultaneous cooling and warming of parts of the root system decreased shoot elongation, leaf emergence and leaf expansion below that of plants with a fully warmed root zone, but not to the same extent as those with a fully cooled root zone. Inflorescence rachis length, flower number and berry number after fertilization were smaller only in those vines exposed to fully cooled root zones. After terminating the treatments, berry enlargement and the onset of veraison were slowed in those vines that had been exposed to complete or partial root-zone cooling. Grapevines exposed to partial root-zone cooling were thus delayed in vegetative and reproductive development, but the inhibition was greater in those plants whose entire root system had been cooled.Plant roots can be exposed to a range of temperatures because root systems can explore large volumes of soil over great depths and distances. The temperature of this soil is dependent on its depth below the surface, composition and moisture, as well as the degree of exposure to sun and wind in relation to aspect, slope and barriers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C32">Kerridge <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). In grapevines, non-uniform irrigation and heterogeneous soil type across a vineyard lead to inconsistent vegetative growth, yield and berry composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C57">Trought 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C11">Bramley <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Simultaneous cool and warm root-zone microclimates may be an additional source of this variability.Springtime soil temperatures are important to grapevine canopy development following dormancy because the preliminary stages of growth are dependent on carbohydrate mobilization from the roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C64">Yang and Hori 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C65">Yang <italic>et al</italic>. 1980</xref>). Cool root zones following winter dormancy in perennial crops can delay carbohydrate reserve mobilization, effectively slowing shoot growth and inflorescence development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C29">Greer <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C25">Field <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C43">Rogiers <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Once leaves become net exporters of carbon, cool root zones can also have a direct effect on vegetative and reproductive growth by lowering net assimilation rates. This is a consequence of either alterations in photosynthetic reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C12">Cai and Dang 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C24">Erice <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>) or decreased stomatal conductance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C58">Wan <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C60">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C42">Rogiers and Clarke 2013</xref>). A reduction in fruit set (the proportion of flowers that become berries) is a common result of this lowered net assimilation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C14">Candolfi-Vasconcelos <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C15">Caspari <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C34">Lebon <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C43">Rogiers <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>).Split-root studies have been used in grapevines to examine the effects of partial root-zone drying (PRD) on grapevine physiology and fruit composition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C20">Dry <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C45">Santos <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C52">Souza <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C5">Antolín <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>). In PRD, the opposing halves of the root zone are alternately exposed to wet and dry cycles by applying or withholding irrigation. This irrigation system decreases vegetative vigour while maintaining plant water status and improves leaf and whole-plant water-use efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C19">Dry <italic>et al</italic>. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C55">Stoll <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>). Partial root-zone drying can advance berry ripening through decreased competition with vegetative growth, increased light penetration into the fruiting zone and modified vine signalling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C45">Santos <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C5">Antolín <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C9">Bindon <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C10">2008</xref>). Because whole root-zone cooling can limit leaf expansion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C42">Rogiers and Clarke 2013</xref>), partial root-zone cooling, comparable with PRD, may result in a similar inhibition of vegetative growth with repercussions on reproductive development.The relative proportions of plant signals or growth regulators such as abscisic acid, cytokinins or gibberellins released by cooled and warmed roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C6">Atkin <italic>et al</italic>. 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C68">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C25">Field <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>) and perceived by expanding buds probably affect shoot and leaf development. However, the delayed vegetative growth that results from roots exposed to cool soil may be overcome by those parts of the root system growing in a warmer segment of the soil. The warmed portion of the root system could, for instance, produce enough signal to drive cell division and expansion so that vegetative growth is equivalent to that of fully warmed roots. Alternatively, growth may be directly proportional to the volume of roots that is exposed to the warm soil. Nutrient and water uptake by plants as well as root carbohydrate mobilization might be reduced when half of the root system is exposed to cool soil and this could result in an intermediate amount of shoot growth. Using a split-pot method, we examined grapevine response to root zones 5 °C above and below the average vineyard soil temperature found at a depth of 15 cm in a warm grape-growing region of Australia. The objective of this work was to clarify how vegetative growth and reproductive development respond to partial root-zone cooling.Timeline of treatment applications and major phenological events.Thermocouples (TT-T-36, Omega Engineering, Northmead, NSW, Australia) were inserted into the centre of the root mass in both halves of one pot and logged at 30-min intervals (CR1000, Campbell Scientific, Townsville, Australia). In addition, manual measurements were carried out to a 15-cm depth twice weekly with a hand-held thermometer. Soil temperature averaged 17.7/17.8 °C for the c/c, 18.0/28.0 °C for the c/w and 28.4/29.6 °C for the w/w treatment. Soil moisture was measured twice weekly on both halves with an ML2x Theta Probe (Delta-T Devices, Cambridge, UK) inserted to a depth of 15 cm. Soil moisture averaged 21/19 % for the c/c, 20/17 % for the c/w and 18/19 % for the w/w treatment. A weather station was placed at canopy height within the trial. It was equipped with an air temperature probe (Intercap HMP50, Vaisala, Hawthorn, VIC, Australia) logging at half-hourly intervals and recorded an average minimum of 10.3 °C and a maximum of 28.5 °C over the duration of the experiment. A quantum sensor (Apogee, SQ-110, Logan, UT, USA), also logging at half hourly intervals, recorded an average daily maximum photosynthetically active radiation of 1200 µmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>. Thermocouples were placed at cluster height, 30–40 cm above the soil surface, and air temperature during the treatment period averaged 20.6 ± 0.2 °C and 20.7 ± 0.3 °C above the cool and warm soil, respectively.Leaf length was measured weekly on each leaf opposite the basal tendril in the three-node repeating leaf/tendril arrangement. Root-zone temperature did not affect the relationship between leaf length and area, and therefore, leaf area was calculated from leaf length using an allometric relationship obtained from leaves destructively harvested from adjacent vines of the same variety and grown over the same period under the same ambient conditions. Area of these leaves was measured using a leaf area meter (LI-3000; Li-Cor, Lincoln, NE, USA) and the following calculation was applied: area (in cm<sup>2</sup>) = 0.00748 × length<sup>2</sup> (in mm) + 0.294 × length<sup>2</sup> (in mm) − 5.86. A leaf was registered as emerged on the day it reached a length of 30 mm, calculated by linear interpolation between leaf length measurements across time points. Shoot length was also measured weekly with a flexible measuring tape from the spur junction to the shoot apex. Nylon mesh bags were placed over each inflorescence just prior to anthesis and percentage fruit set was calculated by counting flower caps and aborted flowers. Berry diameter was measured with digital callipers on eight berries per cluster for all clusters. Veraison was assessed visually as first signs of colour change.An analysis of variance (GenStat release 15.0, VSN, Hertfordshire, UK) was used for comparison of treatment effects during the root-zone temperature treatments and least significant differences (LSDs) were calculated at 5 % significance. Results of the statistical analyses are presented in the tables and figures. Values presented in the text are means ± s.e.Root-zone temperature profiles of a Shiraz grapevine grown in a split pot. Half of the roots were exposed to a warm temperature while the other half were exposed to a cool temperature treatment for 63 days. Beyond this day, the root-zone temperature was not controlled.Shoot growth of Shiraz vines grown in split pots and exposed to cool/cool, cool/warm or warm/warm root-zone temperatures (mean ± s.e.). The treatments were applied from budburst to fruit set. Arrow indicates when treatments were terminated. The main factors of treatment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and day (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) were significant. Exponential curves were fitted to the data.Leaf emergence of Shiraz vines grown in split pots and exposed to cool/cool, cool/warm or warm/warm root-zone temperatures (mean ± s.e.). The treatments were applied from budburst to fruit set. The main factors of treatment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and day (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) were significant during the treatment period. After the termination of the treatments only day (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) was statistically significant.Average leaf size of Shiraz grapevines grown in split pots and exposed to cool/cool, cool/warm or warm/warm root-zone temperatures (mean ± s.e.). Included in the averages are immature and fully expanded leaves. The treatments were applied from budburst to fruit set. Arrow indicates when treatments were terminated. The main factors of treatment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and day (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) were significant. Linear curves were fitted to the data.Fully expanded leaf size at nodes 4–15 for shoots of Shiraz grapevines grown in split pots and exposed to cool/cool, cool/warm or warm/warm root-zone temperatures (mean ± s.e.). The treatments were applied from budburst to fruit set. Treatment was significant at nodes 7–9 and nodes 13–15 (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).Plant leaf area as a function of root-zone temperature. The treatments were applied over a 63-day period from budburst to fruit set. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Onset of flowering expressed as percentage capfall from Shiraz inflorescences grown in split pots and exposed to cool/cool, cool/warm or warm/warm root-zone temperatures (mean ± s.e.). The treatments were applied from budburst to fruit set. The main factors of treatment (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and day (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) were significant. Sigmoidal curves were fitted to the data.Effect of root-zone temperature on mean inflorescence flower number and percentage fruit set. Shiraz vines were exposed to cool/cool, cool/warm or warm/warm root-zone temperatures from budburst to fruit set in the concurrent season. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Percentage of berries per cluster that had reached veraison 118 and 123 days after the initiation of treatments. Shiraz vines were grown in split pots and exposed to cool/cool, cool/warm or warm/warm root-zone temperatures from budburst to fruit set. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Berry diameter as a function of root-zone temperature. The treatments were applied over a 63-day period from budburst to fruit set and the berry diameter assessments were carried out 15 and 60 days after the treatments were terminated. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Effect of root-zone temperature on mean rachis fresh weight, developed and undeveloped berry number. Shiraz vines were exposed to cool/cool, cool/warm or warm/warm root-zone temperatures from budburst to fruit set in the concurrent season. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Root-zone temperature has a key role in grapevine vegetative growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C63">Woodham and Alexander 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C49">Skene and Kerridge 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C66">Zelleke and Kliewer 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C67">1980</xref>). In our study, partially cooled root zones inhibited shoot growth but not to the same extent as fully cooled root zones. When grapevines are released from winter dormancy, the xylem delivers water, carbohydrates, nutrients, hormones and other plant signals to the buds to drive shoot elongation and leaf expansion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C2">Andersen and Brodbeck 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C3">1989<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C13">Campbell and Strother 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C25">Field <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Initially xylem sap is transported by the pressure created through the establishment of an osmotic gradient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C46">Scholander <italic>et al</italic>. 1955</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C53">Sperry <italic>et al</italic>. 1987</xref>). Root pressure is temperature dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C4">Andersen and Brodbeck 1989<italic>b</italic></xref>) and the delivery rate of growth regulators and other metabolites to the shoots can thus be slowed if half of the root zone is cooled, consequently decreasing rates of shoot growth and development. Similarly, as leaves mature and stomata become functional, shoots of plants in a partially warmed root zone would be exposed to less root-derived signal than a fully warmed root zone due to lower leaf transpiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C60">Wan <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C42">Rogiers and Clarke 2013</xref>). Furthermore, the synthesis of signals in the cooled root zone may be slowed due to lower rates of temperature-dependent reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C17">Cox <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>) so that the concentration that the shoot receives is less than in a fully warmed root zone. Shoot elongation is stimulated by cytokinins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C61">Werner <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>) and it has been shown that warm soil can increase nucleotide cytokinin concentration in bleeding sap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C25">Field <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Similar to grapevines exposed to PRD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C20">Dry <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>), a partial inhibition of shoot elongation under partial root-zone cooling may be a direct effect of decreased cytokinin levels. Gibberellins are also important for shoot elongation and appear to decline in xylem exudate as root temperature declines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C6">Atkin <italic>et al</italic>. 1973</xref>).Along with shoot elongation, the rate of leaf emergence and average leaf size were reduced when vines were subjected to partially or fully cooled root zones. While the size of fully expanded leaves located on nodes 4–6 was not altered by the treatments, leaves from nodes 7–9 were largest in vines that had received the fully warmed treatment, with intermediate sizes in the partially warmed root-zone treatments. Even though the first 12 or so grapevine leaves are preformed in the bud and leaf size is ontogenetically predetermined to some extent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C39">Parkhurst and Loucks 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C28">Greer and Weston 2010</xref>), final leaf size is particularly sensitive to stresses imposed early in leaf development, during the cell proliferation and expansion phases. These stresses reduce final leaf size by reducing the rate of leaf expansion and/or the duration over which expansion occurs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C27">Granier and Tardieu 2009</xref>). Because full root-zone cooling inhibited the expansion of leaves at nodes 7–9 more so than partial root-zone cooling, it is possible that plant signals such as abscisic acid, an inhibitor of leaf expansion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C7">Bacon <italic>et al</italic>. 1998</xref>), occurred at higher concentrations in leaves when roots were fully cooled. Conversely, promoters of leaf expansion such as gibberellins and cytokinins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C23">Engelke <italic>et al</italic>. 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C44">Ross <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>) may have been synthesized in the roots of the warmed half of the c/w treatment but not in the roots of the fully cooled treatment.Carbon stress can be induced by exposing roots to cool temperatures. This is because inhibited root carbohydrate mobilization can result in low energy and structural carbon availability for expanding leaves. The roots are the major storage site of starch in grapevines and mobilization is highly dependent on the temperature of the soil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C25">Field <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C43">Rogiers <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Semillon grapevines rely on carbohydrate reserves for canopy development over the first 6 weeks after budburst (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C30">Greer <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>). Because leaf expansion was lower in fully cooled root zones than in those that were partially cooled, perhaps minimal root carbohydrate degradation had occurred in this treatment. It is also probable that root-zone cooling decreased water uptake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C8">BassiriRad <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>) by decreasing hydraulic conductance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C36">Lopez and Nobel 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C16">Cochard <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C59">Wan <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>) or inhibited root uptake of ions such as K<sup>+</sup> and their accumulation within leaf cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C37">Luo <italic>et al</italic>. 2012</xref>), thereby decreasing the osmotic gradient that drives water into the cell.Unlike those leaves from nodes 7–9, leaves located on nodes 10–12 were not different in size. Across the experiment, nodes 10–12 represent a mixed cohort, consisting of leaves formed before and after the treatment period. The relatively large size of the leaves located at nodes 13–15 of the pre-cooled plants indicates that the stress that constrained leaf size was eliminated with the termination of the treatments and some mechanism has promoted the formation of relatively large leaves. This observation also indicates that typical ontogenetic trends in leaf size on grapevine shoots (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C47">Schultz 1992</xref>) may be perturbed when the spring soil temperatures are depressed. The unusually large leaves at nodes 13–15 in the fully cooled root-zone treatment may be due to the under-utilization of the root carbohydrate pool in the period up to fruit set and the subsequent mobilization of these reserves later in the season when photoassimilates from fully functioning leaves are also a source of energy and structural carbon.Full root-zone cooling during inflorescence development decreased inflorescence flower number and delayed the onset of anthesis. Similar observations were made in Chardonnay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C43">Rogiers <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and Muscat of Alexandria grapes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C48">Shimamura and Kubota 1978</xref>). Inflorescence initiation begins in the previous season (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C38">May 1965</xref>) and this is why inflorescence number was not affected by the root-zone treatments from budburst onwards. Furthermore, there was no treatment effect on cluster branching and this is likely because the inflorescence branch primordia were established in the previous season prior to dormancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C54">Srinivasan and Mullins 1981</xref>). Conversely, flower primordia are not initiated until the following spring, after the break of bud dormancy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C51">Snyder 1933</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C62">Winkler and Shemsettin 1937</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C1">Agaoglu 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C54">Srinivasan and Mullins 1981</xref>). Each branch primordium of the inflorescence primordium divides many times and, ultimately, it produces the flower initials. The treatments were applied during the development of the flower initials and this temporal overlap made it possible for the root-zone treatments to have an effect on the flower number. This mode of action may be via decreased carbohydrate supply to the developing organ through cool temperature inhibition of root carbohydrate reserve mobilization or through a reduction of recent photoassimilate supply resulting from impaired vegetative growth. Both of these sources supply carbon to early flower development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C33">Kliewer 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C26">Goffinet 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C34">Lebon <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C50">Smith and Holzapfel 2009</xref>).Root-zone exposure to cool temperatures triggers stomatal closure in grapevines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C42">Rogiers and Clarke 2013</xref>) as well as in other species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C60">Wan <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>) and is hypothesized to be the result of the accumulation of abscisic acid and other root-to-shoot signals transported through the xylem sap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C56">Tachibana 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C35">Lee <italic>et al</italic>. 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C60">Wan <italic>et al</italic>. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C69">Zhou <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). This decline in stomatal conductance is accompanied by a decrease in net photoassimilation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C58">Wan <italic>et al</italic>. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C60">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C42">Rogiers and Clarke 2013</xref>). Therefore, fewer flowers in cool root zones may initially be the result of lower availability of mobilized carbohydrate reserves but subsequently due to reduced photoassimilates as a result of reduced stomatal conductance, smaller functional leaf area and altered partitioning to favour carbohydrate reserve replenishment. A close relationship between carbohydrate status and flower development exists in a number of woody plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C41">Rodrigo <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>).Aside from decreased flower number, the progression of flower opening was markedly slowed in vines with fully cooled root zones compared with fully warmed root zones. The dynamic analysis of anthesis revealed a 5-day delay in the ability of flowers grown on fully cooled vines to reach 90 % capfall, but inflorescences of partially cooled root zones had only a 1-day delay in flower opening. Compared with partial root-zone cooling, full root-zone cooling may result in a more severe delay of hormone production that favours flower development. Alternatively, complete root-zone cooling may decrease to a greater extent both assimilate and water transport to the inflorescence so that flower development is slowed. Flowering, like many other developmental processes, is dependent on cardinal air temperature and thermal sum but soil temperature may be an additional driver for these processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C18">Craufurd and Wheeler 2009</xref>).Whole and partial root-zone cooling until fruit set delayed berry expansion over the following weeks as well as the onset of veraison. This may have been simply a carry-on effect from the delayed flowering period. Additionally, the smaller leaf size of plants grown in partial or whole root-zone cooling likely decreased whole vine carbon assimilation, further delaying the development of the reproductive organs. It is also possible that these vines allocated energy towards root growth after the release from the cool temperature stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C40">Pregitzer <italic>et al</italic>. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C59">Wan <italic>et al</italic>. 2001</xref>), and thus, the availability of photoassimilates for berry development likely declined since roots and reproductive growth often compete for carbohydrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C31">Hansen 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLT036C22">Eissenstat and Duncan 1992</xref>). The ability of root-zone temperature to delay or accelerate the onset of ripening may have important implications for the planning of vineyard activities such as pesticide spray regimes and scheduling of harvest dates.Heterogeneity in soil temperature from budburst to fruit set at the plant scale is strongly expressed in the vegetative and reproductive development that takes place in this period. Partial root-zone cooling elicited intermediate responses in terms of leaf emergence and shoot growth. The effects of soil temperature up to fruit set continued to be evident over the remainder of the season. Depression of vegetative growth prior to fruit set was followed by increases in the rate of shoot elongation and the size of newly emerged leaves. The onset of flowering and veraison was delayed by several days in vines exposed to full root-zone cooling, but this was less severe in those vines exposed to partial root-zone cooling. These observations suggest that warming of one half of the root system did not fully compensate for cooling in the other half. As a result, spatial variations in soil temperature from budburst to fruit set have the potential to produce heterogeneity in cluster phenology, an attribute used to schedule many vineyard activities.This work was supported by the grape growers and winemakers of Australia through their investment body, the <grant-sponsor xlink:type="simple">Grape and Wine Research Development Corporation</grant-sponsor>, with matching funds from the federal government.S.Y.R. and S.J.C. designed and conducted the experiment and analysed the data. S.Y.R. wrote the manuscript and S.J.C. provided significant editorial comments.None declared.We thank Kirstina Lamont, Robert Lamont, Helen Pan, Yan Jia, Anna Fang and Phil Armstrong for their technical expertise.