Comparison of the morphogenesis of three genotypes of pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic>) grown in pure stands and wheat-based intercropsBranching in <italic>Pisum</italic>: inheritance and allelism tests with 17 <italic>ramosus</italic> mutantsLight signals perceived by crop and weed plantsModélisation du partage de la lumière dans l'association de cultures blé—pois (Triticum aestivum L.–Pisum sativum L.)—Une approche de type plante virtuelleHow good is the turbid medium-based approach for accounting for light partitioning in contrasted grass–legume intercropping systems?How does pea architecture influence light sharing in virtual wheat–pea mixtures? A simulation study based on pea genotypes with contrasting architecturesA simple model of pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic>) growth affected by <italic>Mycosphaerella pinodes</italic>The effect of plant density on tillering: the involvement of R/FR ratio and the proportion of radiation intercepted per plantPhylloclimate or the climate perceived by individual plant organs: what is it? How to model it? What for?Interspecific competition for soil N and its interaction with N<sub>2</sub> fixation, leaf expansion and crop growth in pea–barley intercropsAdaptation of the STICS intercrop model to simulate crop growth and N accumulation in pea–barley intercropsThe competitive ability of pea–barley intercrops against weeds and the interactions with crop productivity and soil N availabilityLegume versus fertilizer sources of nitrogen: ecological tradeoffs and human needsUsing functional–structural plant models to study, understand and integrate plant development and ecophysiologyCompetition between herbage plantsImportance économique passée et présente des légumineuses: Rôle historique dans les assolements et les facteurs d’évolutionUnderstanding shoot branching by modelling form and functionRepresenting and encoding plant architecture: a reviewPea compound leaf architecture is regulated by interactions among the genes UNIFOLIATA, COCHLEATA, AFILA, and TENDRIL-LESSOn the composition of the plant by phytons, and some applications of phyllotaxisGrain legume–cereal intercropping: the practical application of diversity, competition and facilitation in arable and organic cropping systemsGenetics and genetic modifications of plant architecture in grain legumes: a reviewGrain yield, symbiotic N<sub>2</sub> fixation and interspecific competition for inorganic N in pea–barley intercropsDeveloppement des ramificationsThe end of flowering in pea: influence of plant nitrogen nutritionInternode length in <italic>Pisum</italic>: phenotypic characterisation and genetic identity of the short internode mutant Wt11242Exploring options for managing strategies for pea–barley intercropping using a modeling approachEffect of pea plant architecture on spatiotemporal epidemic development of ascochyta blight (<italic>Mycosphaerella pinodes</italic>) in the fieldDéterminants écologiques et physiologiques de la productivité et de la stabilité des associations graminées-légumineusesAn algorithm for least-squares estimation of nonlinear parametersDéveloppement reproducteurFlowering in <italic>Pisum</italic>. Hr, a gene for high response to photoperiodFlowering in <italic>Pisum</italic>: multiple alleles at the <italic>lf</italic> locusThe effect of various dynamics of N availability on winter pea–wheat intercrops: crop growth, N partitioning and symbiotic N<sub>2</sub> fixationPréfaceCereal–legume intercropping systemsA model to simulate the final number of reproductive nodes in pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.)Role of phytometric investigations in the studies of plant stand architecture and radiation regimeA versatile growth model with statistically stable parametersMechanisms determining the degree of size asymmetry in competition among plantsEstimation of light capture and partitioning in intercropping systemsBasal branching in field pea cultivars and yield–density relationshipsTime of Flowering of Pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.) as a function of leaf appearance rate and node of first flowerLeaf primordium initiation and expanded leaf production are co-ordinated through similar response to air temperature in pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.)Functional–structural plant modelling: a new versatile tool in crop scienceThe plant as a metapopulationThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.In intercropping systems, plant morphology highly determines the amount of resources captured by each component species. However, morphogenesis of cultivated species has been mainly described in mono-specific growing conditions, although plasticity can occur in multi-specific stands. This paper reports on the variability of the morphogenesis of three pea genotypes grown in pure stands and mixed with wheat. Most morphogenetic parameters of pea were dependent on the genotype. However, there was low variability of pea morphogenesis between sole and mixed stands, except for plant height and branching of the long cycle cultivar.Cereal–legume intercrops represent a promising way of combining high productivity and agriculture sustainability. The benefits of cereal–legume mixtures are highly affected by species morphology and functioning, which determine the balance between competition and complementarity for resource acquisition. Studying species morphogenesis, which controls plant architecture, is therefore of major interest. The morphogenesis of cultivated species has been mainly described in mono-specific growing conditions, although morphogenetic plasticity can occur in multi-specific stands. The aim of the present study was therefore to characterize the variability of the morphogenesis of pea plants grown either in pure stands or mixed with wheat. This was achieved through a field experiment that included three pea cultivars with contrasting earliness (hr and HR type) and branching patterns. Results show that most of the assessed parameters of pea morphogenesis (phenology, branching, final number of vegetative organs and their kinetics of appearance) were mainly dependent on the considered genotype, which highlights the importance of the choice of cultivars in intercropping systems. There was however a low variability of pea morphogenesis between sole and mixed stands except for plant height and branching of the long-cycle cultivar. The information provided in the present study at stand and plant scale can be used to build up structural–functional models. These models can contribute to improving the understanding of the functioning of cereal–legume intercrops and also to the definition of plant ideotypes adapted to the growth in intercrops.In order to ensure agriculture sustainability, efforts have been made by researchers and farmers to reduce the use of fertilizers and pesticides. This challenges the maintenance of efficient and profitable agrosystems being able to face demographic growth. Because of their ability to fix atmospheric N<sub>2</sub>, legume species can improve the sustainability of cropping systems by helping to decrease the use of nitrogen fertilizers and favouring the diversification of crop rotations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C12">Crews and Peoples 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C15">Duc <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Also, seeds or forages of legumes are among the richest sources of proteins in crops, with a high nutritional value for animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C15">Duc <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). However, the potential productivity of legumes has not been reached, mainly because of a strong sensitivity of these species to lodging and foliar diseases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C36">Ney and Carrouée 2005</xref>). This is in particular the case for pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic>), which is the main source of vegetable proteins in Europe. In this context, the increasing interest in growing cereal–legume intercrops (IC), such as wheat–pea mixtures, represents an alternative for reintroducing legume species in cropping systems. Several studies reported that these mixtures can provide high and stable yields compared with pure mono-specific stands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C37">Ofori and Stern 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C22">Jensen 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C9">Corre-Hellou <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C20">Hauggaard-Nielsen <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Such advantages result from a balance between complementary (e.g. separate root and canopy areas) and competition processes for light, water and nitrogen that occur between intercropped species. These complex interactions depend on the pedo-climatic conditions, agricultural practices and also on the morphology and functioning of the component species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C9">Corre-Hellou <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C26">Launay <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C28">Louarn <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C35">Naudin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C3">Barillot 2012</xref>).The latter point is mainly related to the choice of cultivars, which therefore appears as a determinant factor of (i) the proportion of each component species at harvest and (ii) mixture productivity. Cultivars are usually discriminated according to their earliness, sensitivity to diseases or potential yield. However, in the particular case of multi-specific stands, the above-ground architecture of a cultivar, given by its geometry, optical properties and topology of the phytoelements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C17">Godin 2000</xref>), should also be taken into account. Indeed, plant architecture defines the plant interface with biotic (e.g. with <italic>Mycosphaerella pinodes</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C6">Béasse <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C27">Le May <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>) and abiotic factors (e.g. light; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C40">Ross 1981</xref>). In the case of multi-specific stands, the complementarity between the architecture of the mixed species represents a crucial issue as it will determine their respective ability to compete for light that in turn drives the production and allocation of biomass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C47">Varlet-Grancher <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C43">Sinoquet and Caldwell 1995</xref>).For pea, several genes involved in the development of the above-ground architecture have been identified (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C21">Huyghe 1998</xref>). For instance, numerous <italic>ramosus</italic> mutants were described because of their altered branching behaviour (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C1">Arumingtyas <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>). Plant height can also be altered through mutations made on genes involved in internode growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C25">Kusnadi <italic>et al.</italic> 1992</xref>)<italic>.</italic> Genetic control of the compound leaf shape of pea has also been assessed and appears to be related to the <italic>UNIFOLIATA</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C18">Gourlay <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). Precocity of pea cultivars has been shown to be regulated by genes (<italic>Hr</italic> and <italic>Lf</italic>) that control the sensitivity to photoperiod for floral initiation and flowering (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C32">Murfet 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C33">1975</xref>). These studies have promoted the breeding of several pea cultivars with contrasting architectures that therefore constitute as much as potential combinations for wheat–pea IC. Characterizing the morphogenesis (sequence of developmental and growth processes leading to plant architecture) of these various pea genotypes is therefore of major interest for improving the management of intercropped stands. Several descriptors can be used to characterize pea architecture, the most commonly used being those related to the leaf area and its spatial distribution as this strongly determines a plant's ability to compete for light interception. On a finer scale, both the amount and distribution of foliar area are related to the number and geometry of stems and leaves produced during the initiation of each phytomer by the apex. A phytomer is defined as a basic unit repeated along the stem and including an internode, a node, a leaf and one or several axillary buds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C19">Gray 1849</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C49">White 1979</xref>). The sharing of resources within multi-specific stands also depends on the respective height reached by the component species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C43">Sinoquet and Caldwell 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C42">Schwinning and Weiner 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C28">Louarn <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C4">Barillot <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C5">2012</xref>). Although the architectural parameters involved in the leaf area and height of plants are key factors of the mixture development, they have been mainly described in mono-specific growing conditions (for a review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C30">Munier-Jolain <italic>et al.</italic> 2005<italic>a</italic></xref>). However, the morphogenesis of plants can be highly plastic when facing environmental variations; hence the question arises as to whether morphogenetic variations can occur between mono- and multi-specific stands.The aim of the present study was therefore to characterize the variability of pea morphogenesis grown either in pure stands or mixed with wheat. In order to have a large range of plant architectures and morphogenetic responses, a field experiment was performed using three pea cultivars with contrasting growth habits. The growth and phenology of the pea cultivars were measured regularly during their growing cycle. This study provides information at both stand and plant scale in order to identify plant traits of interest that can contribute to the conception of plant ideotypes.A field experiment was carried out in 2010–11 at Brain-sur-l'Authion, western France (47°26′N, 00°26′W) in a clay soil (51 % clay, 26 % silt and 23 % sand). Daily mean air temperature, precipitation and photosynthetically active radiation (PAR) were recorded by a standard automatic agro-meteorological station located close to the field.Winter wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>) cv. Cézanne and three cultivars of winter field pea (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic>), cv. Lucy (hr type), AOPH10 (hr type) and 886/01 (HR type), were sown on 28 November 2010 in sole crops (SC) and IC. Unlike hr types, flowering of the HR cultivar is sensitive to photoperiod. The sowing density of SC was 250 plantsm<sup>−2</sup> for wheat. Optimal densities of pea cultivars were chosen with respect to their ability for lateral development and the underlying risk of lodging. Sole crops composed of pea cultivars Lucy and AOPH10 were sown at 80 plantsm<sup>−2</sup> whereas cultivar 886/01 was sown at 40 plantsm<sup>−2</sup>. Intercrops followed a substitutive design where the two species were mixed within the row. Wheat and pea crops in IC were sown at half their respective density in pure stands. From seedbed preparation to harvest, local agronomic recommendations were followed and pest and weed were chemically controlled. Stands of sole wheat were fertilized with 14 g N m<sup>−2</sup> whereas pea SC and wheat–pea IC were not supplied with external nitrogen.Statistical analyses described below were thus performed considering two factors: (i) pea genotype with three levels (Lucy, AOPH10 and 886/01) and (ii) cropping system with two levels (SC and IC). A sole crop of wheat was added to those six treatments but was not considered for statistical analyses. These seven treatments (3 SC of pea, 3 IC and 1 SC of wheat) were arranged in experimental units of 1.2 × 10 m<sup>2</sup> within a randomized complete block design with three replicates.Harvest time, expressed in growing degree day (DD) from emergence (base, 0 °C), of pea and wheat grown in SC and in IC.Normal distributions of the residuals of ANOVAs as well as those of Schnute's adjustments were tested using the Shapiro–Wilk test. Homoscedasticity was checked by random distribution of the residuals. Tukey's HSD tests were used for mean separation when three or more means were compared.Meteorological conditions during the growing season 2010–11 at Brain-sur-l'Authion, France. Daily mean air temperatures and rainfall are shown in (A). Vertical arrows represent a water supply of 30 mm by irrigation. Daily cumulated PAR is shown in (B). The horizontal arrow represents the growing period of pea and wheat stands.(A) Accumulation of above-ground biomass as a function of thermal time from emergence (base temperature = 0 °C). Sole crops are shown in closed symbols and IC in open symbols. Pea cultivars are in solid lines: Lucy is denoted by circles (filled, open), AOPH10 by squares (filled, open) and 886/01 by diamonds (filled, open). Wheat is in dotted lines with triangles (filled) in SC, and with the corresponding pea cultivar symbol in IC (open circles with ‘Lucy’, open squares with ‘AOPH10’ and open diamonds with ‘886/01’). (B) Contribution of wheat (white bars) and pea (black bars) in the final biomass reached by SC and IC stands.Harvest of IC stands (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU006TB1">1</xref>) was performed when wheat reached maturity (2275 GDD). For pea grown in SC, harvest was made earlier, i.e. between 1900 and 2130 GDD depending on the cultivar. Cultivars Lucy and AOPH10 (hr types) reached their maturity earlier than ‘886/01’. Indeed, cultivar 886/01 (HR type) needs a longer photoperiod to reach flowering and was therefore harvested later than hr cultivars. As a result, the maturity of cultivar 886/01 and that of wheat were reached in a similar period (2130 and 2275 GDD, respectively).Land equivalent ratio of each wheat–pea mixture. Land equivalent ratio values &gt;1 indicate a benefit of intercropping over sole cropping. <italic>N.B.:</italic> unlike pure stands of pea and IC, wheat SC were fertilized with external nitrogen.Height ratio of wheat–pea mixtures according to the growing degree day (GDD).Observed height of canopies during the growing cycle. Sole crops are shown in closed symbols and IC in open symbols. Pea cultivars are in solid lines: Lucy is denoted by circles (filled, open), AOPH10 by squares (filled, open) and 886/01 by diamonds (filled, open). Wheat is in dotted lines with triangles (filled) in SC, and with the corresponding pea cultivar symbol in IC (open circles with ‘Lucy’, open squares with ‘AOPH10’ and open diamonds with ‘886/01’).In a second step, measurements were made at plant scale in order to compare the morphogenesis of pea cultivars grown in pure stands with those intercropped with wheat.Lateral branching of pea cultivars (<italic>n</italic> = 15 plants for each condition). (A) Number of lateral branches developed by the pea cultivars Lucy, AOPH10 and 886/01 grown in SC and in IC. (B) Time of branching expressed in thermal time from crop emergence. Branches were distinguished according to their nodal position on the main stem. Axis-1: branches emerged at the first node; Axis-2: second node; and Axis-3: third node.Lateral branches emerged between 275 and 420 GDD, all cultivars and cropping systems taken together (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU006F5">5</xref>B). Although they were initiated later, branches that developed on the second phytomer of the main stem (Axis-2) appeared 70 GDD earlier than those located on the first node (Axis-1). Indeed, in most cases, the first phytomer (carrying the first vestigial leaf) is located a few millimetres under the ground. This may mechanically delay the emergence of branches, depending for instance on the sowing depth or soil structure, which also affect the quantity of light perceived by the axillary bud (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C23">Jeudy and Munier-Jolain 2005</xref>). Statistical analyses showed that there was a significant effect of the genotype on the time of branch emergence (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,87</sub> = 5.09, <italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.01; <italic>F</italic><sub>2,166</sub> = 3.20, <italic>P</italic>&lt; 0.05 for Axis-1 and -2, respectively). Indeed, branches developed on cultivar Lucy emerged significantly earlier than those of ‘886/01’ (HSD <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 and &lt;0.05 for Axis-1 and -2, respectively), while ‘AOPH10’ had an intermediary behaviour. There were however no significant differences in the time of branch emergence between SC and IC stands, meaning that this parameter of pea morphogenesis was mainly dependent on the genotype.Frequency of pea plants grown in SC and in IC whose measured branches have reached flowering. Branches were distinguished according to their nodal position on the main stem. Axis-1: branches emerged at the first node; Axis-2: second node; and Axis-3: third node (<italic>n</italic> = 15 plants for each condition, only one single branch was considered at each nodal position).Parameters (<italic>A</italic> × 10<sup>−3</sup>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>) of Schnute's adjustments made on the kinetics of phytomer appearance for each pea cultivar (Lucy, AOPH10, 866/01) grown in SC or in IC. Schnute's adjustments were performed for each flowering stem (0: main stem; 1: branch developed on the first node of the main stem; 2: second node). Indicated values are the mean ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 15 plants for each cultivar and cropping system).Typical kinetics of phytomer appearance on a vegetative stem of the pea cultivars. Observed values are in closed symbols. Non-linear adjustment (solid line) was performed using Schnute's equation.Rate of phytomer production of each pea cultivar (Lucy, AOPH10, 866/01) grown in SC or in IC. Maximum rate of phytomer production (<italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>, phytomer degree-day<sup>−1</sup>) and time at which it was reached <inline-formula><tex-math notation="TeX">$({t_{V_{\rm max}}\!, \hbox{DD}} )$</tex-math></inline-formula> are shown (mean ± SD). Computations were carried out for each flowered stem (0: main stem; 1: branch developed on the first node of the main stem; 2: second node) (<italic>n</italic> = 15 plants for each cultivar and cropping system).Frequency of flowering stems according to the final number of phytomers. Measurements were made on three pea cultivars: Lucy, AOPH10 and 886/01 grown in SC and in IC with wheat. Results are shown for stems that reached flowering. Main stems are denoted as Axis-0 and branches were distinguished according to their nodal position on the main stem. Axis-1: branches developed at the first node; Axis-2: second node; and Axis-3: third node (<italic>n</italic> = 15 plants for each condition).Time of flowering of pea cultivars Lucy, AOPH10 and 886/01 grown in SC or in IC. Main stems are denoted as Axis-0 and branches were distinguished according to their nodal position on the main stem. Axis-1: branches developed at the first node; Axis-2: second node; and Axis-3: third node (<italic>n</italic> = 15 plants for each condition).Plant frequency according to the first flowering phytomer of stems. Results are shown for the pea cultivars Lucy, AOPH10 and 886/01 grown in SC or in IC (<italic>n</italic> = 15 plants for each condition). Main stems are denoted as Axis-0 and branches were distinguished according to their nodal position on the main stem. Axis-1: branches developed at the first node; Axis-2: second node; and Axis-3: third node.The aim of the present study was to address the question of the morphological responses of pea to the competition when intercropped with wheat. To this end, a field experiment was conducted on three pea cultivars that were characterized at both stand and plant scale when grown in pure stands and mixed with wheat.Although the present study was conducted throughout 1 year only, our results on crop biomass, species height and maturity were consistent with previous studies performed on different cultivars grown under contrasting pedo-climatic conditions (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C10">Corre-Hellou <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C35">Naudin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The results presented in this study can therefore be assumed to be representative of the conditions commonly encountered in wheat–pea mixtures. These results were obtained from unfertilized mixtures as usually performed in cereal–legume intercropping systems. Furthermore, some authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C22">Jensen 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C9">Corre-Hellou <italic>et al.</italic> 2006</xref>) found that the contribution of the component species to the biomass of the mixture was dependent on the available nitrogen, an increase of which enhances the growth of the cereal species. The level and timing of nitrogen fertilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C34">Naudin 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C35">Naudin <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>) therefore constitute a key factor enabling one to manage the hierarchy between the mixed species. The present study also shows that the three pea cultivars exhibited a similar level of biomass, especially when grown in mixtures. This suggests that despite the genotypic differences and contrasting initial sowing densities, the three pea cultivars had a similar overall development even when they were in competition with wheat. However, this does not necessarily mean that the morphological processes of the pea cultivars had similar responses to the competition with wheat, but their integration at the stand scale leads to an equivalent growth in biomass.Our results also show that pea was strongly affected by lodging when grown in SC. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C11">Corre-Hellou <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> reported that the high sensitivity of pea to lodging caused significant yield losses as well as an enhanced growth of weeds. Pea lodging was however strongly decreased in mixed stands, pea branches being stacked by wheat. Intercropping cereals and legumes is therefore a promising way of both reintroducing legume species within agrosystems and solving the problems encountered in pure stands of legumes. Moreover, the height reached by each species in the canopy is an important feature of the stand which determines, but also emerges from, the competition processes occurring between plants. Component species height ratio has been widely shown to affect light sharing in a mixture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C43">Sinoquet and Caldwell 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C28">Louarn <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C4">Barillot <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C5">2012</xref>) and is therefore a strong component of the inter-specific competition occurring within the mixture. The results described in the present study illustrate that the species height ratio is not constant throughout the growing cycle; pea cultivars were much shorter than wheat until 700 GDD and then reached a similar height. Differences among pea cultivars were also observed but were not constant over time. Although ‘886/01’ was the shorter one in the early stages of development, this cultivar finally reached the same height as that of wheat afterwards. Therefore, it seems that the competition which occurs among the intercropped species cannot be assessed by punctual measurements of the species height ratio (in particular during the early stages of development). This is consistent with the findings reported in a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C5">Barillot <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>) where a virtual plant approach was used to demonstrate that the ability of plants to intercept light was mainly determined by the architectural parameters involved in (i) the LAI (number of branches and phytomers, leaf area) during the early stages and (ii) plant height (internode length, number of phytomers) once canopy closure was established.The time lag between the physiological maturity of wheat and pea is a well-known issue of these mixtures. The choice of harvest timing is indeed complicated by the fact that pea generally reaches its maturity earlier than wheat. Nevertheless, physiological maturity of pea varies among the cultivars according to their earliness, which is assumed to be mainly driven by the sensitivity of flowering to the photoperiod that involves the <italic>Hr</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C32">Murfet 1973</xref>). The maturity of the HR cultivar (886/01) was therefore almost synchronized with that of wheat, whereas the hr cultivars had to be harvested earlier. Gaps of maturity, as encountered with hr cultivars, represent a strong practical constraint at harvest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C28">Louarn <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>); HR pea cultivars therefore appeared to be well suited to intercropping with wheat.In order to deepen the analysis of the variability of pea morphogenesis in response to intercropping, a comparison was performed at plant scale with particular attention to pea branching, flowering, final number of phytomers and their kinetics of appearance. Branching has been shown to be dependent on several factors such as genotype, hormonal balance, environmental factors, e.g. low temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C23">Jeudy and Munier-Jolain 2005</xref>), and also plant density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C44">Spies <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). In the present study, contrasting abilities for branching were indeed found between the genotypes [Lucy–AOPH10] and 886/01. Cultivar 886/01 was the most branching cultivar, which balanced its lower sowing density (50 % less than ‘Lucy’ and ‘AOPH10’). Moreover, the number of branches tended to decrease in IC compared with pure stands, in particular for cultivar 886/01. Some authors like <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C7">Casal <italic>et al.</italic> (1986)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C2">Ballaré and Casal (2000)</xref> or <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C16">Evers <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> showed that branching of several species is affected by the quantity (PAR) and quality (red/far-red ratio) of light perceived by the axillary buds. In the present study, we can therefore hypothesize that quantity of light and/or its quality were quite similar between the respective pure stands and IC of cultivars Lucy and AOPH10. This would mean that the replacement of a ‘Lucy’ or an ‘AOPH10’ plant by a wheat one leads to similar variations of light microclimate. This could be the result of small differences in the architectural patterns of the two species in terms of leaf area, height, geometry and/or optical properties. As cultivar 886/01 has a late development (HR type), we can also hypothesize that when branching started, wheat plants were more developed than neighbour ‘886/01’ pea plants would have been in a pure stand. This could cause variations of the microclimate perceived by axillary buds, leading to an inhibition of branching.The kinetics of phytomer appearance were assessed for main stems and a randomly selected branch at each node by using non-linear fittings. Our analysis showed that there were few statistical differences between the parameters belonging to the different genotypes and cropping systems. It was only found that (i) Axis-2 branches of cultivar 886/01 had kinetics different from those of ‘Lucy’ and ‘AOPH10’ and (ii) the maximum rate of phytomer appearance of ‘886/01’ was reached later compared with the other cultivars. These results mean that the kinetics of phytomer production of different stems can be analysed/modelled by using similar Schnute's functions, at least for Lucy and AOPH10 cultivars whether they were grown in sole stands or mixed with wheat. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C46">Turc and Lecoeur (1997)</xref> also reported similar rates of leaf primordium initiation and emergence for contrasting plant growth rates, cultivars and sowing densities in spring pea. One drawback of using Schnute's function lies in the fact that some of the parameters, especially <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic>, cannot be directly related to a biological meaning. It would be tempting to use linear regressions because of the reduced number of parameters and easy interpretation. However, phytomer production is not intrinsically constant and is actually characterized by a maximum rate (which can be estimated by the derivative of Schnute's functions) and a time at which development stops. These aspects cannot be handled by linear models. Supplementary statistical analyses (data not shown) showed that the residual sum of squares was significantly higher for linear regressions than that obtained with Schnute's function (HSD <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). These tests also indicated that the residuals of most linear regressions were not normally distributed and have means differing from zero. Nevertheless, the estimated parameters derived from Schnute's adjustments were highly variable. This variability is related to pea branching which is rather complex, particularly in the case of winter-sown cultivars. Winter conditions often cause frost damage, which induces the cessation of the development of the main stems and the initiation of numerous branches at different times (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU006F5">5</xref>A and B). The result is a high variability in the characteristics of branches.In the present study, a significant difference was observed among the pea genotypes for the final number of phytomers reached on stems. Indeed, ‘886/01’ (HR type) was found to produce more phytomers than the other cultivars. Similar results were also reported for this particular cultivar but grown in controlled conditions and individual pots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C5">Barillot <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). In contrast, the number of initiated phytomers was similar whether pea plants were grown in pure stands or mixed with wheat, whatever the genotype. Moreover, our results show that the canopy of the three pea cultivars was mainly composed of branches as main stems had stopped growing with few phytomers. As reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C23">Jeudy and Munier-Jolain (2005)</xref>, the development of branches is increased in winter pea cultivars because of the frost damage experienced on the apex of the main stem. Such conditions were encountered during the first months of the growing cycle (December–February; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU006F1">1</xref>) which corresponds to the emergence of the lateral branches (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU006F5">5</xref>B).Flowering is a crucial stage of the growing cycle that has been widely studied and used in order to model pea growth. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C45">Truong and Duthion (1993)</xref> showed that the time of flowering is a function of leaf appearance rate and position of the node bearing the first flower. The reproductive development of pea cultivars was therefore characterized by two main indicators: the nodal position of the first flower and its emergence time. As also reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C24">Jeuffroy and Sebillotte (1997)</xref>, we found similar time of flowering between main stems and basal branches (although these were produced later) for all cultivars and cropping systems. Furthermore, the position of the first flowering node was similar among the genotypes and cropping systems. Some authors also showed that for a given genotype, the position of the first flowering node was constant over various conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C39">Roche <italic>et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C31">Munier-Jolain <italic>et al.</italic> 2005<italic>b</italic></xref>).Finally these results highlight that in the present experiment, the morphogenesis of pea was mainly determined by the genotype and was only little affected by the competition with wheat. This suggests that the architectures of pea and wheat may be quite similar, so that the environmental conditions perceived by plants in the canopy (phylloclimate; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C8">Chelle 2005</xref>) were not strongly different between sole pea crops and wheat–pea mixtures. Functional–structural models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C48">Vos <italic>et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU006C13">DeJong <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>) are able to take into account the explicit architecture of plants and its interactions with physiological processes and environmental conditions. Such models therefore constitute suitable tools for assessing these hypotheses and can in particular be used to characterize the microclimate perceived by plants located in mono- and multi-specific stands.To our knowledge, the present study is the first to compare the morphogenesis of pea grown in sole stands with that of pea grown intercropped with wheat. On the one hand, the present results show that most of the assessed parameters of pea morphogenesis (phenology, branching, final number of phytomers and their kinetics of appearance) were mainly dependent on the considered genotype. This emphasizes the importance of the selection of cultivars, in particular for intercropping systems, as this will determine the level of competition and complementarity between the component species. On the other hand, there was a low variability of pea morphogenesis between sole and mixed stands except for plant height and branching of the late cultivar 886/01. Complementary studies on wheat–pea mixtures under contrasting levels of nitrogen fertilization are now needed to provide information on how nitrogen would affect plant morphogenesis and inter-specific competition. The information provided in the present study can be used for modelling pea morphogenesis in pure and mixed stands and therefore contributes to a better understanding of the functioning of cereal–legume IC. This kind of approach is also well suited for the identification of plant traits to be integrated in the definition of plant ideotypes.This research was supported by ‘La Région Pays de la Loire’, France through a Ph.D. fellowship to R.B. The research of D.C. and A.E.-G. was partially funded by ‘La Région Poitou-Charentes’, France.All authors have contributed substantially to this manuscript. R.B. completed the writing and was involved in each step of the experimentation and analysis. D.C. and A.E.G. were actively involved in the conception and design of the experiment as well as in the analyses and writing of the manuscript. S.P. was involved in the conception of the experiment and also performed the measurements. P.H. was involved in database programming and data analysis.None declared.We gratefully acknowledge the technical staff of LEVA (Légumineuses, Ecophysiologie Végétale, Agroécologie) as well as the experimental station of Brain sur l'Authion (FNAMS, Fédération Nationale des Agriculteurs Multiplicateurs de Semences). We also thank Dr Guénaëlle Corre-Hellou (LEVA, Groupe ESA) for valuable discussions. We also thank reviewers for particularly helpful comments on this article.