QTL analysis of internode elongation in response to gibberellin in deepwater riceReleasing the brakes of plant growth: how GAs shutdown DELLA proteinsCoordinated regulation of apical hook development by gibberellins and ethylene in etiolated <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seedlingsAnatomico-elongation studies on the aerenchyma and the ventilating system in rice plantsDELLAs regulate chlorophyll and carotenoid biosynthesis to prevent photooxidative damage during seedling deetiolation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>Whole genome analysis of the <italic>OsGRF</italic> gene family encoding plant-specific putative transcription activators in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.)Empirical threshold values for quantitative trait mappingPermutation tests for multiple loci affecting a quantitative characterFruit growth in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> occurs via DELLA-dependent and DELLA-independent gibberellin responsesA major QTL confers rapid internode elongation in response to water rise in deepwater riceThe ethylene response factors <italic>SNORKEL1</italic> and <italic>SNORKEL2</italic> allow rice to adapt to deep waterSome observations on ‘Bakanae’ disease of the rice plantOn the relation between position of the lowest elongated internode (LEI) and elongation ability of internodes under rising water conditions in Asian deepwater rice, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L<italic>Slender rice</italic>, a constitutive gibberellin response mutant, is caused by a null mutation of the <italic>SLR1</italic> gene, an ortholog of the height-regulating gene <italic>GAI</italic>/<italic>RGA</italic>/<italic>RHT</italic>/<italic>D8</italic>Relation between elongation ability and internode elongation of floating rice under rising water conditionsVarietal difference for internode elongation caused by exogenous gibberellic acid in floating rice seedlingsSome morphological and ecological differences between floating and non-floating rice varieties in Thai paddy rice, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> LThe gibberellin signaling pathway is regulated by the appearance and disappearance of SLENDER RICE1 in nucleiWhere do gibberellin biosynthesis and gibberellin signaling occur in rice plants?Mapping of QTLs for floating ability in riceExperimental studies on the nature of the substance secreted by the ‘bakanae’ fungusThe biophysical basis of elongation growth in internode of deepwater riceMAPMAKER: an interactive computer package for constructing primary genetic linkage maps of experimental and natural populationsTwo novel QTLs regulate internode elongation in deepwater rice during the early vegetative stageInheritance of early elongation ability in floating rice revealed by diallel and QTL analysesRole of gibberellin in the growth response of submerged deep water riceAccumulation of phosphorylated repressor for gibberellin signaling in an F-box mutantDiseases of agricultural products in JapanStudies on the first joining stage in rice plantsPhysiological genetics of intermodal elongation under submergence in floating riceRelationship between main stem and primary tillers in the position of lowest elongated internode of deepwater riceComparison of QTLs for early elongation ability between two floating rice cultivars with a different phylogenetic originMolecular interactions of a soluble gibberellin receptor, GID1, with a rice DELLA protein, SLR1, and gibberellinA novel gibberellin-induced gene from rice and its potential regulatory role in stem growthUsing the new standard evaluation system to measure elongation abilityPlant hormone jasmonate prioritizes defense over growth by interfering with gibberellin signaling cascadeSCARECROW-LIKE 3 promotes gibberellin signaling by antagonizing master growth repressor DELLA in ArabidopsisIsolation of genomic DNAs from plants, fungi and bacteria using benzyl chloride<bold>Associate Editor:</bold> Abdelbagi M. IsmailThis is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.Gibberellin (GA) is one of the plant hormones which regulates many aspects of plant growth and developmental processes. Rice plants known as deepwater rice can survive during flooding by elongating its internodes to avoid anoxia. Previous studies reported that GA is essential for internode elongation in deepwater rice. However, the interaction between internode elongation and regulator of GA sensitivity is unknown. In this study, we performed a QTL analysis and identified the chromosomal regions that regulate GA responsiveness in deepwater rice. We concluded that deepwater rice could induce internode elongation in response to GA by factors in these regions.Gibberellin (GA) is a plant hormone that has important roles in numerous plant developmental phases. Rice plants known as deepwater rice respond to flooding by elongating their internodes to avoid anoxia. Previous studies reported that GA is essential for internode elongation in deepwater rice. Quantitative trait locus (QTL) analyses identified QTLs regulating internode elongation in response to deepwater conditions. However, the interaction between internode elongation and regulators of GA sensitivity in deepwater rice is unknown. In this study, we applied GA to recombinant inbred lines of T65 (non-deepwater rice) and Bhadua (deepwater rice), and performed a QTL analysis of internode elongation in response to GA. GA-induced internode elongation was detected only in deepwater rice. Our QTL analysis revealed two major QTLs on chromosomes 3 and 9 regulating total internode length, lowest elongated internode and number of elongated internodes. Furthermore, the QTL on chromosome 3 acted as an enhancer of other QTLs (e.g. the QTL on chromosome 12). Nearly isogenic lines of deepwater rice carrying the QTL regions from chromosomes 3 and 12 of the deepwater rice C9285 showed internode elongation in response to GA. Thus, these QTLs may regulate GA responsiveness in deepwater rice. This study furthers our understanding of the mechanism of internode elongation in rice.The plant hormone gibberellin (GA) regulates many aspects of plant growth, organ development and environmental responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C1">Achard and Genschik 2009</xref>). Among its various functions, GA was initially identified to be involved in the phenomenon of stem and leaf elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C15">Hori 1898</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C34">Sawada 1912</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C24">Kurosawa 1926</xref>). In this process of elongation, GA is associated with the regulation of cell division and cell elongation. In non-deepwater rice, GA biosynthesis and signalling occur in elongating and dividing organs and tissues, such as the shoot apex and young leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C22">Kaneko <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Additionally, rice internodes start to elongate after initiation of reproductive growth, and expression of genes involved in GA biosynthesis and signal transduction is upregulated in the basal region of the elongating internodes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C22">Kaneko <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). In contrast, rice plants known as deepwater rice can induce internode elongation during vegetative growth. Deepwater rice can be cultivated under deepwater conditions. The leaves and internodes of the plants elongate to help keep the top leaves above the water surface and avoid anoxia under deepwater conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C41">Vergara and Mazaredo 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C6">Catling 1992</xref>). Previous physiological studies have suggested that GA is involved in deepwater rice elongation. GA treatment induces internode elongation in deepwater rice under normal conditions, and GA biosynthesis inhibitors (e.g. uniconazol and tetcyclacis) suppress internode elongation in deepwater rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C30">Raskin and Kende 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C19">Inouye and Kim 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Additionally, bioactive GA accumulates in deepwater rice under deepwater conditions, but not in non-deepwater rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). These results suggest that GA is essential for internode elongation in deepwater rice. However, GA accumulation does not increase dramatically under deepwater conditions, and a rise in GA content is not sufficient to explain the marked internode elongation of deepwater rice. Deepwater rice may have not only greater GA biosynthesis ability but also higher GA sensitivity than non-deepwater rice. Previously, quantitative trait locus (QTL) analyses were performed to detect genetic loci that regulate the deepwater response. Multiple QTLs were detected on chromosomes 1, 3 and 12 by four independent groups using different populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C28">Nemoto <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C38">Tang <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C13">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C23">Kawano <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Moreover, we detected two QTLs on chromosomes 2 and 4 that enhance internode elongation during the early vegetative stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C27">Nagai <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Among these QTLs, the QTL on chromosome 12, which is most effective for internode elongation, was found to contain <italic>SNORKEL1</italic> (<italic>SK1</italic>) and <italic>SNORKEL2</italic> (<italic>SK2</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). These genes encode ethylene-responsive factor-type transcription factors, and their expression is induced by ethylene. However, genes regulating internode elongation in deepwater rice in response to GA have not been identified. In the present study, we performed a QTL analysis of internode elongation in response to GA using recombinant inbred lines (RILs) of rice, Taichung 65 (T65; non-deepwater rice) and Bhadua (deepwater rice), and successfully detected QTLs. We also confirmed the effects of the detected QTLs using nearly isogenic lines (NILs) possessing the QTL regions of C9285, another deepwater rice, in the T65 genetic background.T65 (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>), Nipponbare (<italic>O. sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>), Bhadua (<italic>O. sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>indica</italic>; Bangladesh) and C9285 (<italic>O. sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>indica</italic>; Bangladesh) were used in this study. C9285 was kindly provided by the National Institute of Genetics in Japan (<uri xlink:href="http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/rice/oryzabase/top/top.jsp" xlink:type="simple">http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/rice/oryzabase/top/top.jsp</uri>) and maintained at Nagoya University. Nipponbare and T65 were maintained at Nagoya University. Recombinant inbred lines were produced by selfing (nine times) F<sub>1</sub> plants derived from a cross between T65 and Bhadua. NIL3, NIL12 and NIL3–12 possessing the deepwater response QTL on chromosomes 3, 12 and 3/12 in the T65 genetic background were derived previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>).Rice seeds were sterilized by boiling at 60 °C for 10 min. After sterilization, the seeds were allowed to germinate in water at 30 °C for 72 h, and then sown individually in a perforated cell tray (cell size, 2.5 × 2.5 × 4.5 cm) filled with soil. To eliminate the effect of endogenous GA, uniconazole (uni), an inhibitor of GA biosynthesis, was administered with or without GA. For GA and uni treatment, 2 mL of a 10<sup>−1</sup> M GA<sub>3</sub> stock solution and 0.2 mL of a 10<sup>−2</sup> M uni stock solution were added to 2 L of water (final concentration, 10<sup>−4</sup> M GA and 10<sup>−6</sup> M uni). For uni treatment, 0.2 mL of a 10<sup>−2</sup> M uni stock solution was added to 2 L of water (final concentration, 10<sup>−6</sup> M uni). Each solution was used to treat 140 individuals. Seedlings were grown under 16 h of light and 8 h of dark, 70 % humidity, at 25 °C in a phytotron. After 3 weeks, the leaf sheath and internode elongation were measured.The developmental stage of a rice stem is defined as non-elongation phase, primary phase or secondary phase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C35">Suetsugu 1968</xref>). Although internode elongation of &lt;3 mm has been reported in primary phase stems, internode elongation exceeding 5 mm has been observed in secondary phase stems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C20">Inouye <italic>et al.</italic> 1985</xref>). Deepwater rice enhances secondary phase growth, resulting in elongated internodes in response to deepwater conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C37">Takahashi 1991</xref>). Based on these reports, we considered internodes longer than 5 mm to be elongated. The main culms of each plant were cut along the midline and total internode length (TIL) was measured. Because plants showing elongation of the lower internodes can increase TIL, lowest elongated internode (LEI) is regarded as an indicator of early internode elongation ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C20">Inouye <italic>et al.</italic> 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C16">Ibi <italic>et al.</italic> 1995</xref>). Lowest elongated internode corresponds to the leaf number. In rice, the culm is characterized by structural superposition, created by the upper and lower nodes, a single internode and a single leaf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C3">Arikado <italic>et al.</italic> 1990</xref>). Based on these reports, when internode elongation occurred from the internode of the third leaf in the main culm, LEI was considered to be 3. Number of elongated internodes (NEI) was defined as the number of internodes that are longer than 5 mm. The phenotype of each line was based on the average of six plants.To construct a linkage map, genomic DNA was extracted from 84 individuals of the RIL using the isoplant method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C44">Zhu <italic>et al.</italic> 1993</xref>). The extracted DNA samples were used for genotyping with single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers <bold>[see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu028/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link>]</bold> using an Affymetrix customized SNP array for rice. Single-nucleotide polymorphisms were detected by the Golden Gate assay of BeadXpress (Illumina, Inc., San Diego, CA, USA). MAPMAKER/EXP, version 3.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C26">Lander <italic>et al.</italic> 1987</xref>) was used to construct the linkage map. R/qtl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C5">Broman and Sen 2009</xref>) was used for the QTL analysis. Composite interval mapping (CIM) was used to detect the QTLs. The number of covariates was assumed to be 1. Quantitative trait loci were considered significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, with the logarithm of odds (LOD) score given by 1000 permutation tests (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C9">Churchill and Doerge 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C10">Doerge and Churchill 1996</xref>). A two-QTL scan was performed for the detection of interacting QTLs. Quantitative trait loci were considered significant at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.1 using the fitqtl method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C5">Broman and Sen 2009</xref>). Candidate QTL regions were identified using the lodint method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C5">Broman and Sen 2009</xref>).Phenotypic evaluation of GA-treated non-deepwater and deepwater rice. (A) Response of T65, Nipponbare, Bhadua and C9285 to GA and uni. (B) Length of the second leaf sheath in response to GA in non-deepwater rice and deepwater rice. LS<sub>GA</sub>/LS<sub>uni</sub> is the ratio of the second leaf sheath length following GA treatment (LS<sub>GA</sub>) to the length with uni (LS<sub>uni</sub>). (C) Length of the internode in response to GA in non-deepwater rice and deepwater rice. Gibberellin and uni mean treatment with 10<sup>−4</sup> M GA + 10<sup>−6</sup> M uni and 10<sup>−6</sup> M uni, respectively. Error bars indicate ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 6). Different letters denote a significant difference (Tukey's test, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).Distribution frequency of TIL, LEI and NEI among the RILs. After 3 weeks of GA treatment, TIL (A), LEI (B) and NEI (C) were measured. White and black arrowheads indicate the phenotypic values for T65 and Bhadua, respectively.Putative QTLs for TIL, LEI and NEI in response to GA. %var, rate of contribution for phenotype. Sig., significance of the QTL was determined by the fitqtl method in R/qtl at **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.Putative QTLs for TIL, LEI and NEI by the two-QTL scan. %var, rate of contribution for phenotype. Sig., significance of the QTL was determined by the fitqtl method in R/qtl at **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.1.Linkage map for the RIL. Lines show the positions of the SNP markers used for the whole-genome survey. The vertical bars to the left of the maps indicate the candidate regions calculated by the lodint method in R/qtl. Arrowheads indicate the positions of the LOD peak for each QTL.Quantitative trait loci for internode elongation in response to GA. (A) LOD score of TIL. (B) LOD score of LEI. (C) LOD score of NEI. Chromosomes with significant LOD values were selected. Dashed lines indicate the values of 1000 permutation tests (PT).Box plots of the phenotypic values for each QTL. The box plots show the distribution of TIL, LEI and NEI value differences between T65 (T) and Bhadua (B), respectively. The values are derived from the phenotypic values at the SNP markers nearest to the peak QTLs.Box plots of the phenotypic values for QTL interactions. The box plots show the distribution of TIL, LEI and NEI value differences between combinations of the T65 (T) and Bhadua (B) genotypes. The values are derived from the phenotypic values at the SNP markers nearest to the peak QTLs.Evaluation of the QTLs on chromosomes 3 and 12. (A) Graphical genotypes of chromosomes 3 and 12. Grey and black boxes indicate T65 chromosomes and C9285 chromosomes, respectively. (B) Length of the elongated internode in response to GA. (C) Length of the elongated internode under deepwater conditions. Plants were submerged for 2 weeks and the internode lengths were measured. Error bars indicate ± SD (<italic>n</italic> = 6).Previously, ethylene-induced internode elongation in deepwater rice was shown to be caused by increased activity of endogenous GA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C30">Raskin and Kende 1984</xref>). Additively, a genetic analysis using F<sub>1</sub> plants of the GA biosynthesis-deficient mutant Tan-ginbozu (a weak allele of ent-kaurene oxidase) and Aswina (deepwater rice) suggested that GA is involved in internode elongation in deepwater rice because the F<sub>1</sub> plants showed a semi-dominant internode elongation phenotype under deepwater conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C36">Suge 1987</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C25">Kutschera and Kende (1988)</xref> also showed that GA controls the internode profile (e.g. extensibility and osmotic potential for internode elongation) of deepwater rice. Furthermore, the endogenous level of GA was increased in deepwater rice under deepwater conditions, but it did not occur in non-deepwater rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Non-deepwater rice induced internode elongation during heading time, and the expression of genes involved in GA biosynthesis and signalling factors has been observed in the elongated internodes of non-deepwater rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C22">Kaneko <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Although previous studies have reported that GA is a critical component of internode elongation in rice, few reports have compared the GA responsiveness of non-deepwater and deepwater rice seedlings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C19">Inouye and Kim 1985</xref>). First, to examine the GA responsiveness of non-deepwater rice and deepwater rice, we applied GA to non-deepwater rice and deepwater rice and measured the length of the second leaf sheath and internode. The second leaf sheath elongated in response to GA in both groups of plants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU028F1">1</xref>). Unexpectedly, whereas deepwater rice induced internode elongation in response to GA, non-deepwater rice did not (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU028F1">1</xref>C). These results indicate the presence of factors that regulate internode-specific elongation in response to GA in deepwater rice seedlings. Given not only the deficiency in GA accumulation but also the absence of GA responsiveness in the internodes of non-deepwater rice seedlings, it appears that non-deepwater rice does not exhibit internode elongation in response to deepwater conditions and GA. Taking our results together, we assumed that a novel factor for GA responsiveness must exist.In this study, CIM and a two-QTL scan for TIL, LEI and NEI detected significant QTLs (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU028F3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU028F4">4</xref>, and Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU028TB1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU028TB2">2</xref>). Interestingly, QTLs were detected on chromosomes 3, 9 and 12 across three phenotypes by CIM and a two-QTL scan. To evaluate the effects of QTLs on chromosomes 3 and 12, we subjected NIL3, NIL12 and NIL3–12 to GA treatment (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU028F7">7</xref>). Although plants carrying the QTL regions on chromosomes 3 and/or 12 were derived from the deepwater rice C9285, internode elongation was stimulated by GA treatment. In particular, NIL3–12, which has the QTLs on chromosomes 3 and 12, strongly induced internode elongation, as compared with NIL3 and NIL12, which have these QTLs singly. These results are consistent with the phenotypic effects in the T65/Bhadua RIL (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU028F6">6</xref>). Since the NILs and RILs were derived from two different deepwater rice varieties, we conclude that these QTLs can lead to internode elongation in response to GA. In previous studies, QTLs of LEI related to deepwater response were detected on chromosomes 3 and 12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C28">Nemoto <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C38">Tang <italic>et al.</italic> 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C13">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C23">Kawano <italic>et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). Because LEI indicated correlations between TIL and NEI, it was proposed that LEI is the most important trait related to internode elongation ability under deepwater conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C18">Inouye 1983</xref>). In addition, the number of non-elongated internodes was reduced by GA treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C37">Takahashi 1991</xref>). This result implies that elongation of the lower internode was induced by GA. Additionally, the GA content of deepwater rice was elevated under deepwater conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Although internode elongation in NIL3, NIL12 and NIL3–12 was induced under deepwater conditions, the magnitudes of the effects were slight when compared with GA treatment (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU028F7">7</xref>). Taken together, our results suggest that chromosome regions in deepwater rice other than the QTL regions on chromosomes 3 and 12 participate in the accumulation of GA under deepwater conditions; the increase in GA responsiveness caused by the QTLs on chromosomes 3 and 12 promotes the onset of lower internode elongation. Consequently, TIL and NEI are enhanced in deepwater rice. It seems that the slight internode elongation of the NILs under deepwater conditions was due to the poor GA biosynthesis ability of these plants; in comparison, the <italic>SK</italic> genes in the QTL region on chromosome 12 caused the elongation of NIL12 and NIL3–12. To test this hypothesis, it is necessary to measure the GA content in the NILs under deepwater conditions. Meanwhile, <italic>qGTIL4</italic>, <italic>qGLEI1</italic>, <italic>qGLEI12</italic> and <italic>qGNEI12</italic> could not be detected without the QTL on chromosome 3 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="PLU028TB2">2</xref>). This result suggests that the QTL on chromosome 3 acts as a central regulator of GA responsiveness. Previously, <italic>O. sativa</italic>-<italic>GROWTH-REGULATING FACTOR1</italic> (<italic>OsGRF1</italic>) and 11 homologues were identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C40">van der Knaap <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C8">Choi <italic>et al.</italic> 2004</xref>). These genes were expected as transcription activators and their expressions were induced in response to exogenous GA and submergence. <italic>OsGRF1</italic> was expressed in the intercalary meristem of the internode in GA-treated or submerged rice, which preceded the expression of marker genes of cell division such as histone H3 and cyclin transcript <italic>cycOs1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C40">van der Knaap <italic>et al.</italic> 2000</xref>). These results imply that <italic>OsGRF1</italic> is involved in GA-dependent stem elongation and meristem maintenance. Although <italic>OsGRF6</italic> and <italic>OsGRF9</italic> were found on chromosome 3, the positions were far from the QTL region on chromosome 3. Hence, the QTL on chromosome 3 is independent of <italic>OsGRF</italic>s. A notable QTL was not found in the QTL region on chromosome 9 in the Q-TARO database (<uri xlink:href="http://qtaro.abr.affrc.go.jp/" xlink:type="simple">http://qtaro.abr.affrc.go.jp/</uri>); thus, the QTL on chromosome 9 may be a new QTL that regulates internode elongation in response to GA. However, the sample size in this study was small to perform high-precision QTL analysis (<italic>n</italic> = 84). A small sample size can lead to the identification of false-positive QTLs. Except for the QTLs on chromosomes 3 and 12, further investigation is necessary to confirm the effects of QTLs on chromosome 9 as well as on the other chromosomes. We previously identified two genes located in the QTL on chromosome 12 that influence the deepwater response, <italic>SK1</italic> and <italic>SK2</italic>. Notably, <italic>SK</italic>s were absent in non-deepwater rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). These <italic>SK</italic>s encode transcription factors possessing an AP2/ERF domain. Only ethylene treatment induced <italic>SK</italic> upregulation; exogenous GA and other phytohormones did not influence <italic>SK</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Although the position of the QTL on chromosome 12 in this study overlapped with the <italic>SK</italic> region, the peak of this QTL was at a distance (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU028F3">3</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C13">Hattori <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C14">2009</xref>). On the other hand, <italic>OsGRF7</italic> was located close to the peak. Hence, it is possible that <italic>OsGRF7</italic> on chromosome 12 regulates GA responsiveness for internode elongation.Previous studies elucidated the GA signalling pathway and downstream factors. Among these, DELLA proteins, which are key regulators of GA signalling, have been characterized in genetic and biochemical studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C17">Ikeda <italic>et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C21">Itoh <italic>et al.</italic> 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C33">Sasaki <italic>et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C39">Ueguchi-Tanaka <italic>et al.</italic> 2007</xref>). In the absence of GA, DELLA proteins function as repressors, leading to plant growth suppression. The DELLA proteins are degraded by 26S proteasome in the presence of GA, and plant growth is released from DELLA suppression. Further, recent reports have suggested that not only DELLA degradation but also DELLA interactions with other factors regulate plant growth, including hypocotyl elongation, GA-jasmonate or -ethylene crosstalk, and seed germination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C43">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C7">Cheminant <italic>et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C2">An <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C42">Yang <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). A DELLA-independent GA response has also been demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="PLU028C12">Fuentes <italic>et al.</italic> 2012</xref>). Based on these reports, the QTL on chromosome 3 and other QTLs may regulate the DELLA function or act downstream of GA signalling. It is also possible that these QTLs induce the formation of a structure that enables internodes to respond to GA.In conclusion, our data showed the presence of factors that regulate internode-specific elongation in response to GA in deepwater rice seedlings. The QTL analysis demonstrated that QTLs on chromosomes 3 and 9 are the main regulators of internode elongation and several QTLs are involved in internode elongation in response to GA (e.g. the QTL on chromosome 12). We previously produced mapping populations for the QTLs on chromosomes 3 and 12. Ongoing studies using these populations will identify genes at each QTL that are responsible for internode elongation in rice. In addition, our data may contribute to the breeding of rice that is adapted for survival in long-term flood areas by raising GA responsiveness.This work was supported by Grants in Aid for Scientific Research (22119007 to M.A.) from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports and Science. This work was also supported by the Japan Science and Technology Agency-Japan International Cooperation Agency within the framework of the SATREPS to M.A.K.N., Y.K., T.K., R.B.A. and T.K. measured the phenotypic values. H.Y. and A.Y. developed RILs. T.N. executed genotyping by BeadXpress. K.N. and M.A. performed QTL analysis.None declared.The following <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aobpla.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/aobpla/plu028/-/DC1" xlink:type="simple">Supporting Information</ext-link> is available in the online version of this article –<bold>Table S1.</bold> Sequences of probe for single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) array.We thank the National Institute of Genetics for providing the rice seeds of C9285 as part of National Bioresource Project of MEXT, Japan.