 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: PB. Performed the experiments: PB. Analyzed the data: PB RK MB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PB RK JPL. Wrote the paper: PB JPL RK MB.  Countries in eastern Africa have set aside significant proportions of their land for protection. But are these areas representative of the diverse range of species and habitats found in the region? And do conservation efforts include areas where the state of biodiversity is likely to deteriorate without further interventions? Various studies have addressed these questions at global and continental scales. However, meaningful conservation decisions are required at finer geographical scales. To operate more effectively at the national level, finer scale baseline data on species and on higher levels of biological organization such as the eco-regions are required, among other factors. Here we adopted a recently developed high-resolution potential natural vegetation (PNV) map for eastern Africa as a baseline to more effectively identify conservation priorities. We examined how well different potential natural vegetations (PNVs) are represented in the protected area (PA) network of eastern Africa and used a multivariate environmental similarity index to evaluate biases in PA versus PNV coverage. We additionally overlaid data of anthropogenic factors that potentially influence the natural vegetation to assess the level of threat to different PNVs. Our results indicate substantial differences in the conservation status of PNVs. In addition, particular PNVs in which biodiversity protection and ecological functions are at risk due to human influences are revealed. The data and approach presented here provide a step forward in developing more transparent and better informed translation from global priorities to regional or national implementation in eastern Africa, and are valid for other geographic regions.  In our compilation, we only considered nationally recognized PAs as these represent areas were the respective national or local governments have a legally binding commitment to protect or use the land and its natural resources in a sustainable way. Where PAs of different IUCN categories overlapped, we assigned the highest IUCN classification ranking to the overlapped areas. Excluded from analysis were areas proposed for protection but not yet assigned protected area status, areas that were represented by point data only and marine locations.  A) The percent area protected of potential natural vegetation types by the protected areas network (GC). B) As A, but only considering the more strictly protected PAs of IUCN class Ib-IV.  A) Scatterplot of the percent area protected (GC) and environmental bias (EB) per potential natural vegetation (PNV). The EB was computed as the absolute difference in the median of the MES1 for the protected areas and the whole PNV, divided by the median absolute deviation of MES1 in the PNV (see text for details). The PNVs are grouped in three classes with small (green), intermediate (blue) and large (red) EB values. Open green circles indicate that the EB does not significantly deviate from 0 (Mann–Whitney with Bonferroni adjustment, two-tailed p&gt;0.05). B) As A, but the GC and EB values given for the PA 1 protected areas only.  For many PNVs (23), the environmental bias is larger when only PA1 are considered, with the opposite being true in only eight cases. Both the smaller numbers and the on average larger size of the PA1 areas may partly explain this observation. For most PNVs it is clear that the less strictly PA2 areas complement the nominally stricter PA1 areas by covering environmental conditions not found in the latter.  A) It combines maps of the 50 PNVs showing how similar environmental conditions in each raster cell are to those in the PA1 + PA2 areas. B) As A, but for PA1 areas only. C) Locations of PA1 and PA2 areas.  A) Map of the distribution of the human influence index (HI), and B) map of the average human influence (HI pnv ) by potential natural vegetation type (PNV).  A) Scatterplot of the average human influence (HI pnv ) and the percent area protected (GC) for PNVs. We defined the CRI (conservation risk index) as the ratio between the HI pnv  and the GC. PNVs with a HI pvn  &gt; 50 and a CRI &gt; 10 were classified as critically endangered; PNVs with a HI pnv  &gt; 40 and CRI &gt; 4 as endangered and PVNs with a HI pnv  &gt; 20 and CRI &gt; 2 as vulnerable. All other PNVs were classified as low risk. Regression statistics: R 2  = 0.35, p &lt; 0.01. B) As A, but with the GC for the PA1 protected areas only. Regression statistics: R 2  = 0.14, p = 0.02.  C1 and H1 are based on all protected areas; C2 and H2 are based on the PA1 protected areas only.  A) The distribution of the potential natural vegetations (PNVs) classified as critically endangered (CR), endangered (EN), vulnerable (VU), and not vulnerable (NV) and the level of environmental bias (EB). High bias (HB), EB &gt; 1; medium bias (MB), 0.5 ≤ EB &lt; 1; slight or no bias (LB), EB &lt; 0.5. B) As A, but for PA1 areas only.  A description of the multivariate similarity index and the environmental bias measure.  (DOCX)  Methods used to compute the human influence  (DOCX)  (TIF)  Stacked barplot with with the percent area protected by country within the PA1 (IUCN categories Ib, II, III and IV) and PA2 (IUCN category VI and unclassified) protected areas. The dots and error bars give the average and standard deviation of the human influence by country.  (TIF)  A) Average and standard deviation of the composite human influence (HI) and the individual HI factors, including the accessibility index (AI), the livestock pressure index (LPI), the human population density index (HPI), the vegetation transformation index (VTI), and the percent area converted to croplands (crops). B) Zonal statistics of the geographic coverage (GC) of the potential natural vegetations (PNVs) in the whole region and by country, (EC) the percent area with environmental conditions that are within the range of conditions found in the protected areas, i.e., MES2&gt;0, and (EB) the environmental bias (see the main body of the text for a definition). Statistics were computed for all protected areas (All) and for the PA1 protected areas only. C) The environmental variables used to compute the environmental representativeness (MES2) and EB.  (XLS)  We are grateful to the Rockefeller Foundation for funding of the Vegetation and Climate change in Eastern Africa (VECEA) project that developed the potential natural vegetation map employed in the current study. We also gratefully acknowledge the many colleagues who have directly or indirectly supported work on this map. We are furthermore grateful to the organizations that freely made available the datasets used in this study. Ian Dawson suggestions to improve the clarity of the manuscript are highly appreciated. Finally, we are grateful for the suggestions provided by Ib Friis and two anonymous reviewers on a draft manuscript. 