Conceived and designed the experiments: AC BL PA. Performed the experiments: AC BL PA. Analyzed the data: AC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AC BL PA. Wrote the paper: AC.The authors have read the journal's policy and have the following conflicts. Optech Int. supported this study and was involved in data collection and analysis. This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.Epi-macrobenthic species richness, abundance and composition are linked with type, assemblage and structural complexity of seabed habitat within coastal ecosystems. However, the evaluation of these habitats is highly hindered by limitations related to both waterborne surveys (slow acquisition, shallow water and low reactivity) and water clarity (turbid for most coastal areas). Substratum type/diversity and bathymetric features were elucidated using a supervised method applied to airborne bathymetric LiDAR waveforms over Saint-Siméon–Bonaventure's nearshore area (Gulf of Saint-Lawrence, Québec, Canada). High-resolution underwater photographs were taken at three hundred stations across an 8-km<sup>2</sup> study area. Seven models based upon state-of-the-art machine learning techniques such as Naïve Bayes, Regression Tree, Classification Tree, C 4.5, Random Forest, Support Vector Machine, and CN2 learners were tested for predicting eight epi-macrobenthic species diversity metrics as a function of the class number. The Random Forest outperformed other models with a three-discretized Simpson index applied to epi-macrobenthic communities, explaining 69% (Classification Accuracy) of its variability by mean bathymetry, time range and skewness derived from the LiDAR waveform. Corroborating marine ecological theory, areas with low Simpson epi-macrobenthic diversity responded to low water depths, high skewness and time range, whereas higher Simpson diversity relied upon deeper bottoms (correlated with stronger hydrodynamics) and low skewness and time range. The degree of species heterogeneity was therefore positively linked with the degree of the structural complexity of the benthic cover. This work underpins that fully exploited bathymetric LiDAR (not only bathymetrically derived by-products), coupled with proficient machine learner, is able to rapidly predict habitat characteristics at a spatial resolution relevant to epi-macrobenthos diversity, ranging from clear to turbid waters. This method might serve both to nurture marine ecological theory and to manage areas with high species heterogeneity where navigation is hazardous and water clarity opaque to passive optical sensors.This work's objectives are to (1) establish the species richness, abundance and composition of the epi-macrobenthic species within the Baie des Chaleurs (Québec, Canada) , (2) retrieve seabed type and diversity data as well as morphometric features from full-waveform LiDAR data, (3) assess the amount of variability in biotic indices that can be reliably predicted by LiDAR-derived controlling factors by means of machine learning techniques, and (4) model the spatial patterns of biotic information across the LiDAR-surveyed whole area using GIS.Water depths ranged from 2.05 to 10.91 m.The α-diversity was defined as the species richness (S) of epi-macrobenthos within each station. Since the observed number of species in the survey is a biased estimator of the true species richness in the area, and since the observed species number increases non-linearly with sampling effort, the species richness of the observed epi-macrobenthic species richness was referred to as species density (d) per m2. The abundance and composition of biotic components were examined by means of seven indices: the overall abundance (A), i.e., sum of the percentages of the colonized surface, and its log transformation, the Simpson diversity index applied to the percentages of the surface (D), expressed as one minus the sum of the squares of the ratio of the image covered by the ith biotic variable with overall abundance, and its log transformation, the Shannon diversity index applied to the percentages of the surface (H'), corresponding to the opposite of the sum of the fraction of the image covered by the ith biotic variable multiplied by the natural logarithm of this same fraction, and its log (X+1) transformation, as well as a modified Pielou evenness (mJ'), computing the ratio between the previous Shannon index and the natural logarithm of the species richness +1.The bathymetric variability and related spatial configuration structuring the neritic benthoscape at fine-scale as well as the seafloor structure and diversity were quantified using the Scanning Hydrographic Operational Airborne LiDAR Survey (SHOALS) system.This signal was acquired at 4.50 m depth and the oblique dashed line consisted of a linear fit of the water column return.Blue tabs indicated initial datasets and the discretization procedure; orange tabs highlighted machine learners used; green tab represented the models' evaluators and red tabs represented analytical evaluators.The Naïve Bayes is a simple probabilistic classifier based on applying Bayes' theorem with strong independence assumptions. Relative frequency was the method used for estimating prior class probabilities from the data, and the classification threshold was fixed at 0.5.The confusion matrix and the Receiver Operating Characteristics (ROC) were exclusively employed for the best learner with the best number of class, and allowed to support finer assessments of performance.The four coloured envelopes correspond to the four nonparametric density contours (each one associated with one evaluator group), drawing a 50% kernel contour shell around the points.Within each node are mentioned the label of the class (1st line), the probability of belonging to the target class (2nd line) and the splitting variable. Above the node is indicated the threshold value related to the splitting variable inherent to the previous node. Pie plots associated with each node show the number of training samples belonging to the &lt;0.3334 (green), [0.3334, 0.6667) (yellow), and &gt;0.6667 (red) classes.The diagonal line (black thin) represents the behaviour of a random classifier. The iso-performance line (black bold) embodies all the points subject to trade-off between true positive (benefits) and false positive (costs), in the ROC space. The confusion matrix is depicted on the bottom right corner.Trendlines correspond to 3-degree polynomial fitting models and R2 stand for the coefficient of determination.Explicitly comparing competitive machine learners enabled to select the Random Forest algorithm (Classification Accuracy: 0.69) and to capture an efficient combination of predictors of epi-macrobenthic Simpson diversity, despite their low Pearson's correlations. Through only three variables derived from bathymetric LiDAR waveform (bathymetry, time range and skewness), efficient predictive mapping of the biotic index was fully driven across turbid nearshore ecosystems.The negative relationship between Simpson index and time range implied that a Simpson-diversified benthic cover was related to a shortening of the benthic return distribution. Taking into account the link between Simpson index and skewness, the latter result could seem paradoxical as it is expected to see a temporal increase of the benthic return. However, the following scenario could suit the change of the benthic return against Simpson index:a. low Simpson diversity over the seabed  = &gt; photons were reflected in a relative short period due to the flatness of the seabed (i.e., acute angle between water column and benthic return), elongated tail of the waveform due to significant noise (positive-skewed benthic return)b. increase of the Simpson diversity over the seabed  = &gt; photons were reflected from and/or absorbed by an increasing suite of horizontal targets-strata inherent to surfaces of the structurally-complex seabed (i.e., less and less acute angle between water column and benthic return), shortening of the tail of the waveform due to the increasing reflection and absorption of photons before the peak of the benthic return (null- and negative-skewed benthic return)c. high Simpson diversity over the seabed  = &gt; photons were reflected from and/or absorbed by a wide range of horizontal targets-strata inherent to surfaces of the structurally-complex seabed (i.e., right or obtuse angle between water column and benthic return), absence of the tail of the waveform due to complete reflection and absorption of photons before the peak of the benthic return (negative-skewed benthic return).The spatial scale at which photographs were acquired played a crucial role in those results. For instance, the species heterogeneity at high depths would have been profoundly reworked (trend to smooth differences) if the acquisition scale has been 10 m. The method of acquisition, besides constraining the scale, filtered out all cryptic and epiphytic macroorganisms. Large and wide thalli of macroalgae have precluded the observation of those organisms (e.g., asteroidea on thalli, echinoidea over seafloor, crustacea in crevices), when the video device projected the volume of algae onto the bottom surface. Both the size and behaviour of biological material strongly conditioned the computed Simpson index.The combination of moderate ground-truth effort (underwater photographs), bathymetric LiDAR and the Random Forest learner allowed to robustly predict the spatial distribution of the Simpson diversity index related to epi-macrobenthic communities over a relatively turbid nearshore area. Bathymetry, skewness and time range were rapidly acquired by airborne LiDAR and had the greatest explanatory power to determine the Simpson diversity response. This species heterogeneity index showed an overall increase in respect to water depth (with a maximum value related to areas inherent to augmented hydrodynamics) and decreased with skewness and time range, which testified the increase of the structural complexity of the benthos/bottom. The degree of species heterogeneity was thereafter linked with the degree of their physical complexity.This study displayed three major novelties within the realm of marine habitat modelling: predicting marine communities' diversity (rather than individual species), employing information from the bathymetric LiDAR full-waveform (not only the bathymetry and its related by-products), as well as confronting the state-of-the-art machine learners.This work underpins that fully-exploited bathymetric LiDAR (not only bathymetrically-derived by-products), coupled with a powerful machine learner, is able to rapidly predict habitat characteristics at a spatial resolution relevant to epi-macrobenthos diversity ranging from clear to turbid waters. This method might serve both to nurture marine ecological theory and to manage areas with high species heterogeneity where navigation is hazardous and water clarity opaque to passive optical sensors.Special thanks to M. Huot for English improvement of the manuscript. This manuscript was greatly improved by the reviews and comments of two anonymous reviewers, whom we deeply thank.