 Conceived and designed the experiments: XW LSC. Performed the experiments: XW LSC. Analyzed the data: XW LSC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: ZH SJD JY FL ZY. Wrote the paper: XW LSC.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Tree survival plays a central role in forest ecosystems. Although many factors such as tree size, abiotic and biotic neighborhoods have been proposed as being important in explaining patterns of tree survival, their contributions are still subject to debate. We used generalized linear mixed models to examine the relative importance of tree size, local abiotic conditions and the density and identity of neighbors on tree survival in an old-growth temperate forest in northeastern China at three levels (community, guild and species). Tree size and both abiotic and biotic neighborhood variables influenced tree survival under current forest conditions, but their relative importance varied dramatically within and among the community, guild and species levels. Of the variables tested, tree size was typically the most important predictor of tree survival, followed by biotic and then abiotic variables. The effect of tree size on survival varied from strongly positive for small trees (1–20 cm dbh) and medium trees (20–40 cm dbh), to slightly negative for large trees (&gt;40 cm dbh). Among the biotic factors, we found strong evidence for negative density and frequency dependence in this temperate forest, as indicated by negative effects of both total basal area of neighbors and the frequency of conspecific neighbors. Among the abiotic factors tested, soil nutrients tended to be more important in affecting tree survival than topographic variables. Abiotic factors generally influenced survival for species with relatively high abundance, for individuals in smaller size classes and for shade-tolerant species. Our study demonstrates that the relative importance of variables driving patterns of tree survival differs greatly among size classes, species guilds and abundance classes in temperate forest, which can further understanding of forest dynamics and offer important insights into forest management.  In this study we assessed the relative importance of tree size, abiotic conditions, and the local biotic neighborhood in driving patterns of tree survival in an old-growth temperate forest in northeastern China at three organizational levels (community, guild and individual species). We used data from multiple censuses of a large (25 ha), fully-mapped forest plot to address the following questions: (1) Does tree size have a consistent positive effect on tree survival? (2) Are abiotic or biotic neighborhood factors more important in influencing spatial patterns of tree survival? (3) Can life history strategy or ecological guild be used to predict the relative importance of factors driving tree survival?  The study area was the Changbai Nature Reserve, which extends along the border of China and North Korea from 127°42′ to 128°17′E and 41°43′ to 42°26′N. It is one of the largest biosphere reserves in China and has been spared from logging and other severe human disturbances. The Changbai Nature Reserve joined the World Biosphere Reserve Network under the UNESCO Man and the Biosphere Programme in 1980. The reserve is ca. 200,000 ha, and elevation ranges from 740 m to 2,691 m at the summit of Changbai Mountain.  Elevation was measured at the corner of each 20 m×20 m quadrat in the 25 ha plot. Elevation values for these 20 m×20 m quadrats were interpolated to calculate the elevation of the corners of the 5 m×5 m subquadrats. Slope and aspect values were then calculated for each subquadrat.  AIC values of the most likely models are shown in bold. Size, Abiotic, Biotic and All factors represent models with only tree size, tree size and abiotic factors, tree size and biotic factors, and all factors included, respectively. Very rare, rare, common, very common denote abundance classes with 1–100, 100–1000, 1000–5000 and &gt;5000 individuals, respectively. Small, medium, and large tree size classes include individuals with 1–20 cm, 20–40 cm, and &gt;40 cm dbh, respectively.  AIC values of the most likely models are shown in bold. Size, Abiotic, Biotic and All factors correspond to models with only tree size, tree size and abiotic factors, tree size and biotic factors, and all factors included, respectively.  However, the best fit models at the community level and for many of the guilds and species examined tended also to include abiotic factors, indicating that abiotic factors do contribute to patterns of tree mortality. Moreover, our study only included topographical and soil nutrient variables, and may have missed some other important abiotic factors, such as light (although variation in light levels will be captured in part by biotic neighborhood variables). It should also be emphasized that our study is constrained to the plot level (i.e. 25 ha) and that abiotic factors were measured at the 5×5 m scale. At larger and smaller spatial scales, the relative importance of abiotic factors may change.  (DOC)  (DOC)  (DOC)  We thank Adrian Das and Richard Condit for valuable comments on the manuscript. We thank the CBS plot census and data management teams, and especially thank Buhang Li, Xuejiao Bai, Liwei Wang, and Dingliang Xing, for assistance with field work and data collection. 