 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: SZ HZ. Performed the experiments: HZ JY CC GD. Analyzed the data: HZ ZP. Wrote the paper: SZ HZ RJ.  The relationship between species richness and evenness across communities remains an unsettled issue in ecology from both theoretical and empirical perspectives. As a result, we do not know the mechanisms that could generate a relationship between species richness and evenness, and how this responds to spatial scale. Here we examine the relationship between species richness(S) and evenness (Pielou’s J′ evenness) using a chronosequence of successional sub-alpine meadow communities in the eastern Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau. These meadows range from natural community (never farmed), to those that have been protected from agricultural exploitation for periods ranging from 1 to 10 years. A total of 30 sampling quadrats with size of 0.5 m×0.5 m were laid out along two transects at each meadow. Using correlation analyses we found a consistent negative correlation between S and J′ in these communities along the successional gradient at the sampling scale of 0.5 m×0.5 m. We also explored the relationship between S and J′ at different sampling scales (from 0.5 m×0.5 m to10 m×10 m) using properly measured ramet-mapped data of a10 m×10 m quadrat in the natural community. We found that S was negatively corrected with J′ at the scales of 0.5 m×0.5 m to 2 m×2 m, but such a relationships disappeared at relative larger scales (≥2 m×4 m). When fitting different species abundance models combined with trait-specific methods, we found that niche preemption may be the determining mechanism of species evenness along the succession gradient. Considering all results together, we can conclude that such niche differentiation and spatial scale effects may help to explain the maintenance of high species richness in sub-alpine meadow communities.  p, p-value; r, correlation coefficient.  p, p-value; r, correlation coefficient.  Considered together, our results demonstrate that niche-preemption is an important mechanism that influences the pattern of the relationship between species evenness and richness along the successional gradient in sub-alpine meadows, and that this relationship is sensitive to the spatial scale of observation. However, stronger tests using field manipulative experiments and more detailed observations are needed to understand the mechanisms that determine species richness and community assembly in these alpine plant communities.  No permits were required to carry out this study.  Sampling was performed in year 2010 in one control meadow (no cropping) and three previously cropped meadows that had been abandoned 1, 3, 7, 9, and 10 years ago, with one meadow of each ‘age’ sampled. All meadows were located within an area of 4000 ha. We use the term ‘successional age’ to refer to the time since each meadow was protected from cropping. Meadows were selected so that meadows with similar successional ages were not closer to each other than to meadows with dissimilar ages. The area of each meadow was at least 120 ha, and had similar orientation, aspect and slope position. An area of 100 m×100 m plot was randomly selected in each meadow. Thirty 50 cm×50 cm quadrats were regularly arranged along the two transects, with 5 m intervals between adjacent quadrats. Grasses were sampled within quadrats in August during the peak of the growing season. In each quadrat, we recorded the number of ramets of each species and species richness.  One 10 m×10 m plot was installed in August during the peak of the growing season in 2011 in the control meadow. We divided each plot regularly into 100 squares of size 1 m×1 m using thin wires. Sampling was conducted at the scale of 0.05 m×0.05 m sub-quadrats. We collected the data of occurrence of species in the sub-quadrats to approximate each ramet of every species.  To explore the effect of spatial scale on the relationship between species richness and evenness, we use Spearman correlation analysis to determine the relationship between S and J′ at different sampling scales in the 10 m×10 m plot. The data of species richness and evenness at a given spatial scale was sampled by continuously locating quadrats of different sizes on the 10 m×10 m plot in the control (natural meadow without farming) meadow. We selected 6 quadrat sizes which increase exponentially in area: 0.5 m×0.5 m (400 quadrats were sampled), 0.5 m×1 m (200), 1 m×1 m (100), 1 m×2 m (50), 2 m×2 m (25), 2 m×4 m (10).  The result of the one-way ANOVA analysis of the variation of evenness along the successional age.  (DOCX)  This work was done in the Research Station of Alpine Meadow and Wetland Ecosystems of Lanzhou University. 