The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: JRW SSH ESB CEAC. Analyzed the data: SSH ESB. Wrote the paper: JRW SSH ESB CEAC. Conducted the fieldwork: JRW CEAC.International efforts to address climate change by reducing tropical deforestation increasingly rely on indigenous reserves as conservation units and indigenous peoples as strategic partners. Considered win-win situations where global conservation measures also contribute to cultural preservation, such alliances also frame indigenous peoples in diverse ecological settings with the responsibility to offset global carbon budgets through fire suppression based on the presumed positive value of non-alteration of tropical landscapes. Anthropogenic fire associated with indigenous ceremonial and collective hunting practices in the Neotropical savannas (cerrado) of Central Brazil is routinely represented in public and scientific conservation discourse as a cause of deforestation and increased CO<sub>2</sub> emissions despite a lack of supporting evidence. We evaluate this claim for the Xavante people of Pimentel Barbosa Indigenous Reserve, Brazil. Building upon 23 years of longitudinal interdisciplinary research in the area, we used multi-temporal spatial analyses to compare land cover change under indigenous and agribusiness management over the last four decades (1973–2010) and quantify the contemporary Xavante burning regime contributing to observed patterns based on a four year sample at the end of this sequence (2007–2010). The overall proportion of deforested land remained stable inside the reserve (0.6%) but increased sharply outside (1.5% to 26.0%). Vegetation recovery occurred where reserve boundary adjustments transferred lands previously deforested by agribusiness to indigenous management. Periodic traditional burning by the Xavante had a large spatial distribution but repeated burning in consecutive years was restricted. Our results suggest a need to reassess overreaching conservation narratives about the purported destructiveness of indigenous anthropogenic fire in the cerrado. The real challenge to conservation in the fire-adapted cerrado biome is the long-term sustainability of indigenous lands and other tropical conservation islands increasingly subsumed by agribusiness expansion rather than the localized subsistence practices of indigenous and other traditional peoples.Photograph by James R. Welch. The legal representative of the depicted individual provided informed written consent for the publication of his image.Permission for the project was provided by the National Indian Foundation (FUNAI) and the National Ethics Committee (CONEP, permission #652-2011).Using Landsat MSS (WRS I Path/Row –240/69; 240/70; 80 meter spatial resolution) and TM (WRS II Path Row –223/69; 223/70; 224/69; 224/70; 30 meter spatial resolution) imagery from the United States Geological Survey (USGS) and Brazilian National Institute for Space Research (INPE), a multi-temporal data set was established for the image dates 1973, 1986, 2000, and 2010. Each date was created using a mosaic of two (1973) and four (1986, 2000, 2010) contiguous images. All images were subjected to radiometric and atmospheric calibrations, georeferenced, and image subsets were layer stacked to form multitemporal images. Image classification was carried out using ERDAS IMAGINE 11.0.4. Deforestation analysis utilized a land cover classification system consisting of water, bare soil/agricultural, grassland/cerrado, and forest.Thematic data extraction for reserve boundaries and a 20 km buffer zone around the reserve was carried out using the tabulate area tool in ArcGIS 10.1. Classification procedure for the 1973 image was based on unsupervised procedures only; for 1986, 2000, and 2010 classification was based on a hybrid approach (i.e., involving integration of unsupervised and supervised classifiers). Images were independently classified. Image classification benefited from field collected georeferenced training samples. Field sites representative of natural vegetation were used as references for all dates, while recently altered sites were used as references for 2010. A layer of field sites was created and referenced into the multi-temporal image dataset.Unsupervised analysis using ISODATA started with high-dimensional unsupervised clustering (50 classes) of the whole image area. Classes were analyzed according to spectral-structural differences (relationship between spectral data and indicators of vegetation structure), spatial distribution, and statistical values (mean, standard deviation, and covariance) for all spectral bands except thermal. Using supervised procedures, training samples with known vegetation and history of land use were created and used to develop spectral signatures for the classes of interest in each data set for 1986, 2000, and 2010. Training samples and unsupervised classes were combined into a single spectral signature file. Analysis of training samples and unsupervised signatures include a combination of Transformed Divergence separability analysis, spectral signature comparison, and correlation analysis of spectral-vegetation data. Based on these procedures, signatures were merged (or eliminated) to produce a final signature set representing a gradient of vegetation structure, from bare soil/agricultural to high forest. Signature sets were submitted to a probability-based Gaussian Maximum-Likelihood classifier. Classification accuracy of the 2010 classified image was assessed for aggregated classes (i.e., bare soil/agricultural, grassland/cerrado, and forests) used in transition matrix analysis. A set of 30 test fields of known features (i.e., training samples not used for supervised classification) was used to assess the accuracy of each class. Classification accuracy ranged from 91% for bare soil/agricultural, 86% for grassland/cerrado, and 84% for forests. Confusion between classes occurred mainly in areas of transitional vegetation structure with mixed elements of soil, herbaceous, arbustive, and arboreal coverage.Legal descriptions of historical reserve boundaries (dates 1972–1975, 1975–1979, 1979–1986, and 1986-present) were digitally reconstructed from archival maps and descriptive documents of delimiting landmarks and overlaid on the multi-temporal image dataset in ArcGIS. Analyses of deforestation trajectories were developed by calculating transition matrices in ERDAS IMAGINE for each subsequent pair of images starting with the earliest date (1973–1986, 1986–2000, and 2000–2010). For the transition matrix analysis grassland and cerrado classes were aggregated. Deforestation was considered when a shrub or arboreous class converted into bare soil or agricultural fields/pasture) at a subsequent date. Areas of bare soil/agricultural that returned into grassland/cerrado or forest classes were recoded as such to indicate a reforestation process. The final thematic layer produced eight classes, including those that remained unaltered across dates (i.e., water, bare soil/agricultural, grassland/cerrado, and forest) and those involving change, including deforestation before 1973, deforestation between 1973 and 1986, deforestation between 1986 and 2000, and deforestation between 2000 and 2010. The final layer was recoded to show the area deforested for each period. We used cross-tabulation in ArcGIS to allow estimation of deforestation during each period within (respective reserve boundaries) and outside (respective buffer zones) the reserve.Burned areas within reserve boundaries in the years 2007–2010 were mapped using Landsat TM and ETM+ imagery from the United States Geological Survey (USGS). Images free of clouds were acquired for each month from July-September for each of the four years to capture the primary annual burning season. As with the land-cover classifications, the imagery used for burned area mapping were coregistered to ensure spatial accuracy. Each image was classified using the ISODATA clustering algorithm in ERDAS IMAGINE. Fifty clusters were initially created using a convergence threshold of 0.995. Burned areas were isolated from other land covers through spectral signature analysis and visual interpretation. Mixed pixels indicating burning scars were manually digitized if necessary. Classifications from all months in the same year were then mosaicked and manually cleaned before running a 3×3 majority filter to complete the burned area classification. Each pair of years was subjected to a transition matrix analysis to estimate areas of consecutive burnings: first the transition from 2007 to 2008, second the transition from 2007/2008 to 2009, and third the transition from 2007/2008/2009 to 2010. A final transition matrix image 2007–2010 comprised of 5 classes was created to illustrate land area by number of consecutive years burned (i.e., burning in no more than 0, 1, 2, 3, and 4 consecutive years).Landsat MSS and TM imagery used in our analyses was obtained courtesy of the United States Geological Survey (USGS) and from the Brazilian National Institute for Space Research (INPE) under Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License.Landsat TM and ETM+ imagery used in our analyses were obtained courtesy of the United States Geological Survey (USGS).Photograph by James R. Welch.Photograph by Carlos E. A. Coimbra Jr.Welch and Coimbra thank the members of the Xavante villages Pimentel Barbosa and Etênhiritipá for their participation and support during research activities. In particular, our field activities benefitted from assistance by Tsuptó Bruprewem Wairi Xavante, José Paulo Seriuwarão Xavante, Marco Aurelio Serenho Ihi Xavante, Tsidowi Wai’adzatse’, Wahipó Xavante, and Pari'õwá Xavante. Brondízio and Hetrick express thanks for the support of Indiana University and the Anthropological Center for Training and Research on Global Environmental Change (ACT), the Institut d'Études Avancées (IEA), Paris, and the Institut des Hautes Études de l′Amérique Latine at Université Sorbonne Nouvelle, Paris.