The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: TER AHB. Performed the experiments: TER. Analyzed the data: TER. Wrote the paper: TER TB JC AHB.Understanding patterns in species richness and diversity over environmental gradients (such as altitude and depth) is an enduring component of ecology. As most biological communities feature few common and many rare species, quantifying the presence and abundance of rare species is a crucial requirement for analysis of these patterns. Coral reefs present specific challenges for data collection, with limitations on time and site accessibility making efficiency crucial. Many commonly used methods, such as line intercept transects (LIT), are poorly suited to questions requiring the detection of rare events or species. Here, an alternative method for surveying reef-building corals is presented; the point count transect (PCT). The PCT consists of a count of coral colonies at a series of sample stations, located at regular intervals along a transect. In contrast the LIT records the proportion of each species occurring under a transect tape of a given length. The same site was surveyed using PCT and LIT to compare species richness estimates between the methods. The total number of species increased faster per individual sampled and unit of time invested using PCT. Furthermore, 41 of the 44 additional species recorded by the PCT occurred ≤ 3 times, demonstrating the increased capacity of PCT to detect rare species. PCT provides a more accurate estimate of local-scale species richness than the LIT, and is an efficient alternative method for surveying reef corals to address questions associated with alpha-diversity, and rare or incidental events.a) overview of transect with count stations, b) one count sample (12 colonies). Shaded shapes represent recorded colonies, with numbers representing the progressive sampling order. Directionality of the count progression (in this case counterclockwise) is flexible, but should be decided prior to the study.Comparative surveys were conducted along the upper reef slope of ‘Big Vickies’ reef, Lizard Island, Australia (145.44° E, 14.683° S). No permit was required from the Great Barrier Reef Marine Park Authority (GBRMPA) due to the limited impact (non-extractive) nature of the research, conducted under the accreditation of James Cook University. Only visual surveys were conducted, and no endangered or protected species were collected or manipulated. Transects to be used for both methods were laid end to end along the reef slope where there was contiguous hard substrata between 2 and 4 m depth. Nineteen replicate 10 m LITs surveys were conducted, covering the same linear reef area as the PCT while representing a sampling intensity significantly greater than the three to five transect recorded in most studies. In addition to species identity, we recorded the time taken to complete each transect. We then conducted 4 PCTs of 50 m in length (containing 6 count stations per transect at 10 m intervals) as described above overlying the same reef area. The time taken to complete each survey was recorded.Species richness (y axis) by number of individual colonies sampled (x axis). Solid lines represent observed species richness, dashed lines show projected species richness rarefied to ~600 individuals, with corresponding 95% CI intervals (shaded area).Species richness (y axis) by number of minutes invested in sampling (x axis). Solid lines represent observed species richness, dashed lines show projected species richness rarefied to ~600 individuals, with corresponding 95% CI intervals (shaded area).The PCT was developed to assess patterns of species richness and meta-community structure along steep environmental gradients (e.g. depth) on coral reefs. These types of research questions do not require metrics of absolute abundance such as coral cover, which can be effectively obtained using LITs. As a result, the PCT represents a complementary data collection technique, rather than a replacement. The sensitivity of the PCT to rare and incidental species allows insight into the poor detection by the LIT, but emphasizes rapid capture of richness at the expense of absolute abundance measures. Using the PCT without considering its own strengths and weaknesses to a specific research question will likely result in an equally erroneous result as misuse of the LIT. Where detection of rare species is important, we propose the PCT as a robust and time-efficient method of collecting ecological data on coral reefs. This method will be particularly effective for examining questions such depth-diversity gradients, where the amount of survey time is greatly restricted. While this protocol was tested in a highly species rich habitat, with high coral abundance, it is applicable to any environment. The flexibility of the methodological framework allows for adjustment to specific systems, and questions.Coral reef ecologists should continue to develop new and improved methodologies to overcome logistical constraints, and improve the precision and scope of available data. Establishing the real-world strengths and weaknesses of various methodologies enables more researchers to make a more informed decision when collecting data. Methods such as the PCT can complement existing techniques, enabling researchers to better match data collection to suit the desired analysis.(XLSX)We would like to thank Martina Prazeres for field assistance, and for comments on the manuscript. We would also like to thank the Lizard Island Research Station for facilitating the research.