 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: JCMF DF EMN. Performed the experiments: JCMF. Analyzed the data: JCMF DF EMN JR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JCMF DF EMN JR. Wrote the paper: JCMF DF EMN JR.  We excluded those sites that were located at a distance of less than 1 km from the closest site to avoid recounting individuals that have high dispersal ability and large home ranges (e.g., falcons and parrots). We randomly selected 40 sites that had 6% to 85% forest cover within a radius of 2 km. Twelve sites had 6% to 30% forest cover, 13 sites had 31% to 50%, and 15 sites had 51% to 85%. The distance between sites ranged from 1 to 105 km. We did not sample in either of the protected areas, and no specific permission was required for the selected locations. However, we secured permission to conduct fieldwork in all sampling sites that were located on private land.  We first evaluated the effect of variation in bird diversity based on biogeographical factors by means of a Mantel test between the geographical distance matrix and two matrices of differences in species richness and abundance between pairs of sampling sites. We then assessed the relationship between the number of species (richness) and the total number of individuals (abundance) of the most representative groups (overall species, generalists, forest-specialist, forest frugivores and forest insectivores) and forest amount in the 40 sites. Total richness and abundance in each site were considered as the sum of the number of species and individuals, respectively, recorded during the three field campaigns in the four counting points. We used a null model, a generalized linear model and a logistic model with four parameters to evaluate the bird response types (linear and nonlinear). We assumed a Poisson error distribution for the abundance and species richness data in each of the models.  Landscapes vary in the amount of remaining forest cover from 6% to 85%. Lines correspond to the best fitting models.  Models: Null model (NULL), generalized linear model (GLM) and logistic model with four parameters (FLM). AICc: Akaike information criterion corrected; Œî i : difference in AICc between the best model and the ith model; k: parameter number of the model; w i : AICc weight. Models are ranked by AICc values.  Landscapes vary in the amount of remaining forest cover from 6% to 85%. Lines correspond to the best fitting models.  Black points represent the scores of landscapes and the numbers indicate the percentages of forest cover (from 6% to 85%). A: Forest-specialist birds, B: Generalist birds, C: Frugivorous birds, D: Insectivorous birds. Pairwise ANOSIM tests showed significant differences (p &lt; 0.05) between the bird compositions of landscapes with percentages of forest cover that were less than (left polygons) and greater than (right polygons) the threshold values.  The vertical line indicates the threshold value estimated by the piecewise model.  (TIF)  The vertical line indicates the threshold value estimated by the piecewise model.  (TIF)  The vertical line indicates the threshold value estimated by the piecewise model.  (TIF)  The vertical line indicates the threshold value estimated by the piecewise model.  (TIF)  (DOCX)  We thank D√©bora Sales-de-Aquino, √caro Menezes, F√°bio Falc√£o, Igor Inforzato and Alessandro Santos for their help with the field work; local landowners for providing logistical assistance; and Superintend√™ncia de Estudos Econ√¥micos e Sociais da Bahia (Bahia-SEI) for the RapidEye images. We thank Gil Reuss and Diogo Carib√© for help with mapping the study area. This is publication number 07 of the REDE SISBIOTA (CNPq 563216/2010-7). 