The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: JL. Performed the experiments: JL YC. Analyzed the data: YC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YW PS. Wrote the paper: YC. Helped in field experiments and data analysis: JS PZ.Soil respiration (SR) is an important process in the global carbon cycle. It is difficult to estimate SR emission accurately because of its temporal and spatial variability. Primary forest succession on Glacier forehead provides the ideal environment for examining the temporal-spatial variation and controlling factors of SR. However, relevant studies on SR are relatively scarce, and variations, as well as controlling factors, remain uncertain in this kind of region. In this study, we used a static chamber system to measure SR in six sites which represent different stages of forest succession on forehead of a temperate glacier in Gongga Mountain, China. Our results showed that there was substantial temporal (coefficient of variation (CV) ranged from 39.3% to 73.9%) and spatial (CV ranged from 12.3% to 88.6%) variation in SR. Soil temperature (ST) at 5 cm depth was the major controlling factor of temporal variation in all six sites. Spatial variation in SR was mainly caused by differences in plant biomass and Total N among the six sites. Moreover, soil moisture (SM), microbial biomass carbon (MBC), soil organic carbon (SOC), pH and bulk density could influence SR by directly or indirectly affecting plant biomass and Total N. Q<sub>10</sub> values (ranged from 2.1 to 4.7) increased along the forest succession, and the mean value (3.3) was larger than that of temperate ecosystems, which indicated a general tendency towards higher-Q<sub>10</sub> in colder ecosystems than in warmer ecosystems. Our findings provided valuable information for understanding temporal-spatial variation and controlling factors of SR.According to the Chinese Glacier Inventory, there are 8607 monsoonal temperate glaciers in China. Hailuogou Glacier, located on the east slope of Gongga Mountain in China, is one of temperate glaciers. Our study was conducted in stands representing different stages of primary succession on the forehead of Hailuogou Glacier. The objectives of this study were to (i) identify the temporal and spatial variation of SR in different stages of primary forest succession on the forehead of a temperate glacier; (ii) distinguish the controlling factors of temporal and spatial variation of SR within and across the succession stages.ST means soil temperature at 5 cm depth; SM means soil moisture in the topsoil (0–20 cm); Biomass means plant biomass of stand which was extracted from unpublished data; Total N and SOC represent total nitrogen and soil organic carbon in the top 20 cm depth respectively; MBC means microbial biomass nitrogen in the top 20 cm depth soil.All necessary permits were obtained for the described field studies. We carried out the study based on Alpine Ecosystem Observation and Experiment Station of Gongga Mountain, which belongs to the Institute of Mountain Hazards and Environment, Chinese Academy of Sciences &amp; Ministry of Water Conservancy. We obtained the permissions from the station and institute to use the sample plots, our study had no harm to the environment and the field study did not involve endangered or protected species.SR, ST and SM means soil respiration, soil temperature and soil moisture, respectively. The six sites represent different stages of forest succession on forehead of Hailougou Glacier in Gongga Mountain, China.(A) Temporal CV of soil respiration for all six sites; (B) spatial CV of soil respiration during the whole year.Three 10 m×10 m plots were randomly located within each site. SR rates were measured about every 5 days in the year 2009, using a soil chamber (LI-6400–09, Li-Cor, Inc., Lincoln, NE) connected to a portable infrared gas analyzer (IRGA, Li-Cor, Inc., Lincoln, NE). To minimize soil surface disturbances, the chamber was mounted on polyvinyl chloride (PVC) soil collars inserted into the soil 2 or 3 cm. Three PVC collars were randomly placed in each plot one day before the measurements. A measurement consisted of placing the chamber on soil collar, scrubbing the CO<sub>2</sub> to sub-ambient levels, and determining soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux over several 5-s periods. Data were recorded at 5-s intervals by the datalogger in the LI-Cor 6400 console. Each measurement usually took 1–3 min after placing the chamber on the collar. Concurrent measurements were made on the same day on each occasion at all six sites.ST is soil temperature at 5 cm depth (°C), SM means soil moisture in the topsoil (0–20 cm), SR is monthly mean soil respiration (µ mol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>), Q<sub>10</sub> is calculated from equation Q<sub>10</sub> = exp(10β), three asterisk means p&lt;0.001.Five 1 m×1 m litter traps were placed randomly in each plot and we collected litter from the traps monthly in 2009 for this study. All litter samples were cleaned, oven dried at 60°C for 48 h and recorded the final dry weight.We applied monthly and yearly values of SR to further investigation. Monthly values were calculated as mean SR on the observation days each month. Then we used the monthly values to calculate the sum for the year. One-way ANOVA was used to compare differences in mean values of SR, ST and SM among the six sites. Pearson correlation analysis was used to examine the relationship between SR and ST/SM in each site. Liner regression model was applied to describe the relationship between mean annual SR and mean ST, mean SM, mean litterfall, biomass, SOC, Total N, MBC, pH and bulk density among the six sites. All statistical analyses were conducted using SAS 9.0.SR means soil respiration. Different letters denote significant differences among means (á = 0.05) as determined by Turkey’s HSD test.SR represented soil respiration; The driving factors were soil temperature (ST) at 5 cm depth (A), litterfall input (B), soil moisture (SM, C), plant biomass (D), total nitrogen (Total N, E), soil organic carbon (SOC, F), microbial biomass carbon (MBC, G), pH (H) and bulk density (I).ST, soil temperature; SM, soil moisture; Biomass, plant biomass; Total N, total nitrogen; SOC, soil organic carbon; MBC, microbial biomass nitrogen.Caret, p&gt;0.05;one asterisk, p&lt;0.05;two asterisk, p&lt;0.01;three asterisk, p&lt;0.001.In summary, we investigated the temporal-spatial variation and the controlling factors of SR in different stages of forest succession on Hailuogou Glacier forehead in Gongga Mountain. Our results indicated that SR was high in growing season and low in non-growing season for all the six sites, and the total annual SR tended to increase with the progress of succession. ST was the main controlling factor of temporal variation of SR. In contrast, spatial variation in SR could be mainly attributed to plant biomass and Total N, while the other variables (SM, MBC SOC, pH and bulk density) could affect SR by directly or indirectly influencing plant biomass and Total N. Q<sub>10</sub> values increased along the forest succession, and the mean value was larger than that of temperate ecosystems, which indicated a general tendency towards higher-Q<sub>10</sub> in colder ecosystems than in warmer ecosystems. Our findings show that successional stage affects microclimate, plant and microbial biomass and soil properties, thus directly and indirectly influencing SR.We thank Qiao Liu for providing the map data of Hailuogou Glacier and Yang Cao for providing some foundation data of Alpine Ecosystem Observation and Experiment Station of Gongga Mountain.