The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: JW, YG. Performed the experiments: TC, YB, BYQ, CBZ. Analyzed the data: JW. Wrote the paper: JW, YG.Phytoextraction is an environmentally acceptable and inexpensive technique for mine tailing rehabilitation that uses metallophyte plants. These plants reduce the soil trace metal contents to environmentally acceptable levels by accumulating trace metals. Recently, whether more trace metals can be removed by species-rich communities of these plants received great attention, as species richness has been reported having positive effects on ecosystem functions. However, how the species richness affects trace metals removal of plant communities of mine tailing is rarely known.We examined the effects of species richness on soil trace metal removal in both natural and experimental plant communities. The root lengths and stem heights of each plant species were measured in order to calculate the functional diversity indices. Our results showed that trace metal (Cu, Cd, Pb and Zn) concentrations in mine tailing soil declined as species richness increased in both the natural and experimental plant communities. Species richness, rather than functional diversity, positively affected the mineralomass of the experimental plant communities. The intensity of plant-plant facilitation increased with the species richness of experimental communities. Due to the incremental role of plant-plant facilitation, most of the species had higher biomasses, higher trace metal concentrations in their plant tissues and lower malondialdehyde concentrations in their leaves. Consequently, the positive effects of species richness on mineralomass were mostly attributable to facilitation among plants.Our results provide clear evidence that, due to plant-plant facilitation, species richness positively affects the removal of trace metals from mine tailing soil through phytoextraction and provides further information on diversity conservation and environmental remediation in a mine tailing environment.No specific permissions were required for this research. The natural plant community experiment was conducted on Huangyan Pb/Zn mine tailings. The exploitation and processing of minerals from the Huangyan Pb/Zn mine stopped about 20 years ago and now plants spontaneously grow on the mine tailings. Consequently, this site is open and no permissions were required to conduct the experiment. The experimental plant community experiment was located at Taizhou University. Some of the authors of the manuscript are Taizhou University staff and the site used for the study was at the authors' experimental research center. Consequently, no specific permissions were needed to conduct the experimental trial on this site. The plant species used in this study were not endangered or protected species.Footnotes: Species abbreviations and their corresponding full names are listed in Table S1.Footnotes: Species abbreviations and their corresponding full names are listed in Table S1.The experimental plant communities were harvested on May 10<sup>th</sup>, 2010. All the aboveground and belowground biomasses (living plants) were sorted into species, dried and weighed separately. Before biomass harvesting, a water treatment experiment was conducted. The water content of each pot was determined 5 days after it received the same amount of water through artificial spraying (no water was added during the final 5 days before harvesting). Five soil cores, to a depth of 0–20 cm, were randomly collected from each pot and then combined into one sample. Soil water content was calculated by comparing the wet and dry soil masses (mass of wet soil − mass of dry soil)/mass of dry soil). A proportion of each soil sample was air-dried at room temperature, homogenized and sieved (&lt;2 mm) in order to determine the soil trace metal concentrations (Cu, Cd, Pb and Zn) and total N. The soil trace metal concentrations and total N were measured using the same method employed in the natural plant communities experiment.The total trace metal content accumulated in the plants (mineralomass) was used to reflect the trace metal removal efficiency by the plants. The mineralomass of a species in one pot was calculated as follows:The mineralomass of the plant communities in each pot was the sum of the mineralomasses of all the component species.Footnotes: the values in the brackets are p-value.Survival ratio  =  the survival number of plants in a certain species richness level/the total planted number in the corresponding species richness level.Footnotes: Species abbreviations and their corresponding full names are listed in Table S1.Our results demonstrated that species-rich plant communities had lower soil trace metal (Cu, Cd, Pb and Zn) concentrations in both the natural and the experimental plant communities than the species-poor communities. More importantly, we found that species richness had significantly positive effects on mineralomass in the experimental plant communities. Consequently, it is almost certain that the positive effects of species richness on mineralomass led to the lower soil trace metal concentrations seen in the more diverse plant communities.(DOC)We thank Xiu Bai and Xing Luo for help in the field and two anonymous referees for their helpful comments.