 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: RMP DJH. Performed the experiments: RMP. Analyzed the data: RMP DJH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LCG DJH AAA. Wrote the paper: RMP. Provided background data and logistical support: LCG AAA. Provided substantial revisions: DJH LCG AAA.  Experiments with realistic scenarios of species loss from multitrophic ecosystems may improve insight into how biodiversity affects ecosystem functioning. Using 1000 L mesocoms, we examined effects of nonrandom species loss on community structure and ecosystem functioning of experimental food webs based on multitrophic tropical floodplain lagoon ecosystems. Realistic biodiversity scenarios were developed based on long-term field surveys, and experimental assemblages replicated sequential loss of rare species which occurred across all trophic levels of these complex food webs. Response variables represented multiple components of ecosystem functioning, including nutrient cycling, primary and secondary production, organic matter accumulation and whole ecosystem metabolism. Species richness significantly affected ecosystem function, even after statistically controlling for potentially confounding factors such as total biomass and direct trophic interactions. Overall, loss of rare species was generally associated with lower nutrient concentrations, phytoplankton and zooplankton densities, and whole ecosystem metabolism when compared with more diverse assemblages. This pattern was also observed for overall ecosystem multifunctionality, a combined metric representing the ability of an ecosystem to simultaneously maintain multiple functions. One key exception was attributed to time-dependent effects of intraguild predation, which initially increased values for most ecosystem response variables, but resulted in decreases over time likely due to reduced nutrient remineralization by surviving predators. At the same time, loss of species did not result in strong trophic cascades, possibly a result of compensation and complexity of these multitrophic ecosystems along with a dominance of bottom-up effects. Our results indicate that although rare species may comprise minor components of communities, their loss can have profound ecosystem consequences across multiple trophic levels due to a combination of direct and indirect effects in diverse multitrophic ecosystems.  Here we present findings from a mesocosm experiment that tested the influence of nonrandom species loss on community structure and ecosystem multifunctionality. Long-term field data from floodplain lagoons were used to identify realistic experimental assemblages. Treatments replicating sequential loss of rare fish species were established using nested subsets of species from a summed rank abundance curve generated from the observed abundances of all species across lagoons. Our diverse experimental ecosystems include complex multitrophic interactions among taxa (i.e. within fish assemblages) and across the aquatic community (e.g. fish, zooplankton, and phytoplankton), thereby providing insight into interactions within (competitive effects) and across (consumptive effects) trophic levels. This study builds on previous research by testing effects of realistic scenarios of nonrandom species loss in a complex multitrophic system, and expands the scope of such studies to species-rich and under-represented ecosystems of the Neotropics. The main objectives of this study were to (1) investigate the effect of sequential loss of rare fish species on community and ecosystem responses over time, and (2) identify direct trophic interactions within these experimental food webs by which loss of rare species affected ecosystem multifunctionality.  All species were properly collected and handled in an ethical manner and with all required permissions from the Brazilian Environmental Ministry (Ministério do Meio Ambiente (MMA), Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade (ICMBio), Sistema de autorização e informação em Biodiversidade (SISBIO)) under protocol number 22442-1, authentication code: 3263346. No other permissions were required for completion of this research, and this study does not include endangered or otherwise protected species.  A) Rank abundance curve of 59 fish species derived from community sampling data from isolated lagoons (n = 11) in the Upper Paraná River floodplain during austral spring from 2000–2007. Species to the left of the dashed line represent the pool of species (n = 18) used in the experiment. B) Proportional rank abundance curve of the 18 species from (A) that provides the basis for experiment stocking abundances. C) Example of stocking abundances for the 18 species richness treatment (total 65 individuals per mesocosm).  Residuals are from simple linear regression of the response variable and fish biomass, and therefore are measures of the response variable among treatments that control for the potentially confounding effect of fish biomass.  (PDF)  (PDF)  (PDF)  (PDF)  (XLSX)  (PDF)  (PDF)  We would like to thank F. A. Teixeria, V. A. Capatti, J. R. Gonçalves, V. R. Casaré, J. D. Latini, A. S. da Silva, and S. Rodrigues for invaluable help in the field. J. E. Hoffman, L. J. Driver, J. C. B. da Silva, B. R. Belini, A. G. Bifi, D. P. Lima Jr., R. M. Tofoli, and W. M. Domingues for tremendous effort and support while conducting the experiment. M. D. C. Roberto, C. C. Bonecker, and S. M. Thomaz for technical analysis and guidance. NUPELIA of the Universidade Estadual de Maringá for providing critical support, equipment, and use of their field station and the Upper Paraná River Floodplain Long Term Ecological Research Program for extensive community datasets and logistical support. 