Conceived and designed the experiments: JTL MR. Performed the experiments: JSM ZM. Analyzed the data: JTL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JTL. Wrote the paper: JTL JSM ZM MR.Current address: Biology Department, University of Regina, Regina, Saskatchewan, CanadaThe authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Green roofs perform ecosystem services such as summer roof temperature reduction and stormwater capture that directly contribute to lower building energy use and potential economic savings. These services are in turn related to ecosystem functions performed by the vegetation layer such as radiation reflection and transpiration, but little work has examined the role of plant species composition and diversity in improving these functions.We used a replicated modular extensive (shallow growing- medium) green roof system planted with monocultures or mixtures containing one, three or five life-forms, to quantify two ecosystem services: summer roof cooling and water capture. We also measured the related ecosystem properties/processes of albedo, evapotranspiration, and the mean and temporal variability of aboveground biomass over four months. Mixtures containing three or five life-form groups, simultaneously optimized several green roof ecosystem functions, outperforming monocultures and single life-form groups, but there was much variation in performance depending on which life-forms were present in the three life-form mixtures. Some mixtures outperformed the best monocultures for water capture, evapotranspiration, and an index combining both water capture and temperature reductions. Combinations of tall forbs, grasses and succulents simultaneously optimized a range of ecosystem performance measures, thus the main benefit of including all three groups was not to maximize any single process but to perform a variety of functions well.Ecosystem services from green roofs can be improved by planting certain life-form groups in combination, directly contributing to climate change mitigation and adaptation strategies. The strong performance by certain mixtures of life-forms, especially tall forbs, grasses and succulents, warrants further investigation into niche complementarity or facilitation as mechanisms governing biodiversity-ecosystem functioning relationships in green roof ecosystems.Heating degree days calculated as the number of days or fraction thereof for which temperatures were below 15°C times (15 (°C) – temperature).Cooling degree days calculated as the number of days or fraction thereof for which temperatures were above 18°C times (temperature (°C) - 18).The best ten treatments for each performance measure are in bold (for aboveground biomass variability and surface temperature, optimal functioning is indicated by the lowest values).We planted 21 individual plants in each module (regardless of the number of life-form groups present) in four rows of four plants (on 9 cm centers) and a center row of five plants (on 7 cm centers). For unvegetated modules, 21 potting soil plugs were inserted into the growing medium in the same pattern. Twenty-one plants per module was chosen as the density level because it represented a reasonable (in terms of growing space) multiple of the number of species per life-form group. The planting sequence involved alternating life-form groups (if more than one group was included in a module), with the life-form and species pattern being randomly chosen (without replacement) until all species to be included had been selected once, after which, the same pattern was repeated throughout the module until a total of 21 plants had been included.To quantify water capture, we added 1300 mL of tap water (equivalent to a 10 mm rain event) to each module four times (June 1, July 8, August 4 and August 26 2009). Water was added to the surface of the growing medium in each module over a period of approximately 30 s. We weighed each module prior to adding water and again ten minutes post-watering. The ten-minute delay ensured that any excess water (runoff) drained out of the module and that the growing medium was near field capacity. Capture was expressed as the pre-watering weight subtracted from the post-watering weight (kg of water captured). Our estimate of water capture is likely conservative since water was applied rapidly (simulating a high intensity rain event that would likely occur over a longer time period if the same amount of water fell during a natural event). Furthermore, rain can be intercepted by the vegetation canopy and re-evaporated without entering the growing medium. We did not quantify this potential capture in our experiment as water was added at the base of the vegetation.The solid line is fitted from a regression (±95% CI) of the ecosystem property on the number of planted species (unplanted controls omitted). This is the same data as in Figure 1, without the substrate-only controls, and with number of species planted, instead of the number of functional groups on the x-axis to permit comparison in a regression framework. (A) R<sup>2</sup><sub>adj</sub> = 0.27, F<sub>1,131</sub> = 54.63, P = 1.20×10<sup>-11</sup>; (B) R<sup>2</sup><sub> adj</sub> = 0.07, F<sub>1,131</sub> = 11.58, P = 8.80×10<sup>-4</sup>; (C) R<sup>2</sup><sub> adj</sub> = 0.12, F<sub>1,131</sub> = 18.47, P = 3.33×10<sup>-5</sup>; (D) R<sup>2</sup><sub> adj</sub> = 0.23, F<sub>1,131</sub> = 41.43, P = 2.11×10<sup>-9</sup>; (E) R<sup>2</sup><sub> adj</sub> = 0.19, F<sub>1,131</sub> = 31.97, P = 9.36×10<sup>-8</sup>; (F) R<sup>2</sup><sub> adj</sub> = 0.14, F<sub>1,131</sub> = 22.45, P = 5.54×10<sup>-6</sup>; (G) R<sup>2</sup><sub> adj</sub> = 0.08, F<sub>1,129</sub> = 11.75, P = 8.18×10<sup>-4</sup>. The horizontal dashed line represents the value of the best performing monoculture replicate. For (A) surface temperature, and (G) temporal variability in aboveground biomass, lower values indicate improved performance. In treatments with three life-form groups, those modules containing the tall forb group are in green, whereas combinations not including tall forbs are in black. Monoculture treatments are grouped by life-form such that all three species within a life-form group have the same colour.Methods and Materials. Detailed methods for the built-in green roof system: used here only to derive estimates of conventional roof temperature, heat flux and albedo.(0.03 MB DOC)Modular green roof assembly.(0.09 MB DOC)Study site for life-form group experiment, showing shadow perpendicular to block arrangement.(0.87 MB DOC)Diagram of built-in green roof system with sensor locations.(0.09 MB DOC)Multiple regression models of ecosystem services and properties for green roof modules planted with monocultures and one, three or five life-form groups (not including growing medium-only controls).(0.07 MB DOC)We thank Deanna Bru and Asha MacDonald for assistance on the roof, and Sarah Robinson for propagating plants. H. H. Bruun, M. Huston, C. Butler and an anonymous reviewer provided helpful comments on earlier drafts of the paper.