 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: VAR MAHR JAM MMR. Performed the experiments: MAHR GJ GIM EM. Analyzed the data: MAHR VAR. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: VAR MAHR JAM MMR EM FPLM BAS. Wrote the paper: MAHR VAR JAM MMR EM BAS FPLM GIM. Plant species identification: MAHR GIM EM.  Rainforests are undergoing severe deforestation and fragmentation worldwide. A huge amount of small forest patches are being created, but their value in conserving biodiversity and forest structure is still controversial. Here, we demonstrate that in a species-rich and moderately-managed Mexican tropical landscape small rainforest patches (&lt;100 ha) can be highly valuable for the conservation of tree diversity and forest structure. These patches showed diverse communities of native plants, including endangered species, and a new record for the country. Although the number of logged trees increased in smaller patches, patch size was a poor indicator of basal area, stem density, number of species, genera and families, and community evenness. Cumulative species-area curves indicated that all patches had a similar contribution to the regional species diversity. This idea also was supported by the fact that patches strongly differed in floristic composition (high β-diversity), independently of patch size. Thus, in agreement with the land-sharing approach, our findings support that small forest patches in moderately-managed landscapes should be included in conservation initiatives to maintain landscape heterogeneity, species diversity, and ecosystem services.  The 26 forest patches located in the Marqués de Comillas region and the four reference areas studied within the continuous forest of the Montes Azules Biosphere Reserve are also indicated (c).  All necessary permits were obtained for this study. It adhered to the laws of the Mexican Government (SEMARNAT, Secretaría de Medio Ambiente y Recursos Naturales) to sample and collect animals and plants in Lacandona (permit no. SGPA/DGVS/09606). Although our institution, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de Mexico (UNAM), does not yet have an Institutional Review Board (IRB) or a similar governing body of ethics, this project was approved by the institutional authorities from UNAM and the Programa de Apoyo a Proyectos de Investigación e Innovación Tecnológica (PAPIIT), DGAPA-UNAM (Projects IA-203111, IB-200812 and RR-280812). The owners of the forest patches gave us the permission to perform the research in the study sites.  Dot size is directly proportional to site size. CF = continuous forest.  Cumulative number of species sampled in 0.1 per patch versus number of patches added. Patches were added from small to large or large to small, respectively, and then corresponding cumulative species counts were obtained. The value of Saturation Index is indicated.  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  The Centro de Investigaciones en Ecosistemas (UNAM) provided logical support. H. Ferreira, A. Valencia and A. López provided technical support, and A. Navarrete provided the SPOT images. C. Dobler digitized the maps and S. Nicasio-Arzeta elaborated the Figure 1. A. Garmendia, M. San-José and M. Solà assisted the field work. MAHR is grateful to M.G.F. Mendes, K.M. Demetrio, U. González-Gordillo, and their families for their support. We are indebted to the local people of the Marqués de Comillas región. Part of this paper was written while MAHR was on a research stay at the Departamento de Botânica, Universidade Federal de Pernambuco, and Departamento de Sistemática e Ecologia, Universidade Federal da Paraíba. 