 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: AF TN YP CLA. Performed the experiments: AF TN YP CLA. Analyzed the data: AF. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AF TN YP CLA. Wrote the paper: AF TN YP CLA.  Predicting the capacity of ecosystems to absorb impacts from disturbance events (resilience), including land-use intensification and landscape fragmentation, is challenging in the face of global change. Little is known about the impacts of fragmentation on ecosystem functioning from a multi-dimensional perspective (multiple traits). This study used 58 500-m linear transects to quantify changes in the functional composition and resilience of vascular plant communities in response to an increase in landscape fragmentation in 18 natural scrubland fragments embedded within a matrix of abandoned crop fields in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Almería, Spain. Changes in functional community composition were measured using functional diversity indices (functional richness and functional dispersion) that were based on 12 plant traits. Resilience was evaluated using the functional redundancy and response diversity from the perspective of plant dispersal, which is important, particularly, in fragmented landscapes. Scrubland fragmentation was measured using the Integral Index of Connectivity (IIC). The functional richness of the plant communities was higher in the most fragmented scrubland. Conversely, the functional dispersion (i.e., spread) of trait values among species in the functional trait space was lower at the most fragmented sites; consequently, the ecological tolerance of the vegetation to scrubland fragmentation decreased. Classifying the plant species into four functional groups indicated that fragmentation favoured an increase in functional redundancy in the ‘short basal annual forbs and perennial forbs’ group, most of which are species adapted to degraded soils. An assessment based on the traits associated with plant dispersal indicated that the resilience of ‘woody plants’, an important component in the Mediterranean scrubland, and habitat fragmentation were negatively correlated; however, the correlation was positive in the ‘short basal annual forbs and perennial forbs’ and the ‘grasses’ groups.  In addition, winds that contain moist marine air (e.g., sea breezes) can influence plant communities within the study area, which is one of the most arid regions in Europe. For that reason, we measured exposure (facing or not facing the sea) and distance to the sea (range: 0.1–6.8 km) of each plant community using ArcGIS software by ESRI.  Fitted values (solid line) and 95% confidence band (grey band) for the optimal Poisson GLMM model applied to the observed functional richness (FRic) in plant communities across a scrubland fragmentation gradient (dIIC) in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain. dIIC (here, square-root transformed) is the relative contribution (%) of each scrubland fragment surveyed to overall landscape connectivity. Low dIIC indicates high fragmentation.  Fitted values (solid line) and 95% confidence band (grey band) for the optimal Gaussian GLMM model applied to the observed functional dispersion (FDis), weighted by relative abundance of species, in plant communities across a scrubland fragmentation gradient (dIIC) in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain. dIIC (here, square-root transformed) is the relative contribution (%) of each scrubland fragment surveyed to overall landscape connectivity. Low dIIC indicates high fragmentation.  Functional redundancy (no. of species) of four functional effect groups across a scrubland fragmentation gradient (dIIC) in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain. dIIC (here, square-root transformed) is the relative contribution (%) of each scrubland fragment surveyed to overall landscape connectivity. Low dIIC indicates high fragmentation. For clarity, the observed functional redundancy points are omitted. Group 1: woody plants; Group 2: Erect annual forbs; Group 3: short basal annual forbs and perennial forbs; and Group 4: grasses. Different letters below each line indicate statistically significant differences in species number with fragmentation across groups based on GLMM followed by multiple pairwise comparisons.  Average functional redundancy (no. of species) of four functional effect groups at non-sea-facing (circles) and sea-facing (triangles) sites in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain. Group 1: woody plants; Group 2: Erect annual forbs; Group 3: short basal annual forbs and perennial forbs; and Group 4: grasses. Different letters above each group indicate statistically significant differences across group in species number based on GLMM followed by multiple pairwise comparisons. An asterisk indicates significantly different species numbers between sites for a given group.  Fitted values for the optimal Gaussian GLMM model applied to the observed functional dispersion (FDis), weighted by relative abundance of species, for the mechanism of plant dispersal of four functional effect groups in plant communities across a scrubland fragmentation gradient (dIIC) in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain. dIIC (here, square-root transformed) is the relative contribution (%) of each scrubland fragment surveyed to overall landscape connectivity. Low dIIC indicates high fragmentation. For clarity, the observed functional dispersion points are omitted. Group 1: woody plants; Group 2: Erect annual forbs; Group 3: short basal annual forbs and perennial forbs; and Group 4: grasses. Different letters below each line indicate statistically significant differences in FDis values with fragmentation across groups based on GLMM followed by multiple pairwise comparisons.  Average functional dispersion (FDis), weighted by relative abundance of species, for the mechanism of plan dispersal of four functional effect groups at non-sea-facing (circles) and sea-facing (triangles) sites in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain. Group 1: woody plants; Group 2: Erect annual forbs; Group 3: short basal annual forbs and perennial forbs; and Group 4: grasses. Different letters above each group indicate statistically significant differences across group in FDis values based on GLMM followed by multiple pairwise comparisons. An asterisk indicates significantly different FDis values between sites for a given group.  Environmental data [exposure to the sea (sites facing or not facing the sea), distance to the sea (km), and scrubland fragmentation measure (dIIC, see text)] of the 18 natural scrubland fragments surveyed in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain.  (XLSX)  Plant species abundance (mean ± SD) in the 18 natural scrubland fragments surveyed in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain.  (XLSX)  Fitted values for the optimal Gaussian GLMM model applied to the observed functional dispersion (FDis), weighted by relative abundance of species, in plant communities across a scrubland fragmentation gradient (dIIC) in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain. dIIC (here, square-root transformed) is the relative contribution (%) of each scrubland fragment surveyed to overall landscape connectivity. Low dIIC indicates high fragmentation. Solid line indicates non-sea-facing sites and dotted line indicates sea-facing sites. For clarity, observed functional dispersion points are omitted.  (DOCX)  Fitted values (solid line) and 95% confidence band (grey band) for the optimal Gaussian GLMM model applied to the observed functional dispersion (FDis), weighted by relative abundance of species, in plant communities and the distance to the sea in Cabo de Gata-Níjar Natural Park, Spain.  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  Correlations between functional traits.  (XLSX)  Number of levels of each trait within each functional group.  (DOCX)  We are grateful to Beatriz Bueno, Elena Lahoz, Benjamin Komac, and Virginia Pascual for assisting with the collection of field data. We thank Luis Villar for his help in translating the biological types. María Felipe, Maite Gartzia, Bruce MacWhirter, and two referees provided critical comments and helpful suggestions on the manuscript. 