The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: LP GCD. Performed the experiments: LP. Analyzed the data: RKG SGB BB SW CDM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RKG GCD SGB. Wrote the paper: RKG GCD LP.Globally, most restoration efforts focus on re-creating the physical structure (flora or physical features) of a target ecosystem with the assumption that other ecosystem components will follow. Here we investigate that assumption by documenting biogeographical patterns in an important invertebrate taxon, the parasitoid wasp family Ichneumonidae, in a recently reforested Hawaiian landscape. Specifically, we test the influence of (1) planting configurations (corridors versus patches), (2) vegetation age, (3) distance from mature native forest, (4) surrounding tree cover, and (5) plant community composition on ichneumonid richness, abundance, and composition. We sampled over 7,000 wasps, 96.5% of which were not native to Hawai’i. We found greater relative richness and abundance of ichneumonids, and substantially different communities, in restored areas compared to mature forest and abandoned pasturelands. Non-native ichneumonids drive these differences; restored areas and native forest did not differ in native ichneumonid abundance. Among restored areas, ichneumonid communities did not differ by planting age or configuration. As tree cover increased within 120 m of a sampling point, ichneumonid community composition increasingly resembled that found in native forest. Similarly, native ichneumonid abundance increased with proximity to native forest. Our results suggest that restoration plantings, if situated near target forest ecosystems and in areas with higher local tree cover, can facilitate restoration of native fauna even in a highly invaded system.We received permission to conduct this study and to collect insect samples in the form of Special Use Permits issued by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service in 2007 (SUP# 12516-07018) and 2008 (SUP#12516-08022). No protected species were sampled.Geometric figures indicate sampling points and corresponding habitat types. Sampling points and a designation of the approximate boundary of the native forest (dotted white line) are overlaid on a 0.5 m-resolution aerial photograph showing tree cover (dark areas are the forest, corridors, and patches).The landscape now comprises a variety of different habitat types, referenced here as:In all but remnant corridors, we recorded the abundance and size class of all vegetation in a 10×10 m<sup>2</sup> square centered on the sampling point. In the excessively steep terrain of remnant corridors, which typically had woody vegetation that extended only 5 m away from a deep gulch, we sampled vegetation in a 5×10 m<sup>2</sup> rectangle centered on the sampling point.We tested the effects of habitat type, surrounding tree cover, and distance to forest on ichneumonids using a number of analyses. First, we compared ichneumonid richness and abundance across habitat types (section 2.4.1). Second, we analyzed ichneumonid community composition variation across habitat types (section 2.4.1). Third, we examined whether three response variables [(a) ichneumonid species richness, (b) native ichneumonid abundance, and (c) the similarity of individual sites to the pooled community of ichneumonids in forest habitats] varied with respect to three explanatory variables [(a) distance to forest, (b) tree cover, and (c) for abundance of native ichneumonids only, the non-koa plant community] (section 2.4.2).We do not consider samples within the same corridor, patch, or grassland independent from one another; nor did we consider the temporal replicates from each point independent. We minimize the risk of pseudoreplication using the techniques described below and detailed in the Supporting Information (S1. Elaboration of Methods).To assess whether ichneumonids visit restoration plantings differently than they do adjacent unrestored areas, we calculated sampled species richness and individual abundance. To determine statistical significance of observed differences, we used a Generalized Linear Mixed Model, a method described in more detail below and in the Supporting Information (S1).Most of the Ichneumonidae collected in all habitat types were non-native to Hawai’i; non-native wasps comprised 100% of wasps sampled in grassland (74 individuals), 97% of wasps sampled in reforested corridors and patches (5,423, of a total of 5,584), and 92% (971 of 1,059) of wasps sampled in forest.Plot demonstrates similarities in ichneumonid community composition in different habitat types.At points represented by a circle we found no native individuals; at points indicated by a triangle we found at least one native individual. Tree cover is calculated within a circle of 120 m radius surrounding each sampling point in all corridors. Our GLMM analysis found the trend of increasing similarity to forest with increasing tree cover significant.(DOCX)(DOCX)We appreciate the many individuals who helped with this project: Pete Oboyski and Paul Ehrlich for providing guidance on project design and specimen identification; Robert Peck for frequent consultation on Hawaiian Ichneumonidae; Susan Culliney, Peter Olson, Ahn Nguyet Vu, and Annie Wattles for collecting the data in the field; Daniel Karp and Benjamin Woodcock for helpful comments on the manuscript; and Akhila Bettadapur, Japna Sethi, Varshini Cherukupalli, Eugene Lee, and Lindley Mease for their hours of microscope work sorting Ichneumonidae from other arthropods.