The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: SS TG JG MB JM SP. Performed the experiments: SS TG JM. Analyzed the data: TG SS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SS TG JM. Wrote the paper: SS TG JG MB JM SP.Habitat loss and fragmentation are leading causes of species extinctions in terrestrial, aquatic and marine systems. Along coastlines, natural habitats support high biodiversity and valuable ecosystem services but are often replaced with engineered structures for coastal protection or erosion control. We coupled high-resolution shoreline condition data with an eleven-year time series of fish community structure to examine how coastal protection structures impact community stability. Our analyses revealed that the most stable fish communities were nearest natural shorelines. Structurally complex engineered shorelines appeared to promote greater stability than simpler alternatives as communities nearest vertical walls, which are among the most prevalent structures, were most dissimilar from natural shorelines and had the lowest stability. We conclude that conserving and restoring natural habitats is essential for promoting ecological stability. However, in scenarios when natural habitats are not viable, engineered landscapes designed to mimic the complexity of natural habitats may provide similar ecological functions.This study involves the analysis of data resulting from routine fisheries research and monitoring efforts by the State of Alabama Department of Conservation and Natural Resources—Marine Resources Division (ADCNR-MRD). ADCNR-MRD research and monitoring is regulated and permitted by the State of Alabama. ADCNR-MRD’s standard protocol for sampling vertebrate fishes involves the live release of specimens when possible. This study did not involve endangered or protected species. The data analyzed and interpreted in this study were collected in Mobile Bay, Alabama USA (30.460795, -87.993580).Photographs of (a) natural, (b) riprap / rubble, (c) vertical wall and (d) vertical wall with riprap shorelines in the study system.Community dissimilarity measured by computing the Euclidean distance in (nMDS) ordination space between mean annual fish community structure observed in all pairs of years for each shoreline type (a). Mean Euclidian distance between fish community structure observed in all pairs of years for each shoreline type (+/- standard error of the mean) (b). Different letters indicate statistically significant differences based on ANOVA and post hoc pairwise comparisons using Tukey-Kramer’s HSD.A single nMDS analysis was performed on the entire dataset (2-D stress = 0.13) and the results were plotted on four different panels based on shoreline type: (a) Natural, (b) Rubble with Riprap, (c) Vertical Wall, (d) Vertical Wall with Riprap. Blue vectors and labels indicate explanatory variables that are significantly correlated with the nMDS axes. Red arrows indicate the trajectory of communities over time, with the red labels representing year number.The global wavelet power represents the time-averaged variance of a signal (i.e., total abundance in panel [a] and species richness in panel [b]) at each period. For average abundance, wavelet analysis was performed for each species to obtain the global wavelet power spectrum. The global wavelet power spectrum was then averages across all species.(DOCX)(DOCX)We thank the Alabama Department of Natural Resources—Marine Resource Division for access to their fisheries monitoring data and the Geological Survey of Alabama for the shoreline condition data.