The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: ZM DJM. Performed the experiments: ZM. Analyzed the data: ZM ES. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DJM AS ZM. Wrote the paper: ZM ES DJM. Identified the material: ZM DJM AS.Responses to microhabitat are often neglected when ecologists sample animal indicator groups. Microhabitats may be particularly influential in non-passive biodiversity sampling methods, such as baited traps or light traps, and for certain taxonomic groups which respond to fine scale environmental variation, such as insects. Here we test the effects of microhabitat on measures of species diversity, guild structure and biomass of dung beetles, a widely used ecological indicator taxon. We demonstrate that choice of trap placement influences dung beetle functional guild structure and species diversity. We found that locally measured environmental variables were unable to fully explain trap-based differences in species diversity metrics or microhabitat specialism of functional guilds. To compare the effects of habitat degradation on biodiversity across multiple sites, sampling protocols must be standardized and scale-relevant. Our work highlights the importance of considering microhabitat scale responses of indicator taxa and designing robust sampling protocols which account for variation in microhabitats during trap placement. We suggest that this can be achieved either through standardization of microhabitat or through better efforts to record relevant environmental variables that can be incorporated into analyses to account for microhabitat effects. This is especially important when rapidly assessing the consequences of human activity on biodiversity loss and associated ecosystem function and services.To the best of our knowledge, no studies to date have investigated the effects of trap placement and microhabitat preference of dung beetles on biodiversity metrics yielded from a typical field-sampling program. Here we specifically assess whether dung beetles show microhabitat level response traits, and if the current sampling methods used by ecologists to estimate dung beetle species diversity, biomass, and guild structure are robust to the effects of microhabitat variation. We analyze our results on the two different scales commonly used by ecologists: the trap and transect, in order to make our findings widely applicable. We discuss the implications of our findings for studies using dung beetles as an indicator taxon to assess habitat changes across multiple forest sites, and in particular those studies which link biodiversity to ecosystem functions and services.All necessary research and export permits were obtained for this project from Ministerio de Ambiente, Energía y Mares de Costa Rica. A reference collection of the insect material collected is curated at the Instituto Nacional de Biodiversidad, Costa Rica.Firstly, if insect indicator taxa are used without representative sampling of the microhabitats they occupy, we may fail to compare like with like, which could in turn result in biases and lead to erroneous biodiversity valuations, or misguided conservation efforts. Secondly, in order to understand the functional roles underlying ecosystem processes performed by indicator groups, there is a need to account for the possibility that micro-scale variation in functioning could result from different microhabitat preferences of distinct functional guilds. In order to overcome these problems we suggest that sampling protocols for indicator taxa should incorporate standardization of microhabitat when placing traps, or record relevant environmental variables at the trap level, which can then be incorporated into analyses to account for microhabitat effects.The lack of treatment differences for most of the environmental variables we measured confirms our samples from traps along paired transects were obtained from much the same macrohabitat, and were even similar in terms of many commonly measured microhabitat environmental variables. The overall differences between species richness and diversity metrics between trap placements were small, inconsistent across scales of analysis, and probably biologically insignificant.We highlight that on a practical level, problems in biodiversity assessments using dung beetles are most likely to arise when trapping methodologies are employed under restricted resources, and are thus incapable of randomly sampling enough of the macrohabitat to guarantee that enough traps are placed to encompass the full range of microhabitats within. In such instances we suggest that standardizing trap placement, or recording microhabitat variables at the trap level and including these in analyses may help to mitigate these biases. However, it is clear from our study that we need a better understanding of exactly which environmental variables are driving fine scale responses. Caution also needs to be applied in making inferences from studies that do control for trap placement: as this will only sample a subset of the community of interest.In conclusion, we have shown that biases exist in current trapping protocols employed for the study of a widely used indicator taxon. We predict such biases to be most important in studies without sufficient replication and randomization along transects to properly represent the distribution of all potential microhabitats existing in a given macrohabitat. We found that the differences in species diversity responses to microhabitat conditions are subtle, but responses of functional guilds were more pronounced. We also found that the scale of analysis influenced the microhabitat bias. Thus, the impact of sampling methodology on decision-making may depend on whether functional or species richness based diversity measures are investigated, or at what scale they are analyzed. We suggest it may be possible to account for microhabitat preferences through standardizing trap placement or by including environmental parameters in analyses, but stress further knowledge of microhabitat preferences is needed to ensure relevant environmental parameters are measured in the field. A sharper focus on this topic would allow us to better understand the spatial patterns in animal ecosystem service provisioning.(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)This project would not have been possible without support from The British Ecological Society, The Royal Geographic Society with IBG (Goldsmiths), Oxford University Expeditions Council (Alexander Allan Paton Memorial Fund), The Duke of Edinburgh, St Hilda’s College (Muriel Wise Trust Fund) and The Explorers Club. Many thanks to MINAE, INBio, Tariq Quereshi and Adib Mehrabi for logistical support and to Peter Coals, Tai Nga Yu, Ben Cowburn, Nasim Mehrabi &amp; Tilia Mehrabi for research assistance in field and laboratory. We also thank Robert Plowes for providing maps, Owen Lewis, Clive Hambler, Robi Bagchi, Joe Nuñez-Miño, Maartje Klapwijk, Claudia Gray, Moya Burns for helpful discussion and comments.