 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: JW. Performed the experiments: DHZ PW WZZ YY BL. Analyzed the data: JW DHZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JW. Wrote the paper: DHZ PW.  Although plant diversity is postulated to resist invasion, studies have not provided consistent results, most of which were ascribed to the influences of other covariate environmental factors.  The results of this study suggest that plant diversity confers resistance to invasion, which is mainly ascribed to the sampling effect of particular species and the complementarity effect among species on resources use.  The experiments, conducted within the campus of Taizhou University, were pot based and therefore required no specific permission. The species defined as exotic in the present study were either natives or common exotic species that had already established local populations in the mountain area around Taizhou city, where Taizhou University is located. Consequently, none of the plant species used in this study is either endangered or protected.  The names of planted species  One year later, in March 2014, the non-target seedlings were removed for the last time from each pot, and the invaders were recorded then on as the seedlings emerged from the soil seed bank or from seeds outside the experimental pots. In order to avoid the influence of interactive invasion between pots, any seedlings of the sixteen experimental species that had not been included originally in each pot were removed every week during the invasion experiment. In September 2014, the number of seedlings of each non-target native species (native species that were not among the sixteen planted species) and exotic species was counted. The total biomass of all living seedlings was sorted according to each non-target species, dried to a constant mass at 80°C for 48 h, and weighed.  Before surveying the non-target native and exotic species, a water treatment experiment was conducted. The water content of each pot was determined 3 days after they had been irrigated. The water content (%, m 3 /m 3 ) at each of the three points was measured at 15:00–16:00 using a ProCheck (Decagon, Pullman, Washington, USA) analyzer. The average water content of the three points measured in triplicate was used as the water content for each pot.  We analyzed two types of invader species: non-target native species and exotic species. Non-target native species are species that were known to grow in the region but were not among the sixteen native species chosen for the experiment whereas exotic species are species that never grew in the region before and were invaders from other places. Total invaders in each pot comprised all the non-target native species and the exotic species. The number of species, biomass, and the number of seedlings of total and exotic invaders were analyzed using a general linear model (GLM) with block as a random factor and species richness as a fixed factor. The relationship between these variables and planted diversity was determined by including planted-species richness as a factor in a regression analysis combined with curve estimation. The effects of particular species were determined in two steps. First, differences in invasibility between monocultures were determined using a GLM with block as a random factor and species identity as a fixed factor. Second, we selected species that differed markedly from other species according to those tests and included the presence of these species as covariates in the extended GLM model. The interaction term between richness and the presence of particular species were also included in the extended GLM model. This procedure was repeated for six variables: the number of species, biomass, and the number of seedlings of both total and exotic invaders.  The light interception efficiency of mixtures was compared to that of the monoculture with the highest light interception efficiency, and the soil water content of mixtures was compared to that of the monoculture with the lowest soil water content. The analysis addressed the following question: Does the percentage of pots with light interception efficiency greater than the highest light interception efficiency or that of pots with soil water content lower than the lowest value increase with the species richness? The relationships between the percentage of pots and species richness was analyzed using bivariate correlation analysis. All analyses were performed using SPSS ver. 20.0 for Windows and the SEM analysis was conducted using AMOS ver. 20.0, which is part of SPSS 20.0 (Amos Development Corp., Mount Pleasant, South Carolina, USA).  The effects of block and species richness on species number, biomass and seedling number of total and exotic invaders.   β  ↓ indicates had positive effect.  (DOC)  (DOC)  We thank International Science Editing for assistance with English and Yuan Ge and Chong B. Zhang for their helpful comments. 