The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: LN KC FB. Performed the experiments: LN KC FB. Analyzed the data: LN KC FB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LN KC FB. Wrote the paper: LN KC FB.The research has been conducted according to the Argentine law.1, Reserva de Vida Silvestre Urugua-í (RVSU), with four undisturbed sampling sites (U1–U4), and 2, Campo Anexo Manuel Belgrano (CAMB), with two undisturbed sampling sites (B1 and B3), and two disturbed sampling sites (B2 and B4). Maps modified from Di Bitetti et al. (2003), Galindo-Leal and Câmara (2003), and Google Earth.In both reserves, land planarians were collected with the same sampling procedure along nine campaigns, between 2008 and 2010. In each site, samplings were performed by one person walking along the paths (1,000–1,500 m long) for 2 h during the day and another 2 h during the night. Therefore, 36 hours of sampling (2 h diurnal ×2 h nocturnal ×9 campaigns) were carried out in each site, totaling 144 hours of sampling effort for each reserve. During the day, the collector searched for planarians beneath and inside fallen logs, leaf litter and stones, whereas during the night, when planarians are more active, the collector performed the direct observation of the soil by means of a headlamp. Land planarians were manually collected and placed in plastic recipients with humid leaf litter, to avoid dehydration stress.Environmental data were obtained from climatological stations near the reserves. The mean temperature of each sampling day and the cumulative rainfall (sum of millimeters of the ten days previous to each sampling day) were recorded.The material studied was deposited in the Invertebrate Collection at Museo de La Plata (MLP), Argentina.Abundance and species richness are interesting parameters to assess the structure of assemblages, since they are simple and fast to measure. Furthermore, these parameters can change according to environmental conditions. Besides the effects of mean temperature and cumulative rainfall on abundance and richness of land planarians, we also evaluated the relationship of these parameters with the conservation condition of each site. Therefore, we performed a multiple regression analysis (GLM), including data of both reserves (2 reserves ×4 sites ×9 campaigns), to test the effects of three independent variables: mean temperature, cumulative rainfall (continuous predictor variables), and conservation condition (categorical predictor variable: disturbed/undisturbed) on two dependent variables (abundance and richness).To assess whether we had found more land planarians in diurnal or nocturnal surveys, we used a non-parametric Wilcoxon test, for dependent samples. We compared the abundance of planarians collected in 36 diurnal and nocturnal samplings (4 sites ×9 campaigns) in each reserve. After this comparison, we pooled diurnal and nocturnal sampling data, summarizing nine replicates (campaigns) per site. This procedure ensured that the actual richness and abundance of each site was well estimated.We then used a two-way ANOVA to tested the effect of the reserves (fixed, orthogonal factor, with two levels: RVSU and CAMB) and sites (random, nested factor, with U1–U4 nested in RVSU level, and B1–B4 nested in CAMB level) on the abundance and richness of land planarians. Data were log-transformed to fulfill ANOVA assumptions. Post-hoc Student-Newman-Keuls (SNK) tests were applied for multiple comparisons.Solid lines show the rarefaction curves (bars delineate 95% confidence intervals). Dashed and dotted lines represent the singleton and doubleton curves, respectively. RVSU (squares) and CAMB (circles).Number of species expected and percentages of inventory completeness according to different richness estimators.Non-parametric Wilcoxon test, for dependent samples was used. Mean (dot), median (line inside the box), 25–75% (box), min-max (whiskers), and N =  total abundance of land planarians.Means and standard errors. Different labels represent significant differences (Student-Newman-Keuls; α = 0.05).Sites with undisturbed condition (U1–U4, B1 and B3) were clustered at 54% similarity (Bray–Curtis coefficient), while disturbed sites B2 and B4 were segregated.C = Cochran's test, NS  =  not significant.Our results suggest that land planarian assemblages are sensitive to the conservation degree of the rainforest. Our study also evidence that not only continuous areas with native forest (e.g., RVSU) but also fragmented landscapes in which the original rainforest is conserved as patches (e.g., B1 and B3 in CAMB) may harbor similar levels of land planarian diversity. Considering the high levels of beta diversity between sites and the low vagility of land flatworms, we suggest that conservation policies should promote the connectivity between fragmented areas.We thank Fundación Vida Silvestre Argentina and Ministerio de Ecología, Recursos Naturales Renovables de Misiones (Misiones, Argentina) for permission to perform surveys at Reserva de Vida Silvestre Urugua-í. We also thank the park rangers Ariel Tombo, Laura Aréjola and Marcelo Rivero for their support during the fieldwork. We are thankful to Administración de Parques Nacionales (APN) and Instituto de Tecnología Agropecuaria (INTA) from San Antonio (Misiones, Argentina) for permission to conduct sampling at the Campo Anexo M. Belgrano. Our gratitude is also due to the park rangers from APN, Luciano Giménez, Jorge Mackoviak and Sandra Muñoz, for their important collaboration in the surveys.