 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: PJM BFNE ETFW GPA KJW R. Mathieu. Performed the experiments: PJM GPA R. Mathieu DEK REM R.Main. Analyzed the data: PJM DEK R. Main. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: BFNE GPA ETFW. Wrote the paper: PJM BFNE ETFW GPA KJW R. Mathieu. Logistics: REM.  ‡ These authors also contributed equally to this work.  Woody biomass dynamics are an expression of ecosystem function, yet biomass estimates do not provide information on the spatial distribution of woody vegetation within the vertical vegetation subcanopy. We demonstrate the ability of airborne light detection and ranging (LiDAR) to measure aboveground biomass and subcanopy structure, as an explanatory tool to unravel vegetation dynamics in structurally heterogeneous landscapes. We sampled three communal rangelands in Bushbuckridge, South Africa, utilised by rural communities for fuelwood harvesting. Woody biomass estimates ranged between 9 Mg ha -1  on gabbro geology sites to 27 Mg ha -1  on granitic geology sites. Despite predictions of woodland depletion due to unsustainable fuelwood extraction in previous studies, biomass in all the communal rangelands increased between 2008 and 2012. Annual biomass productivity estimates (10–14% p.a.) were higher than previous estimates of 4% and likely a significant contributor to the previous underestimations of modelled biomass supply. We show that biomass increases are attributable to growth of vegetation &lt;5 m in height, and that, in the high wood extraction rangeland, 79% of the changes in the vertical vegetation subcanopy are gains in the 1-3m height class. The higher the wood extraction pressure on the rangelands, the greater the biomass increases in the low height classes within the subcanopy, likely a strong resprouting response to intensive harvesting. Yet, fuelwood shortages are still occurring, as evidenced by the losses in the tall tree height class in the high extraction rangeland. Loss of large trees and gain in subcanopy shrubs could result in a structurally simple landscape with reduced functional capacity. This research demonstrates that intensive harvesting can, paradoxically, increase biomass and this has implications for the sustainability of ecosystem service provision. The structural implications of biomass increases in communal rangelands could be misinterpreted as woodland recovery in the absence of three-dimensional, subcanopy information.  Permission to conduct fieldwork in the Bushbuckridge communal rangelands was granted by the local headmen. This study is part of a broad, long-standing relationship with the local community and the University of the Witwatersrand to conduct ecological research in their communal land. The field studies did not involve endangered or protected species. The study sites were located within the Bushbuckridge Municipality in the Lowveld region, a semi-arid savanna in South Africa. Summer rainfall (October to May) usually falls in convective thunderstorms and ranges between &gt;900 mm per annum in the west and 500 mm per annum in the east with an mean annual precipitation (MAP) coefficient of variation of 25%. Summers are hot and humid with mean daily maxima of 30°C and winters are mild and dry with mean daily maxima of 23°C. Droughts can be prolonged and may be experienced every ten years. Within the timeframe of this study (2008–2012), the 2006–2007 and 2007–2008 summer rainfall was below average and the 2011–2012 was a particularly wet summer. Within seasons, notable rainfall peaks occurred in April 2010 (4.1-fold more rain than the monthly 8-year average) and January 2012 (2.4-fold higher than the monthly 8-year average).  Sites are classified (from west to east) as low, high and intermediate wood extraction pressure based on the number of households and people utilising each rangeland. Settlements that utilise each rangeland are shown, including the names of the major settlements, as well as the location of the gabbro intrusions in the predominantly granitic landscape.  In the model equations, y refers to the plot-level (25 m x 25 m) biomass estimate (kg/625 m 2 ) and x to the LiDAR-derived H x CC predictor metrics, where H is plot-averaged height (&gt; 1.5 m) and CC is the proportion of canopy cover (&gt; 1.5 m in height) per plot. Root mean square error (RMSE) was reported in Mg ha -1  for ease of interpretation and n is number of 25 m x 25 m plots.  n is the number of 25 m x 25 m grid cells in each rangeland.  Height categories are a) 1–3 m, b) 3–5 m and c) 5–10 m for rangelands of high, intermediate and low wood extraction pressure. There were no data for the 5–10 m height class in the high wood extraction rangeland and the &gt;10 m height class for all rangelands as there were no grid cells with an average height over 10 m. Grid cell size: 25 m x 25 m.  Height categories are a) 1–3 m, b) 3–5 m and c) 5–10 m for rangelands of high, intermediate and low wood extraction pressure. There were no data for the 5–10 m height class in the high wood extraction rangeland and the &gt;10 m height class for all rangelands as there were no grid cells with an average height over 10 m. Grid cell size: 25 m x 25 m.  Wood extraction levels are: a) high (n = 102 cells), b) intermediate (n = 291 cells), and c) low wood extraction (n = 1654 cells). Contribution of height class change (subcanopy returns) to total change (total vegetation column) (%) is the black bar represented by values on the secondary axis. e.g. In the high wood extraction rangeland, 79% of the change in the total vegetation column was attributable to the 1–3 m height class.  Another indicator of shrub level increase in the rangelands is the change in the number of cells that remained after an average height mask was applied (i.e. that fulfilled the average height criteria threshold to be included in the biomass analysis), expressed as a percentage of each rangeland. The high extraction rangeland changed from 10% of the rangeland that met the average height (&gt;1.5 m) criteria mask in 2008 to 15.9% of the rangeland in 2012 (χ 2  1  = 107.6; p &lt;0.001); the intermediate use site doubled in the percentage of rangeland that met the average height criteria from 8.5% to 17.4% (χ 2  1  = 780.8; p &lt;0.001); and the low use rangeland increased from 54.2% in 2008 to 63.8% of the rangeland in 2012 (χ 2  1  = 220.7; p &lt;0.001).  Wood extraction levels for each rangeland are listed per column as high, intermediate and low.  Data include 2012 LiDAR-derived average height and canopy cover extraction metrics, as well as field-work based allometry. Each line item is per 25 m x 25 m grid cell. Metadata are included in the dataset.  (XLSX)  Data include 2008 and 2012 biomass estimates derived from biomass models as well as % subcanopy returns for voxel data for the height class categories: 1-3m, 3-5m, 5-10m and &gt;10m. Each line item is per 25 m x 25 m grid cell. Data are organized per land extraction category into separate worksheets. Metadata are included in the dataset.  (XLSX)  Data include biomass change estimates (2008–2012), percentage height and canopy cover changes for each 25 m x 25 m grid cell. Each height class (relative to height in 2008) are shown on separate worksheets. Metadata are included in the dataset.  (XLSX)  The residual spread demonstrates heteroskedasticity with increasing biomass fitted values for rangelands with a) high, b) intermediate and c) low extraction pressure.   (TIFF)  Height categories are: 1–3 m, 3–5 m, 5–10 m and &gt;10 m.   (TIF)  We thank T. Kennedy-Bowdoin, J. Jacobson, R. Emerson and C. Anderson for their contributions as CAO staff. We also thank L. Naidoo, N. Naidoo, S. Madonsela and the SAEON staff for their assistance with fieldwork. Rainfall data were provided by the South African Weather Service (SAWS). We are grateful for assistance and commentary from Jolene Fisher during all stages of this work. 