The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: RG TM ARO. Performed the experiments: RG ARO. Analyzed the data: RG ARO. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RG ARO. Wrote the paper: RG. Performed laboratory work and sample analyses: RG. Interpreted the data: RG ARO TM. Revised the manuscript: ARO TM.Biodiversity has diminished over the past decades with climate change being among the main responsible factors. One consequence of climate change is the increase in sea surface temperature, which, together with long exposure periods in intertidal areas, may exceed the tolerance level of benthic organisms. Benthic communities may suffer structural changes due to the loss of species or functional groups, putting ecological services at risk. In sandy beaches, free-living marine nematodes usually are the most abundant and diverse group of intertidal meiofauna, playing an important role in the benthic food web. While apparently many functionally similar nematode species co-exist temporally and spatially, experimental results on selected bacterivore species suggest no functional overlap, but rather an idiosyncratic contribution to ecosystem functioning. However, we hypothesize that functional redundancy is more likely to observe when taking into account the entire diversity of natural assemblages. We conducted a microcosm experiment with two natural communities to assess their stress response to elevated temperature. The two communities differed in diversity (high [HD] vs. low [LD]) and environmental origin (harsh vs. moderate conditions). We assessed their stress resistance to the experimental treatment in terms of species and diversity changes, and their function in terms of abundance, biomass, and trophic diversity. According to the Insurance Hypothesis, we hypothesized that the HD community would cope better with the stressful treatment due to species functional overlap, whereas the LD community functioning would benefit from species better adapted to harsh conditions. Our results indicate no evidence of functional redundancy in the studied nematofaunal communities. The species loss was more prominent and size specific in the HD; large predators and omnivores were lost, which may have important consequences for the benthic food web. Yet, we found evidence for alternative diversity–ecosystem functioning relationships, such as the Rivets and the Idiosyncrasy Model.We therefore expected that the imposed temperature stress would, on the one hand, drive the HD and LD communities to structural convergence based on a set of temperature-resistant species; and, on the other, that the HD assemblage would exhibit a higher degree of functionality than the LD after an environmentally stressful phase, as predicted by the IH.40 sediment cores were sampled at two stations (20 cores each) located on different sandbars of the intertidal, and hosting communities of high or low diversities respectively. A: Samples were taken with a metal cylinder to 10 cm depth. B: Entire sediment cores were placed into containers. C: The sampling corer fitted exactly in the container so that the internal structure of the sediment core remained as intact as possible. D: The metal corer was carefully removed.In the laboratory, four microcosms (two HD and two LD respectively) were randomly assigned to each of ten 100 l tubs. Previously, the tubs had been filled with filtered and sterile seawater (passed through a 1 µm filter and UV treated) to minimize biofouling and maintained at 31°C. All microcosms were acclimated to experimental conditions at 31°C for 5 days. Temperature was maintained constant with thermostats (1000 W titanium heater for high, and regular 250 W heaters for the normal temperature), and the water was homogenized with bubbling air stones placed next to the heaters. All microcosm containers were closed with a transparent plastic lid. Water oxygenation and circulation inside the microcosm containers was achieved by bubbling air with an air stone introduced through a hole in the lid.4 microcosm containers were placed in each of 10 tubs. The time<sub>0</sub> control (A) was analyzed at the start of the experimental treatment when temperature was changed in the high temperature treatments. The experimental groups of high (B<sub>1</sub>) and low (B<sub>2</sub>) diversity were kept at constant temperature throughout the experiment: elevated (36°C) for the test group and normal (31°C) for the "temperature control" group. Each experimental group was replicated 5 times. The live control (C) was used to monitor nematodes throughout the experiment.Samples taken at the time when high temperature treatments reached their target temperature (36°C).We used Student’s t-tests to assess differences in community and environmental attributes between the two field stations. Assumptions of normal distribution and homoscedasticity were met as verified by a Kolmogorov-Smirnov and Bartlett’s test respectively.Samples were collected under permit No. DGOPA. 05335.100707.2458 (SAGARPA).Shannon Wiener diversity index.Index of trophic diversity ITD<sup>−1</sup>.HD = High diversity.LD = Low diversity.1A, 1B, 2A, 2B  =  Feeding groups according to the classification of Wieser (1953).Factors consist of temperature (T, three levels: time<sub>0</sub>, 31° and 36°) and diversity (D, two levels: high and low).The factor ( = treatment) consists of three levels: time<sub>0</sub>, 31° and 36°.In the present study, we assessed the stress response of two intertidal nematode communities, differing in environmental origin and in diversity. Given its environmental background, we expected the low diversity community to cope better with stressful conditions and lose relatively fewer species. On the other hand, according to the IH, we expected that the high diversity community would maintain its functional attributes despite species loss, due to their functional redundancy. In order to test this we exposed natural nematode assemblages of contrasting diversity levels and environmental background to a stressful temperature.In the present study, we set out to test, for the first time, the structural and functional changes of a natural subtropical meiofaunal community in response to increased water temperature. Our results successfully showed that changes in nematode communities are not consistent with the prevalence of functional redundancy, and hence are of consequence to hypotheses relating diversity with ecosystem function. Future experiments on intertidal nematode communities addressing this issue will benefit from the following recommendations: 1) more functional variables (in addition to trophic functions) could be investigated, as nematodes are involved in many different functions in the intertidal, with potentially varying patterns of redundancy. This will greatly improve our understanding in the current diversity-redundancy debate. 2) The experimental setup could incorporate a more realistic simulation of the intertidal environment such as tidal action, as constant water cover may act as an additional stress source on the communities. 3) Additional efforts could be made to better tease apart the effects of community composition and diversity levels in order to identify their potentially independent effects on ecosystem functioning. Admittedly, this represents a major challenge given the difficulty of finding species assemblages from the same type of environment in which diversity and taxonomic composition are not at least partially confounded. 4) Quantitative replicate sampling during the course of the experiment will provide evidence of the temporal changes and response of the community to the environmental stressor and allow testing additional hypotheses regarding the onset and rate of structural and functional changes of the community. 5) Finally, additional environmental variables such as algal and bacterial growth could be measured in the microcosms. This will help clarify causal relationships between the proxies of community function and environmental changes. For example, an increase in a bacteria-feeding guild could be linked to an increase in bacterial growth.(TIF)(TIF)For invaluable help in the field we thank Renato Salvatteci Merino, Mary Carmen Ruiz de la Torre, Ismael Guzman, Jose Abella, Francisco López Rasgado, and to RSM also for his help in the laboratory. We are grateful to Luis Gustavo Alvarez who was instrumental for the morphological characterization of the beach, to Mónica Hernandez and Francisco Valenzuela for technical and logistic help and the setup in the aquaculture facilities of CICESE, and to Tania Campinas-Bezerra for help with the identification of the nematodes. We kindly thank the constructive remarks of an anonymous reviewer that helped improve the manuscript. Samples were collected under permit No. DGOPA. 05335.100707.2458 (SAGARPA).