The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: AM TH RJ. Performed the experiments: AM VP. Analyzed the data: AM VP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AM TH VP. Wrote the paper: AM VP TH LS.Current address: Section for Ecoinformatics &amp; Biodiversity, Department of Bioscience, Ny Munkegade 114–116, Aarhus University, DK 8000, Aarhus, DenmarkSpace-for-time substitution—that is, the assumption that spatial variations of a system can explain and predict the effect of temporal variations—is widely used in ecology. However, it is questionable whether it can validly be used to explain changes in biodiversity over time in response to land-cover changes.Using land-cover maps of the Paris region for 1982 and 2003, we made a holistic description of the landscape disentangling landscape composition from configuration. After controlling for spatial variations, we analyzed and compared the amplitudes of changes in landscape composition and configuration over time.For comparable spatial variations, landscape configuration varied more than twice as much as composition over time. Temporal changes in composition and configuration were not always spatially matched.The fact that landscape composition and configuration do not vary equally in space and time calls into question the use of space-for-time substitution in landscape ecology studies. The instability of landscapes over time appears to be attributable to configurational changes in the main. This may go some way to explaining why the landscape variables that account for changes over time in biodiversity are not the same ones that account for the spatial distribution of biodiversity.Using time series of a holistic description of the landscape in the Seine-et-Marne department near Paris, France, the present study tests the validity of the space-for-time substitution on the landscape scale to assess landscape composition and configuration changes over time. It focuses on understanding the repercussions of subtle changes in LUC over time on landscape composition and configuration, which are assumed to be key landscape characteristics for biodiversity.Agricultural areas: areas given over to arable farming and pasture.Urbanized areas: built areas, urban parks and gardens, building land, or swimming pools.Forest: natural woodlands, forests, and poplar stands.Water and wetlands: rivers, other bodies of water, and wetlands.Transport areas: road, rail, car parksNatural open areas: wasteland and cut forest.We followed a five-step method for comparing the variations in composition and configuration over time:Therefore, in each landscape, we divided the values for the composition and configuration variables by the sum of the standard deviations of the selected axes from the multifactorial analysis to which they belonged (i.e. by the total standard deviation of the CA for the three composition variables and by the total standard deviation of the PCA for the seven configuration variables). After standardization, the summed spatial variation of the three composition variables was equal to the summed spatial variation of the seven configuration variables in 1982 and 2003. Thus, standardization gave the same weight to composition and configuration, regardless of the number of variables composing each. Consequently, the amplitudes of variation in composition and configuration (obtained by summing the standard deviations of the composition or configuration variables) were equal in space (and equal to 1), and their changes over time were therefore comparable.This step was the equivalent of the sum performed in step (ii) to evaluate global spatial variability and global temporal variability.The amplitudes are computed as the sum of the absolute values of the changes of the standardized composition and configuration variables between 1982 and 2003.This study indicates that, under the conditions of our investigation, landscape configuration is more variable over time than landscape composition, up to 2.6 times higher in this study. These results concern the Seine-et-Marne department between 1982 and 2003 and for the given landscape scale. Configuration appears to be more sensitive to LUC changes, suggesting that subtle changes in composition have a marked influence on landscape stability via its configuration. The results highlight the fact that taken independently, the 10 landscape variables (three composition and seven configuration variables) display similar temporal variation. Consequently, the higher temporal variation for configuration than composition is due to the multiple facets of configurational changes induced by land cover changes over time (as a reminder, the variable standardization step made composition and configuration comparable in space and time, independently of the number of variables composing them: we thus expected equal temporal variations between the sums of all composition and configuration variables). For instance, in a simple landscape with two different types of land cover, variations in the total area of one type of land cover will modify the respective amount of the two types of land cover (composition) and have direct consequences for the configuration variables of these two types of land cover (shape, isolation, perimeter, number of patches). In our case, a conversion from one type of land cover to another will affect two composition metrics but probably four configuration metrics (size, distance, perimeter, and/or number of patches).(DOCX)(DOCX)(XLSX)(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)The authors wish to thank the IAU (Institut d’Aménagement et d’Urbanisme) for the land-use and land cover data.