The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: WL G-ZD. Performed the experiments: WL K-LY. Analyzed the data: WL K-LY J-MC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HEE G-ZD. Wrote the paper: WL K-LY HEE.Fertilization via nutrient deposition and agricultural inputs is one of the most important factors driving decreases in plant diversity. However, we still do not fully understand which processes (niche process or neutral process) are more important in leading to decreases in plant diversity caused by fertilization. A hypothesis-based approach was used to test the relative importance of niche versus neutral processes along a fertilization gradient in an alpine meadow community on the eastern Tibetan plateau, China. Niche overlap values were calculated for species biomass, and the null model was used to generate the values of niche overlap expected at random. A linear regression modeling was used to evaluate the relationship between functional traits (specific leaf area, leaf dry matter content, and leaf total nitrogen concentration) and species relative abundance. Our results demonstrated that observed niche overlap for species biomass was significantly higher than expected at lower fertilization gradients. Moreover, we also found a significantly negative correlation between species relative abundance and specific leaf area and leaf dry matter content, but a significantly positive correlation between relative abundance and leaf nitrogen concentration at lower fertilization gradients. However, these relationships were not significant at higher fertilization gradients. We concluded that community assembly is dynamic progression along the environmental gradients, and niche and neutral processes may together determine species diversity loss in response to fertilization.Based on the above two hypotheses, the main objectives of this study were to: (a) determine empirically the relative importance of niche and neutral processes along a fertilization gradient; and (b) evaluate whether soil resource availability alters the relationship between leaf functional traits and species relative abundance in this alpine meadow.The land cover of the Tibetan Plateau is based on the vegetation map of China (Hou et al. 1982).In each plot, we measured light with a Decagon Sunfleck ceptometer (Decagon, Pullman, Washington, DC) at the time of vegetation monitoring on 2 Sept 2011. Light readings were taken on a cloudless day (11:00–13:00h). Photosynthetically active radiation (PAR) was recorded at 10cm above the soil surface and at the top of the canopy. The ratio between these two measurements was taken as a proxy for PAR reaching the understory.We randomly sampled 2 individuals and 6 mature leaves (3 leaves per individual) at flowering time for each of the 25 species in each 4 × 6 m subplot. That is, 18 individuals and 54 mature leaves were measured for each of the 25 species in each fertilization level. Leaves were scanned to measure leaf area in the field, and fresh weight of leaves was determined with a balance (Acculab Lt-320; Acculab, Measurement Standards Inc., Danvers, MA, USA). Following these measurements, leaves were placed in paper bags and dried in the sun. Leaf samples were oven-dried at 80°C for 48 h in the laboratory and their dry masses were measured on a semianalytical balance with an accuracy of 10<sup>−4</sup> g (Sartorius AG, Goettingen, Germany). Dried leaves samples were ground using a ball mill (NM200; Retsch, Haan, Germany). Total N concentrations of leaves were determined using an elemental analyzer (2400 II CHNS/O Elemental Analyzer; Perkin-Elmer, Boston, MA, USA).We used one-way ANOVA to test the effect of fertilization on PAR in the understory, species diversity (species richness and Shannon-Wiener diversity index), aboveground community biomass and each leaf functional trait. Then, we performed a linear regression modeling to test the relationship between functional traits and species relative abundance. Independent manipulation of SLA, LDMC and LNC would be required to truly disentangle these effects. Although this approach is correlative in nature, it can provide a way to test the importance of these mechanisms (functional traits-based niche assembly and dispersal-based neutral assembly). All variables met the statistical assumptions (residuals normality, homogeneity of variance and data linearity) when tested using the Shapiro-Wilk test and Levene’s test, respectively. These analyses were performed with SPSS15.0.F0, F15, F30 and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 30, 60 and 120g m<sup>−2</sup> year<sup>−1</sup>. PAR, Photosynthetically active radiation.F0, F15, F30, and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>.Bars with different letters denote significant difference (P = 0.05); F0, F15, F30, and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>.Significant relationships (P &lt; 0.05) are denoted with solid lines. F0, F15, F30, and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>.Notes: SLA, leaf area per unit dry mass; LDMC, leaf dry matter content; LNC, leaf total nitrogen concentration. F0, F15, F30 and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>.Notes: n refers to the number of species in each fertilization gradient. P &lt;0.05 are in bold. SLA, leaf area per unit dry mass; LDMC, leaf dry matter content; LNC, leaf total nitrogen concentration. F0, F15, F30 and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>.Notes: Statistical tests were performed against the null expectation that species abundances within each fertilization gradient were unrelated to leaf functional traits; all tests were one-tailed; Bold types indicate a significant difference based upon 95% CI; ns, Not significant; F0, F15, F30 and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>.By evaluating the niche overlaps and the relationship between species abundance and functional traits along a fertilization gradient, we found that fertilization significantly increased the overlaps of biomass at lower fertilization gradients. However, with increased fertilization gradient, there were no significant correlations between species functional traits and relative abundance. We concluded that niche and neutral processes may together determine species diversity loss in response to fertilization.We thank colleagues who helped with field work.