The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: XC HG XY. Performed the experiments: HF. Analyzed the data: XC HG XY ZC SY. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HF. Wrote the paper: XC HG XY.Marine ecosystem is a complex nonlinear system. However, ecosystem health assessment conventionally builds on a linear superposition of changes in ecosystem components and probably fails to evaluate nonlinear interactions among various components. To better reflect the intrinsic interactions and their impacts on ecosystem health, an ecosystem coordination index, defined as the matching level of ecosystem structure/services, is proposed and incorporated into the ecosystem health index for a systematic diagnosis in the Pearl River Estuary, China. The analysis results show that the ecosystem health index over the last three decades decreased from 0.91 to 0.50, indicating deteriorating from healthy to unhealthy status. The health index is 3–16% lower than that calculated using the common method without considering ecosystem coordination. Ecosystem health degradation in the Pearl River Estuary manifested as significant decreases in structure/services and somewhat mismatching among them. Overall, the introduction of coordination in ecosystem health assessment could improve the understanding of the mechanism of marine ecosystem change and facilitate effective restoration of ecosystem health.Many of these indicators were assessed by national standards, i.e. Marine Water Quality Standard (GB3097–1997), Marine Sediment Quality Standard (GB18668–2002), and Marine Biological Quality Standard (GB18421–2001). For the indicators that lack of criteria, e.g. biodiversity, biomass and cultural services, data closest to 1980 or the best state (defined as the maximum of the positive indicators or the minimum of the negative indicators) of the existing dataset were used as healthy state. The computation methods are detailed in Supporting Information.(a) the ecosystem variability indexes from 1980 to 2005, (b) the ecosystem variability indexes from 2005 to 2009, (c) the ecosystem health index from 1980 to 2009.b) Habitat destruction was considered among the most important stressors to biodiversity and ecosystem services. The Habitat structure index included four factors in this study, i.e., the area of mangrove swamps, water areas, areas under mariculture, and the volume of freight handled in ports.Overall, the HI decreased from 1 to 0.58, indicating that the HI was approaching unhealthy level. Restoration actions having been taken did not change the decreasing trend. However, they did prevent HI from decreasing straightforward.ii) Water quality contains six parameters, i.e., dissolved oxygen (DO), dissolved inorganic nitrogen (DIN), surface sea temperature (SST), suspended substance (SS), dissolved silicate (DSi), and chemical oxygen demand (COD) in the seawater. Most of these are commonly used in evaluating water quality, e.g. in Marine Water Quality Standard GB 3097–1997.Overall, the SI ranged from 1 to 0.69, indicating a sub-healthy level.As to residual pollutants in benthic molluscas, PCBs evidently returned from unhealthy to healthy state since 2005.Hg returned from unhealthy to healthy state during 1990–2007, but fell to sub-healthy state between 2008 and 2009. TPH increased and was in sub-healthy state since 2000. Pb fluctuated between unhealthy and sub-healthy states for nearly thirty years. These results suggested a certain extent of success in controlling release of heavy metals and persistent organic pollutants to the PRE.Overall, the PI ranged from 0.83 to 0.79, indicating as sub-healthy level.Overall, the RI ranged from 0.95 to 0.32, suggesting a vulnerable ecosystem with weak regulating functions.Over the last three decades, the EVI ranged from 0.94 to 0.57, suggesting an unstable and sometimes unhealthy ecosystem. Although the habitat structure restored to some extents, supporting services and providing services maintained at relatively better level, biotic structure, regulating abilities and cultural services decreased.In this study, ecosystem health assessment is extended to include the nonlinear interactions within the ecosystem. By incorporating the ecosystem coordination index into a health diagnosis of ecosystem structure/services, we attempted to assess ecosystem health from external and internal perspectives, and to illustrate the past, state, and trends of ecosystem health and their causes systematically in the PRE. Moreover, by comparing contributions of each factor to ecosystem incoordination, our study could identify the most important uncoordinated factor influencing ecosystem health, thereby provide a suitable option to prioritize restoration and sustainably managing ecosystem.Particularly, being affected by anthropogenic perturbations that superposed on natural changes, the ecosystem in the PRE was found swinging from healthy to unhealthy state during the past three decades. Ecosystem structure/services decreased to various extents, i.e. ranging from sub- to un-healthy states. Additionally, the mismatching level of structure/services was at sub-healthy level, which is also an important sign of ecosystem degradation which should not be neglected.Overall, assessing ecosystem health focused on interactions among structure/services might raise some urgent research questions for future EHA. For instance, how different ecosystem structure/services dynamically coordinate with others at different scales (spatial and time); and to what extent they are affecting ecosystem health.(DOC)We are grateful to Prof. Dewen Ding for his useful advice. We sincerely thank Ms. Xiuqin Li, Prof. Dongsheng Ke, Prof. Yuejin Jiang and Dr. Zhongyuan Wang from South China Sea Environmental Monitoring Center (SCSEMC) for providing data. Thanks to Jie Chen from SCSEMC and Ms. Jinling Chen from OUC for their help in drawing. Thanks to Prof. Lian Xie from North Carolina State University for his helpful comments. And the authors would like to thank the reviewers for their valuable comments.