 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: AU JPM. Performed the experiments: AU. Analyzed the data: AU. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AU JPM. Wrote the paper: AU JPM.  There are few opportunities to evaluate the relative importance of landscape structure and dynamics upon biodiversity, especially in highly fragmented tropical landscapes. Conservation strategies and species risk evaluations often rely exclusively on current aspects of landscape structure, although such limited assumptions are known to be misleading when time-lag responses occur. By relating bird functional-group richness to forest patch size and isolation in ten-year intervals (1956, 1965, 1978, 1984, 1993 and 2003), we revealed that birds with different sensitivity to fragmentation display contrasting responses to landscape dynamics in the Brazilian Atlantic Forest. For non-sensitive groups, there was no time-lag in response: the recent degree of isolation best explains their variation in richness, which likely relates to these species’ flexibility to adapt to changes in landscape structure. However, for sensitive bird groups, the 1978 patch area was the best explanatory variable, providing evidence for a 25-year time-lag in response to habitat reduction. Time-lag was more likely in landscapes that encompass large patches, which can support temporarily the presence of some sensitive species, even when habitat cover is relatively low. These landscapes potentially support the most threatened populations and should be priorities for restoration efforts to avoid further species loss. Although time-lags provide an opportunity to counteract the negative consequences of fragmentation, it also reinforces the urgency of restoration actions. Fragmented landscapes will be depleted of biodiversity if landscape structure is only maintained, and not improved. The urgency of restoration action may be even higher in landscapes where habitat loss and fragmentation history is older and where no large fragment remained to act temporarily as a refuge.  We tracked the historical fragmentation of an Atlantic Forest area, quantifying landscape structure in ten-year intervals from the time the area was continuous forest until its contemporary configuration, representing probably the most complete historical landscape mapping of the Atlantic Forest. We sampled bird communities in 28 areas (21 forest fragments and seven areas within a large forest tract). From these data, we evaluated when landscape structure best explained the current richness of bird groups based on ecological species traits, allowing us not only to infer time-lag responses but also to exam whether time-lags vary according to bird traits. We hypothesized that bird groups that differ in sensitivity to habitat modification may display different time-lags in response to forest fragmentation. The most sensitive groups may be more likely to present time-lag when certain conditions of the landscape (e.g., large patches or intermediate degree of isolation) prolong the persistence of these species for some time. These groups are composed of species that present low density, low dispersal capacity, and demand larger areas to survive. On the contrary, the non-sensitive species may accommodate faster to the landscape changes as they generally have higher dispersal capacity and are more flexible to adapt to habitat/landscape changes. We also hypothesized that patch size and isolation may affect time-lag in species responses. This can be the case when the patch is reduced to a size that is smaller than the minimum to maintain viable populations, or when patch isolation is too large to connect functionally the populations/resources that could allow for the persistence in the long term of species in the landscape.  Pontal do Paranapanema is an excellent region to study the species’ time lag response to habitat fragmentation, as there are good records of landscape modification (in aerial photos and satellite images) since it was a ~200,000 ha block of continuous forest. Furthermore, during its history the landscape matrix was maintained as homogenous, composed of pasture and sugarcane with low human density, which permits us to keep the analysis relatively simple as there are few other factors influencing species richness in the region besides the spatial structure of forest patches and its dynamics.  The study area was mapped for six different years: 1956, 1965, 1978, 1984, 1993 and 2003. We interpreted aerial photographs to map the study area in 1956 using ArcGIS (scale 1:35,000). Data from 1965 and 1978 were collected by digitalization of topographic maps (scales 1:50,000 and 1:10,000; respectively). We classified LANDSAT 5 satellite images for 1984, 1993 and 2003. For each year, we mapped two categories of occupation: forest and non-forest. Maps were geo-referenced using the same projection and datum and, because the sources were of different resolution, we converted these to raster type and resampled them for a pixel size of 30 m (which corresponded to the lowest map resolution) prior to the analysis. In order to remove small patches, we used a low-pass filter (3 x 3 pixel) and, additionally, eliminated patches smaller than 1 ha. Since the beginning of substantial human occupation in the early 50’s, there has been a great contrast between the natural forest and the surrounding matrix (generally composed of pasture and sugar cane), which facilitates the delimitation of land use and land cover types and reduced the chances of mapping errors.  The variables AREA and PROX represent the logarithm of patch area and degree of proximity calculated for different dates in the Pontal do Paranapanema, Brazil.  Finally, to indicate the patches with a higher potential to hold more species that have yet to stabilize but may be lost in the near future in the region, we used the regression model that best explained the variation of sensitive bird richness to estimate the number of sensitive species in all forest patches in the region. This analysis illustrated how we can use this type of information of landscape dynamics to set priority areas for conservation and restoration.  Higher values define more important variables. Values higher than 0.50 are in boldface.  (DOC)  We thank Clinton Jenkins, Maria Ogrzewalska, Pedro Develey, Miguel Â. Marini, Paulo Inácio Prado and Wesley Silva for revising previous version of this manuscript. We are also grateful for the cooperation of the staff of IPÊ –Institute for Ecological Research for logistical support and for the field assistance of Cicero José da Silva Filho, o Cicinho. Financial support was provided by FAPESP (The São Paulo State Research Foundation, process no. 02/01746-1), Idea Wild and the Association of Field Ornithologists. JP Metzger thanks the Brazilian Science Council (Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico) for his research fellowship (process no. 307934/2011-0). Landsat data available from the U.S. Geological Survey 