 Conceived and designed the experiments: LG HH. Performed the experiments: LG. Analyzed the data: LG HH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LG HH. Wrote the paper: LG HH.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  The study of the interrelationship between productivity and biodiversity is a major research field in ecology. Theory predicts that if essential resources are heterogeneously distributed across a metacommunity, single species may dominate productivity in individual metacommunity patches, but a mixture of species will maximize productivity across the whole metacommunity. It also predicts that a balanced supply of resources within local patches should favor species coexistence, whereas resource imbalance would favor the dominance of one species. We performed an experiment with five freshwater algal species to study the effects of total supply of resources, their ratios, and species richness on biovolume production and evenness at the scale of both local patches and metacommunities. Generally, algal biovolume increased, whereas algal resource use efficiency (RUE) and evenness decreased with increasing total supply of resources in mixed communities containing all five species. In contrast to predictions for biovolume production, the species mixtures did not outperform all monocultures at the scale of metacommunities. In other words, we observed no general transgressive overyielding. However, RUE was always higher in mixtures than predicted from monocultures, and analyses indicate that resource partitioning or facilitation in mixtures resulted in higher-than-expected productivity at high resource supply. Contrasting our predictions for the local scale, balanced supply of resources did not generally favor higher local evenness, however lowest evenness was confined to patches with the most imbalanced supply. Thus, our study provides mixed support for recent theoretical advancements to understand biodiversity-productivity relationships.  H1: Increasing total amount of resources increases algal biovolume at both local patch and metacommunity scales.  H2: Imbalance in resource supply decreases realized algal diversity (evenness) in species mixtures treatments at the local scale.  H3: Resource use efficiency and productivity increase with algal richness at the metacommunity scale since the species with the highest resource use efficiency differs among patches with different resource ratios. Metacommunities consisting of only single species will thus have high biovolume in some local patches but not in others, whereas metacommunities consisting of all species will have high biovolume in all local patches. At the local scale, however, richness will have no effect since single species maximize biovolume production.  For additional information on how species richness and resource supply affected algal biovolume and resource use efficiency we included two extra levels of total phosphorus: 0.32 and 2.02 µmol L-1. These levels were crossed with the species mixture treatment only, yielding 18 extra flasks (grand total number of flasks = 180). Throughout the paper, the five levels of total phosphorus (0.13, 0.32, 0.81, 2.02, and 5.02) are referred to by the roman numbers I, II, III, IV, and V respectively.  The experiment ran for 31 days between February 21 st  and March 23 rd  2007 at the Institute for Botany, University of Cologne (latitude 50° 55′ 48″, longitude 6° 55′ 12″). Flasks were placed in a climate chamber set to 15°C with a 12 h: 12 h light: dark cycle, with each flask assigned a random position in the chamber. We exchanged medium on days 3, 6, 10, and 17 of the experiment by pipetting 5 mL (day 3 and 6) or 10 mL (the other dates) and replacing the removed volume with fresh medium. In total, we removed and replaced 10 ml from each local patch every week. The lids on the flasks had filtered ventilation holes to allow gas exchange while at the same time preventing cross-contamination. Each flask was gently stirred every second day to keep cells in suspension. At the same time, flasks were randomly redistributed to a new position to avoid effects of small-scale variation in light intensity in the climate chamber. All culturing and experimental work was performed under sterile conditions on a clean-bench, and all material was autoclaved and HCl-washed.  For analyses at the local scale on the effects of resource supply on algal biovolume and evenness we used a two-factor ANOVA (with α = 0.05) with total phosphorus (P sup ) and N∶P ratio as factors. When testing for the effects of initial species composition and richness we used a three-factor ANOVA with species composition, P sup  and N∶P ratio as factors. At the metacommunity scale, data were also analyzed with ANOVA with the exception that N∶P ratio was not included (since there was no manipulation of N∶P at this scale).  To explore hypothesis 4 we did correlations between observed patterns of realized algal evenness and RUE, at both local and metacommunity scales. We also did the correlations between realized algal evenness and RUE for the treatment residuals to evaluate if the relationship changes. If the results from the correlations on observed patterns and residuals differ, observed patterns may be largely due to treatment effects.  P sup  generally increased algal biovolume (A), decreased resource use efficiency (B), and decreased evenness (C). Results are based on the mixture treatments only. For this and the following figures, all error bars are 1 standard error.  Algal biovolume generally increased (A) and resource use efficiency decreased (B) with increasing P sup . There were mixed effects of P sup  and N∶P on evenness (C). Results are based on the mixture treatments only.  Results as analyzed with ANOVA with adjusted (adj) number of degrees of freedom in the error term (see text for details). Significant results are shown in bold.  Net diversity, complementarity, and selection effects for algal biovolume (A). Net diversity effects for resource use efficiency, Δ RUE  (B). The difference between evenness (Δ Evenness ) in mixture and in monocultures (C).  3 levels of total phosphorus (P sup ) and 3 levels of N∶P ratio (shown after comma sign as 2, 16 or 128). Δ RUE  and Δ Even  are observed resource use and observed evenness compared to expected values in monocultures. Significant results are shown in bold.  Net diversity effects for algal biovolume (A). Net diversity effects for resource use efficiency, Δ RUE  (B). The difference between evenness (Δ Evenness ) in mixture and in monocultures (C).  At the regional (A,B) and local (C,D) scale. A and C are raw observed data, B and D residuals after analyzing the response of both resource use efficiency and evenness to the resource supply treatments.  (DOC)  (DOC)  We thank Thomas van Gerven, Cordula Krücken and Helga Tiebel for help with the experiment. 