Conceived and designed the experiments: CW WV NB FB MF GG SH ML MSL SS EDS JS JFS WW WW BS. Performed the experiments: RP AW CR RLB NE EK AK AM PAN YO AS CS VMT. Analyzed the data: RP PAN CS JS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CW WV AW CR SA JB RLB NE GG AH EK AK AM SR GS. Wrote the paper: RP CW WV AW CR SA JB RLB NB FB NE MF GG SH AH EK AK ML AM PAN YO SR AS CS MSL SS EDS JS GS JFS VMT WW WW BS.The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.The diversity–stability hypothesis states that current losses of biodiversity can impair the ability of an ecosystem to dampen the effect of environmental perturbations on its functioning. Using data from a long-term and comprehensive biodiversity experiment, we quantified the temporal stability of 42 variables characterizing twelve ecological functions in managed grassland plots varying in plant species richness. We demonstrate that diversity increases stability i) across trophic levels (producer, consumer), ii) at both the system (community, ecosystem) and the component levels (population, functional group, phylogenetic clade), and iii) primarily for aboveground rather than belowground processes. Temporal synchronization across studied variables was mostly unaffected with increasing species richness. This study provides the strongest empirical support so far that diversity promotes stability across different ecological functions and levels of ecosystem organization in grasslands.‘Obs: Plots’ gives the number of measurements recorded across the reported time extent (temporal observations) and the number of assembled species mixtures in which the variables were measured (experimental plots). Superscript letters next to the time extent indicate whether the temporal dynamics of a variable was predominantly seasonal (s) or inter-annual (i). Each ecological function is represented in a multivariate space by three or four field variables, each variable characterizing a different facet of that function at one level of organization (in capital bold letters). Prior to the analyses, each variable was linearly scaled to remove the effect of measurement units.Our synthesis of the diversity–stability hypothesis in the Jena Experiment emphasizes two main results. Firstly, ecological functions at various organizational levels were stabilized with increasing plant species richness, as indicated by a decrease of the variance CV for the abundance of parasitic hymenoptera (food-web complexity), the suppression of non-resident plant species (bioregulation), vegetation structure and biomass production (primary producers), the abundance and diversity of invertebrates (secondary consumers), as well as trace gas fluxes (ecosystem properties). We found that the variance CV of ecological functions processes (Production of Earthworm Biomass and Below-Ground Invertebrates, Soil Nutrient and Water Content) associated to belowground processes was not significantly decreased with increasing species richness.The strong positive correlations among variables measured at the community and ecosystem levels may also result from allometric relationships between plant height, cover and biomass (Plant Stand Structure and Invasive Plant Bioregulation functions), from mathematical relations linking species abundance and richness in ecological communities (Arthropod Diversity function), and from spatial auto-correlation among observations (Soil Water and Nutrient Content functions). Although other factors may cause variables to be more strongly correlated at the higher levels of organization, this should only strengthen the possibility that increasing plant species richness can stabilize ecosystem functions in a bottom-up fashion.The 42 variables used in this study were grouped into twelve ecological functions according to their similarity and level of organization (a short description of each ecological function is given in parentheses): 1) Earthworm Biomass production (soil engineering; population level), 2) Parasitic Hymenoptera Abundance (food-web complexity; population level), 3) Invasive Plant Bioregulation (suppression of spontaneously invading plant species; population level), 4) Belowground Invertebrate Abundance (density of dominant soil macrofauna functional groups; phylogenetic clade level), 5) Aboveground Invertebrate Abundance (density of dominant aboveground, mainly saprophagous, phytophagous and parasitic, insect functional groups; phylogenetic clade level), 6) Plant Functional Group Biomass production (aboveground plant productivity; phylogenetic clade level), 7) Plant Stand Structure (vegetation development in cover, height, and biomass; community level), 8) Invasive Plant Bioregulation (suppression of spontaneously invading vegetation in cover, species diversity, and biomass; community level), 9) Arthropod Diversity (arthropod abundance and richness; community level), 10) Soil Water Content (use of water by organisms; ecosystem level), 11) Soil Nutrient Concentration (use of ammonium and nitrate by organisms; ecosystem level), and 12) Trace Gas Fluxes (net ecosystem–atmosphere exchange of CO2, N2O and CH4; ecosystem; ecosystem level).We would like to thank the gardeners and numerous student helpers for weeding and mowing of the experimental plots and help with data collection. We also thank Michel Loreau for providing helpful comments on a previous version of this manuscript. We acknowledge Teja Tscharntke, Elisabeth Marquard, Holger Bessler, and Christof Engels for their assistance in designing the Jena Experiment.