The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: NK OK. Performed the experiments: NK RS SH CM KI KW S. Kowata YK K. Tsubakimoto KO HS TM SO TO S. Kikuchi HT. Analyzed the data: NK OK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AN CI SC YA. Wrote the paper: NK OK AY K. Takagi.This study was conducted in the Teshio Experimental Forest of Hokkaido University (45°03’N, 142°07’E), which is located in the northernmost Japanese forest zone. The mean annual temperature in this forest is 5°C (max. 35°C, min. −35°C), and the annual precipitation is approx. 1000 mm. About one half of the region’s annual precipitation occurs as snowfall between late November and early April. Because forest fires occurred several times during the last 100 years and customary forest practices have resulted in open spaces that promote bamboo invasion, bamboo bushes cover wide areas in the forests.We invited expert harvesters (aged 25 to 64) to collect bamboo shoots in the harvest treatment plots in early June 2013. During the short time that is suitable for harvesting the bamboo shoots, multiple groups of people enter the bamboo bush areas to collect bamboo shoots from several sites. To mimic this situation, we formed two groups consisting of four members, and they collected bamboo shoots from the harvest treatment plots two times, on June 6th and 10th, 2013. Generally, harvesters collect bamboo shoots moderately instead of exhaustively at each site, because they move to other sites as soon as they cannot easily find the edible bamboo shoots. In this study, we asked our harvesters to collect bamboo shoots based on this ordinary harvesting policy in the plots, and we recorded the number of shoots taken from each quadrat. All of the harvesters were aware that their collections were being performed as part of a scientific study.To compare bamboo shoot productivity between treatments, we measured the number of bamboo shoots in the control plots on the same days that we counted the remaining bamboo shoots in the harvested plots (on June 11th and 28th and July 26th, 2013). We also counted the number of culms of bamboo grass in each quadrat to evaluate bamboo density, which potentially has effects on the productivity of bamboo shoots, on June 28th 2013.To evaluate how harvesting influences bamboo shoot productivity and the density of bamboo grass in the year following harvesting, we evaluated bamboo shoot productivity and the density of bamboo grass in 2014, using the same method as in 2013. We harvested bamboo shoots from harvested plots on May 30th and June 4th 2014, and counted the numbers of produced bamboo shoots and bamboo grass in all experimental quadrats on July 7th 2014.(a) Harvest treatment and (b) control treatment.(a) Numbers of produced bamboo shoots one day after harvesting (on June 11th, 2013) and 2–46 days after harvesting (from June 12th to July 26th 2013). Red circles: harvest. Blue circles: control. (b) Total number of bamboo shoots produced in 2013. Bars: SE values.(a) Relationship between the density of the matured bamboo grass and the bamboo shoot productivity. Red circles: harvest. Blue circles: control. Solid line indicates the linear regression between the density of matured bamboo grass and bamboo shoots. (b) Density of matured bamboo grass. Bars: SE values.(a) Numbers of bamboo shoots produced. Bars: SE values. (b) Relationship of produced bamboo shoots between the year of harvesting (2013) and the next year (2014). Red circles: harvest. Blue circles: control. Solid and dashed lines indicate the linear regression of the harvest and control treatment, respectively.Red circles: harvest treatment. Blue circles: control treatment. Solid and dashed lines indicate the linear regression of the harvest and control treatment, respectively. Dotted line denotes no change in bamboo grass density between 2013 and 2014.Based on the two hypothetical processes described above, we might expect long-term harvesting to lower bamboo shoot productivity. However, the expert harvesters in our study area felt that based on their experiences, greater numbers of bamboo shoots emerge at sites where the harvesters have annually collected them compared to sites where they rarely visit. Several characteristics of bamboo, such as its high photosynthetic rate and resource reallocation, may prevent the reduction of resource storage and bamboo density. We need to investigate how long-term harvesting affects bamboo productivity in future research.(PDF)The relative productivity was the log-transformed proportion of shoot productivity in 2014 divided by that in 2013 for the same plot. Bars: SE values.(PDF)We thank K. Takasu and M. Nosaka of Hokkaido University for the helpful advice. We are also grateful to the staff at the Teshio Experimental Forest of Hokkaido University for their support during this study. We also thank M. Whitaker for correcting the English of the text.