 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: PGS MIMH. Performed the experiments: PGS MIMH. Analyzed the data: PGS MIMH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PGS MIMH. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: PGS MIMH.  Understanding the ecological mechanisms driving beta diversity is a major goal of community ecology. Metacommunity theory brings new ways of thinking about the structure of local communities, including processes occurring at different spatial scales. In addition to new theories, new methods have been developed which allow the partitioning of individual and shared contributions of environmental and spatial effects, as well as identification of species and sites that have importance in the generation of beta diversity along ecological gradients. We analyzed the spatial distribution of dung beetle communities in areas of Atlantic Forest in a mainland-island scenario in southern Brazil, with the objective of identifying the mechanisms driving composition, abundance and biomass at three spatial scales (mainland-island, areas and sites). We sampled 20 sites across four large areas, two on the mainland and two on the island. The distribution of our sampling sites was hierarchical and areas are isolated. We used standardized protocols to assess environmental heterogeneity and sample dung beetles. We used spatial eigenfunctions analysis to generate the spatial patterns of sampling points. Environmental heterogeneity showed strong variation among sites and a mild increase with increasing spatial scale. The analysis of diversity partitioning showed an increase in beta diversity with increasing spatial scale. Variation partitioning based on environmental and spatial variables suggests that environmental heterogeneity is the most important driver of beta diversity at the local scale. The spatial effects were significant only at larger spatial scales. Our study presents a case where environmental heterogeneity seems to be the main factor structuring communities at smaller scales, while spatial effects are more important at larger scales. The increase in beta diversity that occurs at larger scales seems to be the result of limitation in species dispersal ability due to habitat fragmentation and the presence of geographical barriers.  Therefore, the aim of our study was to investigate the effect of spatial scales on the patterns of species diversity of dung beetles in Brazilian Atlantic Forest and to identify the mechanisms that drive these patterns applying aspects of metacommunity theory. We tested the hypothesis that the distribution of dung beetles in the Atlantic Forest is associated with differences in forest structure and that high levels of beta diversity will be found with increasing spatial scale due to dispersal limitation. Our predictions are as follows: (i) because dung beetles are sensitive to environmental changes, environmental gradients should result in high beta diversity among sites via species sorting, (ii) due to differences in habitat structure of each site, environmental characteristics and dung beetle species distribution are spatially structured, (iii) because of dispersal limitation among areas (mainland-island and fragmented landscape), the spatial effect has high importance in structuring communities at increased spatial scales.  Location of the four areas sampled in eastern Santa Catarina state, Brazil. ANH: Environmental Protection Area of Anhatomirim; ITA: Permanent Protection Area of Itapema; PER: Lagoa do Peri Municipal Park; RAT: Permanent Protection Area of Ratones.  The partitioning was performed for species richness and Shannon entropy of dung beetles. α = local diversity, β1 = diversity among sites, β2 = diversity among areas, β3 = diversity among mainland-island.  LCBD analysis used composition, abundance and dry biomass data. ANH: Environmental Protection Area of Anhatomirim; ITA: Permanent Protection Area of Itapema; PER: Lagoa do Peri Municipal Park; RAT: Permanent Protection Area of Ratones. The circles are proportional to the total value of LCBD for each analysis.  E: environmental model, S: spatial model, constructed from MEM variables, E | S: environmental model without spatial patterns within each spatial scale, S | E: spatial model without environmental patterns within each spatial scale, R 2  adj : data variation explained by the model (values are in percentage), DF: degrees of freedom of model. Significant models are in bold.  Environmental model constructed from the altitude variable;  b Spatial model constructed from the MEM1 and MEM2 variables;  c Spatial model constructed from the MEM4, MEM9, MEM5, MEM3, and MEM1 variables;  d Spatial model constructed from all MEM variables;  e Environmental model constructed from the altitude, green cover and land slope variables;  f Spatial model constructed from the MEM1 variable;  g Spatial model constructed from the MEM4, MEM9, MEM3, MEM7, MEM1, MEM2, and MEM5 variables;  h constructed from the MEM4, MEM3, MEM2, MEM5, MEM7, and MEM1 variables.  Between the mainland and the island, beta diversity showed the highest values and at this scale only the environmental model was significant for species composition, while for abundance the environmental and spatial models were significant. The high beta diversity found between the mainland and the island has its origin at site and area scales, where environmental and spatial patterns have high relative importance. Thus, we observed that the distribution of dung beetles along an ecological gradient occurs in a spatially structured environment, where such patterns may be generated due to dispersal limitation at intermediate scales, and due to environmental heterogeneity at local scales.  (EPS)  (XLSX)  (XLSX)  We are grateful to Ana Siegloch, Franciéle Garcês, Javier Toso, Jéssica Pires, Juliano Bogoni, Rafael Schmitt, Renata Calixto and Tamyris Gregolini for help during the fieldwork. We thank Fernando Vaz de Mello and David Edmonds for dung beetle identification. We thank the Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade (ICMBio/MMA) and Fundação do Meio Ambiente (FATMA-SC) for permission to collect. 