The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: NJ NH UW MT. Performed the experiments: NJ. Analyzed the data: NJ MT. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MT. Wrote the paper: NJ MT NH UW.Submarine canyons are considered biodiversity hotspots which have been identified for their important roles in connecting the deep sea with shallower waters. To date, a huge gap exists between the high importance that scientists associate with deep-sea ecosystem services and the communication of this knowledge to decision makers and to the wider public, who remain largely ignorant of the importance of these services. The connectivity and complexity of marine ecosystems makes knowledge transfer very challenging, and new communication tools are necessary to increase understanding of ecological values beyond the science community. We show how the Ecosystem Principles Approach, a method that explains the importance of ocean processes via easily understandable ecological principles, might overcome this challenge for deep-sea ecosystem services. Scientists were asked to help develop a list of clear and concise ecosystem principles for the functioning of submarine canyons through a Delphi process to facilitate future transfers of ecological knowledge. These ecosystem principles describe ecosystem processes, link such processes to ecosystem services, and provide spatial and temporal information on the connectivity between deep and shallow waters. They also elucidate unique characteristics of submarine canyons. Our Ecosystem Principles Approach was successful in integrating ecological information into the ecosystem services assessment process. It therefore has a high potential to be the next step towards a wider implementation of ecological values in marine planning. We believe that successful communication of ecological knowledge is the key to a wider public support for ocean conservation, and that this endeavour has to be driven by scientists in their own interest as major deep-sea stakeholders.Survey steps where experts were directly involved are highlighted as black boxes.Services are grouped into four categories: provisioning, regulating, cultural and intermediate.*Deep-sea ES that were not taken forward for the development of submarine canyon principles.We also asked the expert panel to categorise ecosystem principles according to their level of generality. The following categories were available: (i) general deep-sea principle, (ii) general canyon principle, (iii) shelf-incising canyon specific principles, to (iv) Nazaré Canyon-specific principle. The option with the highest frequency was then presented as the group vote in the subsequent survey.Only in the second stage of the Delphi process were experts asked to distinguish their rating based on evidence on the one side and their expert view (as individuals) on the other side. The evidence base was rated on a five-point scale from ‘very poor’ to ‘very good’. For the presentation of the group result, this was then divided into three categories of good, intermediate or poor evidence, according to the average group scores. These evidence scores had no influence on the decision to include or exclude any principle, but were introduced to separate personal opinion from the levels of evidence that existed in support of the principle.During the workshop experts stressed the importance of the connectivity function of submarine canyons at the continental margin and we therefore chose ‘water circulation and exchange’ as an example to demonstrate how ecosystem principles link the supply of ES with their underlying processes. In the final results section, those ecosystem principles which in their description indicated a relationship between the ES ‘water circulation and exchange’ and other services were linked. The ecosystem principles relevant to this particular ES were assigned by the authors of this paper.ID = principle identification number. The plausibility rating: ten experts participated in the full rating process (i.e. 100% = 10 experts). The evidence rating (1–5 from ‘very good’ to ‘very poor’): poor (mean score &lt;2.5), medium (2.5≤ mean score &lt;3.5) and good (mean score ≥3.5); SE = standard error.ID = principle identification number. The plausibility rating: ten experts participated in the full rating process (i.e. 100% = 10 experts). The evidence rating (1–5 from ‘very good’ to ‘very poor’): poor (mean score &lt;2.5), medium (2.5≤mean score &lt;3.5) and good (mean score ≥3.5); SE = standard error.*Principles P18–P21 were rejected by the majority of experts, i.e. their plausibility was below 50%.Developing principles to link food availability with biodiversity was challenging, and none were rated as plausible (P18 and P20). Experts had strong concerns of oversimplification when it came to the type, quality and amount of organic matter as a source of food and how changes of those parameters affected biodiversity. For biodiversity there was again a concern of over-simplification by omitting information on the spatial scale of biodiversity. In the same way, geographical scale mattered to experts, and lack of information on depth ranges and exact geographical position was criticised. The rating on generality provided a preliminary solution for implementing information on the geographical transferability of principles. Giving experts the chance to express uncertainty about the generality of principles as well as disentangling opinions about the rating of evidence allowed them to express their expectations for submarine canyons based on their research experience, and to transfer widely accepted knowledge from other ecosystems.We share the view of one workshop participant who stated that it will be difficult to determine when the list of ecosystem principles is complete. New evidence, the inclusion of researchers with different academic backgrounds, and assigning more time to the task might increase the number of principles on the list. Thus including a broad range of disciplines into the principle development process is crucial. Nonetheless, there exists an asymptotic relationship between effort expended and the number of principles, where spending more time on identifying and reviewing submarine canyon principles might increase the detail of principles, but not their utility for management decisions. The EPA’s utility lies not in providing large amounts of detail, but in providing meaningful, concise information to better understand the overall functioning of the ecosystem in conjunction with the ES it provides. The EPA is based on what we know today and the ecosystem principles in this paper cover a broad range of topics, with further workshops or surveys being likely to provide diminishing returns of new principles to our established list.The EPA should be seen as an addition to baseline ecological research and economic ES valuation, rather than as a substitute for either. The EPA’s advantage lies where monetary valuation reaches its limits, in highlighting links between ES and their underlying processes, and in linking intermediate services with final ES. While economic ES values can help set marine management priorities that are socially and economically desirable (Daily et al., 2009), the EPA focusses on the ecological ‘value’ of the ecosystem and can provide important information on how such management priorities can be achieved. Where economic values require empirical links to well-being and monetary quantification, ecological ‘value’ is more focussed on the importance of the ecosystem processes and characteristics that lead to such economically valued benefits being produced.Using the EPA it should be possible to provide more precise temporal and spatial information on ecosystem principles, and to develop management strategies based on the list of principles and evidence on social and economic values and resulting management priorities. Showing the EPA’s potential to improve people’s understanding of ecosystem functioning was beyond the scope of this study, but future research involving the wider public and decision makers would be beneficial to test the effect of such simplified ecological knowledge on their decisions.Three insights in particular emerge from our interdisciplinary workshop, which might improve future marine conservation initiatives and their acceptance:To further the field of marine ES valuation it would be beneficial to acknowledge that the traditional approaches to ES valuation, which have their roots in terrestrial research, might not be easily transferable to a highly linked marine environment. Marine ecosystem boundaries are much less clearly defined than in terrestrial environments, and ES flows are less easily traceable. We might therefore need different approaches to valuing ES flows in the marine environment. The EPA is but one potential approach to improve integration of ecological values with social and economic values.The precautionary principle demands that we are cautious with our exploitation of the environment, but in the same time that management recommendations are made on a timely basis to the best of our knowledge, without postponing decisions for indefinite time until more certainty has been gained. The marine science community should more willingly embrace its important societal role in providing recommendations for nature conservation management with the support of social science approaches.We propose greater transparency in decisions on the conservation importance of marine areas. It should be possible to enhance understanding of the social, ecological as well as the economic values of certain areas, and to justify their protection, by providing easy understandable information on marine ES and how they relate to underlying ecosystem processes.(DOCX)We are deeply thankful to the workshop and survey participants for their time and input, and to Dr Rene van der Wal, Dr Nicolas Krucien, and Prof Graham Pierce (University of Aberdeen) for constructive feedback on early drafts of this paper. We also like to thank Dr Veerle Huvenne (National Oceanography Centre) and the Instituto Hidrografico for the Nazaré Canyon bathymetry data, and the conference organizers for the workshop opportunity during the HERMIONE Annual Meeting 2012. We also thank two anonymous reviewers for their comments.