 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: MLC TMA. Performed the experiments: ASC MLC TMA. Analyzed the data: ASC MLC TMA. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MLC TMA ASC AE. Wrote the paper: ASC MLC TMA AE.  Monitoring land change at multiple spatial scales is essential for identifying hotspots of change, and for developing and implementing policies for conserving biodiversity and habitats. In the high diversity country of Colombia, these types of analyses are difficult because there is no consistent wall-to-wall, multi-temporal dataset for land-use and land-cover change.  To address this problem, we mapped annual land-use and land-cover from 2001 to 2010 in Colombia using MODIS (250 m) products coupled with reference data from high spatial resolution imagery (QuickBird) in Google Earth. We used QuickBird imagery to visually interpret percent cover of eight land cover classes used for classifier training and accuracy assessment. Based on these maps we evaluated land cover change at four spatial scales country, biome, ecoregion, and municipality. Of the 1,117 municipalities, 820 had a net gain in woody vegetation (28,092 km 2 ) while 264 had a net loss (11,129 km 2 ), which resulted in a net gain of 16,963 km 2  in woody vegetation at the national scale. Woody regrowth mainly occurred in areas previously classified as mixed woody/plantation rather than agriculture/herbaceous. The majority of this gain occurred in the Moist Forest biome, within the montane forest ecoregions, while the greatest loss of woody vegetation occurred in the Llanos and Apure-Villavicencio ecoregions.  The unexpected forest recovery trend, particularly in the Andes, provides an opportunity to expand current protected areas and to promote habitat connectivity. Furthermore, ecoregions with intense land conversion (e.g. Northern Andean Páramo) and ecoregions under-represented in the protected area network (e.g. Llanos, Apure-Villavicencio Dry forest, and Magdalena-Urabá Moist forest ecoregions) should be considered for new protected areas.  Insert shows the distribution of the six biomes, and the five regions.  The purpose of the present study is to assess land change from 2001 to 2010 in Colombia, with a focus on three objectives: (1) determine how land change varies at the country, biome, ecoregion, and municipality scales; (2) identify and analyze the spatial distribution of areas experiencing significant land change; and, (3) discuss the implications of our findings for land use and conservation planning in Colombia. This research was based on a novel method for mapping LULC annually, which coupled MODIS (250 m) products with reference data interpreted from high spatial resolution imagery (QuickBird) in Google Earth that allows us to quantify land change at multiple spatial scales.  These include only samples filtered by the Random Forest outlier removal step (Biomes follow Olson et al. 2001).  Tropical and Subtropical Moist Broadleaf Forest (Amazon basin section).  Tropical and Subtropical Moist Broadleaf Forest (Coastal lowlands section).  Tropical and Subtropical Dry Broadleaf Forest.  Tropical and Subtropical Grasslands, Savannas and Shrublands.  These estimates are based on estimates from municipality-scale regression models and include all municipalities.  Forest cover (80 crown cover).  Forest cover (25 crown cover).  Cabrera E, Vargas DM, Galindo G, García MC, Ordoñez MF, et al. (2011).  FAO (2010) Global Forest Resources Assessment 2010.  Hansen M, DeFries R, Townshend JR, Carroll M, Dimiceli C, et al. (2006).  (TIF)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  We thank George Riner at Sonoma State University for helping with data processing. We also thank Benjamin J. Crain for editing previous versions of this manuscript. Additional thanks to two anonymous reviewers for comments that helped to improve the manuscript. 