 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: DDS ØT SRM. Performed the experiments: DDS. Analyzed the data: DDS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DDS MP PJP ØT SRM. Wrote the paper: DDS MP PJP ØT SRM.  We have limited understanding of how tropical canopy foliage varies along environmental gradients, and how this may in turn affect forest processes and functions. Here, we analyse the relationships between canopy leaf area index (LAI) and above ground herbaceous biomass (AGB H ) along environmental gradients in a moist forest and miombo woodland in Tanzania. We recorded canopy structure and herbaceous biomass in 100 permanent vegetation plots (20 m × 40 m), stratified by elevation. We quantified tree species richness, evenness, Shannon diversity and predominant height as measures of structural variability, and disturbance (tree stumps), soil nutrients and elevation as indicators of environmental variability. Moist forest and miombo woodland differed substantially with respect to nearly all variables tested. Both structural and environmental variables were found to affect LAI and AGB H , the latter being additionally dependent on LAI in moist forest but not in miombo, where other factors are limiting. Combining structural and environmental predictors yielded the most powerful models. In moist forest, they explained 76% and 25% of deviance in LAI and AGB H , respectively. In miombo woodland, they explained 82% and 45% of deviance in LAI and AGB H . In moist forest, LAI increased non-linearly with predominant height and linearly with tree richness, and decreased with soil nitrogen except under high disturbance. Miombo woodland LAI increased linearly with stem density, soil phosphorous and nitrogen, and decreased linearly with tree species evenness. AGB H  in moist forest decreased with LAI at lower elevations whilst increasing slightly at higher elevations. AGB H  in miombo woodland increased linearly with soil nitrogen and soil pH. Overall, moist forest plots had denser canopies and lower AGB H  compared with miombo plots. Further field studies are encouraged, to disentangle the direct influence of LAI on AGB H  from complex interrelationships between stand structure, environmental gradients and disturbance in African forests and woodlands.  Here, we analyse the relationships between canopy leaf area index (LAI) and above ground herbaceous biomass (AGB H ) in a moist forest and miombo woodland in Tanzania. Our objectives are to test the hypotheses that forest structural attributes (tree richness and size distribution) can be used to predict canopy leaf area (LAI), and that AGB H  is negatively related to LAI due to light extinction through the canopy. We explore the extent to which our findings vary along environmental and disturbance gradients, and between moist forest and miombo woodland systems.  Soil samples were collected at three depths (0–15 cm, 15–30 cm and 30–60 cm) at five points per plot, i.e. from each of the four corners and from the centre of the main plot. We aggregated samples for each depth into composites for subsequent analyses. The resulting 300 soil samples were air-dried and sieved through a 2 mm wire mesh and analysed for soil pH (at 1:2.5 soil: H 2 O), organic carbon (Walkley-Black method), available phosphorous (Bray II), total nitrogen (Kjeldahl method), potassium and sodium (ammonium acetate 1.0 M pH7.0 extraction) at Seliani Agricultural Research Institute, Arusha, Tanzania.  * Corresponding Wilcoxon Mann-Whitney test showing the differences in median of the measured parameters between moist forest (N = 60) and miombo woodland (N = 40).  In a first step, we fitted two subsets of models focussing on: structural variables as predictors of either LAI or AGB H ; and environmental variables as predictors of either LAI or AGB H . Each of these models included disturbance as additional predictor and first term interactions between all predictors. We then combined structural and environmental predictors, disturbance and first term interactions between predictors, into one single model for each response in each vegetation type.  (TIFF)  (Forest 1) LAI show linear relationships with soil nitrogen in moist forest, (Miombo 2) with soil nitrogen, (Miombo 3) soil phosphorous, and (Miombo 4) soil potassium in Miombo woodland. (Forest 5) AGB H  show linear relationships with elevation in moist forest, (Miombo 6) with soil nitrogen, (Miombo 7) soil pH and (Miombo 8) with disturbance in miombo woodland when all other variables are set to their mean values. The solid lines are the fitted partial regression lines with 95% shaded confidence band.  (TIFF)  Models used either structural, environmental variables, or a combination of both. Note: Only predicator variables with variance inflation factor (VIF) ≤ 3 and Pearson correlation coefficient (r) ≤ 50% were included in the model.  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  We thank Hamidu Seki, Rashi Khasim, John Herbet, George Bulenga, Osca Bakombezi, Godgift Swai, Godbless Lema and Hussein Shelukindo who assisted during fieldwork. Mr. Mhoro and Canicius Kayombo helped in plant identification. We thank P.K.T Munishi for his guidance and support during the design of this study. 