The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: EdV KB. Performed the experiments: EdV KB EVG. Analyzed the data: EVG. Wrote the paper: EdV EVG KB.Extensive land-use change in the tropics has produced a mosaic of successional forests within an agricultural and cattle-pasture matrix. Post-disturbance biodiversity assessments have found that regeneration speed depends upon propagule availability and the intensity and duration of disturbance. However, reestablishment of species interactions is still poorly understood and this limits our understanding of the anthropogenic impacts upon ecosystem resilience. This is the first investigation that evaluates plant-herbivore interaction networks during secondary succession. In particular we investigated succession in a Mexican tropical dry forest using data of caterpillar associations with plants during 2007–2010. Plant-herbivore networks showed high resilience. We found no differences in most network descriptors between secondary and mature forest and only recently abandoned fields were found to be different. No significant nestedness or modularity network structure was found. Plant-herbivore network properties appear to quickly reestablish after perturbation, despite differences in species richness and composition. This study provides some valuable guidelines for the implement of restoration efforts that can enhance ecological processes such as the interaction between plants and their herbivores.During the rainy season of each year in the period 2007–2010, surveys were carried out in labeled plants searching for caterpillars on all leaves and stems. A total of 19 surveys were conducted. In order to search for caterpillars on adult trees, a subsample of three branches - comprising approximately 100 leaves - was taken per individual tree. Caterpillars were recorded and raised in the laboratory to procure adults for subsequent taxonomic identification. Plant material was also collected and identified to at least family level.Incidence of plant species in different successional stages of tropical dry forest in the Chamela region. Numbers indicate the number of Lepidopteran species found associated with that plant species. * indicates absence, 0 indicates that the plant is present in the successional stage but has no interaction with Lepidopterans.(DOCX)Incidence of Lepidopteran species in different successional stages of tropical dry forest in the Chamela region. Numbers indicate the number of plant species where that Lepidopteran species was found. 0 indicates absence.(DOCX)We would like to thank the students of the biotic interactions ecology laboratory of CIECO, UNAM, Eloy Castro, Antonio López-Carretero, César Manrique, and Irais Medina and Rubén Pérez for their logistic support. Francisco Mora helped with plant identification and M. Ibarra provided lepidopteran identification. Lucero Sevillano, Martha Lopezaraiza-Mikel, Juan Núñez-Farfán, Heberto Ferreira, Carsten Dorman and Ernesto Vega helped with data analysis. We especially wish to acknowledge the integrative ecology lab of Doñana biological station, especially Jordi Bascompte and Miguel Angel Fortuna for their advice for data analysis. Héctor Arita's comments significantly improve the manuscript.