The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: CR BS. Performed the experiments: CR UG. Analyzed the data: CR JS UG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CR BS. Wrote the paper: CR BS JS.The prevalence of different biotic processes (limiting similarity, weaker competitor exclusion) and historical contingency due to priority effects are in the focus of ongoing discussions about community assembly and non-random functional trait distributions.We experimentally manipulated assembly history in a grassland biodiversity experiment (Jena Experiment) by applying two factorially crossed split-plot treatments to all communities: (i) duration of weeding (never weeded since sowing or cessation of weeding after 3 or 6 years); (ii) seed addition (control vs. seed addition 4 years after sowing). Spontaneous colonization of new species in the control treatment without seed addition increased realized species richness and functional richness (FRic), indicating continuously denser packing of niches. Seed addition resulted in forced colonization and increased realized species richness, FRic, functional evenness (FEve) and functional divergence (FDiv), i.e. higher abundances of species with extreme trait values. Furthermore, the colonization of new species led to a decline in FEve through time, suggesting that weaker competitors were reduced in abundance or excluded. Communities with higher initial species richness or with longer time since cessation of weeding were more restricted in the entry of new species and showed smaller increases in FRic after seed addition than other communities. The two assembly-history treatments caused a divergence of species compositions within communities originally established with the same species. Communities originally established with different species converged in species richness and functional trait composition over time, but remained more distinct in species composition.Contrasting biotic processes (limiting similarity, weaker competitor exclusion) increase functional convergence between communities initially established with different species. Historical contingency with regard to realized species compositions could not be eradicated by cessation of weeding or forced colonization and was still detectable 5 years after application of these treatments, providing evidence for the role of priority effects in community assembly.Vertical arrows indicate the time, when weeding was stopped in different treatments: (S0−)  =  never weeded, no seed addition, (S0+)  =  never weeded, seed addition (2005), (S3−)  =  cessation of weeding after three years (2004), no seed addition, (S3+)  =  cessation of weeding after three years (2004), seed addition (2005), (S6−)  =  cessation of weeding after six years (2007), no seed addition, and (S6+)  =  cessation of weeding after six years (2007), seed addition (2005).(S6−) cessation of weeding after six years (2007), no seed addition,(S6+) cessation of weeding after six years (2007), seed addition (2005),(S3−) cessation of weeding after three years (2004), no seed addition,(S3+) cessation of weeding after three years (2004), seed addition (2005),(S0−) never weeded, no seed addition, and(S0+) never weeded, seed addition (2005).Plots were mown twice per year (June, September) and the mown plant material was removed.Models were fitted by stepwise inclusion of fixed effects. Listed are the results of likelihood ratio tests (L ratio) that were applied to assess model improvement and the statistical significance of the fixed effects (p values). Arrows indicate increase (↑) or decrease (↓) of the variables with species richness, functional group number, after seed addition, with increasing colonization period or with time; SR  =  initial species richness, FG  =  functional group number, ADD  =  seed addition in 2005, C  =  colonization period.FRic as a function of time (A), and plotted against realized species richness (B, C), FEve as a function of time (D), and plotted against realized species richness (E, F), and FDiv as a function of time (G), and plotted against realized species richness (H, I) as mean values (±1SE) per initial species-richness level across colonization periods. Treatments without seed addition are shown in (B, E, H), and treatments with seed addition are shown in (C, F, I).FRic as a function of time (A), and plotted against realized species richness (B, C), FEve as a function of time (D), and plotted against realized species richness (E, F), and FDiv as a function of time (G), and plotted against realized species richness (H, I) as mean values (±1SE) per colonization period across initial species-richness levels. Treatments without seed addition are shown in (B, E, H), and treatments with seed addition are shown in (C, F, I).Dissimilarities based on species composition (A, C), and functional trait composition (B, D) as a function of time. Between-community dissimilarities were calculated as mean pair-wise Bray-Curtis distances between all communities per colonization period × seed addition treatment, and within-community dissimilarities between split-plots with different assembly histories were calculated as mean pair-wise Bray-Curtis distances between colonization period × seed addition treatments per community. Mean values (±1SE) per initial species-richness level across colonization period × seed addition treatments (A, B), and mean values (±1SE) per colonization period × seed addition treatment across sown species-richness levels (C, D) are shown.Models were fitted by stepwise inclusion of fixed effects. Listed are the results of likelihood ratio tests (L ratio) that were applied to assess model improvement and the statistical significance of the fixed effects (p values). Arrows indicate increase (↑) or decrease (↓) of the variables with species richness, functional group number, after seed addition, with increasing colonization period or with time; SR  =  initial species richness, FG  =  functional group number, ADD  =  seed addition in 2005, C  =  colonization period.Between- and within-community coefficients of variation of realized species richness, FRic, FEve and FDiv.(DOC)Reference list for data on specific leaf area of particular plant species included in the matrix of functional traits.(DOC)We thank E.-D. Schulze for discussion on the experimental results. We acknowledge W.W. Weisser for coordination of the Jena Experiment, and A. Weigelt for coordination of the field site. We thank U. Wehmeier, A. Enke and several student helpers for their support with the establishment and maintenance of the split-plot experiment.