 Conceived and designed the experiments: MSL. Performed the experiments: MSL. Analyzed the data: DM SV NWHM MSL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DM SV NWHM MSL. Wrote the manuscript: DM SV NWHM MSL.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  All these biodiversity components are not mutually exclusive but are unlikely to exert equal influence on ecosystem processes and on the multifunctionality of ecosystems. Thus the question is no longer whether each of the three components of biodiversity (taxonomic diversity, functional identity and functional diversity) matters but whether it still matters after removing the effect of two other components? In other words, we examined the additional effect of each biodiversity component on the prediction of ecosystem processes to determine whether each component has an essential and complementary contribution to the explanation of ecosystem multifunctionality. Further, by including the eight biodiversity indices, embracing all aspects of taxonomic and functional structure of communities, we built a minimum adequate model that reached an unprecedented level of explanatory power with functional identity and functional diversity together as predictor variables of multiple ecosystem processes. Finally, we implemented structural equation models to explore both causal and spurious associations between predictors of ecosystem processes.  We used data on several ecosystem processes including biomass production and decomposition trials within the German BIODEPTH experiment (BIODiversity and Ecological Processes in Terrestrial Herbaceous Ecosystems) to predict the effects of biodiversity change on ecosystem functioning. This experiment allows testing all components of biodiversity given that, for each species richness level, different species combinations were constructed.  All statistical analyses were carried out using R software and packages ‘qpcR’, ‘car’ and ‘lavaan’.  Species used in the German BIODEPTH experiment with their traits.  (DOC)  Values of the variance inflation factor (VIF) for each biodiversity index (S: species richness, E: species evenness, PC1 PC2 and PC3: aggregated mean trait values along three PCoA axes, FRic: functional richness, FEve: functional evenness, FDiv: functional divergence).  (DOC)  Calculation of functional diversity indices.  (DOC)  Results from Structural Equation Models (SEM) for each process.  (DOC)  We are grateful to those colleagues that commented on earlier versions of this manuscript, including Michel Loreau, Andy Hector and Eric Garnier. 