The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: SHG MCG. Performed the experiments: SHG MCG. Analyzed the data: CAB. Wrote the manuscript: CAB DAL. Aphidophagous coccinellids (ladybeetles) are important providers of herbivore suppression ecosystem services. In the last 30 years, the invasion of exotic coccinellid species, coupled with observed declines in native species, has led to considerable interest in the community dynamics and ecosystem function of this guild. Here we examined a 24-year dataset of coccinellid communities in nine habitats in southwestern Michigan for changes in community function in response to invasion. Specifically we analyzed their temporal population dynamics and species diversity, and we modeled the community’s potential to suppress pests. Abundance of coccinellids varied widely between 1989 and 2012 and became increasingly exotic-dominated. More than 71% of 57,813 adult coccinellids captured over the 24-year study were exotic species. Shannon diversity increased slightly over time, but herbivore suppression potential of the community remained roughly constant over the course of the study. However, both Shannon diversity and herbivore suppression potential due to native species declined over time in all habitats. The relationship between Shannon diversity and herbivore suppression potential varied with habitat type: a positive relationship in forest and perennial habitats, but was uncorrelated in annual habitats. This trend may have been because annual habitats were dominated by a few, highly voracious exotic species. Our results indicated that although the composition of the coccinellid community in southwestern Michigan has changed dramatically in the past several decades, its function has remained relatively unchanged in both agricultural and natural habitats. While this is encouraging from the perspective of pest management, it should be noted that losses of one of the dominant exotic coccinellids could result in a rapid decline in pest suppression services if the remaining community is unable to respond. All studies occurred at Michigan State University’s Kellogg Biological Station (KBS) in southwestern Michigan (42°24’N, 85°24’W) at 288 m elevation. Coccinellid surveillance data were collected starting in 1989 at the KBS Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) site as part of the Main Cropping System Experiment (MCSE) and forest sites. See http://lter.kbs.msu.edu/research/long-term-experiments/main-cropping-system-experiment/ and http://lter.kbs.msu.edu/research/long-term-experiments/successional-and-forest-sites/ for a detailed experimental design. The MCSE consists of seven treatments including treatments of annual field crops (maize, soybeans and wheat) in annual rotation under 4 levels of management intensity (conventional, no-till, reduced input, and biologically based), as well as alfalfa, poplar and early successional vegetation (i.e. abandoned agricultural fields). Each treatment is replicated six times with individual plot sizes of 1 ha. Observations are taken from five permanent sampling stations within each treatment-replicate combination. Instead of grouping by management intensity for this analysis, coccinellid abundance data from the MCSE were grouped by the particular host crop planted in that treatment-replicate combination in a given observation-year combination. Forest sampling began in 1993, at sites within 3 km of the MCSE on the KBS. Forest types included: 40-60 year old conifer forest plantations, late successional deciduous forest, and successional forests occurring on abandoned agricultural land. Three 1 ha replicates of each forest type are monitored at five sampling stations, as in the MCSE. The LTER experiment continues to date. Detailed agronomic records for the site are available at http://lter.kbs.msu.edu/datatables/150. Coccinellid abundance data is available online at http://lter.kbs.msu.edu/datatables/67. A relational database in MS Access® integrating coccinellid data with the relevant environmental and agronomic records used in this analysis is available from the authors by request.Data were examined at two different temporal resolutions to gain insight into both real-time interactions and between season trends. First, the sum of all captures from each sampling station in a given week, in a given treatment by replicate combination, was called ‘weekly average,’ and the sum of all captures in a given treatment over a calendar year, was referred to as ‘yearly total.’ Data were further subdivided into sets of ‘all coccinellids’ and ‘native species only’ to detect differences in diversity and function of native coccinellids compared to the community as a whole. To aide in data visualization, a Gaussian smoother with a span of 3 units was used to produce smoothing curves. To reduce the likelihood of erroneous conclusions from a large dataset with numerous sources of variation, α=0.01 was observed for all analyses.<sup>***</sup> Based on average consumption rate for several strains of a given species of coccinellid, collected from different localitiesTo detect linear trends in herbivore suppression potential over the observation period, one way ANOVA or, if data did not meet assumptions of ANOVA, Kruskal-Wallis one way analysis of variance on ranks were performed for herbivore suppression potential by habitat for both datasets. Least square regressions weighted by the number of reporting traps were performed herbivore suppression potential were examined using data at the weekly resolution only. A least-square linear regression analysis was performed comparing the Shannon Index to herbivore suppression potential for captured coccinellids for each habitat type on the weekly average dataset. Year was treated as a factor in the analysis to account for year-to-year variability in overall coccinellid occurrence. ANOVA was performed on the regression model to determine if the interaction of Shannon diversity and herbivore suppression potential differed between habitats.Between 1989 and 2012, 739,047 individual observations were recorded (species by trap) in the KBS LTER coccinellid database, 61,377 traps were monitored, and 57,813 aphidophagous coccinellids corresponding to thirteen species were captured.Proportional abundance of most common coccinellid species by year. Data were collected at Kellogg Biological Station, Hickory Corners, MI, 1989-2012. Average trap captures per year of aphidophagous coccinellids at Kellogg Biological Station, Hickory Corners, MI, 1989-2012, in the annual and perennial crop habitats and in the adjacent forest habitat. <sup>*</sup> Data failed assumptions of ANOVA for all comparisons except for Shannon’s H for all species at the yearly resolution; Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA on ranks was used. Treatment groupings indicated by letters following median values computed by Dunn's method for multiple comparisons. α=0.01Herbivore suppression potential as a function of Shannon diversity index in three habitat types. For clarity, plotted points represent the average herbivore suppression potential per trap per year vs. the average Shannon index for each repetition by a crop type by sampling week combination in a given year. Regression lines are based on weighted regression of weekly observations. Regression lines marked with an asterisk indicate significant slopes at α=0.01.The authors would like to thank William Snyder and Helen Roy for helpful comments offered on an earlier draft of this manuscript, and two anonymous reviewers whose insights will help direct future analyses involving this coccinellid community. We acknowledge the numerous field assistants for weekly field data collection and data preservation. We also thank the KBS-LTER Management Team for their assistance with trapping logistics and information management. 