 Conceived and designed the experiments: HD MJV HH. Performed the experiments: HD MJV HH. Analyzed the data: HD. Wrote the paper: HD MJV HH.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Food webs may be affected by evolutionary processes, and effective evolutionary time ultimately affects the probability of species evolving to fill the niche space. Thus, ecosystem history may set important evolutionary constraints on community composition and food web structure. Food chain length (FCL) has long been recognized as a fundamental ecosystem attribute. We examined historical effects on FCL in large lakes spanning &gt;6 orders of magnitude in age. We found that food chains in the world’s ancient lakes (n = 8) were significantly shorter than in recently formed lakes (n = 10) and reservoirs (n = 3), despite the fact that ancient lakes harbored much higher species richness, including many endemic species. One potential factor leading to shorter FCL in ancient lakes is an increasing diversity of trophic omnivores and herbivores. Speciation could simply broaden the number of species within a trophic group, particularly at lower trophic levels and could also lead to a greater degree of trophic omnivory. Our results highlight a counter-intuitive and poorly-understood role of evolutionary history in shaping key food web properties such as FCL.  Age of lakes indicate the averages of age with refer to recent literatures. Endemic species indicate observed and predicted endemic species number with refer to recent literatures. δ 15 N top-predator  and δ 15 N baseline  indicates mean values.  Our assumption, because of short history of the reservoir.  A) Boxplot for food-chain length in lakes of different origins. Symbols represent the median FCL, boxes  =  inter-quartiles, and bars  =  maximum and minimum values. Different letters indicate significant differences by multiple comparison using ANOVA (p&lt;0.001). B) Correlation between age of lake and food-chain length. Different symbols are for reservoir, glacial and ancient lakes (see A). Lake Victoria and Lake Kyoga are originally from 400,000 years ago, but are thought to have dried up 14,600 years ago.  Though it is perhaps impossible to measure the FCL of a single lake over a long time period, our comparative results suggest that lake food chains lengthen over time periods of hundreds to thousands of years as a stable biological community assembles. In contrast, over time periods of thousands to millions of years, food chains actually become shorter as species diversity rises and endemic species emerge. Because our findings are observational and comparative in nature, we ultimately cannot infer mechanisms that underlie this pattern. Nevertheless, the relationship between FCL and ecosystem age is striking. Our study is a first step towards understanding the role of historical and evolutionary factors in determining fundamental food web properties such as FCL.  We sincerely thank M. Kondoh, G. Takimoto, and K. Yoshida for their comments on the early draft of the manuscript. 