 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: SL GF KDF JSL. Performed the experiments: SL GF KDF JSL. Analyzed the data: SL GF. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SL GF KDF JSL. Wrote the paper: SL JSL.  Current Address: ICES Secretariat, Copenhagen, Denmark  Current Address: Department of Fisheries Oceanography, School for Marine Science and Technology, Fairhaven, Massachusetts, United States of America  The ability to understand and ultimately predict ecosystem response to multiple pressures is paramount to successfully implement ecosystem-based management. Thresholds shifts and nonlinear patterns in ecosystem responses can be used to determine reference points that identify levels of a pressure that may drastically alter ecosystem status, which can inform management action. However, quantifying ecosystem reference points has proven elusive due in large part to the multi-dimensional nature of both ecosystem pressures and ecosystem responses. We used ecological indicators, synthetic measures of ecosystem status and functioning, to enumerate important ecosystem attributes and to reduce the complexity of the Northeast Shelf Large Marine Ecosystem (NES LME). Random forests were used to quantify the importance of four environmental and four anthropogenic pressure variables to the value of ecological indicators, and to quantify shifts in aggregate ecological indicator response along pressure gradients. Anthropogenic pressure variables were critical defining features and were able to predict an average of 8-13% (up to 25-66% for individual ecological indicators) of the variation in ecological indicator values, whereas environmental pressures were able to predict an average of 1-5 % (up to 9-26% for individual ecological indicators) of ecological indicator variation. Each pressure variable predicted a different suite of ecological indicator’s variation and the shapes of ecological indicator responses along pressure gradients were generally nonlinear. Threshold shifts in ecosystem response to exploitation, the most important pressure variable, occurred when commercial landings were 20 and 60% of total surveyed biomass. Although present, threshold shifts in ecosystem response to environmental pressures were much less important, which suggests that anthropogenic pressures have significantly altered the ecosystem structure and functioning of the NES LME. Gradient response curves provide ecologically informed transformations of pressure variables to explain patterns of ecosystem structure and functioning. By concurrently identifying thresholds for a suite of ecological indicator responses to multiple pressures, we demonstrate that ecosystem reference points can be evaluated and used to support ecosystem-based management.  EXP, exploitation; EXP_1, 1-yr lagged exploitation; LANDINGS_1, 1-yr lagged landings (t); LANDINGS, landings (t); SST, sea surface temperature (°C); NAO_w, winter North Atlantic Oscillation Index; AMO_a, mean annual Atlantic multi-decadal oscillation index; PRECIP, precipitation.  Common scale allows for the direct comparison ecosystem response across pressure variables.  Binned raw importance of splits from random forests for ecological indicator value relative to the pressure variable on the horizontal axis. Density plots (lines) illustrate the estimated importance or turnover rate at any given pressure value, which is estimated as the ratio of the density of split importance to the density of observed predictor values along the predictor gradient. The dashed line indicates where the ratio is 1. Ratios &gt; 1 indicate locations of relatively greater change in community composition, such that peaks in the density plot indicate threshold values for each environmental predictor where ecosystem status is expected to shift.  Environmental and anthropogenic pressure variables used in the analysis displayed as vectors.  In this study, we explored ecosystem response to a suite of anthropogenic and environmental pressure variables using an extension of random forest models, gradient forest. Specifically, we sought to 1) quantify the importance of environmental and anthropogenic pressure variables in predicting ecological indicator response, and 2) explore empirical shape and magnitude of changes in indicator response across these pressure gradients.  It can be useful to think of gradient forests in a multivariate sense, similar to PCA. The importance of each pressure variable is comparable to the length of a vector on a PCA scree-plot. But the gradient forest proves to be more informative, as the cumulative response curve is an ecologically informed transformation of the pressure variables, which can be used to predict and map potential patterns of ecological composition.  (CSV)  (TIF)  (TIF)  We thank all those who participated in the NEFSC bottom trawl survey and have maintained this database, and J. Gove and A. Heenan for their thoughtful comments on earlier versions of this work. 