 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: TL YC GS JC. Performed the experiments: YC GS. Analyzed the data: TL PL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: TL PL. Wrote the paper: TL PL YC GS JC. Collected the data: YC GS.  Understanding how communities respond to natural disturbances is fundamental to assess the mechanisms of ecosystem resistance and resilience. However, ecosystem responses to natural disturbances are rarely monitored both through space and time, while the factors promoting ecosystem stability act at various temporal and spatial scales. Hence, assessing both the spatial and temporal variations in species composition is important to comprehensively explore the effects of natural disturbances. Here, we suggest a framework to better scrutinize the mechanisms underlying community responses to disturbances through both time and space. Our analytical approach is based on beta diversity decomposition into two components, replacement and biomass difference. We illustrate this approach using a 9-year monitoring of coral reef fish communities off Moorea Island (French Polynesia), which encompassed two severe natural disturbances: a crown-of-thorns starfish outbreak and a hurricane. These disturbances triggered a fast logistic decline in coral cover, which suffered a 90% decrease on all reefs. However, we found that the coral reef fish composition remained largely stable through time and space whereas compensatory changes in biomass among species were responsible for most of the temporal fluctuations, as outlined by the overall high contribution of the replacement component to total beta diversity. This suggests that, despite the severity of the two disturbances, fish communities exhibited high resistance and the ability to reorganize their compositions to maintain the same level of total community biomass as before the disturbances. We further investigated the spatial congruence of this pattern and showed that temporal dynamics involved different species across sites; yet, herbivores controlling the proliferation of algae that compete with coral communities were consistently favored. These results suggest that compensatory changes in biomass among species and spatial heterogeneity in species responses can provide further insurance against natural disturbances in coral reef ecosystems by promoting high levels of key species (herbivores). They can also allow the ecosystem to recover more quickly.  LCBD values indicate the extent to which each local community is unique in terms of its composition. Circle surface areas are proportional to the LCBD values. Circles with a black rim indicate significant LCBD indices at the 0.05 level. Marginal diagrams indicate LCBD value averages per year (upper margin) and per reef (right margin); values are multiplied by 1000.  (a) Temporal response measure as beta diversity for the 13 spatial groups (13 reefs with 14 time steps for each reef). (b) Spatial response measure as beta diversity for the 14 temporal groups (14 time steps with 13 reefs for each time steps). Blue points represent the means over the different time step pairs (or reef pairs).  Our most interesting result revealed that despite major environmental changes, the reef fish communities were extremely resistant to these disturbances. That conclusion emerged consistently whether the response of the coral reef fish community was analyzed globally (among all observations), temporally (among time steps within each reef), or spatially (among reefs within each time step). Stability in reef fish composition underlined an important part of the response (~70%). Temporal variations in coral reef fish composition were mainly explained by replacement in biomass among species (~20%) suggesting that, despite the severity of the two disturbances, fish communities exhibited a high resistance and an ability to reorganize their compositions to maintain the same level of total community biomass as before the disturbances. Different stabilizing mechanisms such as compensatory dynamics may have been at work. As a result, total biomass exhibited little fluctuation over time, which contributed little (~10%) to temporal variation in coral reef fish composition. The compensatory dynamics of local communities were characterized by an increase in biomass of some species and a significant decrease of other species, leading to significant shifts in reef fish composition over time. However, compositional shifts involved changes in different species, especially when comparing the western and northeastern reefs.  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (TIFF)  (TIFF)  (TIFF)  Circles are proportional to species score in a RDA with MRT groups corresponding to the temporal shift (i.e., before/after the shift). Black circles indicate significant indicator species. Blue circles correspond to species that increased in biomass after the temporal shift, while red circles correspond to species that decreased in biomass after the temporal shift. Species are classified according to their relative frequencies at the regional (Whole Island) scale (percent within brackets). Species are colored according to their trophic groups: herbivores fish (green); fish feeding predominantly on mobile benthic invertebrates (blue); planktivores (light orange); fish feeding predominantly on sessile invertebrates (red) and piscivores (black).  (TIFF)  The authors thank Yu-Yun Chen for discussions on decomposition of beta diversity, José Carlos Carvalho, Pedro Cardoso and one anonymous reviewer for providing constructive comments on previous versions of this manuscript. 