The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: SF. Performed the experiments: JZ SW CZ ZL LZ. Analyzed the data: JZ SW CZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SF. Wrote the paper: JZ SF.Soils were sampled on 20 September, 1 October and 6 November 2009, 11 March, 15 June and 14 October 2010, corresponding to 10 days before and 7, 37, 160, 256, 376 days after treatments were implemented. Soil cores (2.5 cm in diameter, 5 cm in length) were taken at 0–5 cm and 5–10 cm depths from eight locations selected randomly in each subplot within each plantation. Eight cores of the same depth from each subplot were combined to form one composite sample; there were three replicate samples for each treatment. The surface litter was removed carefully when soil sample was taken.Nematodes were extracted from 50 g of fresh soil using the Baermann funnel method. After fixation in 4% formalin solution, nematodes were counted with a differential interference contrast (DIC) microscope (ECLIPSE 80 i, Nikon), and the first 100 individuals encountered were identified to genus level. All nematodes were identified to genus level when the sample contained fewer than 100 individuals.Bivariate plots of the microbial PLFA diversity (a), evenness (b), richness (c) and dominance (d) indices versus soil temperature. Points represent results from all six sampling events at 0–5 cm soil depth. Soil temperatures used here were the mean daily temperatures of the six days that soil samplings were carried out.Bivariate plots of the soil nematode diversity (a), evenness (b), richness (c) and dominance (d) indices versus soil temperature. Points represent results from all six sampling events at 0–5 cm soil depth. Soil temperatures used here were the mean daily temperatures of the six days that soil samplings were carried out.The negative effects of vegetation removal on soil biodiversity also gradually increased over time, which indicated that alterations in bottom-up control and soil microclimate induced by vegetation removal were time-dependent. Firstly, vegetation removal significantly reduced the food resource for soil biota. However, the decomposition of the remained soil residuals (e.g., roots and litter) is time consuming. Therefore, the soil biodiversity declined with the exhaustion of soil residuals. Secondly, the soil microclimate changes that induced by vegetation removal were from March to October (mainly in wet season) in 2010, which was overlapped with the significant declines of soil biodiversity in this study. Thus, the seasonal variation of soil microclimate might be another reason for the time-dependent response of soil biodiversity to vegetation removal.(DOCX)(DOCX)This study was conducted at Heshan Hilly Land Interdisciplinary Experimental Station, CAS and Heshan National Field Research Station of Forest Ecosystem. We thank Dejun Li for refine the language of the manuscript. We also thank the editor Dafeng Hui and two anonymous reviewers for their comments.