 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: LL ZLH. Performed the experiments: JYL ZCC. Analyzed the data: SGW GJL. Wrote the paper: SGW ZYY.  Based on a detailed data set from six subtropical forests, in this study we intend (1) to examine the validity of the random-placement, power law and logarithm model for subtropical forests, to fit the corresponding SAR relationships and then compare their fitted results to find the appropriate model to express the SAR of subtropical forests; (2) to focus on the second type of SAD models, i.e., to fit the lognormal, logseries and logcauchy distributions, and to find the suitable SAD models for subtropical forests; and (3) to compare species richness among different communities, and based on SAR models to explain ecological changing processes of the subtropical forests based on fitted SAR models. We also discuss the influence of different sampling sizes and sampling methods on model fitting. This study thus contributes to our understanding of SAR and SAD in subtropical forests.  No specific permits were required for the described field studies. Our study site (six 1-ha plots in the subtropical forests of southern China) is owned by the Chinese government and managed by South China Botanical Garden, Chinese Academy of Sciences. We can do our research works freely in these plots under the Regulations of the People’s Republic of China on Nature Reserves. Our field studies did not involve endangered or protected species.  The means of parameters are the same as in the lognormal model.  Ranking of communities by estimated species richness was not associated with forest type, with the ranking from lowest to highest estimated species richness being: monsoon evergreen broad-leaved forest, needle and broad-leaved mixed forest, needle and broad-leaved mixed forest, monsoon evergreen broad-leaved forest, broad-leaved forest and broad-leaved forest. Given this particular sequence and the same sample size, no trend can possibly be discerned between forest types.  Likewise, ranking of communities by number of stems per ha was not associated with forest type, with the ranking from lowest to highest tree density being: needle and broad-leaved mixed forest, monsoon evergreen broad-leaved forest, monsoon evergreen broad-leaved forest, monsoon evergreen broad-leaved forest, broad-leaved forest and needle and broad-leaved mixed forest. Given this particular sequence and the same sample size, no trend can possibly be discerned between forest types.  To conclude, we found that our measures of tree density and diversity varied widely among the three forestry types, with the reasons remaining unclear, which should be subjected of further study. The three SAR models fitted most real data of subtropical forest trees very well for most sampling sizes. But due to intermediate sampling sizes, the logarithm model had the better fit among the three models, especially using randomized sampling. When fitting SADs, the logcauchy model had the better fit among the three tested models. Furthermore, our results suggest that many rare and undiscovered species remain undetected.  We thank Dinghushan Forest Ecosystem Research Station (DFERS), Nanling Nature Reserve, Maoershan Nature Reserve and Jinggangshan Nature Reserve bureau for supporting our field investigations. We thank Bruno A. Walther for his helpful revision and good suggestion. We thank Professor Fangliang He of University of Alberta, Dr. I Fang Sun of National Dong Hwa University, Dr. Richard Condit of CTFS, Dr. Pierre Legendre of University of Montreal for training of data analysis. We also thank Dr. Wan hui Ye, Hong lin Cao, Jun Hui Shi, Xiao Yong Zhou, Qian Mei Zhang and Jiong Li for their help in field work. 