 Conceived and designed the experiments: MFR MP. Performed the experiments: MFR MP JL. Analyzed the data: MFR MP JL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MFR MP JL. Wrote the paper: MFR MP JL.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Most of the landscape in the south and southwest of Minas Gerais, Brazil, is composed of small forest fragments immersed in an agriculturally diversified matrix. Although vegetation corridors occur frequently, they are far less studied than the remaining fragments. In this study, we evaluated the conservation value of thin forest strips (corridors) resulting from the tree colonization of linear ditches. These ditches were made by the slave workforce during the nineteenth century to isolate pastures and farm borders. We evaluated the composition and structure of the small mammal community in forest fragments, a vegetation corridor and a coffee matrix in a model system.  (B) Location of the study area. (C) Schematic design of the treatments and transects.  The small mammals were sampled in two forest fragments, one vegetation corridor and one coffee matrix, referred to here as treatments. The peculiar features of each treatment, including shape and size, prevented us from acquiring an equal sample size from each treatment. Thus, in each forest fragment, two parallel transects 100 m in length and 50 m apart were marked. In the vegetation corridor, five transects 100 m in length were placed in lines approximately 250 m from each other. In the coffee matrix, five transects 100 m in length were installed perpendicular to the corridor transects. Thus, 14 transects in total were marked. This sampling design enabled us to evaluate which species were present in each treatment and to determine any species exclusive to certain treatments.  In each transect, six sampling stations were marked with a distance of 20 m from each other. Two traps were placed in each station, one on the ground (lower strata) and another in the understory vegetation at 1–2 m above the ground (middle strata). The ground trap alternated between the large (43.0×12.5×14.5 cm) and small (25.0×9.0×8.0 cm) Sherman traps and medium and large (45.0×16.0×16.0 cm) wire mesh traps. Only small Sherman traps were used in the understory vegetation.  The total abundance, or sum of the individuals captured in every species, and the abundance per species, or number of individuals captured in each species, were calculated on a transect basis.  The coffee matrix presented the least richness (6 species), stabilizing with approximately 30 individuals and indicating few active species in this system. The corridor richness (13) was greater than that of the fragment (10), and the curve did not stabilize, suggesting that the corridors harbor a larger number of species than the other sampled systems.  The findings also indicate that the vegetation corridors function as an extension of the fragment for many species of small mammals because most fragment-inhabiting species were also present in the vegetation corridor and because the most abundant species in the fragment are more abundant in the corridor. This highlights the importance of these landscape elements in the conservation of small mammals in fragmented tropical landscapes. 