 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: CVC FM MGIA SD TY MV JJM. Performed the experiments: CVC FR FM MGIA BG. Analyzed the data: CVC FM MGIA FR BG. Wrote the paper: CVC FR PMJH JJM.  Hypoxia represents one of the major causes of biodiversity and ecosystem functioning loss for coastal waters. Since eutrophication-induced hypoxic events are becoming increasingly frequent and intense, understanding the response of ecosystems to hypoxia is of primary importance to understand and predict the stability of ecosystem functioning. Such ecological stability may greatly depend on the recovery patterns of communities and the return time of the system properties associated to these patterns. Here, we have examined how the reassembly of a benthic community contributed to the recovery of ecosystem functioning following experimentally-induced hypoxia in a tidal flat. We demonstrate that organism-sediment interactions that depend on organism size and relate to mobility traits and sediment reworking capacities are generally more important than recovering species richness to set the return time of the measured sediment processes and properties. Specifically, increasing macrofauna bioturbation potential during community reassembly significantly contributed to the recovery of sediment processes and properties such as denitrification, bedload sediment transport, primary production and deep pore water ammonium concentration. Such bioturbation potential was due to the replacement of the small-sized organisms that recolonised at early stages by large-sized bioturbating organisms, which had a disproportionately stronger influence on sediment. This study suggests that the complete recovery of organism-sediment interactions is a necessary condition for ecosystem functioning recovery, and that such process requires long periods after disturbance due to the slow growth of juveniles into adult stages involved in these interactions. Consequently, repeated episodes of disturbance at intervals smaller than the time needed for the system to fully recover organism-sediment interactions may greatly impair the resilience of ecosystem functioning.  In order to avoid disturbance in the plots due to repetitive sampling, samples were collected from a bridge, and sampling holes were filled with closed PVC tubes, pushed flush with the sediment surface. Furthermore, to minimise possible edge effects, sampling only occurred in the inner 3×3 m.  Top panel; trophic group composition, abundance and species richness. Bottom panel; sediment reworking trait group composition, biomass and community bioturbation potential. Error bars represent ±95% confidence intervals.  denotes adapted significance levels deduced from Greenhouse-Geisser corrections when sphericity assumption for repeated measures was not met. Data of bed level height were occasionally lacking for week 0 and week 12 and data of oxygen penetration depth for week 4.  (a) organic matter mineralization (DIC), (b) total sediment oxygen consumption, (c) denitrification, (d) percentage of total organic matter, (e) oxygen penetration, (f) pore water ammonium concentration in surface sediment, (g) ammonium pore concentration in deep sediments, (h) chlorophyll a concentration, and (i) sediment bed level height. Error bars represent ±95% confidence intervals.  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  We would like to thank B. Beuselinck, D. Peelaers, J. van Soelen and B. Koutstaal for their assistance during the field work, and D. Van Gansbeke, D. Schram, M. Houtekamer, C. Kleppe, H. Francke and Y. van der Maas for their assistance during the processing of the samples. At the time of writing, NIOZ-Yerseke was part of the Netherlands Institute of Ecology (NIOO-KNAW); this is publication 5366 of the Netherlands Institute of Ecology (NIOO-KNAW) 