 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: JZ XH KW. Performed the experiments: JZ SL LL. Analyzed the data: JZ SL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XH LL. Wrote the paper: JZ SL KW.  Karst ecosystems are fragile and are in many regions degraded by anthropogenic activities. Current management of degraded karst areas focuses on aboveground vegetation succession or recovery and aims at establishing a forest ecosystem. Whether progressive succession of vegetation in karst areas is accompanied by establishment of soil biota is poorly understood. In the present study, soil microbial and nematode communities, as well as soil physico-chemical properties were studied along a progressive succession of secondary vegetation (from grassland to shrubland to forest) in a karst area in southwest China. Microbial biomass, nematode density, ratio of fungal to bacterial biomass, nematode structure index, and nematode enrichment index decreased with the secondary succession in the plant community. Overall, the results indicated a pattern of declines in soil biota abundance and food web complexity that was associated with a decrease in soil pH and a decrease in soil organic carbon content with the progressive secondary succession of the plant community. Our findings suggest that soil biota amendment is necessary during karst ecosystem restoration and establishment and management of grasslands may be feasible in karst areas.  The restoration of degraded karst areas in southwest China is currently evaluated based on the degree of forest vegetation establishment but the restoration of ecosystem services will also depend on the recovery of other organisms including soil organisms. Whether a secondary vegetation succession can promote the increment of biomass and abundance of soil biota in degraded karst areas is largely unknown, and this lack of knowledge limits our ability to understand and predict the functioning of such ecosystems.  In this study, we determined whether the progressive succession of the plant community is accompanied by the establishments of soil microbial and nematode communities in karst shallow soils; by progressive succession, we mean that the community becomes more complex, with increased species richness, community biomass, and food web trophic links. We explored the compositions of soil microbial and nematode communities along a secondary vegetation succession from grassland to shrubland to forest in the karst region in southwest China, where ecosystems have been severely disrupted and where the soils are very shallow. We test the hypothesis that progressive succession of the plant community should improve the soil habitat (because of increases in soil organic matter and nutrients) and thereby support the establishments of the soil microbial and nematode communities.  No specific permits were required for the described field studies. No specific permissions were required for these locations/activities. The location is not privately owned or protected in any way and the field studies did not involve endangered or protected species.  This study was carried out at the Huanjiang Observation and Research Station for Karst Ecosystems (107°51′–108°43′E, 24°44′–25°33′N), Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS), Guangxi Province, China. The climate is subtropical monsoon with a distinct wet (from April to September) and dry season (from October to March). The mean annual temperature and precipitation are 18.5°C and 1,389 mm, respectively. The soil developed from a dolostone base and is calcareous.  In 2011, the three identified plant communities at nine sites were selected, among which each plant community including three sites (replicates). A 10×10 m plot was established at each of the grassland and shrubland site, while a 20×30 m plot was established at each of the forest site. Because of anthropogenic disturbances in this area over the past decades, no primary forest ecosystem on calcareous soil that developed from a dolomite base existed near the research station. Therefore, no primary forest ecosystems were included in the present study.  Soil was sampled in September 2012. Soil cores (2.5 cm in diameter, 5 cm in length) were taken at 0–5 cm and 5–10 cm depths from 15 random locations within each of the nine plots. The 15 cores of the same depth from each plot were combined to form one composite sample, giving three replicate samples for each combination of vegetation type and depth. The surface litter was carefully removed before soil cores were collected. Samples were brought to the laboratory in insulated boxes. Then, the soil was sieved to pass through a 2 mm sieve to remove the roots. The soil water content, microbial and nematode communities were determined on a fresh subsample. Another subsample was thereafter air-dried and used for determination of soil pH, soil organic C and total nitrogen.  SWC (%), pH, TN (g kg −1  dry soil), SOC (g kg −1  dry soil), and C:N stand for soil water content, soil pH, soil total nitrogen, soil organic carbon, and ratio of soil organic carbon to total nitrogen, respectively.  (a) Bi-plot with four quadrats; (b) Magnified quadrate-area of bi-plot A. Bars indicate the standard errors of means.  Ordination diagrams present species scores and environmental factor scores (vectors). Environmental factors include soil water content (SWC), soil pH, soil total nitrogen (TN), soil organic carbon (SOC), and ratio of soil organic carbon to total nitrogen (C:N). Microbial and nematode community indices include ratio of fungal biomass to bacterial biomass (F:B), cy/pre ratio of PLFAs (cy/pre), nematode maturity index (MI), plant parasite index (PPI), structure index (SI), and enrichment index (EI). Variables of microbial community biomass include total microbial biomass (Microbiomass), fungal biomass (Fu biomass), bacterial biomass (Ba biomass), and actinomycetes biomass (Act biomass). Variables of nematode community density include densities of total nematodes (Total), bacterivores (Ba), fungivores (Fu), herbivores (He), omnivores (Om), and predators (Pr).  We thank Bruce Jaffee for his help in preparing the manuscript. We also thank the editor and two anonymous reviewers for their comments. 