 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: TZ JXG WS. Performed the experiments: TZ RG SG. Analyzed the data: TZ SG WS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RG SG. Wrote the paper: TZ JXG WS.  Climate change has profound influences on plant community composition and ecosystem functions. However, its effects on plant community composition and biomass production are not well understood. A four-year field experiment was conducted to examine the effects of warming, nitrogen (N) addition, and their interactions on plant community composition and biomass production in a temperate meadow ecosystem in northeast China. Experimental warming had no significant effect on plant species richness, evenness, and diversity, while N addition highly reduced the species richness and diversity. Warming tended to reduce the importance value of graminoid species but increased the value of forbs, while N addition had the opposite effect. Warming tended to increase the belowground biomass, but had an opposite tendency to decrease the aboveground biomass. The influences of warming on aboveground production were dependent upon precipitation. Experimental warming had little effect on aboveground biomass in the years with higher precipitation, but significantly suppressed aboveground biomass in dry years. Our results suggest that warming had indirect effects on plant production via its effect on the water availability. Nitrogen addition significantly increased above- and below-ground production, suggesting that N is one of the most important limiting factors determining plant productivity in the studied meadow steppe. Significant interactive effects of warming plus N addition on belowground biomass were also detected. Our observations revealed that environmental changes (warming and N deposition) play significant roles in regulating plant community composition and biomass production in temperate meadow steppe ecosystem in northeast China.  No specific permissions were required for the described field studies because the Songnen Grassland Ecological Research Station is a department of Northeast Normal University, and the performance of this study has followed the guidelines set by Northeast Normal University. No endangered or protected species were involved in this field investigation.  The mean monthly temperature and precipitation from 2006 to 2009 were recorded using an eddy covariance system installed 200 m away from the experimental site. One EM50/R probe (Decagon Ltd, Pullman WA, USA) was buried 0–15 cm from the soil surface in each experimental plot, measuring soil temperature (ST) and soil moisture (SM) at one-hour intervals.  LHT, life history traits; A, annual plants; P, perennial plants; AB, annual &amp; biennial. +, plants were present in samples. The individual contribution values of coverage (%) of the most abundant species are listed. The abbreviations of the individual species are used in the RDA analyses.  The belowground biomass was estimated using the ingrowth core method. Two holes (7 cm diameter, 50 cm height) were drilled randomly in each plot using a soil drill. The collected soil samples were sieved to remove roots and then placed it into nylon mesh bags (the size of each bag was similar to the dimensions of the soil hole). Next, the nylon mesh bags were again carefully placed into the holes in the experiment plots. The nylon mesh bags were harvested on 18 July annually. The roots in each mesh bags were selected, washed, and then dried at 65°C for 48 h.  Different lowercase letters above the columns indicate significant differences (P&lt;0.05) among treatments every year. Data are reported as the mean ± SE (n = 6).  Different lowercase letters above the columns indicate significant differences (P&lt;0.05) among the treatments every year. Data are reported as the mean ± SE (n = 6).  Over the four experimental years, the effects of warming and N addition on plant species richness and diversity increased gradually with the increase in N addition and extension of warming. These results suggest that long-term warming and N deposition might significantly alter plant community composition in our system and thus affect ecosystem function in the future. Furthermore, as the influences of warming and N deposition were affected by soil moisture; therefore, the effect of precipitation should be included in further studies on the effects of warming and N deposition on grassland ecosystems.  In addition, significant differences were observed between the warming and warming plus N addition treatments in the aboveground and belowground biomass levels. This result further demonstrates that N is an important limiting factor for plant productivity in the Songnen meadow steppe; furthermore, the improvement in plant growth attributed to increased N deposition might alleviate the negative effects of warming on plant growth.  Our study has revealed that both warming and N addition altered both plant community composition and biomass production in the Songnen meadow ecosystem. Warming had no significant impact on species richness. N addition highly decreased species richness and diversity. This effect is gradually enhanced over time with N enrichment. Warming had no significant influence on the aboveground biomass but increased the belowground productivity. N addition highly enhanced both the aboveground and the belowground productivity. The synergetic effect of warming and N addition on the belowground productivity was also detected in the later three experimental years. These observations have further improved our understanding of how community composition and biomass production in temperate meadow ecosystems respond to these simultaneous climate changes.  Data was from the eddy tower adjacent (approximately 200 m) to the experimental plots.  (TIF)  (TIF)  We thank Dr. Jushan Liu and Bonifacio Pasion for help with manuscript writing. 