 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: DT QP XH YB. Performed the experiments: DT QP HC BD YB. Analyzed the data: DT QP HW MS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DT HC BD HW YB. Wrote the paper: DT QP MS XH.  At the individual level, an individual was divided into vegetative tillers and reproductive tillers. At the tiller level, a reproductive tiller was divided into a spike and non-spike components. At the spike level, a spike was divided into seeds and non-seed components.  In 1999, the 120 m ×70 m study site was fenced off from large animals. The nutrient addition experiment began in 2000 and included 7 treatments, each with 9 replications. Plots (5 m ×5 m) were arranged following a randomized block design. Six levels of nitrogen addition (0, 1.75, 5.25, 10.5, 17.5 and 28.0 g N m −2  yr −1 ) were created by adding NH 4 NO 3  to plots at the beginning of July every year. To ensure that N was the only limiting element, the following elements were also added: P (10 g P 2 O 5  m −2  yr −1 ), S (0.2 mg m −2  yr −1 ), Zn (190 µg m −2  yr −1 ), Mn (160 µg m −2  yr −1 ) and B (31 µg m −2  yr −1 ). In addition, there were 9 control plots in which no nutrient was added. In total, there were 63 plots with 54 plots being fertilized every year and 9 plots never receiving any nutrients.  The proportion of reproductive individuals (PRI) was calculated as follows: PRI (%)  =  the density of reproductive individuals in 1m 2  / the density of total individuals in 1 m 2 . Plant size (aboveground biomass) frequency distributions were determined by dividing the range of individual plant sizes into 10 equal deciles. The effects of nutrient addition on PRI, population density and biomass were tested by one-way ANOVA with SPSS software (SPSS 11.0 for windows, USA). The differences between treatments were compared by Duncan's multiple range tests.  Based on our hierarchical sampling method, we assessed four types of RA within an individual. At the individual level, we calculated the fractions of reproductive tiller biomass in individual biomass. At the tiller level, we calculated the fractions of spike biomass in reproductive tiller biomass. At the spike level, we calculated the fractions of seed biomass in spike biomass. At the whole plant level, we determined the fractions of seed biomass in individual biomass. Accordingly, we examined the four types of reproductive allometric relationships.  No detailed study has evaluated size-dependent versus size-independent effects on plant RA at different hierarchical levels within a population. Our results revealed that the size-dependent effect and the size-independent effect may play different roles in plant RA at different hierarchical levels. At the spike level, the R-V relationships did not follow an allometric trajectory, suggesting that the size-independent effect plays a dominant role. In contrast, the R-V relationships followed a fixed allometric trajectory at the tiller level, implying that a size-dependent effect plays a primary role in regulating plant RA. At the individual level, we found a shift from a non-allometric relationship in control plots to a fixed allometric relationship following nutrient addition. These findings indicate that the dominant drivers in the variation of RA change from size-independent effects to size-dependent effects. Because the individual-level R-V relationship in all nutrient addition plots exhibited a fixed allometric relationship, a size-dependent effect is likely to be a major mechanism in regulation of plant RA at the individual level.  More interestingly, the final R-V relationship (seeds vs. non-seed components) at the whole plant level followed a plastic allometric trajectory, suggesting that this relationship represents the integration of R-V relationships along hierarchical levels and the final RA at the whole plant level is determined by both size-dependent and size-independent effects.  (TIF)  (DOC) 