 Conceived and designed the experiments: SV JRM DFH DM. Performed the experiments: SV JRM DFH. Analyzed the data: SV. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SV JRM DFH. Wrote the paper: SV JRM DFH DM.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  The field sampling protocol received the agreement of the Mexican National Commission for Aquaculture and Fisheries (permit number: 070503-613-03).  In particular, ontogenic changes were not considered as the studied species were mainly represented by juveniles and sub-adults, thus exhibiting a relatively small size-range.  Matrices of species abundances in set of communities (i.e. a stratum) and of pairwise functional distances are illustrated at the top. Note that species present at the stratum scale are a subset of the species present at the regional scale (i.e. global area of the study) and thus some columns of the abundance matrix contain only null values. A hypothetical example is provided on the top right, with the sum of columns (i.e. species abundances at the stratum scale) and lines (i.e. total abundances in local communities). The first procedure consists in shuffling abundances among the species present in each local community. This generates expected values of dissimilarity in taxonomic structure given the observed dissimilarity in taxonomic composition (null-model 1) as well as expected values of dissimilarity in functional structure given observed dissimilarity in functional composition (null-model 4). The second procedure randomly permutes columns of the abundance matrix at the regional scale to generate expected values of dissimilarity in functional composition without modifying the dissimilarity in taxonomic composition (null-model 2). The third procedure is similar but columns are permuted only among species present at the stratum scale so it produces the expected level of dissimilarity in functional structure without modifying dissimilarity in functional composition (null-model 3). None of the three permutation processes modifies the distribution of local abundances (i.e. contribution of the local communities to the total abundance of the stratum). For each procedure an illustration of output given the above example is provided.  A total of 46,012 and 25,639 individuals were caught in 2003–2004 and 2006–2007 respectively for corresponding weights of 557 and 398 kg. Species richness was 87 for both periods while total species richness was of 105 species over the two periods.  The 16 functional traits were measured on 1021 individuals belonging to 70 species. Among these 70 species, the 16 functional traits were estimated on 20 individuals for 40 species and on more than 10 individuals for 50 species. Indeed, some fish species were very rare and thus not captured in sufficient numbers during the 2006–07 campaign, preventing an estimation of their functional traits. Consequently, the rare species were not included in our study but their low biomass would only marginally influence the estimations of our functional diversity components that are based on abundances.  The 16 samples where the biomass of species functionally characterized represented less than 80% of community biomass were not considered in the analyses. For the remaining communities, the biomass belonging to species not functionally characterized was removed before conducting analyses.  Local (mean α) and regional (γ) components are expressed as equivalent number of species (mean±SD), of taxonomic (circles) and functional (squares) diversities computed on community composition (white) or abundance structure (black) for temporal and spatial strata. The grey triangles represent species richness.  The relative abundance is the mean relative biomass of the group. The percentage of occurrence is computed for each functional group over the 810 stations studied. The five most abundant groups for each function are named with letters (a-e) in the two plots. Number of species in each functional group is reported above the bars.  (JPG)  (DOC)  (DOC)  (DOC)  (DOC)  (TXT)  We thank Peter Winterton for correcting the English and we are grateful to two anonymous reviewers and to the editor Nathan G. Swenson for their comments that helped us to improve this manuscript. 