The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development provided financial support. Anthony J. Hall-Martin is an employee of Hall-Martin Consulting. This does not alter the authors’ adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.Conceived and designed the experiments: ML AJH GIHK. Performed the experiments: ML AJH. Analyzed the data: ML DS. Wrote the paper: ML DS GIHK.Surface water availability is a key driver of elephant impacts on biological diversity. Thus, understanding the spatio-temporal variations of these impacts in relation to water is critical to their management. However, elephant piosphere effects (i.e. the radial pattern of attenuating impact) are poorly described, with few long-term quantitative studies. Our understanding is further confounded by the complexity of systems with elephant (i.e. fenced, multiple water points, seasonal water availability, varying population densities) that likely limit the use of conceptual models to predict these impacts. Using 31 years of data on shrub structure in the succulent thickets of the Addo Elephant National Park, South Africa, we tested elephant effects at a single water point. Shrub structure showed a clear sigmoid response with distance from water, declining at both the upper and lower limits of sampling. Adjacent to water, this decline caused a roughly 300-m radial expansion of the grass-dominated habitats that replace shrub communities. Despite the clear relationship between shrub structure and ecological functioning in thicket, the extent of elephant effects varied between these features with distance from water. Moreover, these patterns co-varied with other confounding variables (e.g. the location of neighboring water points), which limits our ability to predict such effects in the absence of long-term data. We predict that elephant have the ability to cause severe transformation in succulent thicket habitats with abundant water supply and elevated elephant numbers. However, these piosphere effects are complex, suggesting that a more integrated understanding of elephant impacts on ecological heterogeneity may be required before water availability is used as a tool to manage impacts. We caution against the establishment of water points in novel succulent thicket habitats, and advocate a significant reduction in water provisioning at our study site, albeit with greater impacts at each water point.Experimental plots were placed at increasing distances from Hapoor water point in the area originally fenced in 1954. The incremental expansion of AMC caused a substantial increase in the number of permanent artificial water points (from 6 in 1954 to a total of 12 in 2008); only two of these (shown by overlapping symbols) maintained water availability for elephant since the initial fencing.N/APlots were 5 m wide, while plot length (17–45 m) scaled inversely with the abundance of the dominant shrub taxa. We estimated the volume (m<sup>3</sup>.m<sup>−2</sup>) of all canopy shrubs (24 spp.: 5 succulents, 19 woody shrubs) encountered by measuring the maximum height and canopy diameters of individual plants. Because most shrubs are multi-stemmed re-sprouters, stems within 50 cm of each other at ground-level were considered to be of the same individual. Individuals were measured if at least half the rooted area occurred within the plot. We calculated shrub density as the number of individuals per unit area.To identify the likely mechanism of the predicted change in functionality, we hypothesized that this process will be associated with a change in the structure (or integrity) of the organic-rich mounds that occur beneath patches of canopy shrubs. Hence, we considered intact mounds to be those for which patch area was equal to, or exceeded mound area and thus where resources were conserved beneath patches. The reverse was true for exposed mounds; these occurred more frequently near water, reflecting areas vulnerable to erosion. Thus, at each marked experimental plot we measured the canopy and mound diameters of ten randomly selected shrub patches and estimated patch and mound area (m<sup>2</sup>), respectively. Ratios of patch and mound area were correlated with ratios of run-on and run-off per plot.Because shrub structure varied non-linearly with distance from water and we expected a clear relationship between ecological functioning and shrub structure, we modeled trends in functionality with a simple self-starting logistic growth curve.Sample codes refer Sample Period-Distance to water (m).Photo credits: M. Stalmans (1981), M. Landman (2008).Sample Period different from all other periods combined.Best-fit mixed-effects logistic growth models of (A) the ratio between areas of run-on and run-off, and (B) the proportion of intact mounds as a function of distance from water.(TIF)We thank South African National Parks for permission to conduct the study within the Addo Elephant National Park.