 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: AW JVO RPH RM. Performed the experiments: AW JVO AB RPH. Analyzed the data: AW JVO AB RPH RM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AW RM. Wrote the paper: AW JVO AB RPH RD RM.  A key part of tropical forest spatial complexity is the vertical stratification of biodiversity, with widely differing communities found in higher rainforest strata compared to terrestrial levels. Despite this, our understanding of how human disturbance may differentially affect biodiversity across vertical strata of tropical forests has been slow to develop. For the first time, how the patterns of current biodiversity vary between three vertical strata within a single forest, subject to three different types of historic anthropogenic disturbance, was directly assessed. In total, 229 species of butterfly were detected, with a total of 5219 individual records. Butterfly species richness, species diversity, abundance and community evenness differed markedly between vertical strata. We show for the first time, for any group of rainforest biodiversity, that different vertical strata within the same rainforest, responded differently in areas with different historic human disturbance. Differences were most notable within the canopy. Regenerating forest following complete clearance had 47% lower canopy species richness than regenerating forest that was once selectively logged, while the reduction in the mid-storey was 33% and at ground level, 30%. These results also show for the first time that even long term regeneration (over the course of 30 years) may be insufficient to erase differences in biodiversity linked to different types of human disturbance. We argue, along with other studies, that ignoring the potential for more pronounced effects of disturbance on canopy fauna, could lead to the underestimation of the effects of habitat disturbance on biodiversity, and thus the overestimation of the conservation value of regenerating forests more generally.  The study site lay within one of these cultural buffer strata. It consists of ~800ha of regenerating lowland tropical forest, accessed by a 20km trail system, and covers an altitudinal range of 450–740m asl. During the period of the study (2011–2014) the average daily wet season (October-March) temperature was 24.78°C (average high of 27.89°C; average low of 22.19°C), the average humidity was 90.58% (average high of 96.32%; average low of 69.26%) and the average seasonal rainfall was 3098mm. The average dry season (April-September) temperature was 23.74°C (average high of 27.17°C; average low of 20.95°C), humidity was 84.89% (average high of 94.54%; average low of 66.16%) and the average seasonal rainfall was 1557mm (weather data collected as part of this research).  O = Overall community, U = Understorey community, M = Midstorey community and C = Canopy community. Disturbance types: SLR–selectively logged and now regenerating forest, CCR–completely cleared and now regenerating forest and MXD–mixed disturbance and now regenerating forest.  NB  Solid lines represent the observed number of individuals recorded and dashed lines represent extrapolated species richness. The grey shades represent 95% confidence intervals. Mean species accumulation lines falling outside of this envelope are statistically significant. (a) the overall community, (b) the understorey community, (c) the midstorey community and (d) the canopy community.  The average estimated understorey species richness was highest in the forest regenerating after selective logging (an average estimated 213 ±11.56 species) and 30% lower in forest regenerating after complete clearance (149 ±8.82 species). For the midstorey butterfly community the difference between disturbance types increased slightly to 33%, with average estimated midstorey butterfly species richness higher in past selectively logged regenerating forest (an average estimated 176 ±12.33 species) than the past clear-felled regenerating forest (118 ±8.11 species). The canopy community showed the largest difference between disturbance types (47%). The average estimated canopy butterfly species richness was higher in the past selectively logged regenerating forest, with an average estimated 117 ±6.88 species in SLR and just 61 ±12.54 species in CCR.  Error bars are 95% confidence intervals.  We sampled fruit and carrion-feeding butterflies at the same study site within forest areas differing in the type of past disturbance, and found that the canopy community was more affected by more intensive past disturbance than both the midstorey and understorey communities. This is the first investigation of the disruption to biodiversity across vertical strata carried out at the same site that compares areas subjected to different historic disturbances. Although more stratum specialist species were found within the understorey, 31% were detected above the ground (within the midstorey and the canopy), and would therefore have been either underrepresented or for some species, undetected, had only an understorey assessment been carried out. We found that differences between past disturbed areas were most notable within the canopy. Regenerating forest following complete clearance had 47% lower canopy species richness than regenerating forest that was once selectively logged, while the reduction in the midstorey was 33% and at ground level, 30%. There were also significant differences in species diversity and community evenness. Species diversity and community evenness were different between all three vertical strata within past logged regenerating forest, but regenerating forest that was cleared in the past didn’t show any difference in species diversity or community evenness between understorey and midstorey communities. Although abundance was lower across all three strata in past cleared regenerating forest when compared to past logged regenerating forest, the pattern remained the same, with both areas differing in abundances between all three vertical strata. We show that butterfly communities within a regenerating tropical forest displayed many marked differences between vertical strata, with species richness, species diversity, species abundance and community evenness all differing significantly. The understorey community was the most biodiverse, followed by the midstorey and finally, the canopy community displayed the lowest species richness, diversity and abundance. The canopy also displayed less evenly balanced community evenness. Our results also show for the first time, that even long term regeneration (over the course of 30 years) was insufficient to erase differences in butterfly biodiversity linked to different types of past human disturbance.  The Ministerio de Agricultura of Peru provided the permit to conduct research at the Manu Learning Centre in Peru, which involved the trapping and handling of butterflies for this study (Permit provided by the Ministerio de Agricultura of Peru; Permit Number ‘Codigo de Tramite’: 25397; Authorisation Number ‘Autorización No.’ 2904-2012-AG-DGFFS-DGEFFS). Once species codes were assigned and photographs were taken to aid further identification, all individuals were later released; therefore no species of protected status were collected.  (TIF)  (TIF)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX) 