The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: AL. Performed the experiments: AL. Analyzed the data: AL. Wrote the paper: AL.Detailed information about interspecific spatial associations among tropical tree species is scarce, and hence the ecological importance of those associations may have been underestimated. However, they can play a role in community assembly and species diversity maintenance. This study investigated the spatial dependence between pairs of species. First, the spatial associations (spatial attraction and spatial repulsion) that arose between species were examined. Second, different sizes of trees were considered in order to evaluate whether the spatial relationships between species are constant or vary during the lifetime of individuals. Third, the consistency of those spatial associations with the species-habitat associations found in previous studies was assessed. Two different tropical ecosystems were investigated: a montane cloud forest and a lowland moist forest. The results showed that spatial associations among species exist, and these vary among life stages and species. The rarity of negative spatial interactions suggested that exclusive competition was not common in the studied forests. On the other hand, positive interactions were common, and the results of this study strongly suggested that habitat associations were not the only cause of spatial attraction among species. If this is true, habitat associations and density dependence are not the only mechanisms that explain species distribution and diversity; other ecological interactions, such as facilitation among species, may also play a role. These spatial associations could be important in the assembly of tropical tree communities and forest succession, and should be taken into account in future studies.Additionally, I examined whether pairwise associations were more common between species with similar life forms and shade tolerances. The debate on functional characteristics will not be addressed in this study because it is beyond the scope of the current research. Nevertheless, I bring this information up here because it offers a broader view on forest organization, and it could be more fully examined in future studies.In every of the 5 different cases, the intertype function used to detect the spatial dependence is in a white box, the observed spatial dependence and the values in a grey box, the function that support that result is in a blue box. The potential underlying mechanisms that caused the observed pattern are indicated in green characters. Only the species comprising the pair of target species were represented in this scheme, named species A and B, while the other species were blind. Species A and B may be any pair of species, different in each case. Rosy upper box: light tolerance and growth form classification of the analysed species. The four different cases of inter cross guilds for species A and B are represented below.Type II errors (false positives) were minimised in the BNC approach because the results from three different spatially separated plots were used. Therefore, the casual associations in one plot were removed, and only coincident results were considered, making the results more robust.As a large number of tests were carried out, 5% of the associations were expected to be false positives (type I errors), which equates to four associations in each of the two analyses (with and without including trunk diameter) in BNC and six in each of the two analysis for BCI, based on the number of statistical tests (20 and 25 species, respectively) that were conducted.(ZIP)Ms refers to Morphospecies.(DOCX)(DOCX)This research was funded through a PhD grant from the Universidad Politécnica de Madrid, and finished thanks to the support of a FP7-PEOPLE-2013-IEF Marie-Curie Action. We are indebted to Wilder Caba Culquicondor for his help with the field work. I accept responsibility for all missing species identifications. Data from BCI were provided by the Center for Tropical Forest Science of the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute and the primary granting agencies that have supported the BCI plot. Thanks to Sonia Condes and Fernando Montes, supervisors of my PhD.