The authors declare that one of the authors [TKN] is affiliated with one of the funding organizations of this research study, Fujitsu Laboratories Ltd. This affiliation does not alter the authors’ adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.Conceived and designed the experiments: HK DL BM. Performed the experiments: HK DB LM SO. Analyzed the data: HK LC. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: HK DL BM. Developed the conceptual framework and global context: HK DL BM TKN.Carbon stock change due to forest management and disturbance must be accounted for in UNFCCC national inventory reports and for signatories to the Kyoto Protocol. Impacts of disturbance on greenhouse gas (GHG) inventories are important for many countries with large forest estates prone to wildfires. Our objective was to measure changes in carbon stocks due to short-term combustion and to simulate longer-term carbon stock dynamics resulting from redistribution among biomass components following wildfire. We studied the impacts of a wildfire in 2009 that burnt temperate forest of tall, wet eucalypts in south-eastern Australia. Biomass combusted ranged from 40 to 58 tC ha<sup>−1</sup>, which represented 6–7% and 9–14% in low- and high-severity fire, respectively, of the pre-fire total biomass carbon stock. Pre-fire total stock ranged from 400 to 1040 tC ha<sup>−1</sup> depending on forest age and disturbance history. An estimated 3.9 TgC was emitted from the 2009 fire within the forest region, representing 8.5% of total biomass carbon stock across the landscape. Carbon losses from combustion were large over hours to days during the wildfire, but from an ecosystem dynamics perspective, the proportion of total carbon stock combusted was relatively small. Furthermore, more than half the stock losses from combustion were derived from biomass components with short lifetimes. Most biomass remained on-site, although redistributed from living to dead components. Decomposition of these components and new regeneration constituted the greatest changes in carbon stocks over ensuing decades. A critical issue for carbon accounting policy arises because the timeframes of ecological processes of carbon stock change are longer than the periods for reporting GHG inventories for national emissions reductions targets. Carbon accounts should be comprehensive of all stock changes, but reporting against targets should be based on human-induced changes in carbon stocks to incentivise mitigation activities.Under the UNFCCC and Kyoto Protocol, each country constructs GHG inventories and reports on their net annual emissions, that is, flows of CO<sub>2</sub> and other GHGs, due to specific activities and sectors including Land Use, Land Use Change and Forestry. Flow-based inventories in the land sector, however, obscure important differences between ecosystems types and between the impacts of human activities and natural disturbances. A more comprehensive, stock-based approach to accounting can address these problems and provide information that complements flow-based accounts (Ajani et al. 2013). The flow-based accounts are currently used for national reporting against emission reduction targets over short time periods, such as annual or 5 to 8 year commitment periods, as determined by political negotiations. However, this short time period exposes nations to high variability in emissions due to natural disturbance events, especially wildfires, which are outside human control, yet create large GHG fluctuations. The resulting variability in national net emissions due to natural disturbance can be much greater than the changes due to land use impacts, thus confounding attempts to provide incentives for reducing emissions in the land sector through improved forest management.The objectives of this study were to investigate the magnitude and timeframe of carbon stock changes due to wildfire and to evaluate the results in terms of implications for national carbon accounts.We assessed the magnitude of carbon stock losses due to combustion in a wildfire in terms of the amount and proportion of the total forest ecosystem carbon stock. We then considered the significance of these carbon losses compared with potential impacts from human activities.We considered the impact of fire on the ecosystem carbon stock in terms of the timeframe of stock changes. The mean residence times of carbon stocks change in response to redistribution of carbon among biomass components post-fire and their subsequent relative rates of losses and gains. We investigated the dynamics of carbon stock change within the current disturbance regime and not predicted future regimes or climate.Location of field sites is marked, including long-term ecological monitoring sites (n = 54) where carbon stocks in biomass components were measured, and inventory sites (n = 876) where carbon stocks were estimated and used for upscaling. The spatial extent of wildfires shown represents the outer boundary of the burnt area.The fire was categorised as low-severity where most trees survived, and high-severity where most trees were killed.Sites of 100 m×100 m included central and perpendicular transects (dashed lines), 10 m×10 m plots (hatched), 10 m transects (black lines), and area sampled for large trees 2×30 m×100 m = 0.51 ha) (grey shaded area). Different biomass components were sampled in different parts of the site.Combustion of shrub biomass in woody stems, branches and twigs was assessed using measurements of: (i) minimum sizes of tips remaining on stems after the fire, (ii) the proportion of biomass lost from a shrub when different tip sizes were removed, and (iii) the amount of biomass in each stem diameter size class of shrubs from the inventory data. A range of species and sizes of understorey shrubs was sampled.Combustion of CWD was determined on each piece along the measurement transects by the proportion of the piece charred, or by the number of lines of charcoal remaining on the ground. The initial carbon stock of the logs that were completely converted to charcoal was assumed to be represented by the mean size of logs at the site. CWD was too variable between burnt and unburnt sites within stand age categories to allow a comparison to be indicative of the amount combusted as the mean of a category. The proportion of the litter layer combusted was estimated from photographs of quadrats taken soon after the fire in low- and high-severity burnt areas and compared with litter biomass in unburnt sites.Impacts of the wildfire on ecosystem carbon stocks were quantified by determining first, the loss in carbon stock of each biomass component combusted, and second, the redistribution of carbon among biomass components within the ecosystem. Spatial estimation of the carbon stock post-2009 fire was based on measured reductions in the stock according to the fire severity category in the burnt areas and forest age.Carbon stock is shown as the proportion in stem size classes of DHB and trees with hollows, averaged for the sites in each age/fire category (n = 6 sites per category).CWD biomass was highly variable among sites in the age/fire categories, ranging from 15 to 186 tC ha<sup>−1</sup>, with a mean of 67 tC ha<sup>−1</sup>. There was no significant difference in CWD biomass between forest age categories, reflecting the varied disturbance history of these forests where CWD remained after logging and wildfire, and its biomass was not related to the age of the stands. Litter biomass in the unburnt sites ranged from 6 tC ha<sup>−1</sup> in the 1983 regrowth to 9 tC ha<sup>−1</sup> in mature and old growth stands. This litter biomass corresponded to average site depth of litter when compressed of 2 cm and 3 cm, respectively, with the majority of measured points less than 5 cm and only a few points with 5–10 cm depth.Mass of carbon (mean ±standard error, n = 6 sites).Total biomass combusted is the sum of all components combusted.Total carbon stock (above- and below-ground) pre-fire is current carbon stock before the fire.Proportion combusted is the total biomass combusted divided by the pre-fire carbon stock.Distribution is shown as the proportion of carbon in each biomass component, including living vegetation, dead standing trees, litter and coarse woody debris.Initial fire occurred in year 1 and the change over time in each biomass component, plus the total biomass, is simulated; (a) old growth forest initially that is burnt in year 1 and recovery is simulated over 250 years assuming no other disturbance; (b) old growth forest initially that is burnt in years 1 and 113, according to the average fire frequency, and recovery simulated over two fire cycles; (c) 1939 regrowth forest initially that is simulated over two fire cycles; (d) 1983 regrowth forest initially that is simulated over two fire cycles.Under a regime of repeated fires on a 112-year return time, trends occurred in the total biomass carbon stock because forest age changed from that of the initial forest. The old growth forest decreased in carbon stock because of the more frequent disturbance, whereas the 1983 and 1939 regrowth forests increased in carbon stock because they remained undisturbed for a longer period than at their initial age. These scenarios of carbon stock dynamics represent an average forest stand of a given initial age subject to the average wildfire regime. A range of forest age classes occur across the landscape, including forests much older than 112 years. Forests that remain undisturbed for several hundred years have the capacity to continue accumulating carbon stocks.Change in carbon stock was calculated as the difference between pre- and post-2009 wildfire, including total biomass of living and dead trees, above- and below-ground, shrubs, litter and coarse woody debris.Although the total amount of carbon stock loss across the landscape burnt during the wildfire was large as an annual flow in the national inventory, we found that the proportion of total ecosystem carbon stock combusted was relatively small, both at site and landscape scales. The major impact of wildfire was the redistribution of carbon among biomass components, from living to dead biomass and CWD, and their longer-term rates of change due to decomposition and regeneration. Assessing the carbon stock loss by combustion in relation to the total stock, rather than fuel load, meant that changes in stock could be tracked over time and compared between different human activities and disturbance types.The major impact of wildfire in the montane ash forest was the redistribution of carbon among biomass components, from living to dead, and subsequent long-term stock losses from decomposition and gains by regeneration. The relative rates of these processes and subsequent mean residence times of the biomass components determine the long-term dynamics of carbon stock in the ecosystem. These long-term dynamics resulted in changes of up to 20% about the mean stock, whereas direct losses from combustion represented 6–14% of the total biomass stock.Our results about the magnitude and timeframes of carbon stock changes due to wildfires suggest that carbon accounts need to be comprehensive and include all stocks and flows. Such accounts enable differentiation of stock changes due to natural disturbances and human activities. There are four reasons why constructing carbon accounts which differentiate carbon stock changes are beneficial.Third, the increases and decreases in carbon stock post-fire resulting from differential rates of regeneration, mortality and decomposition mean that excluding burnt areas from the national inventory until carbon stocks are restored to pre-fire levels, is not an adequate method for excluding the effect of natural disturbances on net changes in carbon stocks. In fact, the increase in carbon stocks for some decades post-fire would produce artificial credits, but later decreases due to decomposition would produce artificial debits in the national inventory, which are not related to human activities. Additionally, the high levels of uncertainty in these long-term dynamics could produce errors in the national inventory.Our results suggest that current national accounting that uses default values (Tier 2 methodology) for fuel combustion efficiency and fuel load can be improved by using site data from different ecosystems. Data from existing state forest inventories need to be augmented by comprehensive sampling of forest age structure, including old growth forests, and all components of the carbon stock, including dead wood. The methods used here are generic and would constitute Tier 3 methodology that is appropriate for national and project-based accounting. The sampling methods were non-destructive and feasible to apply to a large number of sites.Carbon stocks in forest ecosystems change in response to wildfire in the short-term by combustion and in the long-term by redistribution among biomass components and their subsequent differential rates of decomposition and regeneration. It is important that carbon accounts include these processes because all stock changes, activities and land areas contribute to quantifying the global carbon cycle. However, the timeframes of the ecological processes that determine carbon stock changes are longer than the time periods for reporting of national inventories for compliance with emissions reductions targets. This problem of incongruous timeframes means that reporting against targets should be based on net changes in carbon stocks from human activities to incentivise mitigation activities. If the carbon accounts differentiate stock changes between the sources from natural and human-induced disturbances, then the net stock change from human activities can be extracted from the accounts for use in reporting. This distinction is currently made between the comprehensive UNFCCC accounts and the reports against targets for the Kyoto Protocol, except that the guidelines for the Protocol include net stock changes from natural disturbances that can be discounted above an averaged background level. However, our results indicate that the spatial and temporal variability in carbon dynamics is too high and the uncertainty of estimates too great to enable a realistic averaged background level that would prevent distortions of the inventory by stock changes that were outside human control.(DOCX)We wish to thank Clive Hilliker for expert assistance with the figures and Steve Meacher for assistance with field measurements of shrub biomass. Helpful discussions about fire ecology with Malcolm Gill, Geoff Cary and Michael Doherty are gratefully acknowledged. The inventory plot data and spatial data for the Central Highlands were obtained from the Victorian Department of Sustainability and Environment under data access licence agreement DALA_2009_082. We thank anonymous reviewers for comments that have improved the manuscript.