The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. Conceived and designed the experiments: JPD CAM MM. Performed the experiments: JPD. Analyzed the data: JPD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JPD MM. Wrote the manuscript: JPD CAM MM. Conversion of farmland land-use matrices to surface mining is an increasing threat to the habitat quality of forest remnants and their constituent biota, with consequences for ecosystem functionality. We evaluated the effects of matrix type on bird community composition and the abundance and evenness within avian functional groups in south-west Ghana. We hypothesized that surface mining near remnants may result in a shift in functional composition of avifaunal communities, potentially disrupting ecological processes within tropical forest ecosystems. Matrix intensification and proximity to the remnant edge strongly influenced the abundance of members of several functional guilds. Obligate frugivores, strict terrestrial insectivores, lower and upper strata birds, and insect gleaners were most negatively affected by adjacent mining matrices, suggesting certain ecosystem processes such as seed dispersal may be disrupted by landscape change in this region. Evenness of these functional guilds was also lower in remnants adjacent to surface mining, regardless of the distance from remnant edge, with the exception of strict terrestrial insectivores. These shifts suggest matrix intensification can influence avian functional group composition and related ecosystem-level processes in adjacent forest remnants. The management of matrix habitat quality near and within mine concessions is important for improving efforts to preserveavian biodiversity in landscapes undergoing intensification such as through increased surface mining.All field work was approved by the University of Queensland Animal Ethics Committee under permit number GPEM/191/10. Permission to access conservation reserves was granted by the Forestry Commission and the Wildlife Division of Ghana. Permission to access private company properties (e.g. mining sites adjacent reserves) was granted by relevant authorities.Insert in bottom right shows the location of Ghana in Africa.* Explanatory variables used in analyses in addition to matrix type and distance to edgeSignificance codes: &lt;0.001 '*** '; &lt; 0.01 '** ' &lt;0.05 '* 'Significance codes: &lt;0.001 '*** '; &lt; 0.01 '** ' &lt;0.05 '* 'Matrix intensification and proximity to remnant edge significantly influenced the abundance and evenness of several different functional groups. We found that both factors strongly influenced the representation within the assemblage of species with particular dietary preferences and foraging strategies. Mean abundance and evenness of obligate frugivores, terrestrial insectivores, lower and upper strata birds as well as foliage and bark gleaning insectivores were all significantly lower in remnants adjacent to surface mining sites compared to their remnants in agricultural landscapes. Our study suggests a significant shift in functional composition of avian communities adjacent to highly-intensive mining matrices. This implies that even with no further tropical forest loss in fragmented Upper Guinea forest landscapes, the conversion of low contrast agricultural lands to high intensive surface mining may have significant negative consequences for tropical forest ecosystem functioning.Changes in functional evenness and abundance can influence ecosystem level processes independently of species richness (Dangles &amp; Malmqvist 2004). Matrix change due to the replacement of low-intensity agricultural lands with higher-contrast surface mining affects bird species groups, potentially via alteration of vegetation structure and composition and chemical pollution in fragmented landscapes of southwest Ghana. The influence of these disturbances varies among species and functional groups, resulting in perturbed assemblages with altered representation within different functional groups. In this study, obligate frugivores, terrestrial insectivores and insect-gleaners were most affected functional groups.(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)We thank Dr K. A Monney, Dr A. Asamoah, D. Dramani, Selasi Dzitse, James Biney and the many field assistants for help during fieldwork in Ghana. We would also like to thank two anonymous reviewers for providing useful comments on the manuscript.