 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: LW SKD. Performed the experiments: LW SKD YYL XYL JJS YLW DML YSM. Analyzed the data: LW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LW SKD. Wrote the paper: LW.  The deterioration of alpine grassland has great impact on ecosystem services in the alpine region of Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau. However, the effect of grassland degradation on ecosystem services and the consequence of grassland deterioration on economic loss still remains a mystery. So, in this study, we assessed four types of ecosystem services following the Millennium Ecosystem Assessment classification, along a degradation gradient. Five sites of alpine grassland at different levels of degradation were investigated in Guoluo Prefecture of Qinghai Province, China. The species composition, aboveground biomass, soil total organic carbon (TOC), and soil total nitrogen (TN) were tested to evaluate major ecological services of the alpine grassland. We estimated the value of primary production, carbon storage, nitrogen recycling, and plant diversity. The results show the ecosystem services of alpine grassland varied along the degradation gradient. The ecosystem services of degraded grassland (moderate, heavy and severe) were all significantly lower than non-degraded grassland. Interestingly, the lightly degraded grassland provided more economic benefit from carbon maintenance and nutrient sequestration compared to non-degraded. Due to the destruction of the alpine grassland, the economic loss associated with decrease of biomass in 2008 was $198/ha. Until 2008, the economic loss caused by carbon emissions and nitrogen loss on severely degraded grassland was up to $8 033/ha and $13 315/ha, respectively. Urgent actions are required to maintain or promote the ecosystem services of alpine grassland in the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau.  In this study, vegetation composition, aboveground biomass, soil total organic carbon and total nitrogen were measured in study sites with different levels of degradation (none, light, moderate, heave and severe). Four major ecosystem services of the alpine grassland, including biodiversity conservation, carbon sequestration, nitrogen maintenance and primary production, were selected for evaluation in this study. The reasons for choosing these four ecosystem services are described below.  The parameters for grassland degradation and ecosystem services were measured in the field during growing seasons from July to August of 2008 and 2009. Vegetation composition, coverage and plant biomass were surveyed within four 100 cm×100 cm quadrats in each site of the alpine grassland at different degrees of degradation to quantify the level of grassland degradation in the present study. Plant diversity in each of degraded grasslands was surveyed in each site with thirty randomly distributed 50 cm×50 cm quadrats. Margalef richness index, Simpson index and Pielou evenness index were calculated.  The evaluation in this study was a first attempt of integrating direct market valuation, indirect market valuation and contingent valuation to estimate the value of alpine grasslands along the degradation gradient based on the first-hand data from the field surveys. The assessment of the ecosystem service values of the alpine grassland in Qinghai-Tibet Plateau were standardized into US dollars ($1 =  RMByuan 6.85, August 2008), so as to reflect welfare in ways that are not mediated by the consumption of purchased goods. Because soil carbon, nitrogen and plant diversity losses did not all occur in a given year, the values for these services represent the values accumulated up to 2008.  Note: ND, LD, MD, HD, SD represent non-degradation, light degradation, moderate degradation, heavy degradation and severely degradation, respectively.  Note: ND, LD, MD, HD, SD represent non-degradation, light degradation, moderate degradation, heavy degradation and severely degradation, respectively.  Note: ND, LD, MD, HD, SD represent non-degradation, light degradation, moderate degradation, heavy degradation and severely degradation, respectively.  Note: ND, LD, MD, HD, SD represent non-degradation, light degradation, moderate degradation, heavy degradation and severely degradation, respectively.  The value of plant diversity maintenance in non-degradation grassland was $400/ha, and in light, moderate and heavy degradation grasslands were $300/ha, but in severely degradation it was only $200/ha.  Note: ND, LD, MD, HD, SD represent non-degradation, light degradation, moderate degradation, heavy degradation and severe degradation, respectively.  The authors wish to express their great thanks to the reviewers and the editors for their efforts and time. 