 Conceived and designed the experiments: JAGC JAM EJG. Performed the experiments: JAGC JAM EJG EEL MAR EAP RGC JLH CM. Analyzed the data: JAGC JAM EJG EEL MAR EAP RGC CM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JAGC JAM EJG EEL MAR EAP RGC JLH CM. Wrote the paper: JAGC JAM EJG EEL MAR EAP RGC JLH CM.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  The goal of this study was to examine the potential of textural properties of a VHR Quickbird image to model secondary vegetation attributes measured in the field, in a seasonally dry tropical region. We wanted to test the power of the texture of remote images to describe and predict vegetation attributes, while identifying those texture attributes with the highest predictive potential. In modeling the relationship between textural and vegetation attributes, we succeeded in producing simple models that can be easily obtained for many regions, and that have a straightforward biological interpretation.  We assessed the potential of the 40 texture variables to describe the observed changes in each of the 14 vegetation variables by means of linear models. In all cases the response variables were log-transformed before model fitting. This procedure guaranteed that the estimated values, when transformed to their original scale, would be positive; additionally, such transformation tends to homogenize the residuals, which are usually proportional to the mean in most probability density functions restricted to the positive numbers domain.  The  U  set was arbitrarily defined as those trees that were above the median of the canopy cover cumulative distribution of each fallow. The proportion of BA U  with respect to BA T  was generally high, mostly above 60%, and often higher in mid-age fallows, despite the very low number of individuals included in this community's subset (in all cases less than 2% of stem density of the entire community).  We constructed three types of linear models to describe the relationship between the 14 vegetation attributes and the 40 image texture variables. These types corresponded to the number of texture variables used in constructing the model: one, two or three texture variables.  The ability to predict characteristics of secondary vegetation accurately depends on a combination of three relevant methodological aspects, all of which synergically contribute to the high predictive value of the models.  The third aspect was the decision to assess and contrast two large sets of models derived from alternative modeling procedures: one set included a limited number of descriptive models that included all sampling sites, whereas the other consisted of numerous predictive models constructed through leave-two-out cross-validation. The high degree of consistency between the models selected from either procedure confers increased reliability to the results, and implies that constructing descriptive models may suffice for assessing the secondary vegetation in a region. This is a valuable result as the construction of predictive models may require a large computational capacity as well as ample programming and statistical skills.  Understanding why some textural attributes are more useful than others in predicting vegetation properties, and therefore why they were repeatedly incorporated into the models, is important for a number of reasons. From a practical perspective this knowledge will orient future efforts to assess secondary vegetation by guiding researchers as to which variables they should focus on. Also, this information will provide a firmer ground for theoretical inquiry, as it represents an efficient way to identify relevant biological properties of the vegetation system and its spatially explicit spectral expression.  Analyzing the extent and complexity of secondary vegetation by recognizing the spatial variation of its spectral information opens new and attractive research avenues; these differ substantially from previous efforts to study secondary vegetation that have been primarily based on the examination of spectral reflectance properties. Overall, the procedure is potentially usable in any successional plant community whose development involves large changes in heterogeneity through time. The current availability of VHR imagery, together with increasing computing capabilities, make it possible to develop faster and more efficient ways to assess the amount and condition of secondary vegetation in increasingly human-impacted regions world-wide based on this approach.  (XLS)  (XLS)  Armando Peralta provided support in image processing. JAGC and EJG thank the Graduate Program in Biological Sciences of the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México for providing continuous support during their PhD studies. Thanks to Trudy Kavanagh for revision and edition of the manuscript. We warmly thank the people of Nizanda for their hospitality, permission to work on their land and assistance during fieldwork. We thank two anonymous reviewers for commenting on a previous draft of this work. 