 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: MJC ICB. Performed the experiments: MJC. Analyzed the data: MJC MLM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: ICB. Wrote the paper: MJC MLM ICB.  Across US Great Plains grasslands, a gradient of increasing mean annual precipitation from west to east corresponds to increasing aboveground net primary productivity (ANPP) and increasing N-limitation. Previous work has shown that there is no increase in net N mineralization rates across this gradient, leading to the question of where eastern prairie grasses obtain the nitrogen to support production. One as-yet unexamined source is soil organic N, despite abundant literature from other ecosystems showing that plants take up dissolved soil organic N. This study measured KCl-extractable dissolved organic N (DON) in surface soils across the grassland productivity gradient. We found that KCl-extractable DON pools increased from west to east. If available to and used by plants, this DON may help explain the high ANPP in the eastern Great Plains. These results suggest a need for future research to determine whether, in what quantities, and in what forms prairie grasses use organic N to support primary production.  This exploratory study examined the spatial pattern in abundances and rates of production of KCl-extractable dissolved inorganic N (DIN) and DON along the west to east precipitation gradient across US grasslands.  MAP =  mean annual precipitation (mm), MAT =  mean annual temperature (°C), TNC =  The Nature Conservancy, LTER =  National Science Foundation Long-Term Ecological Research site. Data in lower panel is from this study; values in parentheses represent one standard error of the mean.  At each site, we set up three 25 m long transects within a 100 m radius of each other in undisturbed areas representative of the surrounding vegetation. From June 6–15, 2011, we collected soil cores (10 cm length ×5 cm diameter) from two microsites (under plant canopies and interspaces between plants) and at two depths (0–5 cm and 5–10 cm) at three random locations on each transect, for a total of 180 soil samples (2 microsites ×2 depths ×3 locations ×3 transects ×5 sites). Soils were immediately sieved through a 2 mm mesh and homogenized in a plastic bag.  We installed one pair of Plant Root Simulator (PRS) resin probes (Western Ag Innovations Inc., Saskatoon, Saskatchewan) per microsite at 10 random locations along each transect (2 microsites ×10 locations ×3 transects ×5 sites  = 300 pairs), to estimate inorganic N supply rate. Each pair consisted of one anion and one cation probe to collect mobile NO 3  −  and NH 4  + , respectively. Probes were inserted into the soil with the adsorption membrane extending from the surface to 5.5 cm depth, and were buried for 30 days from early May to early June 2011. At each site, the probes were removed on the same day as the soil sampling. Probes were sorted into two groups of five pairs of probes from each microsite type. This resulted in two replicate sets of probes per each microsite type per each transect for a total of 60 (2 replicates ×2 microsites ×3 transects ×5 sites) probe sets. Probes were washed in the laboratory with DI water within two days of unearthing and then sent to Western Ag Innovations, Inc. (Saskatoon, Saskatchewan) for inorganic N analysis.  The eluate from the extraction cups was shaken for 1 hour and filtered in the laboratory using Whatman #1 filter paper and frozen immediately thereafter. For measurement of total KCl-extractable dissolved total N and inorganic N, we thawed the eluate and diluted a 2.5 mL subsample with 17.5 mL DI water. We analyzed total dissolved N on a Shimadzu TOC-V Analyzer (Shimadzu Scientific Instruments, Wood Dale, IL, USA). Dissolved inorganic N was analyzed at the Natural Resource Ecology Laboratory (Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO) using an Alpkem Flow Solution IV Automated wet chemistry system (O.I. Analytical, College Station, TX, USA). We estimated KCl-extractable DON as the difference between total dissolved N and dissolved inorganic N.  We found that the abundance of DON increased across the west-to-east along the precipitation and productivity gradient of US Great Plains grasslands, suggesting that it could be a significant source of N if plants are able to utilize it. If organic N is an important component of available N in US grasslands, it may explain why ecosystem models that do not include plant use of organic N are unable to predict N supply rates across the US grasslands. Additional studies must be conducted to determine if grass species dominating the US Great Plains assimilate biologically-relevant quantities of organic N.  (TIF)  (XLSX)  We wish to thank The Nature Conservancy, Fort Hays State University, USDA-ARS, and the Long-Term Ecological Research Sites at Konza Prairie and Shortgrass Steppe for access to field sites. We thank Colin Pinney (EcoCore Analytical Services, a Colorado State University Core Facility) and Leann Naughton for assistance with nitrogen analysis. This manuscript was improved by comments from William Lauenroth, Urszula Norton, David Bell, Daniel Schlaepfer, Otgonsuren Avirmed, Ariuna Lkhagva, Lynn Moore, Cait Rottler, and four anonymous reviewers. 