 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: MTS. Performed the experiments: MTS. Analyzed the data: HD FdB MTS. Wrote the paper: HD FdB MTS.  Plant functional traits underlie vegetation responses to environmental changes such as global warming, and consequently influence ecosystem processes. While most of the existing studies focus on the effect of warming only on species diversity and productivity, we further investigated (i) how the structure of community plant functional traits in temperate grasslands respond to experimental warming, and (ii) whether species and functional diversity contribute to a greater stability of grasslands, in terms of vegetation composition and productivity. Intact vegetation turves were extracted from temperate subalpine grassland (highland) in the Eastern Pyrenees and transplanted into a warm continental, experimental site in Lleida, in Western Catalonia (lowland). The impacts of simulated warming on plant production and diversity, functional trait structure, and vegetation compositional stability were assessed. We observed an increase in biomass and a reduction in species and functional diversity under short-term warming. The functional structure of the grassland communities changed significantly, in terms of functional diversity and community-weighted means (CWM) for several traits. Acquisitive and fast-growing species with higher SLA, early flowering, erect growth habit, and rhizomatous strategy became dominant in the lowland. Productivity was significantly positively related to species, and to a lower extent, functional diversity, but productivity and stability after warming were more dependent on trait composition (CWM) than on diversity. The turves with more acquisitive species before warming changed less in composition after warming. Results suggest that (i) the short-term warming can lead to the dominance of acquisitive fast growing species over conservative species, thus reducing species richness, and (ii) the functional traits structure in grassland communities had a greater influence on the productivity and stability of the community under short-term warming, compared to diversity effects. In summary, short-term climate warming can greatly alter vegetation functional structure and its relation to productivity.  At the end of the experiment, 17 weeks after the start, above-ground biomass was estimated by harvesting vegetation on a 20 x 20 cm quadrat placed in the middle of a subset of 28 out of the 60 turves used for species frequency. A previous harvest was carried out in 28 different turves 10 weeks after the start of the experiment. The biomass data at the two dates were used to analyze the diversity-productivity relationship.  This study did not involve protected or endangered species and it was not necessary to obtain specific permission to sample at any of the sampling sites.   a P-values in bold indicate significant relationships.   a ***P &lt; 0.001   b P-values in bold indicate significant relationships.  Relationship between the initial CWM SLA and the change in vegetation composition (Bray-Curtis dissimilarity) between beginning and end of experiment, in both the highland and the lowland. The black points correspond to the lowland, and the white points correspond to the highland. Solid linear regression line reflects significant relationship (p &lt; 0.05) in the lowland; and no line represents no significance.  Relation between above-ground biomass and diversity indices: Species richness (left), Simpson’s diversity index with equivalent numbers (centre), and Functional diversity’s index Rao with equivalent numbers (right) in both the highland and the lowland. The black points correspond to the lowland, and the white points correspond to the highland. Solid linear regression line reflects significant relationship (p&lt;0.05) between the variables in the lowland; dashed line refers to a marginal significant correlation (p&lt;0.1) in the highland; and no line represents no significance.   a ***P &lt; 0.001   b P-values in bold indicate significant relationships (P-values &lt; 0.05)  Overall, we found that a short-term warming enhanced productivity and reduced diversity significantly. A change in vegetation composition, manifested by a shift in dominance towards acquisitive fast-growing species, was also observed. Our results also advocate that a higher diversity did not contribute to a greater stability of the community under stress; instead plant functional traits, particularly high SLA, were responsible for the stability of the vegetation to increased temperature. Also, the changes in CWM of certain traits (% rhizomes, growth form, and start of first flowering) seem to be the main drivers of increased biomass production under climate warming. The relationship between productivity and species richness remained positive within both the highland and the lowland. We postulate that seasonal climate change strongly affects functional traits and diversity. On the long term, however, knowledge of sensitivity of grasslands to climate change is scant and thus more experiments over longer periods are needed. Particularly, complementary observational studies and reciprocal transplanting (from the lowland back to the highland) could be useful tools to better understand the observed patterns. Also, we suggest that further studies should address the recovery of the vegetation after a short period of climate warming, in terms of functional diversity and plant functional traits.  Correlation coefficients between the CWM of traits: SLA, LDMC, height, start of first flowering, % prostrate, % rhizomes.  (PDF)  Correlation coefficients between the diversity indices: species richness SR, Simpson’s diversity index, and functional diversity FD.  (PDF)  (PDF)  Results of stepwise regression model to assess the effect of the most significant CWM traits and the most significant diversity indices (according to the previous multiple regression models) on biomass, in the lowland and the highland.  (PDF)  Results of stepwise regression model to assess the effect of the CWM traits and diversity indices on the change in vegetation composition (Bray-Curtis dissimilarity) in the lowland.  (PDF)  We would like to thank all the people who helped in the experimental set up and sampling. We would also like to thank Dr. Jan Lepš for suggestions on data analyses. We are particularly grateful to two anonymous reviewers for improving the paper, through their useful suggestions and comments. 