The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: WL G-ZD. Performed the experiments: WL K-LY. Analyzed the data: WL K-LY J-MC LG G-HJ JZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HEE LG G-ZD. Wrote the paper: WL K-LY HEE.Past studies have widely documented the decrease in species diversity in response to addition of nutrients, however functional diversity is often independent from species diversity. In this study, we conducted a field experiment to examine the effect of nitrogen and phosphorus fertilization ((NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub> HPO<sub>4</sub>) at 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup> (F0, F15, F30 and F60) after 4 years of continuous fertilization on functional diversity and species diversity, and its relationship with productivity in an alpine meadow community on the Tibetan Plateau. To this purpose, three community-weighted mean trait values (specific leaf area, SLA; mature plant height, MPH; and seed size, SS) for 30 common species in each fertilization level were determined; three components of functional diversity (functional richness, FRic; functional evenness, FEve; and Rao’s index of quadratic entropy, FRao) were quantified. Our results showed that: (i) species diversity sharply decreased, but functional diversity remained stable with fertilization; (ii) community-weighted mean traits (SLA and MPH) had a significant increase along the fertilization level; (iii) aboveground biomass was not correlated with functional diversity, but it was significantly correlated with species diversity and MPH. Our results suggest that decreases in species diversity due to fertilization do not result in corresponding changes in functional diversity. Functional identity of species may be more important than functional diversity in influencing aboveground productivity in this alpine meadow community, and our results also support the mass ratio hypothesis; that is, the traits of the dominant species influenced the community biomass production.We assessed the relationship between species diversity and functional diversity by using correlation analysis. We used one-way ANOVA to test the effect of fertilization on plant species diversity (species richness, Shannon-Wiener diversity index, evenness index), the CWM traits and functional diversity (FRic, FEve and FRao). Then, we performed linear regression modeling to test the relationships between community biomass and species diversity, the CWM traits and functional diversity. These statistical analyses were performed using the R 3.2.0 software (R Development Core Team, 2011).Fric, functional richness; FRao, Rao index.FEve, functional evenness. Values in bold indicate a significant (p &lt;0.05) correlation.F0, F15, F30, and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>. Significant differences indicated by dissimilar letters above each bar were determined using Tukey’s honestly significant difference (HSD) test (P&lt; 0.05) after one-way ANOVA.CWM, community-weighted mean trait values; SLA, leaf area per unit dry mass; MPH, mature plant height; SS, seed size. F0, F15, F30, and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>. Significant differences indicated by dissimilar letters above each bar were determined using Tukey’s honestly significant difference (HSD) test (P&lt; 0.05) after one-way ANOVA.R<sup>2</sup>and P value was estimated from a linear regression model. F0, F15, F30, and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>.R<sup>2</sup>and P value was estimated from a linear regression model. CWM, community-weighted mean trait values; SLA, leaf area per unit dry mass; MPH, mature plant height; SS, seed size.The results of our present grassland experiments complement past work on diversity loss due to fertilization by comparing different measurements of plant diversity (species diversity and functional diversity) along a fertilization level, and its relationship with productivity in an alpine meadow community. Our results emphasized that community productivity is linked to the functional traits of the dominant species rather than functional diversity, and also supported the mass ratio hypothesis.Overall, these results suggest that decreases in species diversity due to fertilization do not directly result in corresponding changes in functional diversity, and species composition and functional identity of species may be more important than functional diversity in influencing ecosystem processes (e.g., primary productivity) in this alpine meadow community. Our study also supports the mass ratio hypothesis, that is, the functional traits of the dominant species influenced community productivity. A long-term investigation is further needed to better disentangle the drivers of functional diversity and its consequences for ecosystem functioning.FG, functional group; G, grasses; F, Forbs; L, Legumes; F0, F15, F30 and F60 represent (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> fertilizer applications of 0, 15, 30 and 60 g m<sup>-2</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>.(DOCX)We thank colleagues who helped with field work. We are grateful to Alpine Meadow Ecosystem Research Station of Lanzhou University for providing experimental site. We also thank two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on an earlier version of this manuscript.