The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: AE STM NE HH AV AW WWW. Performed the experiments: STM NE AV AE ML MA HH AW. Analyzed the data: AE STM CS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: STM CS NE AE HH AW WWW. Wrote the paper: AE STM MA NE HH ML AV AW WWW.Loss of plant diversity influences essential ecosystem processes as aboveground productivity, and can have cascading effects on the arthropod communities in adjacent trophic levels. However, few studies have examined how those changes in arthropod communities can have additional impacts on ecosystem processes caused by them (e.g. pollination, bioturbation, predation, decomposition, herbivory). Therefore, including arthropod effects in predictions of the impact of plant diversity loss on such ecosystem processes is an important but little studied piece of information. In a grassland biodiversity experiment, we addressed this gap by assessing aboveground decomposer and herbivore communities and linking their abundance and diversity to rates of decomposition and herbivory. Path analyses showed that increasing plant diversity led to higher abundance and diversity of decomposing arthropods through higher plant biomass. Higher species richness of decomposers, in turn, enhanced decomposition. Similarly, species-rich plant communities hosted a higher abundance and diversity of herbivores through elevated plant biomass and C:N ratio, leading to higher herbivory rates. Integrating trophic interactions into the study of biodiversity effects is required to understand the multiple pathways by which biodiversity affects ecosystem functioning.Here, we integrate consumers into our models of plant diversity effects on ecosystem processes by focusing on three components of plant communities (food quantity: aboveground biomass; food quality: C:N ratio of plants, and species richness- hereafter: plant diversity), two components of consumer communities (arthropod abundance, arthropod species richness), and two processes (decomposition and herbivory). We test (1) if plant diversity effects on arthropods and decomposition/herbivory found in former studies can be confirmed, (2) if effects of plant diversity on decomposition and herbivory are mediated by altered arthropod community composition in terms of overall abundance, and (3) which mechanisms link plants to arthropods (plant diversity, quantity or quality), and arthropods to decomposition and herbivory (abundance or species richness).Arthropod sampling was conducted with the permission of the city council of Jena, Germany.Herbivorous arthropods were collected by suction sampling in June and July using a modified commercial vacuum cleaner (Kärcher A2500, Kärcher GmbH, Winnenden, Germany). Three subplots of 0.75 m×0.75 m were randomly chosen within each plot, covered quickly by a cage with gauze coat of the same size, and sampled until no arthropods were spotted anymore. The sampling was carried out between 9 a.m. and 4 p.m. within two 4-day sampling periods. Pit fall samples and suction samples were sorted to order level and most orders containing decomposers and herbivores were further identified to species level. For herbivores only Auchenorrhyncha, Coleoptera, and Heteroptera were identified to species level, and these orders covered 55% of the potential herbivores we sampled. Aphids and Diptera, which made together 30.2% of the sampled potential herbivores were not identified, because of their patchy distribution within a single plot (Aphids) and due to identification difficulties (Diptera).Data of the different sampling campaigns were pooled.Overall, the final dataset contained 1,316 macrofauna decomposer individuals belonging to 12 species (four Isopoda and eight Diplopoda species). Isopoda dominated the macrofauna decomposer community, representing on average 92.8% of the total community.Even if we used wheat straw as litter material in our study we expected a negative effect of plant C:N ratio on the environment for decomposers (lower nutrient availability in litter and soil), thereby indirectly affecting their fitness (in our case: abundance). In contrast to our hypothesis we detected no significant effect of aboveground plant quality (C:N ratio) on decomposer abundance and species richness, maybe indicating that the C:N ratio of the fresh plant material is a poor predictor of the C:N ratio of the litter material.(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)(DOCX)