 Conceived and designed the experiments: BML IIA MGL EGB. Performed the experiments: IIA MGL ICA IP DGA EGB EOR IPA BW. Analyzed the data: BML. Wrote the paper: BML. Contributed to the discussion: IIA MGL ICA IP EGB EOR IPA BW JAG FSM CLS. Supervised experimental design: JAG CM MO.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Ecosystem service assessments have increasingly been used to support environmental management policies, mainly based on biophysical and economic indicators. However, few studies have coped with the social-cultural dimension of ecosystem services, despite being considered a research priority. We examined how ecosystem service bundles and trade-offs emerge from diverging social preferences toward ecosystem services delivered by various types of ecosystems in Spain. We conducted 3,379 direct face-to-face questionnaires in eight different case study sites from 2007 to 2011. Overall, 90.5% of the sampled population recognized the ecosystem’s capacity to deliver services. Formal studies, environmental behavior, and gender variables influenced the probability of people recognizing the ecosystem’s capacity to provide services. The ecosystem services most frequently perceived by people were regulating services; of those, air purification held the greatest importance. However, statistical analysis showed that socio-cultural factors and the conservation management strategy of ecosystems (i.e., National Park, Natural Park, or a non-protected area) have an effect on social preferences toward ecosystem services. Ecosystem service trade-offs and bundles were identified by analyzing social preferences through multivariate analysis (redundancy analysis and hierarchical cluster analysis). We found a clear trade-off among provisioning services (and recreational hunting) versus regulating services and almost all cultural services. We identified three ecosystem service bundles associated with the conservation management strategy and the rural-urban gradient. We conclude that socio-cultural preferences toward ecosystem services can serve as a tool to identify relevant services for people, the factors underlying these social preferences, and emerging ecosystem service bundles and trade-offs.  Sample points are indicated with red circles. National and Natural Parks are shown in dark and light green, respectively.  C.I. refers to its 95% confidence.  PAs  =  If respondent visited protected areas during the previous year.  S.D. refers to standard deviation.  S.D.  =  standard deviation.  PAs  =  If respondent visited protected areas during the previous year.  The biplot shows the relationships between stakeholders’ perceptions towards particular ecosystem services and variables related to stakeholders’ characteristics and land management strategies. Grey variables in bold represent explaining variables with higher standardized canonical coefficients for Axes 1 and 2. Detail legend: circles  =  ecosystem services; squares  =  land management strategy (i.e., National Park, Natural Park, or non-protected land); triangles  =  environmental behavior and socio-economic characteristics of stakeholders; diamonds  =  ecosystems. (PAs  =  If respondent visited protected areas during the previous year, LEK  =  local ecological knowledge and sense of place services).  The dendogram shows ecosystem service bundles resulting from diverging social preferences. Ecosystem service bundles are shown in different colors to improve visualization.  (PDF)  (PDF)  (PDF)  (PDF) 