 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: SJH WJL. Performed the experiments: XMS GHD. Analyzed the data: XKZ XMS SXZ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XMS. Wrote the manuscript: XMS XKZ WJL.   The environmental changes arising from nitrogen (N) deposition and precipitation influence soil ecological processes in forest ecosystems. However, the corresponding effects of environmental changes on soil biota are poorly known. Soil nematodes are the important bioindicator of soil environmental change, and their responses play a key role in the feedbacks of terrestrial ecosystems to climate change. Therefore, to explore the responsive mechanisms of soil biota to N deposition and precipitation, soil nematode communities were studied after 3 years of environmental changes by water and/or N addition in a temperate forest of Changbai Mountain, Northeast China. The results showed that water combined with N addition treatment decreased the total nematode abundance in the organic horizon (O), while the opposite trend was found in the mineral horizon (A). Significant reductions in the abundances of fungivores, plant-parasites and omnivores-predators were also found in the water combined with N addition treatment. The significant effect of water interacted with N on the total nematode abundance and trophic groups indicated that the impacts of N on soil nematode communities were mediated by water availability. The synergistic effect of precipitation and N deposition on soil nematode communities was stronger than each effect alone. Structural equation modeling suggested water and N additions had direct effects on soil nematode communities. The feedback of soil nematodes to water and nitrogen addition was highly sensitive and our results indicate that minimal variations in soil properties such as those caused by climate changes can lead to severe changes in soil nematode communities.  No specific permits were required for the described field studies and activities. The location is not privately owned or protected in any way and the field studies did not involve endangered or protected species.  Nematode abundances were ln (x+1) transformed prior to the statistical analysis for normality of the data. The general linear model (GLM) procedure with multivariate analyses of variance (MANOVA) for a split-plot design were performed to test the effects of N addition, water addition and their interactions on soil properties and nematodes. All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS (vers.13.0; SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA).  Bars indicate standard errors. SM, soil moisture; SOC, total soil organic carbon; TN, total nitrogen; MBC, microbial biomass carbon; and MBN, microbial biomass nitrogen.  Bars indicate standard errors. OP, omnivores-predators; PP, plant-parasites; FF, fungivores; BF, bacterivores.  Estimate indicate estimate of regression weight.  In terms of nematode ecological indices, the significant water and N addition effects on TD and NCR were mostly explained by the variation in the abundances of fungivores and plant-parasites. These results indicate that N deposition and precipitation could affect nematode community through changes in the trophic group level.   We thank Prof. T. Martijn Bezemer (Netherlands Institute of Ecology) and the two anonymous reviewers provided by the journal for insightful reviews of the manuscript. This research was conducted at the Research Station of Changbai Mountain Forest Ecosystems, Chinese Academy of Sciences.  