The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: KM DAW SP. Performed the experiments: KM AJF DJM. Analyzed the data: KM. Wrote the paper: KM DAW SP AJF DJM.The high concentration of the world’s species in tropical forests endows these systems with particular importance for retaining global biodiversity, yet it also presents significant challenges for ecology and conservation science. The vast number of rare and yet to be discovered species restricts the applicability of species-level modelling for tropical forests, while the capacity of community classification approaches to identify priorities for conservation and management is also limited. Here we assessed the degree to which macroecological modelling can overcome shortfalls in our knowledge of biodiversity in tropical forests and help identify priority areas for their conservation and management. We used 527 plant community survey plots in the Australian Wet Tropics to generate models and predictions of species richness, compositional dissimilarity, and community composition for all the 4,313 vascular plant species recorded across the region (&gt;1.3 million communities (grid cells)). We then applied these predictions to identify areas of tropical forest likely to contain the greatest concentration of species, rare species, endemic species and primitive angiosperm families. Synthesising these alternative attributes of diversity into a single index of conservation value, we identified two areas within the Australian wet tropics that should be a high priority for future conservation actions: the Atherton Tablelands and Daintree rainforest. Our findings demonstrate the value of macroecological modelling in identifying priority areas for conservation and management actions within highly diverse systems, such as tropical forests.The study region, being the Wet Tropics Bioregion (blue line) and 100 km of surrounding area, in Queensland, Australia (inset). Protected areas (dark green), unprotected natural habitat (pale green) and modified habitat (grey) are shown, along with the locations of the 527 plant community surveys used in our analyses (black dots).Predictions of the overall conservation value for plant diversity of each community (grid cell) in the Australian Wet Tropics, as synthesised across the four different elements of diversity we considered (from Fig. 3).The proportion of QLD Herbarium Corveg survey sites that contain different proportions of taxa not identified to species level, and the spatial distribution of the retained and omitted data across the Australian Wet Tropics.(DOCX)The proportion of records omitted from the retained QLD Herbarium survey sites as a function of the total number of taxa recorded, and the spatial distribution of sites.(DOCX)(DOCX)We thank the Queensland Herbarium and K.J Williams for providing biological and environmental data. The CSIRO survey data were collected under permits issued by the Queensland State Government.