 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: RU-J YM. Performed the experiments: RU-J. Analyzed the data: RU-J. Wrote the paper: RU-J YM AL. Helped with the interpretation of the data: YM AL.  How do stand structure and aboveground biomass vary between the two sites?  How do patterns of NPP and its allocation vary between the two sites?  How do the productivity and carbon dynamics of these forests compare to other temperate forest ecosystems worldwide?    Automatic weather stations (Skye instruments, Powys, UK) were installed in clearings less than 1 km from the study plots in both areas. These stations recorded precipitation, relative humidity, temperature and total solar radiation every 30 minutes. Soil temperature was recorded with a Decagon sensor EC-T (Pullman, WA, USA) installed at a single point at 10 cm depth within the plots AC1 and AA1.  After testing soil conditions using a steel soil sampler, two and three soil pits were excavated in AC1 and AC2 plots, respectively for physical and chemical characterization. In the Andes two soil pits were excavated in each plot. Chemical analyses were done separately for each surface horizon, where most of the roots develop. Analyses included the main macro- and micronutrients and were performed at the Laboratorio de Suelos Forestales at Universidad Austral de Chile.  In order to have an estimate of woody biomass for trees &lt; 10 cm DBH, two 10x10 m plots were established within each plot and small trees (2–10 cm DBH) were censused using callipers. The same equations mentioned above were used to estimate biomass.  Left panel: a) Aboveground woody biomass per species in all trees ≥10 cm diameter, b) proportion of the woody biomass presented in a) contributed by the different species in percentage (%) and c) woody biomass contributed by the large (trees≥10 cm DBH) and small (trees &lt; 10 cm DBH) tree components within each plot. Right panel: d), e), f) the same as a), b) and c), respectively, but for aboveground woody productivity.  Total productivity in Mg C ha -1  year -1  for the one-year period November 2011-October 2012 in the four studied plots and its allocation to the different components. Below-ground NPP is indicated as negative values.   a : Fc: Fitzroya cupressoides, Mb: Mixed-broadleaf evergreen forests, Ac: Austrocedrus chilensis, Nb: Nothofagus betuloides, Aa: Agathis australis (values reported are just for this species and not for the accompanying trees), Ns: Nothofagus solandri, Ps-Th: Picea sitchensis-Tsuga heterophylla, Pm-Th: Pseudotsuga menziesii-Tsuga heterophylla, Ap-Pm: Abies procera-Pseudotsuga menziesii, Tm-Al-Pe: Tsuga mertensiana-Abies lasiocarpa-Picea engelmanii, Pe-Al: Picea engelmanii-Abies lasiocarpa, Ss: Sequoia sempervirens, EN: Evergreen needleleaf, MOT: Mature-old-growth temperate forests, OT: Old-growth temperate forests, MOCTM: Mature-old-growth cool temperate moist forests  (DOC)  (DOCX)  Especial thanks to CONAF (National Forest Service) for their permission and support to work in the Alerce Costero and Alerce Andino National Parks. Thanks to Aldo Farias for the map of this publication and to all the field assistants: Aldo Farias, Emilio Cuq, Oscar Concha, Waldo Iglesias, Moisés Rojas, Darcy Galiano, Carmen Gloria Rodríguez Diego Aliste, Yasna Salazar, Eduardo Vergara, Andrea Castillo and Cesar Leiva. Thanks to professors Victor Sandoval and Alicia Ortega from Universidad Austral de Chile for facilitating essential field instruments. Finally, thanks to the Park Ranger Marcelo Hernández and family, to the Alerce Mountain Lodge owner Nelson García for giving access to the Andean site through his property and to Nixy Barra and Ruperto Mascareña for their support with fieldwork. 