 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: PGS MIMH. Performed the experiments: PGS MIMH. Analyzed the data: PGS MIMH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: PGS MIMH. Wrote the paper: PGS MIMH.  Community structure is driven by mechanisms linked to environmental, spatial and temporal processes, which have been successfully addressed using metacommunity framework. The relative importance of processes shaping community structure can be identified using several different approaches. Two approaches that are increasingly being used are functional diversity and community deconstruction. Functional diversity is measured using various indices that incorporate distinct community attributes. Community deconstruction is a way to disentangle species responses to ecological processes by grouping species with similar traits. We used these two approaches to determine whether they are improvements over traditional measures (e.g., species composition, abundance, biomass) for identification of the main processes driving dung beetle (Scarabaeinae) community structure in a fragmented mainland-island landscape in southern Brazilian Atlantic Forest. We sampled five sites in each of four large forest areas, two on the mainland and two on the island. Sampling was performed in 2012 and 2013. We collected abundance and biomass data from 100 sampling points distributed over 20 sampling sites. We studied environmental, spatial and temporal effects on dung beetle community across three spatial scales, i.e., between sites, between areas and mainland-island. The γ-diversity based on species abundance was mainly attributed to β-diversity as a consequence of the increase in mean α- and β-diversity between areas. Variation partitioning on abundance, biomass and functional diversity showed scale-dependence of processes structuring dung beetle metacommunities. We identified two major groups of responses among 17 functional groups. In general, environmental filters were important at both local and regional scales. Spatial factors were important at the intermediate scale. Our study supports the notion of scale-dependence of environmental, spatial and temporal processes in the distribution and functional organization of Scarabaeinae beetles. We conclude that functional diversity may be used as a complementary approach to traditional measures, and that community deconstruction allows sufficient disentangling of responses of different trait-based groups.  We sampled Scarabaeinae dung beetles using baited pitfall traps made with plastic containers (15 cm diameter x 20 cm depth) buried with the top edge at ground level, allowing beetles to fall in. The traps were protected against rain using a small sheet supported by wooden sticks, placed approximately 10 cm above the trap to prevent overflow. A mixture of water and neutral detergent (300 ml) was added to each container to retain trapped beetles. Human feces and rotting flesh (aged in plastic containers at room temperature three days prior to sampling) were used as bait to attract dung beetles to attract both coprophagous and necrophagous species. Approximately 30 g of each bait type was wrapped in thin cloth and tied in the central part of the rain protection above the traps, preventing the insects from handling the baits. Collected beetles were sorted and dried in an oven (60°C for 72 h), then weighed on a precision balance (0.0001 g). Specimens were identified to species level by expert taxonomists (Dr. Fernando Vaz de Mello, Universidade Federal de Mato Grosso, Cuiabá, Brazil and Dr. David Edmonds, Marfa, Texas, USA) and deposited in the Entomological Collection of the Centro de Ciências Biológicas at the Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina, Brazil. Type specimens were donated to the taxonomic experts for future reference.  A dummy variable was used to represent different sampling years. Thus, we were able to test and remove the temporal effect from environmental and spatial models when testing their effects using variation partitioning techniques (see Variation partitioning section).  We also used combinations of food relocation behavior and body size to create new functional groups. Thus, we created four additional groups: large-sized tunnelers, medium-sized tunnelers, large-sized rollers, and medium-sized rollers. Other groups were represented by only one or two species, and thus were not used in the analyses. Combinations of diet and activity period were not used because we expect that these traits are least important for ecosystem functions provided by these beetles. In addition, the majority of dung beetles were attracted to feces (coprophages and trophic generalists) and these resources are both spatially and temporally unpredictable, so the division into trophic categories seems to be less important with respect to ecological functions.  α = average local diversity, β1 = diversity among sites, β2 = diversity among areas, β3 = diversity among mainland-island. The observed partitions (Obs) are compared with the expected values (Exp) as predicted by the null model based on 999 randomizations. Black star: Exp &lt; Obs, p &lt; 0.05. Black cross: Exp &gt; Obs, p &lt; 0.05.  Diversity partitioning was analyzed for functional groups of food relocation behavior, diet, diel activity, body size, rarity, relocation behavior and size combined. α = average local diversity, β1 = diversity among sites, β2 = diversity among areas, β3 = diversity among mainland-island. The observed partitions (Obs) are compared with the expected values (Exp) as predicted by the null model based on 999 randomizations. Black star: Exp &lt; Obs, p &lt; 0.05. Black cross: Exp &gt; Obs, p &lt; 0.05.  The highest values of all β-components were found among nocturnal, rare and coprophagous dung beetles. Medium-sized tunnelers, medium-sized, tunnelers, generalists, large-sized tunnelers, large-sized, and small-sized dung beetles also showed higher β-components. In general, the β3-component had the largest values followed by β1-component, with the exception of medium-sized dung beetles. The β3-component accounted for on average 24.2% of the diversity of these functional groups, and was higher than expected by chance for most groups. For medium-sized tunnelers, the β3-component accounted for 70% of the diversity variation. On the other hand, for common species and necrophages it accounted for only 7.1%.  Env: pure environmental fraction, Spa: pure spatial fraction, Temp: pure temporal fraction, Sha: shared fraction (all other fractions summed). Right portion after dashed line represents the community deconstruction approach.   1 ALT: altitude; GC: green cover; GTBA: greater tree basal area; GTD: greater tree distance; GTH: greater tree height; GTTD: greater tree top diameter; LL: percentage of leaf litter; LLB: leaf litter biomass; LS: land slope; TD: tree distance; TH: tree height; TTD: tree top diameter.   2 Food relocation behavior: rollers and tunnelers; Diet: coprophages, necrophages and trophic generalists; Diel activity: diurnal, nocturnal and diurnal-nocturnal; Body size: large, medium and small; Rarity: common and rare; Combined functional groups: large tunnelers, medium tunnelers, large rollers and medium rollers.   1 ALT: altitude; GC: green cover; GTBA: greater tree basal area; GTD: greater tree distance; GTH: greater tree height; GTTD: greater tree top diameter; LL: percentage of leaf litter; LLB: leaf litter biomass; LS: land slope; TD: tree distance; TH: tree height; TTD: tree top diameter.   2 Food relocation behavior: rollers and tunnelers; Diet: coprophages, necrophages and trophic generalists; Diel activity: diurnal, nocturnal and diurnal-nocturnal; Body size: large, medium and small; Rarity: common and rare; Combined functional groups: large tunnelers, medium tunnelers, large rollers and medium rollers.   1 ALT: altitude; GC: green cover; GTBA: greater tree basal area; GTD: greater tree distance; GTH: greater tree height; GTTD: greater tree top diameter; LL: percentage of leaf litter; LLB: leaf litter biomass; LS: land slope; TD: tree distance; TH: tree height; TTD: tree top diameter.   2 Food relocation behavior: rollers and tunnelers; Diet: coprophages, necrophages and trophic generalists; Diel activity: diurnal, nocturnal and diurnal-nocturnal; Body size: large, medium and small; Rarity: common and rare; Combined functional groups: large tunnelers, medium tunnelers, large rollers and medium rollers.  Altitude, green cover and greater tree distance were the environmental variables selected to compose the environmental model to explain the variation in abundance data, while altitude, tree height, green cover, tree top distance and greater tree height were selected to explain the variation in biomass data. For functional diversity, the environmental variables selected were altitude, land slope and green cover.  Groups were formed by similar responses.  Env: pure environmental model, Spa: pure spatial model, Tem: pure temporal model, G: group, SG: subgroup.   1 G1: response group more influenced by environmental than spatial processes, and not influenced by temporal processes; SG1 (G1): subgroup where spatial effects were important only at the intermediate scale; SG2 (G1): subgroup where spatial effects were important at the intermediate and regional scales, being spatial effects more important than environmental ones at the intermediate scale; G2: response group also influenced by environmental, spatial and temporal processes; SG1 (G2): subgroup where spatial effects were more important than environmental and temporal ones at the intermediate scale, and environmental effects were more important than other at the regional scale; SG2 (G2): subgroup where spatial effects were more important than environmental and temporal ones at the intermediate and regional scales.  The variables that comprised the environmental models differed among response groups. However, altitude was included as a variable in all models. Greater tree basal area, greater tree distance, greater tree height, green cover, leaf litter biomass, percentage of leaf litter, tree distance, tree height, and tree top diameter were the variables that comprised the environmental models, yet they did not show any pattern among the aforementioned groups.  Based on our community deconstruction approach, we were able to identify two main robust response groups, each with two subgroups according to their responses to explanatory models at each spatial scale. The two main response groups are formed by functional groups that were influenced only by environmental and spatial patterns at intermediate scales (group 1) and by the three sets of explanatory predictors at higher spatial scales (group 2). Group 1 can be divided into functional groups that showed a higher importance of spatial effects at the intermediate scale (subgroup 1), and those that also showed greater importance of environmental than of spatial effects (subgroup 2). Subgroup 1 was composed mainly of roller groups and medium-sized dung beetles (composed of rollers, tunnelers and dwellers). Subgroup 2 was formed by coprophages, trophic generalists and diurnal-nocturnal dung beetles, and by unrelated groups. Group 2 showed greater environmental than temporal effects at the local scale. It also showed a greater spatial, followed by environmental and temporal effects at the intermediate scale. At the mainland-island scale the environmental effects were higher than spatial and temporal ones. Moreover, the subgroups can be identified by their different responses at the regional scale; subgroup 1 showed a higher environmental effect while subgroup 2 showed a higher spatial effect.  In summary, our study increases evidence of the importance of environmental, spatial and temporal factors acting differently at the local, intermediate and regional spatial scales in Scarabaeinae beetle distribution in Neotropical region. It also highlights that the effect of these processes on species abundance in the Atlantic Forest also changes some aspects of the functional organization of dung beetle communities.  Dung beetle species were characterized in terms of four ecological attributes: food relocation behavior, diet, active period and biomass.  (DOCX)  Environmental variables were measured using the adapted point-centered quarter method.  (DOCX)  Samplings were performed in Brazilian Atlantic Forest, Santa Catarina, Brazil using baited pitfall traps from January to February 2012 and 2013.  (XLSX)  Abundances are expressed as the percentage of the total abundance within the metacommunity. The dotted line indicates the inflection point of the curve used to classify the species into common or rare.  (EPS)  (EPS)  (TIF)  Identity and traits for 28 dung beetle species sampled in the Atlantic Forest from southern Brazil. NA: unavailable data. Other: unknown, but different from others.  (XLSX)  Averages (mean or median, as appropriate), quartiles, minimum and maximum values. 25%: 25 percentile, 75%: 75 percentile; max: maximum recorded for the entire dataset.  (XLSX)  ANH: Environmental Protection Area of Anhatomirim in Governador Celso Ramos (mainland); ITA: Permanent Protection Area of Itapema (mainland); PER: Lagoa do Peri Municipal Park, Florianópolis (island); RAT: Permanent Protection Area of Ratones, Florianópolis (island). T: total; GT: grand total.  (XLSX)  We thank all who contributed to this study in any way. We thank Fernando Vaz de Mello and David Edmonds for dung beetle identification, and Jani Heino and anonymous reviewers who helped us to improve this paper. We also thank the Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade (ICMBio/MMA) and Fundação do Meio Ambiente (FATMA-SC) for permission to collect. 