The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: LS CL HY. Performed the experiments: HY CL Z. Liu. Analyzed the data: HY Z. Li BM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LS CL HY CH. Wrote the paper: HY CL LS. Obtained permission for field site use: CL Z. Liu.Annuals are an important component part of plant communities in arid and semiarid grassland ecosystems. Although it is well known that precipitation has a significant impact on productivity and species richness of community or perennials, nevertheless, due to lack of measurements, especially long-term experiment data, there is little information on how quantity and patterns of precipitation affect similar attributes of annuals. This study addresses this knowledge gap by analyzing how quantity and temporal patterns of precipitation affect aboveground biomass, interannual variation aboveground biomass, relative aboveground biomass, and species richness of annuals using a 29-year dataset from a dry steppe site at the Inner Mongolia Grassland Ecosystem Research Station. Results showed that aboveground biomass and relative aboveground biomass of annuals increased with increasing precipitation. The coefficient of variation in aboveground biomass of annuals decreased significantly with increasing annual and growing-season precipitation. Species richness of annuals increased significantly with increasing annual precipitation and growing-season precipitation. Overall, this study highlights the importance of precipitation for aboveground biomass and species richness of annuals.The objective of this study was to determine the influence of precipitation variation on aboveground biomass and species richness of annuals based on a 29-year of dataset from the dry steppe in Inner Mongolia, China. We addressed the following three research questions: 1) How does annual precipitation variation affect aboveground biomass and species richness of annuals? 2) How does aboveground biomass and species richness of annuals respond to seasonal (spring and growing-season) precipitation variation? 3) Does there exist a compensatory effect of annuals on perennials in grassland community?The field site was located on the east side of the test field and measured 50 m × 600 m. It was further subdivided into 10 units (50 m × 60 m). For each unit, 9 equal-sized plots were established from south to north. Twenty quadrats (1 × 1 m<sup>2</sup>) spaced at least 1 m apart were randomly arranged in each plot.The number of individual species was recorded in each quadrat by the same research group. Aboveground biomass was harvested by clipping all biomass at ground level in all quadrats twice a month throughout the growing season (May to September). Biomass samples were oven-dried at 65°C for 48 h and then weighed. Species richness was determined by the total number of species found in each quadrat. Aboveground biomass and species richness data were collected from 1982 to 2012, with the exception of 1995 and 1996. We used annual peak biomass (usually at the end of August) as the aboveground biomass of annuals.AP, Annual precipitation; MAT, Mean annual temperature; GP, Growing-season precipitation; MGT, Mean growing-season temperature; SP, Spring precipitation; MST, Mean spring temperature.(A) Annual precipitation; (B) Growing-season precipitation; (C) Spring precipitation.(A) Annual precipitation; (B) Growing-season precipitation; (C) Spring precipitation.(A) Annual precipitation; (B) Growing-season precipitation; (C) Spring precipitation; (D) May precipitation.(A) Annual precipitation; (B) Growing-season precipitation; (C) Spring precipitation.Abbreviations: PR, perennial rhizome grass; PB, perennial bunch grasses; PF, perennial forbs; SS, shrubs and semi-shrubs; AS, annual plants.Based on long-term (29-year) data, we examined the influence of precipitation on aboveground biomass and species richness of annuals in the dry steppe in Inner Mongolia, China. The relationships between quantity and temporal patterns of precipitation and between aboveground biomass and species richness of annuals were assessed and yielded two key results: (1) aboveground biomass of annuals showed an increasing trend with increasing precipitation (annual, growing-season and spring precipitation), yet the coefficient of variation in aboveground biomass showed an opposite trend, decreasing significantly with increasing annual and growing-season precipitation; (2) relative aboveground biomass of annuals was significantly and positively correlated with precipitation.Our data clearly indicate that the relationships between aboveground biomass, species richness of annuals, and precipitation are more complex than previously suspected. This study highlights the importance of precipitation for aboveground biomass, interannual variation in aboveground biomass, relative aboveground biomass, and species richness of annuals in the arid and semiarid steppe ecosystem of the Inner Mongolia Grassland Ecosystem Research Station. Additionally, we found that spring precipitation had a great impact on annuals and relative aboveground biomass of annuals increased significantly with increased spring precipitation.(XLS)We would like to thank all those who helped with the field work. We thank Ping Wang, Zhanhui Tang, and Wenbo Luo for helpful discussions. Review of the text and suggestions for improvement by Ruthmarie Mitsch are gratefully acknowledged. We are also grateful to the reviewers for their helpful comments.