The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: YW HC BL DY LZ W. Zhou XF W. Zhao LD. Performed the experiments: YW W. Zhou XF W. Zhao. Analyzed the data: YW ML HC LD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DY LZ W. Zhou LD. Wrote the paper: YW ML HC BL LD. Language proofread: ML BL LD.The northeastern forest region of China is an important component of total temperate and boreal forests in the northern hemisphere. But how carbon (C) pool size and distribution varies among tree, understory, forest floor and soil components, and across stand ages remains unclear. To address this knowledge gap, we selected three major temperate and two major boreal forest types in northeastern (NE) China. Within both forest zones, we focused on four stand age classes (young, mid-aged, mature and over-mature). Results showed that total C storage was greater in temperate than in boreal forests, and greater in older than in younger stands. Tree biomass C was the main C component, and its contribution to the total forest C storage increased with increasing stand age. It ranged from 27.7% in young to 62.8% in over-mature stands in boreal forests and from 26.5% in young to 72.8% in over-mature stands in temperate forests. Results from both forest zones thus confirm the large biomass C storage capacity of old-growth forests. Tree biomass C was influenced by forest zone, stand age, and forest type. Soil C contribution to total forest C storage ranged from 62.5% in young to 30.1% in over-mature stands in boreal and from 70.1% in young to 26.0% in over-mature in temperate forests. Thus soil C storage is a major C pool in forests of NE China. On the other hand, understory and forest floor C jointly contained less than 13% and &lt;5%, in boreal and temperate forests respectively, and thus play a minor role in total forest C storage in NE China.The focus of this study therefore was to quantify the partitioning pattern of C storage in different forest components – tree, understory, forest floor and soil – across different aged forests (from young to over-mature) for the major natural temperate and boreal forests in NE China. The overall goal was to better understand C sequestration potential in boreal and temperate forests, and to provide information on carbon balances that might be used to improve forest management practices intended to increase carbon storage.All necessary permits for the described field investigation were obtained at the start of the study from the provincial and locally state-owned forestry bureaus. The study forests refer neither to privately-owned field and biosphere nature reserves, nor to endangered or protected species.MAT = mean annual temperature; MAP = mean annual precipitation.Forest types: LF: larch forest; BF: birch forest; CMF: coniferous mixed forest; BMF: broadleaved mixed forest; CBF: coniferous and broadleaved mixed forest.Statistical analyses were conducted using SPSS 16.0 software. Two-way ANOVA was used to test for effects of forest zone (boreal vs. temperate) and stand age on C storage by total C, tree C, understory C, forest floor C, and soil C. Within each forest zone, effects of forest type and stand age on C storage and its proportion in different components were tested using two-way ANOVA, followed by one-way ANOVA (LF vs. BF) or Tukey’s HSD test, to compare the means across the four stand age classes. Significance levels were set at P&lt;0.05 for all analyses.Note: df1 and df2 are the numerator and denominator degrees of freedom, respectively. Statistical significances were tested using two-way ANOVA based on F-values; a P value of &lt;0.05 indicates significance of differences at the 0.05 level. The two forest zones are boreal zone and temperate zone; the four stand age classes are young, mid-aged, mature, and over-mature.Notes: (1) Forest types in boreal forest zone: larch forest (LF); birch forest (BF); Forest types in temperate forest zone: coniferous mixed forest (CMF); coniferous and broadleaved mixed forest (CBF); broadleaved mixed forest (BMF). (2) Different letters within each cell indicate significant differences among the four age classes.Forest types in boreal forest zone: larch forest (LF); birch forest (BF). Forest types in temperate forest zone: coniferous mixed forest (CMF); broadleaved mixed forest (BMF); coniferous and broadleaved mixed forest (CBF).Boreal forests are composed of larch and birch; temperate forests include coniferous mixed forest, broadleaved mixed forest, coniferous and broadleaved mixed forest.Refers to numerator (df1) and denominator (df2) degrees of freedom, respectively.Statistical significances was tested using two-way ANOVA; a P value of &lt;0.05 indicates significance of difference at the 0.05 level.Stand age classes are young, mid-aged, mature, and over-mature.Forest types in boreal forest zone: larch forest (LF) and birch forest (BF). Forest types in temperate forest zone: coniferous mixed forest (CMF), broadleaved mixed forest (BMF), coniferous and broadleaved mixed forest (CBF). Age classes: young (A), mid-aged (B), mature (C), over-mature (D).Our study represents an early step in understanding the carbon pool size and its distribution varies among different ecosystem components, and across stand ages in the forests of NE China. We found that total forest C storage was greater in the temperate than in the boreal forests, as well as in older than in younger forests. Tree biomass C was the main component of total forest C storage, and its fraction increased with increasing stand age. This supports the great C sequestration potential of old-growth forests as observed by Zhou et al. (2006) and Luyssaert et al. (2008). Tree biomass C was significantly affected by forest zone (temperate vs. boreal), stand age, and forest type, which in turn are associated with climate, biomass accumulation rate, and stand composition and diversity. The large fraction of soil C within the total forest C storage indicated that soil C storage is also an important C pool in the forests of NE China. On the other hand, understory and forest floor C storages jointly contributed to &lt;13% in boreal and &lt;5% in temperate forests play a minor role to total forest C storage in NE China.We would like to thank Qing-jun Wang (Yichun’s Academy of Forestry), and Fei Wang (Inner Mongolia Agricultural University) for their help with fieldwork conducted from July through September of 2011.