The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: JS YL. Performed the experiments: LL YL. Analyzed the data: JC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LL. Wrote the paper: LL JC.The relationship between species richness (SR) and aboveground net primary productivity (ANPP) is still a central and debated issue in community ecology. Previous studies have often emphasized the relationship of alpha diversity (number of species identity) to the mean ANPP with respect to the SR-ANPP relationship while neglecting the contribution of beta diversity (dissimilarity in species composition) to the mean ANPP and to the stability of ANPP (coefficient of ANPP: CV of ANPP). In this study, we used alpha and beta diversity, mean ANPP and the CV of ANPP collected from 159 sites and belonging to three vegetation types in the Xinjiang temperate grassland to first examine their trends along climatic factors and among different vegetation types and then test the relationship among alpha (beta) diversity and mean ANPP and the CV of ANPP. Our results showed that in the Xinjiang temperate grasslands, alpha diversity was positively and linearly correlated with MAP but unimodally correlated with MAT. Meanwhile, beta diversity was unimodally correlated with MAP but linearly correlated with MAT. Relative to desert steppe, meadow steppe and typical steppe had the highest alpha and beta diversity, respectively. Except for ANPP exhibiting a quadratic relationship with MAP, no significant relationship was found among ANPP, the CV of ANPP and climatic factors. ANPP and the CV of ANPP also exhibited no apparent patterns in variation among different vegetation types. Our results further showed that mean ANPP was closely associated with alpha diversity. Both linear and unimodal relationships were detected between alpha diversity and mean ANPP, but their particular form was texture-dependent. Meanwhile, the CV of ANPP was positively correlated with beta diversity. Our results indicated that in addition to incorporating alpha diversity and mean ANPP, incorporating beta diversity and the CV of ANPP could expand our understanding of the SR-ANPP relationship.Here, we used alpha and beta diversity, mean ANPP and the CV of ANPP measured in the Xinjiang temperate grasslands in northwest China, which cover a wide range of climatic gradients and include different vegetation types, to address the following three questions: (1) how does alpha and beta diversity, mean ANPP and the CV of ANPP in the Xinjiang temperate grassland vary along a climatic gradient and among different vegetation types? (2) What is the general relationship between alpha diversity and ANPP and the CV of ANPP in the Xinjiang temperate grasslands? (3) What is the general relationship between beta diversity and ANPP and the CV of ANPP in the Xinjiang temperate grasslands?The green color represented the place where was dominated by grassland.By examining variations in alpha and beta diversity, mean ANPP and the CV of APPP along climatic factors and among different vegetation types, our study showed that in the Xinjiang temperate grasslands, alpha and beta diversity were closely associated with both MAP and MAT and were highest in meadow and typical steppes relative to desert steppe. Except for ANPP exhibiting a quadratic relationship with MAP, no significant relationship was found between ANPP, the CV of ANPP and climatic factors. ANPP and the CV of ANPP also exhibited no apparent patterns in variation among different vegetation types. Based on testing the relationship between species diversity and ANPP, our results further showed that alpha diversity was tightly correlated with mean ANPP, whereas beta diversity was significantly associated with the CV of ANPP. Our results demonstrated that a positive linear and unimodal relationship appeared simultaneously in different vegetation types in the Xinjiang temperate grasslands.We are grateful to students from Xinjiang Agriculture University for their field assistance in surveying community composition. This work was financially supported by the Strategic Priority Research Program of Chinese Academy of Sciences (XDA05050405).