 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: ZCD DLD. Performed the experiments: SSQ ZCD CCS QXZ. Analyzed the data: SSQ ZCD DLZ SCC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RPW. Wrote the paper: SSQ ZCD DLZ SCC PH. Species identification: QXZ.  The pie charts show the mean number of the invasive, native, and alien non-invasive species in a 5 m×5 m plot. Dongfang (DF), Danzhou (DZ), Haikou (HK), Qionghai (QH), Sanya (SY), Tunchang (TC), Wenchang (WC), and Wanning (WN).  (2) Invasives – all invasive plants, Natives - native plants.  The total economic output value included farming, forestry, and animal husbandry in each sampled cities in 2006.  Bold type indicates significant differences at the 0.05 probability level.  Due to the existence of curvilinear effects, introduced non-native species do not present a threat to the local ecological environment in the initial stage. Therefore, insufficient attention is usually paid to these non-native species by concerned governments until the situation is out of control. Thus, prior to the large-scale introduction of exotic horticultural or economic plants, it is necessary to conduct an adequate risk assessment for these introduced plants. Moreover, for introduced exotic species, we recommend that human disturbances should be decreased in local ecosystems, and the eradication of invasive species should be increased to reduce the success of invasion before biodiversity declines.  However, the ecological and the phenological responses of invasive plants to the indicated time-lag effects remain unknown, and further work should be conducted to elucidate the underlying mechanisms of plant invasion. For example, wider ranging surveys involving larger sample numbers should be performed to assess plant invasion, long-term species diversity and the function of community dynamics in permanent plots and for functional comparisons of diversity in invaded communities.  List of plant species in the investigated plots.  (DOC) 