The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: CIA HGF LB. Performed the experiments: CIA AL. Analyzed the data: CIA LB HH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CIA HGF LB. Wrote the paper: CIA HH LB.Deforestation in the tropical Andes is affecting ecological conditions of streams, and determination of how much forest should be retained is a pressing task for conservation, restoration and management strategies. We calculated and analyzed eight benthic metrics (structural, compositional and water quality indices) and a physical-chemical composite index with gradients of vegetation cover to assess the effects of deforestation on macroinvertebrate communities and water quality of 23 streams in southern Ecuadorian Andes. Using a geographical information system (GIS), we quantified vegetation cover at three spatial scales: the entire catchment, the riparian buffer of 30 m width extending the entire stream length, and the local scale defined for a stream reach of 100 m in length and similar buffer width. Macroinvertebrate and water quality metrics had the strongest relationships with vegetation cover at catchment and riparian scales, while vegetation cover did not show any association with the macroinvertebrate metrics at local scale. At catchment scale, the water quality metrics indicate that ecological condition of Andean streams is good when vegetation cover is over 70%. Further, macroinvertebrate community assemblages were more diverse and related in catchments largely covered by native vegetation (&gt;70%). Our results suggest that retaining an important quantity of native vegetation cover within the catchments and a linkage between headwater and riparian forests help to maintain and improve stream biodiversity and water quality in Andean streams affected by deforestation. This research proposes that a strong regulation focused to the management of riparian buffers can be successful when decision making is addressed to conservation/restoration of Andean catchments.In this study, our objective was to investigate the influence of vegetation cover at three spatial scales (local, riparian buffer and catchment) on structure and composition of macroinvertebrate communities and on water quality of headwater streams in the southern Ecuadorian Andes. These streams are located in two contrasting regions of varying intensities of anthropogenic pressure (i.e. deforestation, population growth, and farming). The questions we addressed were: what spatial scale and how much vegetation cover are associated with healthy streams based on macroinvertebrate metrics? In order to address these questions, we calculated several diversity and water quality metrics from macroinvertebrate communities, derived spatial information on land cover from GIS, and related these metrics statistically to three spatial scales and stream parameters. Finally, we addressed management and conservation problems in order to help mitigating impacts of deforestation on stream ecosystems.For this study, the Ministry of Environment of Ecuador issued us a general research permit for every sampling site and to collect water samples and macroinvertebrate specimens. In the case of the Zamora upstream catchment (Zu), the Municipality of Loja granted a specific permission to work at sites Zu1–2, 4–5, 8 because these streams are used for the water supply of the city. To work at the San Francisco catchment (SF), the administration of the San Francisco Research Station and Nature and Culture International allowed us to access sites SF1–7. For all other sites we used the general research permit.Most of macroinvertebrates collected in this study were identified at genus level and we do not know if any of these genera are endangered or protected, because of the lack of information for Ecuador.This ordination analysis detected two groups of macroinvertebrate assemblages: solid circles represent macroinvertebrate communities in catchments with 70–95% in VC and triangles indicate macroinvertebrate communities in catchments with less than 70% in VC. Each symbol represents the community of a single catchment, i.e. macroinvertebrate community at catchment SF3. A Shows the RDA ordination with vector fitting of five variables selected during analysis. DO =  dissolved oxygen, TC =  total coliforms, PO<sub>4</sub> =  phosphate. B Displays in green curves the fitted surface only for the percentage of VC, which is the most explicative variable of the ordination (65%). Dashed lines enclose and separate the detected groups.Overall, macroinvertebrate communities in the 23 study streams present specific patterns. They are composed of a total of 13,512 individuals belonging to 11 orders, 33 families and 53 genera (data available at PANGAEA – Data Publisher for Earth &amp; Environmental Science; doi:10.1594/PANGAEA.831687). Only two taxa (taxa–1 =  Empididae; taxa–2 =  Pyralidae) were not identified to genera level.(DOCX)(DOCX)Special thanks are due to the personnel of the San Francisco Research Station, Nature and Culture International, Municipality of Loja and the Ministry of Environment for the provision of research facilities. Many thanks are due to C. Prieto to provide us additional information on stream parameters and macroinvertebrates of the Zamora catchment; and to L.M. Cun for his support with field sampling and stream measurements. The help of C. Romero, S. Aguilar and M. Villa with water analyses is appreciated. We would like to thank S. Bourret for proof reading, C. Espinosa for his assistance with R functions and routines, and P.F. Quintana–Ascencio and two anonymous reviewers for constructive comments on previous drafts of the manuscript.