The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: MTT JJH JY SAO TB. Performed the experiments: MTT JJH SAO TB. Analyzed the data: MTT JJH JY TB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MTT JJH JY SN SAO TB. Wrote the paper: MTT JJH JY SN SAO TB.Several marine ecosystems under anthropogenic pressure have experienced shifts from one ecological state to another. In the central Baltic Sea, the regime shift of the 1980s has been associated with food-web reorganization and redirection of energy flow pathways. These long-term dynamics from 1974 to 2006 have been simulated here using a food-web model forced by climate and fishing. Ecological network analysis was performed to calculate indices of ecosystem change. The model replicated the regime shift. The analyses of indicators suggested that the system’s resilience was higher prior to 1988 and lower thereafter. The ecosystem topology also changed from a web-like structure to a linearized food-web.Detritus pool is divided into two groups: detritus on the sediment (detritus (s)) and water column detritus (detritus (w)).The time series were transformed into quintiles and sorted according to the PC1 axis scores: (A) model forcing; (B) modeled biomass.This study demonstrated that i) the regime shift in the Baltic Sea in the late 1980s is well reflected by the ENA indices, and ii) two different ecosystem regimes can be distinguished. The first regime between 1974 and 1988 reflected a more mature and balanced ecosystem, with more diverse flow structure, higher resilience, characterised also by high primary production, and high fishing pressure at relatively high trophic levels. The second regime, between 1994 and 2006, was characterised as a more stressed, less resilient regime with high primary production and high fishing pressure on lower TL species, indicating a more productive and linearized food-web. We hypothesise that the regime shift was caused by the interplay of multiple drivers: climate, eutrophication and fishing.Our study revealed that the cumulative nature of anthropogenic stressors, such as fishing and eutrophication, needs to be analysed in combination with large scale environmental drivers (climate), ecosystem characteristics and emergent properties. This encapsulates the holistic approach needed for ecosystem based management. This is the first study where an abrupt regime shift was demonstrated by using an index of resilience calculated from the ecological network analysis using an Ecopath with Ecosim model that described the system as a whole.(DOCX)We would like to thank Dr. Karen Alexander from SAMS in Oban and two anonymous reviewers for useful comments and language corrections and Erik Smedberg from Baltic Nest Institute for graphical support.