The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: KCH SHB PW DPE CVK. Performed the experiments: PW RJN DPE. Analyzed the data: PW DPE KCH. Wrote the paper: PW DPE KCH.All necessary permits were obtained for the described field studies. Approval and permits were provided by Yayasan Sabah, the Danum Valley Management Committee, Sabah Chief Minister’s Department, the Economic Planning Unit of the Prime Minister’s Department and the Sabah Forestry Department.Differences between unlogged and logged forest in the trophic organisation of the assemblage were investigated by using Kolmogorov-Smirnov tests to compare the frequency distribution of trophic positions of colonies in each type of forest. We first examined the location and shape of the distributions, and then focused only on the shape by centring each distribution around a mean of zero. Changes in the location of the distribution would indicate a systematic increase or decrease in trophic positions of the assemblage, whilst changes in the shape of the distribution would indicate that colonies become more or less concentrated within the food web. This approach compares differences in trophic structure without considering species identity. It is thus focused on summarising how each colony contributes to the overall trophic structure of the assemblage. Lastly, we used a LME to compare food chain lengths – defined from the 5% of colonies with the highest trophic positions in each type of forest – between unlogged and logged forest. As with previous analyses, each sample was used as a separate measure of trophic position, and ‘subfamily’ and ‘species’ were treated as nested random effects.Trophic positions of (a) colonies and (b) species in unlogged and logged forest are grouped into trophic categories of 0.5 trophic levels (&lt;2.25, 2.25–2.75, 3.25–3.75 etc.). Bubble sizes represent the proportion of colonies or species in each trophic category for each type of forest (i.e. expressed as a percentage of the total number of colonies [a] or species richness [b] for each forest type).Mean trophic positions±S.E. are shown for species found in both unlogged (UL) and logged (L) forest, for species found only in logged forest, and for species found only in logged forest. Means are based on all samples and presented for all species, and for the two commonest ant subfamilies (Myrmicinae and Ponerinae).The higher trophic positions of species in logged forest translated into shifts in overall trophic organisation, with a significant difference between forest types in the frequency distribution of the trophic positions of colonies (z = 1.86, p = 0.002). When distributions were centred around zero, trophic organisation was marginally significantly different between forest types (z = 1.29, p = 0.071). We also found a significant increase in mean food chain length in logged forest based on the trophic positions of the top 5% of colonies (mean <sub>unlogged forest</sub> = 3.89±0.04, n = 42 colonies; mean <sub>logged forest</sub> = 4.10±0.04, n = 29 colonies; LME F <sub>1, 29</sub> = 10.3, p = 0.0032). This finding was repeatable using the top 10% of colonies (mean <sub>unlogged forest</sub> = 3.73±0.03, n = 84 colonies; mean <sub>logged forest</sub> = 3.93±0.03, n = 58 colonies; LME: F<sub> 1, 91</sub> = 22.6, p&lt;0.001).Map of study sites.(DOCX)Abundance distributions for ant colonies and ant species in unlogged and logged forest.(DOCX)Mean trophic positions for ant species in unlogged and logged forest.(DOCX)We thank staff at the Danum Valley Field Centre, especially Adam, Dedy Mustapha and Anthony Karolus for fieldwork assistance, and Glen Reynolds and Apech Karolus for logistical support and advice. Tom Fayle, Noel Tawatao and Sukarman Sukimin helped with the identification of ants, and Elly van der Linde assisted with sample preparation and isotope analysis. We also thank Owen Lewis, Mahesh Sankaran and two anonymous reviewers for helpful and constructive comments. We are grateful to Yayasan Sabah, the Danum Valley Management Committee, the State Secretary, Sabah Chief Minister’s Department, the Prime Minister’s Department (EPU) and the Sabah Forestry Department for permission to conduct research. This study is part of the Royal Society’s Southeast Asia Rainforest Research Programme (Project No. RS266).