The authors have declared that no competing interest exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: FR BG. Performed the experiments: FR BG FG VDS. Analyzed the data: FR BG FG VDS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JJM. Wrote the paper: FR BG FG VDS JJM.Each rectangle corresponds to 1 m<sup>2</sup> plot. Numbers refers to the detrital enrichment. (0: no addition; 200∶200 g WW were added twice at a 1 week interval; 600∶600 g WW were added twice with a 1 week interval). Distance among plots are not in scale.Flux rates of TCO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> between the sediment and the overlying water were estimated as difference between the initial and the final TCO<sub>2</sub> or O<sub>2</sub> concentrations during dark incubation, assuming constant solute exchange with time. The oxygen dissolved into the water samples was analyzed using the standard method of Winkler titration, while water TCO<sub>2</sub> and porewater DIC were determined by the flow injection/diffusion cell technique, which is based on the diffusion of CO<sub>2</sub> through a hydrophobic membrane into a flow of deionized water, thus generating a gradient of conductivity proportional to the concentration of CO<sub>2</sub>.A− represent the sediment after 1 month from the burial of net to exclude burrowing species. A+ is the procedural control treatment (see Materials and Methods for details).Data were sampled one month after detrital addition. Asterisk indicates significant differences.Symbols indicate mean (± SE) for macroalgal biomass and are relative to experiments 2.Significant values (P&lt;0.05) are in bold. Sphericity test was not significant.These findings clearly demonstrate that under natural conditions, the local extinction of an ecosystem engineer may have complex effects on the ecological stability of marine sediment biogeochemistry and benthic communities of consumers. They also highlight the importance of performing experiments under natural conditions if we are to understand and predict the response of ecosystems to perturbation and species loss.The authors wish to thank the technicians for their invaluable help in the chemical analyses and E. Weerman, JJ Jansen and F Montserrat and numerous other students for their help in the field. S. Thrush is kindly thanked for his critical revision of an early version of this MS. This study is part of the BIOFUSE project, within the MARBEF network of excellence.