 The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Conceived and designed the experiments: CS WSH KNS. Performed the experiments: CS. Analyzed the data: CS LMH. Wrote the paper: CS LMH. Commented on manuscript: WSH KNS.  The concept of ecosystem services – the benefits that nature provides to human's society – has gained increasing attention over the past decade. Increasing global abiotic and biotic change, including species invasions, is threatening the secure delivery of these ecosystem services. Efficient evaluation methods of ecosystem services are urgently needed to improve our ability to determine management strategies and restoration goals in face of these new emerging ecosystems. Considering a range of multiple ecosystem functions may be a useful way to determine such strategies. We tested this framework experimentally in California grasslands, where large shifts in species composition have occurred since the late 1700's. We compared a suite of ecosystem functions within one historic native and two non-native species assemblages under different grazing intensities to address how different species assemblages vary in provisioning, regulatory and supporting ecosystem services. Forage production was reduced in one non-native assemblage (medusahead). Cultural ecosystem services, such as native species diversity, were inherently lower in both non-native assemblages, whereas most other services were maintained across grazing intensities. All systems provided similar ecosystem services under the highest grazing intensity treatment, which simulated unsustainable grazing intensity. We suggest that applying a more comprehensive ecosystem framework that considers multiple ecosystem services to evaluate new emerging ecosystems is a valuable tool to determine management goals and how to intervene in a changing ecosystem.  No permits were required for the described study, which complied with all relevant regulations. Endangered or protected species were not involved in this study.  To assess changes in species abundances we identified all vascular plant species within a permanently marked 1 m 2  subplot and visually estimated the percent cover of each species at peak standing biomass. Species abundance data were taken in mid May 2008, 2009 and 2010.  All measurements were taken in 2010.   weighting factor to take into account that non-palatable species provide some low quality forage during their early development stages which we estimated to be approx. 30% of their total biomass.  * as number of initially planted species varied among the grassland types, we did not use species richness as a diversity index.  We used two measures of soil carbon sequestration: fine root production and potential soil respiration rates. We measured fine root production using the root ingrowth technique. In December 2009, we filled fiberglass mesh bags (mesh size 1.5 mm, 4 cm diameter, 20 cm height) with root-free sieved soil and vertically buried them 20 cm deep in the rooting zone for 15 weeks. We homogenized the soil in each core and picked roots from the soil cores by hand over a standardized time period. Subsequently, we cleaned the roots of residual soil and detritus, dried them at 60°C to constant mass and weighed them. In February 2010, we measured potential soil respiration rates from freshly collected soil samples (we pooled three subsamples per grazing × species assemblage plot, each 2 cm diameter, 10 cm depth). We placed 2 g of air dried root-free soil into glass vials and added DI water to reach 25% soil moisture. We incubated two replicates from the pooled subsamples for each of the treatment plots and allowed each to reach ambient temperature of approximately 20°C; we opened the vials just prior to the incubation so that headspaces would equilibrate with ambient air. Then we sealed the vials, maintained them in the laboratory at 20°C, and collected 10 mL of headspace after two hours. We immediately injected each gas sample into an EGM-4 Infrared Gas Analyzer.  To characterize nutrient retention, we measured potential decomposition rates and nitrogen availability. We measured potential decomposition rates via litterbags (nylon screen, 2 mm mesh size, 10 cm×17 cm) filled with three pieces of filterpaper (Whatman No. 1, 11 mm diameter) that we placed directly on the soil surface on Dec.13 th , 2009 and removed on March 30th, 2010. We cleaned the filterpaper of residual soil and detritus, dried it at 60°C to constant mass and weighed it. We quantified soil nitrogen availability using three ion exchange resin bags (Sigma Aldrich Dowex Marathon MR-3 hydrogen and hydroxide form 13687-U mixed beads wrapped in Nylon/Lycra swimsuit liner material) placed in the center of each plot at a depth of 10 cm. We placed the resin bags in the ground from December 16 th , 2009 to March, 23 rd , 2010 and extracted them with 2 mol/L KCL. We measured inorganic-N availability (ammonium and nitrate) with a SmartChem autoanalyzer.  The (a) three original planted species assemblages are clearly distinguishable based on their species composition as shown by (b) results of CCA of species abundances from 2008–2010 with year and study site as covariate. (c) Residual dry matter measured in 2010 to describe grazing gradient within the three ecosystem types. Letter above bars indicate significant differences among grazing levels as determined by planned orthogonal contrasts at P&lt;0.01.  (TIF)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  (DOCX)  We thank the staff at the University of California Sierra Foothill Research and Extension Center, and William Schlegel, Michelle Chang, Charlotte Riggs, and Hui Gao for their invaluable support. We also thank two anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments. 