 Conceived and designed the experiments: AESG JPW CR. Performed the experiments: BMM JPW. Analyzed the data: AESG JPW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AESG JPW CR. Wrote the paper: AESG CR.  The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.  Global biodiversity loss has prompted research on the relationship between species diversity and ecosystem functioning. Few studies have examined how plant diversity impacts belowground processes; even fewer have examined how varying resource levels can influence the effect of plant diversity on microbial activity. In a field experiment in a restored wetland, we examined the role of plant trait diversity (or functional diversity, (FD)) and its interactions with natural levels of variability of soil properties, on a microbial process, denitrification potential (DNP). We demonstrated that FD significantly affected microbial DNP through its interactions with soil conditions; increasing FD led to increased DNP but mainly at higher levels of soil resources. Our results suggest that the effect of species diversity on ecosystem functioning may depend on environmental factors such as resource availability. Future biodiversity experiments should examine how natural levels of environmental variability impact the importance of biodiversity to ecosystem functioning.  DNP is an ecosystem function that plants influence indirectly by modifying the soil environment. We hypothesized three categories of traits by which plant traits could impact DNP: (1) Carbon Quantity, (2) Carbon Quality, and (3) Redox (potential). We hypothesized that DNP will be promoted if the plant community trait values either increase (AGB, BGB, and POR) or decrease (AGCN and BGCN) such that C quantity, quality, and soil oxygen increase.  This study had two primary objectives. The first was to determine the relationship between plant trait diversity and a microbial process, denitrification potential. The second was to explicitly examine the nature of the interactions between plant trait diversity and environmental conditions making use of the range of soil resources present at our field site.  * =  measured in the field plots; otherwise measured in the greenhouse;   =  n is variable depending on how many monocultures we had of the species (2, 3, or 4);  AGB  =  aboveground biomass, BGB  =  belowground biomass, BGCN  =  belowground C:N ratio (unitless), AGCN  =  aboveground C:N ratio (unitless), POR  =  root porosity (%).  Soil samples were collected all at the same time in September 2007, the third growing season of the experiment. Samples were collected from all plots with healthy vegetation (95 of the original 100). Two soil samples (2.5 cm diameter) from each plot were collected from the upper 15 cm of each plot.  The lines are the lowess (locally-weighted scatterplot smoothing using least-squares) curves that follow the trends in the data.  The lines are lowess (locally-weighted scatterplot smoothing) curves that follow the trends in the data.  *P&lt;0.05,  **P&lt;0.01,  ***P&lt;0.001,  n.s.  = P&gt;0.05.  We thank O. Petchey for help using his R code for calculating FD and S. Qian for statistical advice. We also thank the following people for helping the field and lab: E. Thorsos, S. Wang, S. Arora, S. Diehl, J. Unghire, and K. Vaughn. We also thank the many people who helped us establish the field experiment: M. Ho, J. Pahl, M. Osland, J. Morse, J. DeMeester, A. McHugh, A. Mendoza, J. Sexton, E. Thorsos, D. Jung, and N. Morgans. 