The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.Conceived and designed the experiments: EH CC DW MEM. Performed the experiments: EH CC DW. Analyzed the data: EH CC DW MEM. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: DW CC. Wrote the paper: EE CC DW MEM.Nitrogen (N) is considered the dominant limiting nutrient in temperate regions, while phosphorus (P) limitation frequently occurs in tropical regions, but in subtropical regions nutrient limitation is poorly understood. In this study, we investigated N and P contents and N:P ratios of foliage, forest floors, fine roots and mineral soils, and their relationships with community biomass, litterfall C, N and P productions, forest floor turnover rate, and microbial processes in eight mature and old-growth subtropical forests (stand age &gt;80 yr) at Dinghushan Biosphere Reserve, China. Average N:P ratios (mass based) in foliage, litter (L) layer and mixture of fermentation and humus (F/H) layer, and fine roots were 28.3, 42.3, 32.0 and 32.7, respectively. These values are higher than the critical N:P ratios for P limitation proposed (16–20 for foliage, ca. 25 for forest floors). The markedly high N:P ratios were mainly attributed to the high N concentrations of these plant materials. Community biomass, litterfall C, N and P productions, forest floor turnover rate and microbial properties were more strongly related to measures of P than N and frequently negatively related to the N:P ratios, suggesting a significant role of P availability in determining ecosystem production and productivity and nutrient cycling at all the study sites except for one prescribed disturbed site where N availability may also be important. We propose that N enrichment is probably a significant driver of the potential P limitation in the study area. Low P parent material may also contribute to the potential P limitation. In general, our results provided strong evidence supporting a significant role for P availability, rather than N availability, in determining ecosystem primary productivity and ecosystem processes in subtropical forests of China.At each location, four subplots (20×20 m<sup>2</sup>) were randomly set up with a distance of at least 10 m between them. In each subplot, 3 small sampling areas (20×20 cm<sup>2</sup>) were randomly located with the constraints that they were 1–2 m away from the nearest tree (diameter at breast height ≥5 cm) and at least 5 m from its nearest neighbor. All fine forest floor materials within the sampling area were collected, including leaf litter, and senesced branches, bark, flowers and fruits with diameters ≤1 cm. Forest floor materials were carefully separated into two layers (L layer, litter layer; F/H layer, mixture of fermentation layer and humus layer) in the field. After forest floor materials were sampled, a soil profile was excavated at the same area. Mineral soil from the 0–15 cm depth was sampled by 3 successive cutting rings (Height 5 cm, Volume 100 cm<sup>3</sup>) from top to bottom (each 5 cm depth by one cutting ring). By using a cutting ring to sample soil, we also measured the bulk density at the same time of soil sampling. The three forest floor samples from the same layer in each subplot were bulked together as one composite sample (one composite L layer sample and one composite F/H layer sampler per subplot). Nine soils (3 cutting rings per area×3 areas) of each subplot were bulked together as one mineral soil sample. Both forest floor and soil samples were stored at 4°C in the refrigerator within 4 h after sampling.Leaves were directly oven-dried at 65°C for 72 h prior to grinding for determination of total N and P concentrations. For forest floor materials, the fresh weight (w1, unit: g) was recorded and then the sample was mixed well. A subsample was oven-dried at 65°C for 72 h for the determination of dry weight transfer coefficient (t, proportion of dry weight over the fresh weight). The forest floor biomass was calculated by the equation followed:L layer (or F/H layer) forest floor biomass (g/cm<sup>2</sup>) = (w1×t)/(400 cm<sup>2</sup>×3).The unit was converted later to Mg/ha and shown in the results. After t was determined, the oven-dried sample was ground for the determination of total N and P concentrations. Another subsample was taken and cut into 2–4 mm pieces and stored at 4°C prior to the determination of microbial biomass C concentration, respiration and β-glucosidase activity.For soil samples, fresh weight (W1, unit: g) was recorded and the sample was mixed well. Stones with diameter &gt;4 mm were picked out during the sieving (4 mm mesh) and weighed (W2, unit: g). A subsample of the sieved soil was air-dried for 2 weeks prior to grinding and determination of soil nutrient concentration. A subsample was used for the soil dry weight transfer coefficient (T; proportion of dry weight after over-dried in fresh weight) determination by oven-dried at 105°C for 72h. The bulk density was calculated by equations followed:Bulk density (g/cm<sup>3</sup>) = W2+ (W1–W2)×T/(100 cm<sup>3</sup>×9).The remaining soil was weighed and stored at 4°C for the determination of microbial properties (data not shown here) and fine roots (diameter ≤2 mm) collection. Fine roots retained on a 0.6 mm screen were collected and dried at 65°C for 72 h and then weighed for the fine root biomass calculation (data not shown here). Fine roots were finely ground for measurements of total N and P concentrations.Forest floor turnover rate (yr<sup>−1</sup>) = litterfall C production/forest floor biomass C.Forest floor biomass C was the sum of L layer and F/H layer biomass C.Since the data are mostly (near-) normal distributed, Pearson correlation analysis and Pearson linear regression technique were used throughout the manuscript. All N:P ratios shown in this study were calculated on a mass basis. All analyses were performed using SPSS version 16.0. Pearson correlation was used to investigate the correlations between N and P concentration and N:P ratio for all plant and soil samples, and was also used to investigate the correlations between nutrient measures of the plant samples and those of the soil samples. Pearson linear regression technique was used to examine the relationships between community biomass, litterfall C, N and P productions, forest floor turnover rate and forest floor microbial properties with nutrient measures of the soil or the forest floors.For soil total fraction, inclusion and exclusion of the pine forest (PF) site showed distinct results and thus, correlations for all data and data excluding PF were both shown.Data in the brackets are SE; n = 96 for foliage, = 32 for L and F/H layers and fine roots.Our study has revealed consistently stronger relationships between measures of P availability and community biomass, litterfall C, N and P productions, forest floor turnover rates and litter chemistry than we found for measures of N availability, indicating a significant role of P in determining ecosystem primary productivity and processes at the study sites. Vegetation N:P ratios indicated strong P limitation at all sites in this study. The results also showed that different ecosystem compartments or processes may differ in the extent of the nutrient limitation at different sites that depend on the soil nutrient status and land use history of these sites. In general, these results suggested constraint of ecosystem development by soil P availability at the study sites. We proposed that markedly N enrichment was probably a significant driver of the strong P limitation at these study sites. Low P parent material may also partly contribute to the P limitation. Further study is warranted on the mitigation of P limitation of ecosystem productivity and processes in the tropical and subtropical China.Correlations between N and P concentrations and N:P ratio of the foliage samples.(TIF)Correlations between total N and total P concentrations and total N:P ratio of the 0–15 cm mineral soil.(TIF)Characteristics of eight study forest sites at Dinghushan Biosphere Reserve, China.(DOC)Litterfall C production, forest floors biomass C, and forest floor turnover rate of eight study forests.(DOC)Site averages of N and P concentrations and N:P ratio of foliage, L and F/H layers and fine roots of eight study forests.(DOC)Species averages of foliar N and P concentrations and mass-based N:P ratio of 13 tree species selected from eight study forests.(DOC)The authors thank Marijke Heenan, Xuejin Wang, and Yujin Zhang for assistance in field samples collection and some laboratory analyses.