Estimation and Analysis of Irrigation in Single-Family Homes in Central FloridaAbstractThere are several studies that have estimated how much water is used for residential irrigation, principally at the national level, with outputs varying from 30 to 64% of total household potable water use. A methodology to estimate irrigation from potable use data in central Florida is presented in this paper. Monthly potable water billing records of single-family homes for the City of Tampa Water Department (TWD) and Orange County Utilities (OCU), Florida, were available from 2003 to 2007. Basic indoor water use at the household scale was estimated using two methods: the minimum month method and the per capita method. A range of impervious surfaces values (5, 15, and 20% from total green area) was considered to estimate the irrigable area. Irrigation was estimated on a monthly basis as the difference of total water use minus the estimated indoor water use, divided by the irrigable area. The estimated irrigation values were compared to a monthly theoretical irrigation requirement calculated by a daily soil water balance. The average total potable water use was 29.2 and 53.3  m3/month in TWD and OCU, respectively. The basic indoor water use ranged from 15.7 to 35.9  m3/month in TWD and OCU, respectively, based on the minimum month method, and from 16.9 to 18.3  m3/month when the per capita method was used. Some inaccuracy in the minimum month method was detected, at least for OCU, and the per capita method would be better for estimating indoor water use. Our results showed that 57–62% and 45–64%% of homeowners overirrigated in OCU, with an estimated irrigation amount of 104–62 mm/month when the per capita method and the minimum month method were used, respectively. In TWD, 31–36 to 22–27% of homeowners overirrigated when the per capita method and the minimum month method were used, with averages of 54 and 31  mm/month, respectively. The minimum month method showed the lowest estimated values on irrigation compared to the per capita method. Further work is needed to determine which indoor use method is most accurate.