Elevated CO2 reduces disease incidence and severity of a red maple fungal pathogen via changes in host physiology and leaf chemistry.Atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations are predicted to double within the next century. Despite this trend, the extent and mechanisms through which elevated CO<sub>2</sub> affects plant diseases remain uncertain. In this study, we assessed how elevated CO<sub>2</sub> affects a foliar fungal pathogen, <em>Phyllosticta minima</em>, of <em>Acer rubrum</em> growing in the understory at the Duke Forest free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment experiment in Durham, North Carolina. Surveys of <em>A. rubrum</em> saplings in the 6th, 7th, and 8th years of the CO<sub>2</sub> exposure revealed that elevated CO<sub>2</sub> significantly reduced disease incidence, with 22%, 27%, and 8% fewer saplings and 14%, 4%, and 5% fewer leaves infected per plant in the three consecutive years, respectively. Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> also significantly reduced disease severity in infected plants in all years (e.g. mean lesion area reduced 35%, 50%, and 10% in 2002, 2003, and 2004, respectively). To assess the mechanisms underlying these changes, we combined leaf structural, physiological and chemical analyses with growth chamber studies of <em>P. minima</em> growth and host infection. <em>In vitro</em> exponential growth rates of <em>P. minima</em> were enhanced by 17% under elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, discounting the possibility that disease reductions were because of direct negative effects of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> on fungal performance. Scanning electron micrographs (SEM) verified that conidia germ tubes of <em>P. minima</em> infect <em>A. rubrum</em> leaves by entering through the stomata. While stomatal size and density were unchanged, stomatal conductance was reduced by 21-36% under elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, providing smaller openings for infecting germ tubes. Reduced disease severity under elevated CO<sub>2</sub> was likely due to altered leaf chemistry and reduced nutritive quality; elevated CO<sub>2</sub> reduced leaf N by 20% and increased the C : N ratio by 20%, total phenolics by 15%, and tannins by 14% (<em>P</em><0.05 for each factor). The potential dual mechanism we describe here of reduced stomatal opening and altered leaf chemistry that results in reduced disease incidence and severity under elevated CO<sub>2</sub> may be prevalent in many plant pathosystems where the pathogen targets the stomata.