Annual growth rings of the shrub Anarthrophyllum rigidum across Patagonia: Interannual variations and relationships with climate.Annual growth rings are well-defined in some shrubby species distributed along the Patagonian steppe and provide useful information to identify the environmental factors that influence the radial growth of shrubs in the region. However, little is known about variations in ring width from these species and their relationships with local environment. In this paper we present 18 growth ring width chronologies covering the last 2-3 decades from the shrub Anarthrophyllum rigidum (Fabaceae) encompassing most of its natural range of distribution in Argentina. Interannual variations in growth were first analyzed collectively to identify common regional patterns. In addition, shrub growth at each site was compared with local climate records and site-specific characteristics. Based on a principal component analysis (PCA), sites were joined in four major groups related to the site proximity to the Andes (foothills versus Patagonian plateau) and latitude (north versus south Patagonia). The relatively similar percentage of PCA variance associated with each group reflects environmental differences among sites. Consistent with this observation, we noted large variability in the responses of the A. rigidum woody growth to regional climatic fluctuations. At most sites, this species is favored by abundant winter precipitation, warmer spring and autumn temperatures (controlling the duration of the growing season), cool summers, or a combination of these factors. However, deviations from these patterns are also recorded. Our study represents the first large-scale dendroclimatological analysis of a shrubby species in southern South America. The results presented here provide information on the main patterns and factors affecting the growth of A. rigidum in Patagonia, and may be useful for determining well-suited practices for management and conservation of this ubiquitous species.