The role of wood density and stem support costs in the growth and mortality of tropical trees.<ol><li>The rapid growth rates of light-demanding tree species have been attributed in part to their low-density, low-cost stems. We evaluated the influence of light and biomass support costs on growth rates of trees 8-25 cm in diameter at breast height (d.b.h.) among 21 species differing in wood density in two aseasonal rain forests.</li><li>Measurements of crown width, tree height, d.b.h. and wood density (Ï) were used to estimate the stem biomass (<em>M</em><sub>s</sub>) of a standard-sized tree (17 m tall and 16 m<sup>2</sup> in crown area), i.e. the cost in stem biomass of supporting a given sized crown at a given height.</li><li>The species showed a three-fold range in support cost, which was highly correlated with wood density (<em>M</em><sub>s</sub> âˆ Ï<sup>0.77</sup>, <em>r</em><sup>2</sup> = 0.72 for the log-transformed relationship). This relationship is due to the high interspecific variation in wood density and the fact that the stem diameter of the standard-sized tree increased only slightly with decreasing wood density, i.e. light-wooded species did not compensate for their lighter, weaker wood by substantially increasing stem thickness.</li><li>Mean growth rate per species showed a 10-fold range and increased with the fraction of trees at least partly in gaps (gap fraction), the reciprocal of support cost (1/<em>M</em><sub>s</sub>), and the reciprocal of wood density (1/Ï). The relationship between mean growth rate and 1/<em>M</em><sub>s</sub> was particularly strong when one outlier was excluded (<em>r</em><sup>2</sup> = 0.88) and among the Dipterocarpaceae (<em>r</em><sup>2</sup> = 0.89).</li><li>Log(mortality rate), as determined for all trees per species â‰¥ 1 cm d.b.h., increased linearly with 1/<em>M</em><sub>s</sub>, 1/Ï and gap fraction.</li><li>These results suggest an important role for wood density and support costs in the classic tradeoff between rapid growth and increased risks of damage and death.</li></ol>