Net ecosystem carbon dioxide exchange over grazed steppe in central Mongolia.This paper presents results of 1 year (from March 25, 2003 to March 24, 2004, 366 days) of continuous measurements of net ecosystem CO<sub>2</sub> exchange (NEE) above a steppe in Mongolia using the eddy covariance technique. The steppe, typical of central Mongolia, is dominated by C<sub>3</sub> plants adapted to the continental climate. The following two questions are addressed: (1) how do NEE and its components: gross ecosystem production (GEP) and total ecosystem respiration (<em>R</em><sub>eco</sub>) vary seasonally? (2) how do NEE, GEP, and <em>R</em><sub>eco</sub> respond to biotic and abiotic factors? The hourly minimal NEE and the hourly maximal <em>R</em><sub>eco</sub> were -;3.6 and 1.2 &mu;mol m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>, respectively (negative values denoting net carbon uptake by the canopy from the atmosphere). Peak daily sums of NEE, GEP, and <em>R</em><sub>eco</sub> were -;2.3, 3.5, and 1.5 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> day<sup>-;1</sup>, respectively. The annual sums of GEP, <em>R</em><sub>eco</sub>, and NEE were 179, 138, and -;41 g C m<sup>-;2</sup>, respectively. The carbon removal by sheep was estimated to range between 10 and 82 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup> using four different approaches. Including these estimates in the overall carbon budget yielded net ecosystem productivity of -;23 to +20 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>. Thus, within the remaining experimental uncertainty the carbon budget at this steppe site can be considered to be balanced. For the growing period (from April 23 to October 21, 2003), 26% and 53% of the variation in daily NEE and GEP, respectively, could be explained by the changes in leaf area index. Seasonality of GEP, <em>R</em><sub>eco</sub>, and NEE was closely associated with precipitation, especially in the peak growing season when GEP and <em>R</em><sub>eco</sub> were largest. Water stress was observed in late July to early August, which switched the steppe from a carbon sink to a carbon source. For the entire growing period, the light response curves of daytime NEE showed a rather low apparent quantum yield (<em>&alpha;</em>=-;0.0047 &mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> &mu;mol<sup>-;1</sup> photons of photosynthetically active radiation). However, the <em>&alpha;</em> values varied with air temperature (<em>T</em><sub>a</sub>), vapor pressure deficit, and soil water content.