Performance of different spectral and textural aerial photograph features in multi-source forest inventoryMost multi-source forest inventory (MSFI) applications have thus far been based on the use of medium resolution satellite imagery, such as Landsat TM. The high plot and stand level estimation errors of these applications have, however, restricted their use in forest management planning. One reason suggested for the high estimation errors has been the coarse spatial resolution of the imagery employed. Therefore, very high spatial resolution (VHR) imagery sources provide interesting data for stand-level inventory applications. However, digital interpretation of VHR imagery, such as aerial photographs, is more complicated than the use of traditional satellite imagery. Pixel-by-pixel analysis is not applicable to VHR imagery because a single pixel is small in relation to the object of interest, i.e. a forest stand, and therefore it does not adequately represent the spectral properties of a stand. Additionally in aerial photographs, the spectral properties of the objects are dependent on their location in the image. Therefore, MSFI applications based on aerial imagery must employ features that are less sensitive to their location in the image and that have been derived using the spatial neighborhood of each pixel, e.g. a square-shaped window of pixels. In this experiment several spectral and textural features were extracted from color-infrared aerial photographs and employed in estimation of forest attributes. The features were extracted from original, normalized difference vegetation index and channel ratio images. The correlations between the extracted image features and forest attributes measured from sample plots were examined. Additionally, the spectral and textural features were used for estimating the forest attributes of sample plots, applying the k nearest neighbor estimation method. The results show that several spectral and textural image features that are moderately or well correlated with the forest attributes. Furthermore, the accuracy of forest attribute estimation can be significantly improved by a careful selection of image features.