A monocarpic tree species in a polycarpic world: how can Tachigali vasquezii maintain itself so successfully in a tropical rain forest community?.<ol><li>Although monocarpy is rare among long-lived plant species that grow in stable habitats, one monocarpic species, <em>Tachigali vasquezii</em>, is extremely abundant in the rain forests of the Bolivian Amazon. We analyse how <em>T. vasquezii</em> is able to maintain itself successfully by comparing its life-history traits with those of polycarpic tree species of the same community. We then evaluate the relative importance of such traits using population matrix models.</li><li>Monocarpic species are expected to have a high fecundity. Seed production per basal area for <em>T. vasquezii</em> is indeed nearly twice that of an average polycarpic species, but this is not sufficient to maintain stable populations.</li><li>Life-history theory predicts that a monocarpic strategy is advantageous if juvenile survival rates are high compared with adult survival. Although seedlings of <em>T. vasquezii</em> have a lower mortality rate than polycarpic species, its sapling have higher mortality.</li><li>We found that the success of <em>T. vasquezii</em> is due to its very high diameter growth rates in the larger size classes, which are four times higher than that of an average, co-occurring polycarpic species. Fast diameter growth is enabled by investment in large, leafy crowns and by a low wood density. Applying this high diameter growth in a population model yielded a population growth rate close to that of polycarpic species. Life table response experiment analysis of <em>Tachigali</em> and polycarp models showed that higher growth compensated for the negative demographic effect of 100% adult mortality following reproduction.</li><li>Rapid growth enables <em>T. vasquezii</em> to reach reproductive maturity in only 49 years, compared with 79 years for an average polycarpic species. It also reduces the risk of dying before reproducing, and 50% more seedlings survive to maturity for <em>T. vasquezii</em> compared with polycarpic species.</li><li>The dramatic negative demographic consequences of one-time flowering can therefore be completely balanced by taking a shorter time to reach maturity. Taking a time perspective, it appears that <em>Tachigali vasquezii</em> has an advanced, rather than a delayed, reproduction.</li></ol>