Soil restoration in semiarid Patagonia: Chemical and biological response to different compost qualityRestoration of soils burned by a wildfire using composted amendments of different origin (biosolids and municipal organic wastes) and final particle size (screened and unscreened) was studied after 6 and 12 months of application in a field trial in semiarid NW Patagonia. Composts were applied at 40 Mg ha(-1). A fertilized treatment with soluble N (100 kg ha(-1)) and P (35 kg ha(-1)), and a non-treated control were also included. As indicators of soil response, chemical (electrical conductivity, pH, organic C, total N, extractable P), biological (potential microbial respiration, potential net N mineralization, N retained in microbial biomass) and physical (temperature and soil moisture) properties were evaluated. Plant soil cover was also estimated. Soil chemical and biological properties showed a high response to organic amendment addition, more evident after the wet season (12 months of application). Soil organic C, total N and extractable P increased significantly with biosolids composts (C-13), and soil pH with municipal composts (MC). Potential microbial C respiration and net N mineralization were similar for both MC and BC, and significantly higher than in the control and the inorganic fertilized treatment; when calculated on C or N basis the highest values corresponded to MC. Results imply that in terms of organic C accretion, BC were more effective than MC due to higher amounts of total and recalcitrant C. Screened and unscreened composts did not differ significantly in their effects on soil properties. The increase of organic C with BC did not contribute to increase soil moisture, which was even higher in control plots after the wet season; higher plant cover and water consumption in amended plots could also explain this pattern. Inorganic fertilization enhanced higher plant cover than organic amendments, but did not contribute to soil restoration. (c) 2007 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.