Revision of the South American Species of Leptohyphes Eaton (Ephemeroptera: Leptohyphidae) with a Key to the NymphsThe male imago of Leptohyphes eximius Eaton, 1882 (type species of the genus) and male and female adults of L. cornutus Allen (1967) and L. plaumanni Allen (1967) are described for the first time. The nymphs of these species are redescribed. A new generic definition is proposed to include all the stages. Characters for separating male, female, eggs and nymphs of this genus from the other genera of the family are discussed and illustrated. Cotopaxi Mayo (1968) is proposed to be a junior synonym of Leptohyphes Eaton; its type species C. macuchae is declared a Nomen Dubium. The type material of all the South American species of Leptohyphes described as nymphs was studied, and a key together with a diagnosis with illustrations are presented for them. The following new synonymies are proposed: Leptohyphes eximius Eaton (= L. bruchi Navás and Bruchella nigra Navás), L. maculatus Allen (= L. comatus Allen, L. hirsutus Allen & Roback and L. myllonotus Allen & Roback), L. setosus Allen (= L. echinatus Allen & Roback), L. tacajalo Mayo (= L. albus Mayo) and L. plaumanni Allen (= L. pereirae da Silva). After this revision the number of valid South American species of Leptohyphes is eighteen (18). Scanning microscope photographs of the eggs of two species: L. eximius and L. cornutus are presented. Resumen Se describen por primera vez el imago macho de Leptohyphes eximius Eaton, 1882 (especie tipo del género) y los imagos de ambos sexos de L. cornutus Allen (1967) y L. plaumanni Allen (1967). Las ninfas de estas especies son redescriptas. Se propone una nueva definición del género para incluir todos los estados. Se ilustran y discuten los caracteres para distinguir a los machos, hembras, ninfas y huevos de Leptohyphes. Se propone a Cotopaxi Mayo (1968) como un nuevo sinónimo de Leptohyphes Eaton; y su especie tipo, C. macuchae, es declarada Nomen Dubium. Se estudió el material tipo de todas las especies sudamericanas de Leptohyphes descriptas sobre la base de ninfas, y se presenta una clave, diagnosis e ilustraciones para distinguirlas. Se proponen los siguientes nuevos sinónimos: Leptohyphes eximius Eaton (= L. bruchi Navás y Bruchella nigra Navás), L. maculatus Allen (= L. comatus Allen, L. hirsutus Allen & Roback y L. myllonotus Allen & Roback), L. setosus Allen (= L. echinatus Allen & Roback), L. tacajalo Mayo (= L. albus Mayo) y L. plaumanni Allen (= L. pereirae da Silva). Después de esta revisión son dieciocho (18) las especies de Leptohyphes que permanecen válidas en Sudamérica. Se presentan fotografías de microscopio electrónico de barrido para los huevos de dos especies: L. eximius y L. cornutus.