Land surface emissivity retrieval from combined mid-infrared and thermal infrared data of MSG-SEVIRIThis work addressed the retrieval of Land Surface Emissivity (LSE) from combined mid-infrared and thermal infrared data of Spinning Enhanced Visible and Infra-Red Imager (SEVIRI) onboard the geostationary satellite—Meteosat Second Generation (MSG). To correct for the atmospheric effects in satellite measurements, a new atmospheric correction scheme was developed for both Middle Infra-Red (MIR) and Thermal Infra-Red (TIR) channels. For the MIR channel, because it is less sensitive to the change of water vapor content, the clear-sky and time-nearest European Centre for Median-range Weather Forecast (ECMWF) atmospheric data were used for the images where no atmospheric data are available. For TIR channels, a modified model of Diurnal Temperature Cycle (DTC) used by Göttsche and Olesen [Göttsche, F. M., and Olesen, F. S. (2001). Modeling of diurnal cycles of brightness temperature extracted from METEOSAT data. Remote Sensing of Environment, 76, 337–348.] and Schädlich et al. [Schädlich, S., Göttsche, F. M., and Olesen, F. S. (2001). Influence of land surface parameters and atmosphere on METEOSAT brightness Temperatures and generation of land surface temperature maps by temporally and spatially interpolating atmospheric correction. Remote Sensing of Environment, 75, 39–46.] was adopted. The separation of Land Surface Temperature (LST) and LSE is based on the concept of the Temperature Independent Spectral Indices (TISI) [Becker, F., and Li, Z. L. (1990a). Temperature independent spectral indices in thermal infrared bands. Remote Sensing of Environment, 32, 17–33.] constructed with one channel in MIR and one channel in TIR. The results of two different combinations (combination of channels 4 and 9 and of channels 4 and 10) and two successive days at six specific locations over North Africa show that the retrievals are consistent. The range of emissivity in MSG-SEVIRI channel 4 goes from 0.5 for bare areas to 0.96 for densely vegetated areas, whereas the emissivities in MSG-SEVIRI channels 9 and 10 are usually from 0.9 to 0.95 for bare areas and from 0.95 to 1.0 for vegetated areas. For densely vegetated areas, the emissivities in MSG-SEVIRI channel 9 are larger than the ones in channel 10, whereas the opposite is observed over bare areas. The rms differences between two combinations over the whole studied region are 0.017 for emissivity in channel 4, 0.008 for emissivity in channel 9 and 0.007 for emissivity in channel 10.