On the use of the dual-frequency ENVISAT altimeter to determine snowpack properties of the Antarctic ice sheetThe primary purpose of ice-sheet altimetry is to monitor the changes in ice-sheet topography which may impact on global sea-level. However, the altimetric signal is sensitive to different properties of the snowpack, and therefore can also be used to determine these properties. The radar altimeter onboard the European Space Agency's ENVISAT satellite provides a dual-frequency dataset at Ku (13.6 GHz) and S band (3.2 GHz). In this paper, these signals are studied over the Antarctic ice-sheet during the 4 first years of the mission (2002–2006), in order to retrieve snowpack properties.The altimeter signal can be described by 4 classical waveform parameters. The 4 year time-series of all these parameters are decomposed into a linear and a seasonal time component. The linear component is almost constant. The distribution of the mean parameters over the Antarctic ice-sheet shows that the altimeter signal is sensitive to small-scale (mm) surface roughness.For the first time, the amplitudes and phases of the seasonal variations are characterized. The S band amplitudes are greater than the Ku band, and the phase varies over the entire ice-sheet. Previous studies suggested that the seasonal variations of the altitude from the altimeter are created by a decrease of the snowpack height through compaction. The dual-frequency observations shown here suggest that this hypothesis is too simple. Instead, the altitude variations observed in the altimetric signal are not created by the snowpack height change, but are more likely caused by the seasonal change of the snow properties, which cause a different response between the S and Ku bands. Therefore, both the linear and the seasonal variations of the altimetric signal can be used to retrieve snowpack properties.Here, we compare the dual-frequency ENVISAT signal with a model of the altimetric echo over the Antarctic ice-sheet. The model combines a surface model with a sub-surface model, for both the S and Ku bands. The Brown model [Brown G. S. (1977). The average impulse response of a rough surface and its applications. IEEE Transactions on Antennas and Propagation, 25, 1.] is used to describe the interaction of the radar wave with the snow surface. The backscatter coefficient of the surface is derived using the IEM method [Fung, A. K. (1994). Microwave scattering and emission models and their applications, Boston, MA: Artech House.]. The sub-surface signal takes into account both the layering effects and the scattering caused by the homogeneous media which is composed of small snow grains. The model is tested in two areas of the Antarctic plateau which present very different waveform parameters. The sensitivity of the radar signal to the different snowpack properties is investigated. The analysis of the waveform behaviours shows that the sub-surface signal can be completely masked by the small-scale surface roughness signal.Finally, the temperature and surface density effects are investigated in order to explain the seasonal variations of the altimetric signal. Both the temperature and the compaction rate of the snow change seasonally. Temperature is shown to impact on the Ku band signal. Furthermore, the compaction rate of the snow surface can explain all of the seasonal variation characteristics observed at both the S and Ku bands. The seasonal change of compaction rate in the snow creates a change in the waveform shape that can bias the altitude. In particular, the snow compaction can induce a bias in the retrieved altimetric altitude of more than 80 cm for the Ku band and 1.5 m for the S band. This work underlines that the altitude time-series needs to be corrected for the shape of the altimetric echo over ice-sheets.