The Sustainable Biosphere Initiative: An Ecological Research Agenda: A Report from the Ecological Society of AmericaIn this document, the Ecological Society of America proposes the Sustainable Biosphere Initiative (SBI), an initiative that focuses on the necessary role of ecological science in the wise management of Earth's resources and the maintenance of Earth's life support systems. This document is intended as a call-to-arms for all ecologists, but it also will serve as a means to communicate with individuals in other disciplines with whom ecologists must join forces to address our common predicament. Many of the environmental problems that challenge human society are fundamentally ecological in nature. The growing human population and its increasing use and misuse of resources are exerting tremendous pressures on Earth's life support capacity. Humankind must now develop the knowledge required to conserve and wisely manage Earth's resources. Citizens, policy-makers, resource- managers, and leaders of business and industry all need to make decisions concerning the Earth's resources, but such decisions cannot be made effectively without a fundamental understanding of the ways in which the natural systems of Earth are affected by human activities. Investigator In this document, the Ecological Society of America proposes the Sustainable Biosphere Initiative (SBI), an initiative that focuses on the necessary role of ecological science in the wise management of Earth's resources and the maintenance of Earth's life support systems. This document is intended as a call-to-arms for all ecologists, but it also will serve as a means to communicate with individuals in other disciplines with whom ecologists must join forces to address our common predicament. Many of the environmental problems that challenge human society are fundamentally ecological in nature. The growing human population and its increasing use and misuse of resources are exerting tremendous pressures on Earth's life support capacity. Humankind must now develop the knowledge required to conserve and wisely manage Earth's resources. Citizens, policy-makers, resource- managers, and leaders of business and industry all need to make decisions concerning the Earth's resources, but such decisions cannot be made effectively without a fundamental understanding of the ways in which the natural systems of Earth are affected by human activities. Investigator initiated, peer-reviewed basic research is the foundation on which informed environmental decisions must be based. Ecological knowledge and understanding are needed to detect and monitor changes, to evaluate consequences of a wide range of human activities, and to plan for the management of sustainable natural and human-dominated ecological systems. In response to these national and international needs, the Ecological Society of America has developed the Sustainable Biosphere Initiative (SBI), a framework for the acquisition, dissemination, and utilization of ecological knowledge which supports efforts to ensure the sustainability of the biosphere. The SBI calls for (1) basic research for the acquisition of ecological knowledge, (2) communication of that knowledge to citizens, and (3) incorporation of that knowledge into policy and management decisions.