Seedling survival in a northern temperate forest understory is increased by elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide and atmospheric nitrogen deposition.We tested the main and interactive effects of elevated carbon dioxide concentration ([CO<sub>2</sub>]), nitrogen (N), and light availability on leaf photosynthesis, and plant growth and survival in understory seedlings grown in an N-limited northern hardwood forest. For two growing seasons, we exposed six species of tree seedlings (<em>Betula papyrifera, Populus tremuloides, Acer saccharum</em>, <em>Fagus grandifolia</em>, <em>Pinus strobus</em>, and <em>Prunus serotina</em>) to a factorial combination of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> (ambient, and elevated CO<sub>2</sub> at 658 &mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> mol<sup>-;1</sup>) and N deposition (ambient and ambient +30 kg N ha<sup>-;1</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>) in open-top chambers placed in an understory light gradient. Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> exposure significantly increased apparent quantum efficiency of electron transport by 41% (<em>P</em><0.0001), light-limited photosynthesis by 47% (<em>P</em><0.0001), and light-saturated photosynthesis by 60% (<em>P</em><0.003) compared with seedlings grown in ambient [CO<sub>2</sub>]. Experimental N deposition significantly increased light-limited photosynthesis as light availability increased (<em>P</em><0.037). Species differed in the magnitude of light-saturated photosynthetic response to elevated N and light treatments (<em>P</em><0.016). Elevated CO<sub>2</sub> exposure and high N availability did not affect seedling growth; however, growth increased slightly with light availability (<em>R</em><sup>2</sup>=0.26, <em>P</em><0.0001). Experimental N deposition significantly increased average survival of all species by 48% (<em>P</em><0.012). However, seedling survival was greatest (85%) under conditions of both high [CO<sub>2</sub>] and N deposition (<em>P</em><0.009). Path analysis determined that the greatest predictor for seedling survival in the understory was total biomass (<em>R</em><sup>2</sup>=0.39, <em>P</em><0.001), and that carboxylation capacity (<em>V</em><sub>cmax</sub>) was a better predictor for seedling growth and survival than maximum photosynthetic rate (<em>A</em><sub>max</sub>). Our results suggest that increasing [CO<sub>2</sub>] and N deposition from fossil fuel combustion could alter understory tree species recruitment dynamics through changes in seedling survival, and this has the potential to alter future forest species composition.