Wood CO2 efflux in a primary tropical rain forest.The balance between photosynthesis and plant respiration in tropical forests may substantially affect the global carbon cycle. Woody tissue CO<sub>2</sub> efflux is a major component of total plant respiration, but estimates of ecosystem-scale rates are uncertain because of poor sampling in the upper canopy and across landscapes. To overcome these problems, we used a portable scaffolding tower to measure woody tissue CO<sub>2</sub> efflux from ground level to the canopy top across a range of sites of varying slope and soil phosphorus content in a primary tropical rain forest in Costa Rica. The objectives of this study were to: (1) determine whether to use surface area, volume, or biomass for modeling and extrapolating wood CO<sub>2</sub> efflux, (2) determine if wood CO<sub>2</sub> efflux varied seasonally, (3) identify if wood CO<sub>2</sub> efflux varied by functional group, height in canopy, soil fertility, or slope, and (4) extrapolate wood CO<sub>2</sub> efflux to the forest. CO<sub>2</sub> efflux from small diameter woody tissue (<10 cm) was related to surface area, while CO<sub>2</sub> efflux from stems >10 cm was related to both surface area and volume. Wood CO<sub>2</sub> efflux showed no evidence of seasonality over 2 years. CO<sub>2</sub> efflux per unit wood surface area at 25° (<em>F</em><sub>A</sub>) was highest for the N-fixing dominant tree species <em>Pentaclethra macroloba</em>, followed by other tree species, lianas, then palms. Small diameter <em>F</em><sub>A</sub> increased steeply with increasing height, and large diameter <em>F</em><sub>A</sub> increased with diameter. Soil phosphorus and slope had slight, but complex effects on <em>F</em><sub>A</sub>. Wood CO<sub>2</sub> efflux per unit ground area was 1.34±0.36 &mu;mol m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>, or 508±135 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>. Small diameter wood, only 15% of total woody biomass, accounted for 70% of total woody tissue CO<sub>2</sub> efflux from the forest; while lianas, only 3% of total woody biomass, contributed one-fourth of the total wood CO<sub>2</sub> efflux.