Modelling and mapping potential hooded warbler (Wilsonia citrina) habitat using remotely sensed imageryModelling and mapping of hooded warbler (Wilsonia citrina) nesting habitat in forests of southern Ontario were conducted using Ikonos and Landsat data. The study began with an analysis of skyward hemispherical photography to determine canopy characteristics associated with nest sites. It showed that nest sites had significantly less overhead canopy cover and larger maximum gap size than in non-nest areas. These findings led to the hypothesis that brightness variability in high to moderate resolution remotely sensed imagery may be greater at nest sites than in non-nest areas due to larger shadows and greater shadow variability related to these gap characteristics. This was confirmed when, in addition to some spectral band brightness variables, several image texture and spectrally unmixed fraction (shadow, bare soil) variables were found to be significantly different for nest and non-nest sites in Ikonos and Landsat imagery. These significantly different variables were used in maximum likelihood classification (MLC) and logistic regression (LR) to produce maps of potential nesting habitat. Mapping was conducted with Ikonos and Landsat in a local area where most known nest sites occur, and regionally using Landsat data for almost all of the hooded warbler range in southern Ontario. For the local area mapping using Ikonos data, a posteriori probabilities for both the MLC and LR methods showed that about 62% of the nest sites set aside for validation had been classified with high probability (p>0.70) in the nest class. MLC mapping accuracy was 70% for the validation nest sites and 87% of validation nest sites were within 10 m of classified nesting habitat, a distance approximately equivalent to expected positional error in the data. LR accuracy was slightly lower. Nest site MLC mapping accuracy in the local area using Landsat data was 87% but the map was much coarser due to the larger pixel size. Regional mapping with Landsat imagery produced lower classification accuracy due to high errors of commission for the habitat class. This resulted from a poor spatial distribution and low number of observations of nest sites throughout the region compared to the local area, while the non-nest site data distribution was too narrow, having been defined and assessed (using standard accepted methods) as areas with no ground shrubs. If either of these problems can be ameliorated, regional mapping accuracy may improve.