Soil CO2 efflux of two silver birch clones exposed to elevated CO2 and O3 levels during three growing seasons.In the present open-top chamber experiment, two silver birch clones (<em>Betula pendula</em> Roth, clone 4 and clone 80) were exposed to elevated levels of carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) and ozone (O<sub>3</sub>), singly and in combination, and soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux was measured 14 times during three consecutive growing seasons (1999-2001). In the beginning of the experiment, all experimental trees were 7 years old and during the experiment the trees were growing in sandy field soil and fertilized regularly. In general, elevated O<sub>3</sub> caused soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux stimulation during most measurement days and this stimulation enhanced towards the end of the experiment. The overall soil respiration response to CO<sub>2</sub> was dependent on the genotype, as the soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux below clone 80 trees was enhanced and below clone 4 trees was decreased under elevated CO<sub>2</sub> treatments. Like the O<sub>3</sub> impact, this clonal difference in soil respiration response to CO<sub>2</sub> increased as the experiment progressed. Although the O<sub>3</sub> impact did not differ significantly between clones, a significant time &times; clone &times; CO<sub>2</sub>&times; O<sub>3</sub> interaction revealed that the O<sub>3</sub>-induced stimulation of soil respiration was counteracted by elevated CO<sub>2</sub> in clone 4 on most measurement days, whereas in clone 80, the effect of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> in combination was almost constantly additive during the 3-year experiment. Altogether, the root or above-ground biomass results were only partly parallel with the observed soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux responses. In conclusion, our data show that O<sub>3</sub> impacts may appear first in the below-ground processes and that relatively long-term O<sub>3</sub> exposure had a cumulative effect on soil CO<sub>2</sub> efflux. Although the soil respiration response to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> depended on the tree genotype as a result of which the O<sub>3</sub> stress response might vary considerably within a single tree species under elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, the present experiment nonetheless indicates that O<sub>3</sub> stress is a significant factor affecting the carbon cycling in northern forest ecosystems.