Net ecosystem CO2 exchange in Mojave Desert shrublands during the eighth year of exposure to elevated CO2.Arid ecosystems, which occupy about 35% of the Earth's terrestrial surface area, are believed to be among the most responsive to elevated [CO<sub>2</sub>]. Net ecosystem CO<sub>2</sub> exchange (NEE) was measured in the eighth year of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment at the Nevada Desert Free-Air CO<sub>2</sub> Enrichment (FACE) Facility between the months of December 2003-December 2004. On most dates mean daily NEE (24 h) (&mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>) of ecosystems exposed to elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> were similar to those maintained at current ambient CO<sub>2</sub> levels. However, on sampling dates following rains, mean daily NEEs of ecosystems exposed to elevated [CO<sub>2</sub>] averaged 23 to 56% lower than mean daily NEEs of ecosystems maintained at ambient [CO<sub>2</sub>]. Mean daily NEE varied seasonally across both CO<sub>2</sub> treatments, increasing from about 0.1 &mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup> in December to a maximum of 0.5-0.6 &mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup> in early spring. Maximum NEE in ecosystems exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> occurred 1 month earlier than it did in ecosystems exposed to ambient CO<sub>2</sub>, with declines in both treatments to lowest seasonal levels by early October (0.09±0.03 &mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>), but then increasing to near peak levels in late October (0.36±0.08 &mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>), November (0.28±0.03 &mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>), and December (0.54±0.06 &mu;mol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>). Seasonal patterns of mean daily NEE primarily resulted from larger seasonal fluctuations in rates of daytime net ecosystem CO<sub>2</sub> uptake which were closely tied to plant community phenology and precipitation. Photosynthesis in the autotrophic crust community (lichens, mosses, and free-living cyanobacteria) following rains were probably responsible for the high NEEs observed in January, February, and late October 2004 when vascular plant photosynthesis was low. Both CO<sub>2</sub> treatments were net CO<sub>2</sub> sinks in 2004, but exposure to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> reduced CO<sub>2</sub> sink strength by 30% (positive net ecosystem productivity=127±17 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup> ambient CO<sub>2</sub> and 90±11 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup> elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, <em>P</em>=0.011). This level of net C uptake rivals or exceeds levels observed in some forested and grassland ecosystems. Thus, the decrease in C sequestration seen in our study under elevated CO<sub>2</sub>- along with the extensive coverage of arid and semi-arid ecosystems globally - points to a significant drop in global C sequestration potential in the next several decades because of responses of heretofore overlooked dryland ecosystems.