Contemporary carbon balance and late Holocene carbon accumulation in a northern peatland.Northern peatlands contain up to 25% of the world's soil carbon (C) and have an estimated annual exchange of CO<sub>2</sub>-C with the atmosphere of 0.1-0.5 Pg yr<sup>-;1</sup> and of CH<sub>4</sub>-C of 10-25 Tg yr<sup>-;1</sup>. Despite this overall importance to the global C cycle, there have been few, if any, complete multiyear annual C balances for these ecosystems. We report a 6-year balance computed from continuous net ecosystem CO<sub>2</sub> exchange (NEE), regular instantaneous measurements of methane (CH<sub>4</sub>) emissions, and export of dissolved organic C (DOC) from a northern ombrotrophic bog. From these observations, we have constructed complete seasonal and annual C balances, examined their seasonal and interannual variability, and compared the mean 6-year contemporary C exchange with the apparent C accumulation for the last 3000 years obtained from C density and age-depth profiles from two peat cores. The 6-year mean NEE-C and CH<sub>4</sub>-C exchange, and net DOC loss are -;40.2±40.5 (±1 SD), 3.7±0.5, and 14.9±3.1 g m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>, giving a 6-year mean balance of -;21.5±39.0 g m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup> (where positive exchange is a loss of C from the ecosystem). NEE had the largest magnitude and variability of the components of the C balance, but DOC and CH<sub>4</sub> had similar proportional variabilities and their inclusion is essential to resolve the C balance. There are large interseasonal and interannual ranges to the exchanges due to variations in climatic conditions. We estimate from the largest and smallest seasonal exchanges, quasi-maximum limits of the annual C balance between 50 and -;105 g m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>. The net C accumulation rate obtained from the two peatland cores for the interval 400-3000 bp (samples from the anoxic layer only) were 21.9±2.8 and 14.0±37.6 g m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>, which are not significantly different from the 6-year mean contemporary exchange.