A Test of Two Annual Cover Crops for Controlling Phalaris arundinacea Invasion in Restored Sedge Meadow Wetlands.Rapid establishment by aggressive plants such as <em>Phalaris arundinacea</em> (reed canarygrass) often interferes with sedge meadow establishment in restored prairie pothole wetlands in the mid-continental United States. Introducing a cover crop during community establishment might suppress <em>P. arundinacea</em> invasion in restored prairie potholes by reducing resource availability. We evaluated two potential cover crops, <em>Echinochloa crusgalli</em> (barnyardgrass) and <em>Polygonum lapathifolium</em> (nodding smartweed), for suppressing <em>P. arundinacea</em> invasion in an experimental wetland using replacement series competition experiments. Further, we assessed the effects of <em>E. crusgalli</em> and <em>P. lapathifolium</em> on sedge meadow establishment by sowing <em>Carex hystericina</em>, a common wetland sedge, as a third species at a constant density in the replacement experiments. <em>Echinochloa crusgalli</em>, compared with no cover crop, reduced <em>P. arundinacea</em> biomass by more than 1,000 g/m<sup>2</sup> (65%) after two growing seasons. <em>Polygonum lapathifolium</em> did not affect <em>P. arundinacea</em> biomass. Dense <em>E. crusgalli</em> canopies in the first year and thick <em>E. crusgalli</em> thatch in the second year substantially reduced light availability for <em>P. arundinacea</em> establishment. <em>Echinochloa crusgalli</em> also reduced <em>C. hystericina</em> biomass by more than 1,800 g/m<sup>2</sup> (99%) after two growing seasons. <em>Carex hystericina</em> biomass was similar in plots sown with <em>E. crusgalli</em> to <em>P. arundinacea</em> monocultures. Neither <em>E. crusgalli</em> nor <em>P. lapathifolium</em> is likely to improve sedge meadow restoration success. These trends were not sensitive to initial sowing density or elevation above water level. Without methods to suppress <em>P. arundinacea</em> invasions, sedge meadow restorations may often fail. Thorough site preparation to remove <em>P. arundinacea</em> propagule sources before restoration is essential.