Annual soil CO2 effluxes in the High Arctic: The role of snow thickness and vegetation typeLittle work has been done to quantify annual soil CO2 effluxes in the High Arctic region because of the difficulty in taking winter measurements. Since the effects of climate change are expected to be higher in Arctic than in temperate ecosystems, it is important that summer measurements are extended to cover the entire year. This study evaluates the quantity and quality of soil organic C (SOC) and seasonal controls of soil CO2 effluxes in three soils under three dominating types of vegetation (Dryas, Cassiope, and Salix) at Svalbard. Measurements included Soil CO2 effluxes in the field and the laboratory, temperature, water content, and snow thickness. About 90% of the variation in soil respiration throughout 1 year was due to near-surface soil temperatures which ranged from -12 to + 12 degrees C. Total annual Soil CO2 effluxes varied from 103 g C m(-2) at soils under Cassiope, 152 g C m(-2) under Dryas sites, and 176 g C m(-2) under Salix, with 20%, 14%, and 30%, respectively, being released during a 6-month winter period. The sensitivity of soil respiration with respect to soil temperature was the same year round and differences in winter CO2 effluxes at the three vegetation types were mainly related to subsurface soil temperatures controlled by snow depth. The quantity and quality of soil organic matter varied under the different vegetation types. Soils under Salix had the largest and most labile pool of SOC and were characterized by a long period of snow cover. In contrast, soils under Cassiope were more nutrient-poor, more acidic and held the smallest amount of total and labile SOC, whereas soils under Dryas remained snow-free most of the winter and therefore had the coldest winter conditions. Thus, winter soil respiration rates under Dryas and Cassiope were significantly lower than those under Saliv; under Dryas this was mainly due to snow depth, under Cassiope this was a combination of snow depth and poor litter quality. It is concluded that winter respiration is highly variable across Arctic landscapes and depends on the spatial distribution of snow, which acts as a direct control on soil temperatures and indirect on vegetation types and thereby, the amount and quality of soil organic matter, which serve as additional important drivers of soil respiration. (c) 2006 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.