Linear glandular trichomes of Helianthus (Asteraceae): morphology, localization, metabolite activity and occurrenceThe plant surface of sunflower is covered with at least three types of trichomes, two of which have glandular nature and produce a rich spectrum of allelochemicals. While the development and metabolic activity of the biseriate multicelluar glands has been investigated intensively in the past, hardly any information was yet available on the uniseriate linear glands. The current study of this latter type of plant hairs provides first detailed results on: (i) the occurrence in Helianthus and related genera, (ii) the accumulation of sesquiterpenes and other metabolites, and (iii) a possible a function of the trichomes in plant insect interaction. Capitate glandular trichomes of sunflower are well investigated, but detailed studies are lacking for the linear glandular trichomes (LGT), a second type of physiologically active plant hair present on the surface of sunflowers. Light, fluorescence and scanning electron microscopy as well as histochemical staining were used to investigate the structure and metabolite deposition of LGT. Consisting of 6–11 linearly arranged cells, LGT were found on the surface of most plant organs of Helianthus annuus. They were associated with the leaf vascular system, and also occurred along petioles, stems and the abaxial surface of chaffy bracts, ray and disc florets. The highest density was found on the abaxial surface of phyllaries. Phenotypically similar LGT were common in all species of the genus, but also occurred in most other genera of the Helianthinae so far screened. Brownish and fluorescent metabolites of an as yet unknown chemical structure, together with terpenoids, were produced and stored in apical cells of LGT. The deposition of compounds gradually progressed from the tip cell to the basal cells of older trichomes. This process was accompanied by nucleus degradation in metabolite-accumulating cells. The localization of these trichomes on prominent plant parts of the apical bud and the capitulum combined with the accumulation of terpenoids and other as yet unknown compounds suggests a chemo-ecological function of the LGT in plant–insect or plant–herbivore interaction.