The immature stages, larval food plants and biology of Neotropical mistletoe butterflies (Lepidoptera: Pieridae). II. The Catasticta group (Pierini: Aporiina)We present an overview of the morphology, larval food plants and general biology of the immature stages of the ‚ÄúCatasticta group‚Ä, one of three clades of aporiine pierids that specialize predominantly on mistletoes, based on extensive field observations and captive reared material in Costa Rica, review of the literature, and examination of material preserved in museum collections. Of the 8 genera recognized in the group, 6 are restricted to the Neotropics of which detailed descriptions and/or illustrations are given for 11 species representing the genera Melete, Pereute, Leodonta and Catasticta. The life histories of these taxa are compared with those of Neophasia and Eucheira, two Nearctic genera in the Catasticta group that specialize on host trees of mistletoes. Larval food plants of the Neotropical genera include Struthanthus, Tripodanthus (Loranthaceae), Antidaphne (Santalaceae), Dendrophthora and Phoradendron (Viscaceae), all aerial-stem hemiparasites in the order Santalales. The butterflies are multivoltine and, with the exception of Melete in which adults are possibly migratory, appear to breed throughout the year. Eggs are deposited in clusters on the larval food plant, larvae feed gregariously and spin considerable quantities of silk, particularly in the late instars, adults are frequently aposematic, and at least four genera form complex mimicry rings. In Melete, Pereute, Leodonta and one species of Catasticta, larval instars III‚ÄìV feed nocturnally and aggregate near the base of the host tree during the day: silken trails are constructed between mistletoe foraging sites and host tree diurnal resting sites to facilitate movement and communication. The morphology and biology of the immature stages of the Catasticta group are compared with other members of the Aporiina, particularly those of Delias, Aporia and the more distantly related Mylothris, and comments made on their systematic relationships. Simple optimization of several key life history traits in the context of a recent phylogenetic hypothesis of the Aporiina suggests aposematism (larval repellent defence and adult warning colouration) evolved once in the common ancestor of the subtribe, but egg clustering and larval gregariousness are derived traits that coincided with the evolution of mistletoe feeding. It is hypothesized that following the evolution of aposematism, the spatial distribution (patchiness) of mistletoe food plants, which are assumed to contain toxic alkaloids, has been a selective force in the evolution of larval gregariousness in these butterflies. Se presentan aspectos generales de la morfolog√≠a, las plantas hospederas y la biolog√≠a general de los estadios inmaduros del ‚Äúgrupo Catasticta‚Ä, uno de los tres grupos de pi√©ridos del Aporiina que se especializan en matapalos; bas√°ndose en observaciones extensas en el campo, crianza en cautiverio en Costa Rica, revisi√≥n de la literatura disponible, y el examen de materiales almacenados en colecciones de museos. De los ocho g√©neros reconocidos en el grupo, se restringen seis al neotr√≥pico; de los cuales se dan descripciones e ilustraciones detalladas para diez especies que representan los g√©neros: Melete, Pereute, Leodonta y Catasticta. Se comparan las historias naturales de dichas especies con las de Neophasia y Eucheira, dos g√©neros de ne√°rctica en el grupo Catasticta que se especializan en los √°rboles hospederos de matapalos. Las plantas hospederas de los g√©neros de neotr√≥pico incluyen Struthanthus, Tripodanthus (Loranthaceae), Antidaphne (Santalaceae), Dendrophthora y Phoradendron (Viscaceae), todas son hemipar√°sitos de tallos a√©reos y son del orden Santalales. Las mariposas son multivoltinas que se reproducen a trav√©s del a√±o, con la excepci√≥n de Melete en que los adultos son posiblemente migratorios. Depositan los huevos en grupos en las plantas hospederas; las larvas son gregarias y se alimentan en grupo, y producen cantidades considerables de seda, particularmente en los √∫ltimos estadios. Los adultos frecuentemente son aposem√°ticos, y por lo menos cuatro g√©neros forman anillos de mimetismo complejo. En Melete, Pereute, Leodonta y una especie de Catasticta, las larvas en III a V se alimentan durante la noche, y durante el d√≠a se agregan en las bases de los √°rboles hospederos de matapalos alimenticios; construyen senderos de seda entre los matapalos en que forrajean y los sitios de descanso del d√≠a para facilitar el movimiento y la comunicaci√≥n. Se comparan la morfolog√≠a y biolog√≠a de los estadios inmaduros del grupo Catasticta con otros miembros del Aporiina, particularmente con los de Delias, Aporia y de Mylothris que est√°n menos relacionados, y se presentan comentarios sobre sus relaciones sistem√°ticas. El mejoramiento de algunos rasgos importantes de la historia natural en el contexto de una hip√≥tesis reciente de la filogen√©tica del Aporiina sugiere que el aposematismo (defensa larval para repeler y la coloraci√≥n de advertencia de adulto) evolucion√≥ una vez en el ancestro com√∫n de la subtribu, pero los huevos puestos en grupos y las larvas gregarias son rasgos derivados que coincidieron con la evoluci√≥n de alimentarse de matapalos. Se supone que siguiendo la evoluci√≥n del aposematismo, la distribuci√≥n espacial (dispersi√≥n) de los matapalos, los cuales se considera que contienen alcaloides t√≥xicos, ha sido una fuerza selectiva en la evoluci√≥n del gregarismo en su estadio larval, de estas mariposas diurnas.