Forest vertical structure from GLAS: An evaluation using LVIS and SRTM dataThe Geoscience Laser Altimeter System (GLAS) on the Ice, Cloud and land Elevation Satellite (ICESat) is the first spaceborne lidar instrument for continuous global observation of the Earth. GLAS records a vertical profile of the returned laser energy from its footprint. To help understand the application of the data for forest spatial structure studies in our regional projects, an evaluation of the GLAS data was conducted using NASA's Laser Vegetation Imaging Sensor (LVIS) data in an area near NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Maryland, USA. The tree height indices from airborne large-footprint lidars such as LVIS have been successfully used for estimation of forest structural parameters in many previous studies and served as truth in this study.The location accuracy of the GLAS footprints was evaluated by matching the elevation profile from GLAS with the Shuttle Radar Topography Mission (SRTM) DEM. The results confirmed the location accuracy of the GLAS geolocation, and showed a high correlation between the height of the scattering phase center from SRTM and the top tree height from GLAS data. The comparisons between LVIS and GLAS data showed that the GLAS waveform is similar to the aggregation of the LVIS waveforms within the GLAS footprint, and the tree height indices derived from the GLAS and LVIS waveforms were highly correlated. The best correlations were found between the 75% waveform energy quartiles of LVIS and GLAS (r2=0.82 for October 2003 GLAS data, and r2=0.65 for June 2005 GLAS data). The correlations between the 50% waveform energy quartiles of LVIS and GLAS were also high (0.77 and 0.66 respectively). The comparisons of the top tree height and total length of waveform of the GLAS data acquired in fall of 2003 and early summer of 2005 showed a several meter bias. Because the GLAS footprints from these two orbits did not exactly overlap, several other factors may have caused this observed difference, including difference of forest structures, seasonal difference of canopy structures and errors in identifying the ground peak of waveforms.