Micromorphological and microchemical indicators of pedogenesis in Ornithogenic Cryosols (Gelisols) of Hope Bay, Antarctic PeninsulaMicromorphological investigations of Antarctic soils are comparatively scarce, however, they could help understand the genesis of cryogenic soils under extreme polar conditions and different biotic factors. In most areas of Maritime Antarctica, the soil structure is apparently influenced by the local lithology, cryoturbation, guano deposition and reaction of guano solutions. The present study was carried out in Hope Bay, in the northern part of the Antarctic Peninsula, possibly one of the oldest sites of penguin occupation in the region. We describe and analyze the most important micro and sub-microscopic features of selected Ornithogenic Cryosols (Gelisols) from this part of Antarctic Peninsula, representing a transitional climatic zone between the wetter South Shetlands and the much drier Weddell Sea sector. Nine pedons representing the main ornithogenic soils found in ice-free areas of Hope Bay were selected for the micromorphological study. Undisturbed soil blocks were sampled at different depths, ranging between 0 and 30 cm. The microstructure and sub-microstructure were further investigated using a JEOL 8200 and a Zeiss scanning electron microscopes, both coupled with an microprobe (SEM/WDS). These pedons have a very limited surface accumulation of organic matter formed by mosses and lichens, changing abruptly to a mineral phosphatic horizon of bleached colours, and usually hardcemented by ice. A small to medium-sized granular structure is generally observed, with ovoidal, subrounded forms, including several well-defined ornithogenic materials, such as P-rich organic remains, nodular phosphates forms and minute fragments of bone apatite. The chemical composition of ornithogenic materials and phosphatic coatings indicates the presence of discrete forms of taranakite, minyulite, leucophosphite, struvite and fluorapatite, typical of phosphatization process in these soils. Phosphatization and enhanced chemical alteration of the substrate and is one of the main soil-forming process in ornithogenic soils, resulting in P-rich ovoidal aggregates formation. P-rich solutions penetrate desiccation fractures and cleavage planes in large clasts and react preferably with plagioclases. P reacts with Al and Fe to form various amorphous and crystalline P phases. Present day permafrost cementation of deeper phosphate layers indicate that warmer/wetter conditions occurred in the past, during which P was leached downwards and reacted with the rock substrates, developing stable ovoidal aggregates, now incorporated in ice-cemented subsurface horizon.