Impact of outdoor winter sports on the abundance of a key indicator species of alpine ecosystems.<ol><li>Tourism and leisure activities have increased continuously all over the world during the past decades, exerting a growing pressure upon naturally fragile ecosystems, such as mountainous habitats. Recent studies have established that disturbance by outdoor winter sports (e.g. skiing, snowboarding and snowshoeing) is a source of stress for wildlife. This may in turn affect its abundance, but we still lack quantitative evidence.</li><li>We tested the effect of outdoor winter sports (ski lifts and related recreational activities) on the abundance of the alpine black grouse <em>Tetrao tetrix</em>, a vulnerable indicator species of the timberline ecosystem, the favoured habitat for outdoor winter sports in the European Alps.</li><li>Generalized linear models and a model selection approach were used to rank environmental factors influencing black grouse abundance and to make predictions about population status in the theoretical absence of ski resorts. We modelled the number of displaying cocks along census transects in spring, as a function of habitat characteristics (vegetation structure and typology), ski lift density and hunting pressure at 15 natural sites (none or a very low level of anthropogenic disturbance) and 15 ski resorts in the south-western Swiss Alps.</li><li>Ski lift density and habitat typology were the principal determinants of black grouse abundance, whereas hunting pressure had no discernable effect. Ski lifts and related winter sport activities had a strong negative effect on the number of displaying cocks, which may have led to a mean 36% reduction of local abundance in ski lift areas, as determined after controlling for the confounding effect of habitat type.</li><li><em>Synthesis and applications</em>. Conservation action plans for black grouse should aim at reducing the multiple negative effects generated by outdoor winter sports (ski facilities and related winter sport activities). First, vegetation patchiness (i.e. a mosaic of grassy shrubland with scattered trees) should be maintained along ski runs. Secondly, wintering preserves where human access is banned or strictly limited should be promoted within ski resorts. Spatially explicit human-wildlife conflict maps can be constructed from the present model to allow delineation of those areas likely to become effective protection areas.</li></ol>