Candidatus               Phytoplasma aurantifolia (16SrII Group) Associated with Witches’ Broom Disease of Bamboo (               Dendrocalamus strictus               ) in IndiaSolid or Calcutta bamboo (Dendrocalamus strictus Nees., Poaceae) is found in the tropical regions of Indian subcontinent, Southeast Asia, and China. D. strictus is semelparous and has a flowering cycle of 20 to 65 years. It is one of the toughest bamboos in India and extensively used in making pulp and rayon for paper mills and construction of light-weight houses as well as furniture, making it a commercially significant plant species. Its young shoots are used as food, its leaves as fodder, and it is also used in traditional medicine (Nadgauda et al. 1993). Leaf samples from symptomatic bamboo plants were collected from five geographically separated plantations from Maharashtra State during September 2014 to January 2015. Observed symptoms were typical witches’ broom phenotype with severe proliferative branching at nodal regions and reduction in leaf size, as described earlier by Suryanarayana et al. (2009), and which were suggestive of a phytoplasma infection. To confirm the presence of a phytoplasma, 1 g of leaf tissue from each of the symptomatic and asymptomatic plants were used for total DNA extraction using the CTAB method. The phytoplasma 16S rRNA gene was detected in all 16 collected symptomatic D. strictus samples using nested PCR with phytoplasma universal primers P1 and P7 followed by primers R16F2n/R16R2 (Smart et al. 1996) on agarose gel. No amplification was observed in template DNA isolated from asymptomatic plants. PCR fragments generated using R16F2n/1492R primers were sequenced directly using six different primers, namely R16F2n, R16R2, 343R, 704F, 907R, and 1492R. The obtained 16S rRNA gene sequence (GenBank Accession No. LN811707, 1337 bp) showed 99.4% homology with a strain WBDL belonging to Peanut Witches’ broom group phytoplasma (Candidatus Phytoplasma aurantifolia, U15442) found in Catharanthus roseus (Asteraceae) when compared using the EzTaxon 16S rRNA database. The virtual RFLP pattern (Zhao et al. 2009) derived from the 16S rRNA sequence (LN811707) was found most similar to the reference pattern of the 16Sr group II, subgroup C (AJ293216), with a pattern similarity coefficient of 0.99. To our knowledge, this is the only report of Ca. Phytoplasma aurantifolia associated with witches’ broom disease of D. strictus from India in addition to Ca. Phytoplasma asteris (AB242433) associated with Phyllostachys nigra (black bamboo) reported from Korea (Jung et al., 2006). While Suryanayana et al. (2009) reported symptoms of witches’ broom disease on D. strictus from Karnataka, India; it was not clear whether observed symptoms were related to phytoplasma infection. Additionally, there was no evidence to establish the species of the disease-causing organism. Dendrocalamus strictus being an economically important plant, its susceptibility to phytoplasma diseases, especially involving vegetative propagation, can cause significant negative effect on yield and therefore socio-economic status of the population engaged in its cultivation. Diagnostic accreditation of bamboo species for phytoplasma diseases and management of phytoplasma insect vectors will help reduce its exposure to witches’ broom disease.