Sphaeralcea Angustifolia as a Substitute for Alfalfa for Growing Goats.Narrowleaf globemallow (<em>Sphaeralcea</em> <em>angustifolia</em> [Cav.] G. Don) occurs on millions of hectares of rangeland in the United States and Mexico, and it constitutes an important forage for herbivores. Forty 2-mo-old crossbred female goats (native×dairy goats; 9.4 ± 2.2 kg) were randomly allotted to five dietary groups (two] goats per pen, four replications per ration) to evaluate the effects of feeding different levels of <em>S. angustifolia</em> in a complete ration on growth performance and diet digestibility. The rations were a total mixed control ration containing 0% <em>S. angustifolia</em> (T0) and four rations in which <em>S. angustifolia</em> progressively replaced alfalfa (25% [T25], 50% [T50], 75% [T75], and 100% [T100]). Grains and forage made up 70% and 30% of the dietary dry matter (DM) in all rations. Differences (<em>P</em> < 0.05) were observed between treatments in average daily gain (ADG; range 88-124 g·d<sup>−1</sup>) and DM intake (DMI; range 3.3-4.0% body weight). Feed conversion ratio (DMI/ADG; range 4.0-4.8) was similar (<em>P</em>>0.20) among treatments. Goats fed diets with any of the <em>S. angustifolia</em> levels had similar apparent nitrogen (N) digestion (range 67.6-69.8%) as those fed only alfalfa, but N retention was greater (<em>P</em> < 0.05) in goats on T25 and T50 diets compared to other diets. The apparent digestibilities of DM, neutral detergent fiber, and acid detergent fiber were greater (<em>P</em> < 0.05) for T25 and T50 than for other diets. Results indicate that <em>S. angustifolia</em> at the flowering stage was a savory and nutritious roughage, which could fully replace alfalfa hay in diets of growing goats. Considering that <em>S. angustifolia</em> is readily consumed by foraging animals, it is abundant enough that it is a significant source of forage, and has a sufficient quality to nutritionally satisfy herbivores, this forb is a potentially useful forage for pen-fed goats.