BRYOPHYTE RESPONSES TO MICROCLIMATIC EDGE EFFECTS ACROSS RIPARIAN BUFFERS.ugh riparian buffers are an important aspect of forest management in the boreal forest of Canada, little is known about the habitat conditions within buffers, due in part to complex edge effects in response to both the upland clearcut and the stream. We investigated microclimatic conditions and bryophyte growth and vitality in seven locations between the stream edge and 60 m into the upland undisturbed conifer forests and at the clearcut sites with riparian buffer 30 km northwest of Thunder Bay, Ontario, Canada. We hypothesized that the growth and vitality of a pleurocarpous moss, <em>Hylocomium splendens</em>, and an acrocarpous moss, <em>Polytrichum commune</em>, would be directly related to the microclimatic gradients detected. We further hypothesized that sensitivity of the bryophytes to environmental factors will vary depending on their life form type, i.e., pleurocarpous moss will respond differently than the acrocarpous moss. Both bryophyte species were transplanted in pots and placed at 10-m intervals along 60-m transects perpendicular to the stream across the buffer and undisturbed sites. Bryophyte growth, cover, and vitality, as well as microclimatic parameters and plant cover, were measured over the summer in 2003.<br><br>The riparian buffers were simultaneously affected by microclimatic gradients extending from both the clearcut edge and the riparian-upland ecotonal edge. Both bryophyte species responded to changes in the microclimatic conditions. However, vapor pressure deficit (VPD) was the most important factor influencing the growth of <em>H. splendens</em>, whereas for <em>P. commune</em> growth soil moisture was most important. Our study confirms earlier findings that interior forest bryophytes such as <em>H. splendens</em> can be used as indicators to monitor edge effects and biodiversity recovery following forest harvesting. We demonstrate that growth and vitality of these bryophytes reflect the prevailing near-ground microclimatic conditions at the forest edges. Abundance estimates of such bryophytes can be used to determine the depth of edge effects across both ecotonal edges (e.g., riparian-upland forest edge) and anthropogenically created edges (e.g., clearcut edge). Forest management practices must consider depth of edge in determining the appropriate width of riparian buffers that would be necessary to sustain biodiversity and associated values at the land/water interface.