Carbon dioxide balance of a fen ecosystem in northern Finland under elevated UV-B radiation.The effect of elevated UV-B radiation on CO<sub>2</sub> exchange of a natural flark fen was studied in open-field conditions during 2003-2005. The experimental site was located in Sodankyl&auml; in northern Finland (67°22&prime;N, 26°38&prime;E, 179 m a.s.l.). Altogether 30 study plots, each 120 cm &times; 120 cm in size, were randomly distributed between three treatments (<em>n</em>=10): ambient control, UV-A control and UV-B treatment. The UV-B-treated plots were exposed to elevated UV-B radiation level for three growing seasons. The instantaneous net ecosystem CO<sub>2</sub> exchange (NEE) and dark respiration (<em>R</em><sub>TOT</sub>) were measured during the growing season using a closed chamber method. The wintertime CO<sub>2</sub> emissions were estimated using a gradient technique by analyzing the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the snow pack. In addition to the instantaneous CO<sub>2</sub> exchange, the seasonal CO<sub>2</sub> balances during the growing seasons were modeled using environmental data measured at the site. In general, the instantaneous NEE at light saturation was slightly higher in the UV-B treatment compared with the ambient control, but the gross photosynthesis was unaffected by the exposure. The <em>R</em><sub>TOT</sub> was significantly lower under elevated UV-B in the third study year. The modeled seasonal (June-September) CO<sub>2</sub> balance varied between the years depending on the ground water level and temperature conditions. During the driest year, the seasonal CO<sub>2</sub> balance was negative (net release of CO<sub>2</sub>) in the ambient control and the UV-B treatment was CO<sub>2</sub> neutral. During the third year, the seasonal CO<sub>2</sub> uptake was 43±36 g CO<sub>2</sub>-C m<sup>-;2</sup> in the ambient control and 79±45 g CO<sub>2</sub>-C m<sup>-;2</sup> in the UV-B treatment. The results suggest that the long-term exposure to high UV-B radiation levels may slightly increase the CO<sub>2</sub> accumulation to fens resulting from a decrease in microbial activity in peat. However, it is unlikely that the predicted development of the level of UV-B radiation would significantly affect the CO<sub>2</sub> balance of fen ecosystems in future.