Establishment and Growth of Living Fence Species: An Overlooked Tool for the Restoration of Degraded Areas in the Tropics.Numerous tree species can establish by vegetative means in the tropics. Many are used in agriculture as living fences and in alley cropping and could also be used in a restorational setting. However, little is known about their establishment ability. This study evaluated the establishment ability and cover development of multiple species in three separate field trials in northern Honduras. First, 11 species were evaluated for their ability to establish in a common garden experiment. Second, of the former species, <em>Bursera simaruba</em> and <em>Gliricidia sepium</em> were evaluated for 2 years for their ability to establish vegetatively and develop cover at three deforested sites. Lastly, a study examined whether greater initial stake height and diameter at breast height increased the establishment success and crown development of <em>G. sepium</em> stakes. First, five species, <em>Erythrina berteroana</em>, <em>Erythrina fusca</em>, <em>Jatropha curcas</em>, <em>G. sepium</em>, and <em>B. simaruba</em>, had high establishment success. Others showed promise but may have been planted in the wrong season. Second, establishment for <em>G. sepium</em> was nearly 100% at all sites, whereas <em>B. simaruba</em> ranged from 30-50%. <em>Gliricidia sepium</em> stakes developed more rapidly and attained greater cover than <em>B. simaruba</em>. Dry season planting may increase the establishment success of both species. Lastly, greater initial stake height and diameter at breast height each resulted in greater crown development for <em>G. sepium</em>. The use of living fence species as a restorational tool has been overlooked. Aside from the advantages of planting tree species vegetatively, species can act as seed recruitment foci by attracting seed dispersers and provide shade to improve microclimatic conditions for seedling establishment. The technique described is simple and could have broad application throughout tropical regions.