Ecosystem services of Phragmites in North America with emphasis on habitat functionsIn North America, Phragmites australis (common reed) has generally been regarded as a weed to be controlled. This paper shows that Phragmites-dominated vegetation provides important non-habitat ecosystem services (e.g., carbon sequestration, water quality maintenance) in proportion to its biomass, and many habitat functions for other organisms that vary depending on characteristics of the vegetation and surrounding landscape. Phragmites has both detrimental and beneficial functions; therefore decision-makers must clarify their management goals and understand the local situation. Extensive dense Phragmites may be managed to optimize ecosystem services by partial removal of biomass for a bioenergy feedstock. Phragmites australis (common reed) is widespread in North America, with native and non-native haplotypes. Many ecologists and wetland managers have considered P. australis a weed with little value to the native biota or human society. I document important ecosystem services of Phragmites including support for many common and rare species of plants and animals. This paper is based on an extensive review of the ecology and natural history literature, discussions with field workers, and observations in 13 US states and one Canadian province during the past 40 years. Phragmites sequesters nutrients, heavy metals and carbon, builds and stabilizes soils, and creates self-maintaining vegetation in urban and industrial areas where many plants do not thrive. These non-habitat ecosystem services are proportional to biomass and productivity. Phragmites was widely used by Native Americans for many purposes; the most important current direct use is for the treatment of wastes. Most of the knowledge of non-habitat ecosystem services is based on studies of P. australis haplotype M (an Old World haplotype). Phragmites also has habitat functions for many organisms. These functions depend on the characteristics of the landscape, habitat, Phragmites stand, species using Phragmites and life history element. The functions that Phragmites provides for many species are optimal at lower levels of Phragmites biomass and extent of stands. Old World Phragmites, contrary to many published statements, as well as North American native Phragmites, provide valuable ecosystem services including products for human use and habitat functions for other organisms. Phragmites stands may need management (e.g. thinning, fragmentation, containment or removal) to create or maintain suitable habitat for desired species of animals and plants.