Does the house mouse self-regulate its density in maturing sorghum and wheat crops?.<ol><li>One of the central questions in population ecology and management is: what regulates population growth? House mouse <em>Mus domesticus </em>L. populations erupt occasionally in grain-growing regions in Australia. This study aimed to determine whether mouse populations are self-regulated in maturing sorghum and wheat crops. This was assessed by examining food supply to mice (i.e. yield) and the relationship between initial mouse density (<em>D</em><sub>I</sub>) and density at harvest (<em>D</em><sub>H</sub>). Eight levels of <em>D</em><sub>I</sub> ranging from 89 to 5555 mice ha<sup>-;1</sup> were introduced to sorghum at the hard dough stage and to wheat crops at the milky stage in mouse-proofed pens. <em>D</em><sub>H</sub> was measured by trapping out mice 49 days after the introduction.</li><li>There were at least 3·11 tonnes ha<sup>-;1</sup> of wheat and 1·85 tonnes ha<sup>-;1</sup> of sorghum grain available for mice at harvest. The estimated relationship between <em>D</em><sub>I</sub> and <em>D</em><sub>H</sub> was asymptotic exponential, with <em>D</em><sub>H</sub> initially increasing almost linearly with <em>D</em><sub>I</sub>. When <em>D</em><sub>I</sub> was above <em>c</em>. 500 mice ha<sup>-;1</sup>, <em>D</em><sub>H</sub> increased asymptotically with <em>D</em><sub>I</sub> and then saturated at <em>c</em>. 3100 mice ha<sup>-;1</sup>. The asymptotic increases in and saturation of <em>D</em><sub>H</sub> was due partly to more young mice being born and recruited in pens treated with lower levels of <em>D</em><sub>I</sub>.</li><li>Our findings indicated that mouse densities in maturing cereal crops were driven by a numerical response of mice to the abundant supply of grain, modified by some unknown self-regulation mechanism that reduced this numerical response of mice at higher mouse densities. The mechanism was possibly spacing behaviours. Although the nature of this self-regulation mechanism is not known our model is, nevertheless, useful for predicting increases and eruptions in mouse population density in sorghum and wheat crops. Understanding the nature of this mechanism may provide insights into population processes that can be exploited in controlling mice in cereal crops.</li></ol>