Spatial associations, size-distance relationships and population structure of two dominant life forms in a semiarid enclave of the Venezuelan AndesThe role of three thorny legume species as nurse plants and competitive relationships with columnar cacti were evaluated in a semiarid enclave of the Venezuelan Andes. Abundance and size of three columnar cacti species (Stenocereus griseus, Cereus repandus and Pilosocereus tillianus) under isolated shrubs of three thorny legumes species (Prosopis juliflora, Acacia farnesiana and A. macracantha) were recorded and compared with open areas. Using size-distance data we inferred the intensity of intra- and interspecific competition between both life forms in a "cardonal" (xeric zone) and "espinar" (mesic zone) of the enclave. Sixty-one columnar cacti were found beneath the three thorny legume species (92%), while only 5 cactus individuals were found in open areas (8%). Comparison of observed and expected number of cactus individuals shows that S. griseus and C. repandus are significantly associated with isolated shrubs of A. farnesiana and A. macracantha. Although P. juliflora contributed more than 40% of the total legume plant cover, the number of columnar cacti under its isolated shrubs was significantly lower than would be expected by chance. In all, 19 of 21 possible plant-plant combinations between and within columnar cacti and legume shrubs were recorded (espinar: 18, cardonal: 13, common combinations: 12). In both zones, intra- and interspecific combinations among columnar cacti species were relatively high (positive correlation between the sum of neighbour plant sizes and the distances separating them). Our results strongly suggest, at least for case of S. griseus and C. repandus, that these columnar cacti species require nurse plants for their establishment. The results on interference need still support from further research. We discuss the effects of plant-plant positive interactions on natural regeneration of these columnar cacti.