Wildfire temperature and land cover modeling using hyperspectral dataWildfire temperature retrieval commonly uses measured radiance from a middle infrared channel and a thermal infrared channel to separate fire emitted radiance from the background emitted radiance. Emitted radiance at shorter wavelengths, including the shortwave infrared, is measurable for objects above a temperature of 500 K. The spectral shape and radiance of thermal emission within the shortwave infrared can be used to retrieve fire temperature. Airborne Visible Infrared Imaging Spectrometer (AVIRIS) data were used to estimate fire properties and background properties for the 2003 Simi Fire in Southern California, USA. A spectral library of emitted radiance endmembers corresponding to a temperature range of 500–1500 K was created using the MODTRAN radiative transfer model. A second spectral library of reflected solar radiance endmembers, corresponding to four vegetation types and two non-vegetated surfaces, was created using image spectra selected by minimum endmember average root mean square error (RMSE). The best fit combination of an emitted radiance endmember and a reflected solar radiance endmember was found for each spectrum in the AVIRIS scene. Spectra were subset to reduce the effects of variable column water vapor and smoke contamination over the fire. The best fit models were used to produce maps of fire temperature, fire fractional area, background land cover, land cover fraction, and RMSE. The highest fire temperatures were found along the fire front, and lower fire temperatures were found behind the fire front. Saturation of shortwave infrared channels limited modeling of the highest fire temperatures. Spectral similarity of land cover endmembers and smoke impacted the accuracy of modeled land cover. Sensitivity analysis of modeled fire temperatures revealed that the range of temperatures modeled within 5% of minimum RMSE was smallest between 750 and 950 K. Hyperspectral modeling of wildfire temperature and fuels has potential application for fire monitoring and modeling.