Strontium isotopes in tap water from the coterminous USAStrontium isotope analysis has proven useful in geo-location investigations of organic and inorganic materials and may complement the region-of-origin information provided by hydrogen and oxygen stable isotope analysis. In this study, we analyzed 99 drinking (tap) water samples collected from 95 municipal water systems across the USA to investigate the potential that 87Sr/86Sr can be used to provenance samples from managed hydrological systems. Results from a leaching and exchange experiment demonstrated that non-ideal storage conditions did not prohibit Sr isotope analysis of previously archived water samples stored in glass. Tap water samples were analyzed via multi-collector inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry, which was preceded by a novel, automated, in-line Sr purification method. Measured tap water 87Sr/86Sr was compared to expected 87Sr/86Sr for collection location, which was predicted using four published isotope landscape (isoscape) models: age of bedrock (bedrock model), age plus major and minor lithology of bedrock (major bedrock model), weathering of Sr from rock (local water model), and surface fluxes within watershed (catchment model). The geologic history of the geographic regions represented by collected tap waters was diverse and we therefore expected significant covariation in measured and modeled 87Sr/86Sr values. Tap water exhibited large ranges in both Sr concentration (0–1.9 mg/L) and 87Sr/86Sr (0.7037–0.7320). Measured tap water 87Sr/86Sr ratios were significantly and positively correlated with predictions based on bedrock and catchment models. However, these bedrock and catchment models explained relatively little of the tap water Sr isotopic variation (10% and 17%, respectively), suggesting that the factors affecting drinking water 87Sr/86Sr are complex and more numerous than the variables included in current water models. This could be due to the reliance of some municipal water systems on groundwater, rather than surficial water sources; the natural movement of water across distinct geologic gradients; and/or the managed transport of water from source to point-of-use. Although published isoscape models for predicting Sr isotopic variation within the continental USA are reasonable approaches for estimating surface water 87Sr/86Sr, additional efforts are needed to develop a prediction model specifically for tap water 87Sr/86Sr.