Carbon storage and turnover, and respiratory activity, in the litter and soil of an old-growth southern beech (Nothofagus) forestSoil and litter carbon pools and turnover, and their relationship to forest floor respiratory activity, were estimated in a lowland old-growth beech (Nothofagus) forest in New Zealand. Although the soils varied spatially over the site, their morphological, chemical and some physical properties were characteristic of spodosols. Two profiles representing the range of soils were analysed by horizon for: C, C-14 and a number of chemical and physical properties. C in the fine litter and mineral soil, in the most representative soil at the site, was ca 3.0 and 15.8 kg m-2 respectively. About 0.65 kg CO2-C m-2 was respired annually from the forest floor, based on a simple exponential model relating CO2 efflux measured by a chamber technique, and soil temperature values. Temperature mainly controlled CO2 production by litter and soil because the site was well supplied with rainfall throughout the year. Annual transfers of C from the litter to the atmosphere and the soil, and mean residence times for C in the litter (ca 12 yr) and soils were estimated from the distribution of C-14 using a 'bomb' radiocarbon model. A major source of soil C was root turnover, based on fine litterfall measurements and modelling of total C input. Root turnover and woody debris together represented 64% of the total C input of ca 0.8 kg m-2 yr-1 to the soil. Live root respiration, estimated experimentally and from a relationship between total root C allocation and litterfall, was ca 23% of the forest floor respiration. An imbalance of ca 0.35 kg C m-2 was observed in the annual soil C cycle, assuming steady-state conditions. Errors in estimating C fluxes from a combination of direct measurements and models, and underestimation of forest floor respiration, were probably responsible for this imbalance. Modelled mean residence times for soil C ranged from 76 to 207 yr, and resulted from widely different amounts of 'inert organic matter' being present in the upper 23 cm of the soils. A long history of tree overturn is the most likely cause of this concentration of recalcitrant C near the soil surface, and may explain the longer C storage time of soils developed under beech in New Zealand compared to those developed under native grassland.