Using Gall Wasps on Oaks to Test Broad Ecological Concepts.Planning conservation of insect herbivores requires knowing what needs to be conserved and developing a set of predictor variables that aid management. We conducted a state-wide survey to examine the species richness of gall wasps (Hymenoptera: Cynipidae) on six oak species dominant in the threatened scrub-oak vegetation in peninsular Florida. Eighty-eight cynipid species were recorded; 23 were new species to Florida (a 35% increase), including 17 species new to science and 6 species newly recorded in the state. The cynipid species represented 68% of cynipids of Florida, on only 24% of oak species sampled. This fauna represents a hotspot of richness, justifying conservation initiatives in scrub-oak habitat and throughout the state. We derived predictor variables from general ecological concepts: (1) the theory of island biogeography that insect species richness increases as host plant geographic area increases and as local abundance increases, (2) the plant-architecture hypothesis that insect species richness increases with increased plant size, and (3) phytochemical patterns in leaves, including nutrients and digestibility reducers predicting suitability for insect herbivores. Concepts 1 and 2, developed for large scales and species numbers, were tested at smaller scales relevant to much conservation research and management. A stepwise multiple regression including all predictor variables accounted for 99% of the variance in cynipid species richness with three variables: foliar hemicellulose concentration (81%), host geographic area (16%), and tree height (2%). The trends were negative, however, and opposite to those predicted by concepts 1 and 2. Ecological theory was not applicable to discovery of predictors of cynipid species richness on six oak species. Thus, we promote caution in applying ecological theory to a narrow set of species without specific testing of how patterns conform to theoretical predictions.