Soil-surface carbon dioxide efflux and microbial biomass in relation to tree density 13 years after a stand replacing fire in a lodgepole pine ecosystemThe effects of fire on soil-surface carbon dioxide (CO2 ) efflux, F (S) , and microbial biomass carbon, C (mic) , were studied in a wildland setting by examining 13-year-old postfire stands of lodgepole pine differing in tree density (< 500 to > 500 000 trees ha(-1) ) in Yellowstone National Park (YNP). In addition, young stands were compared to mature lodgepole pine stands (similar to110-year-old) in order to estimate ecosystem recovery 13 years after a stand replacing fire. Growing season F (S) increased with tree density in young stands (1.0 mumol CO2 m(-2) s(-1) in low-density stands, 1.8 mumol CO2 m(-2) s(-1) in moderate-density stands and 2.1 mumol CO2 m(-2) s(-1) in high-density stands) and with stand age (2.7 mumol CO2 m(-2) s(-1) in mature stands). Microbial biomass carbon in young stands did not differ with tree density and ranged from 0.2 to 0.5 mg C g(-1) dry soil over the growing season; C (mic) was significantly greater in mature stands (0.5-0.8 mg C g(-1) dry soil). Soil-surface CO2 efflux in young stands was correlated with biotic variables (above-ground, below-ground and microbial biomass), but not with abiotic variables (litter and mineral soil C and N content, bulk density and soil texture). Microbial biomass carbon was correlated with below-ground plant biomass and not with soil carbon and nitrogen, indicating that plant activity controls not only root respiration, but C (mic) pools and overall F (S) rates as well. These findings support recent studies that have demonstrated the prevailing importance of plants in controlling rates of F (S) and suggest that decomposition of older, recalcitrant soil C pools in this ecosystem is relatively unimportant 13 years after a stand replacing fire. Our results also indicate that realistic predictions and modeling of terrestrial C cycling must account for the variability in tree density and stand age that exists across the landscape as a result of natural disturbances.