Detecting taxonomic signal in an under-utilised character system: geometric morphometrics of the forcipular coxae of Scutigeromorpha (Chilopoda)Abstract To date, the forcipules have played almost no role in determining the systematics of scutigeromorph centipedes though in his 1974 review of taxonomic characters Markus Würmli suggested some potentially informative variation might be found in these structures. Geometric morphometric analyses were used to evaluate Würmli’s suggestion, specifically to determine whether the shape of the forcipular coxa contains information useful for diagnosing species. The geometry of the coxae of eight species from the genera Sphendononema, Scutigera, Dendrothereua, Thereuonema, Thereuopoda, Thereuopodina, Allothereua and Parascutigera was characterised using a combination of landmark- and semi-landmark-based sampling methods to summarize group-specific morphological variation. Canonical variates analysis of shape data characterizing the forcipular coxae indicates that these structures differ significantly between taxa at various systematic levels. Models calculated for the canonical variates space facilitate identification of the main shape differences between genera, including overall length/width, curvature of the external coxal margin, and the extent to which the coxofemoral condyle projects laterally. Jackknifed discriminant function analysis demonstrates that forcipular coxal training-set specimens were assigned to correct species in 61% of cases on average, the most accurate assignments being those of Parascutigera (Parascutigera guttata) and Thereuonema (Thereuonema microstoma). The geographically widespread species Thereuopoda longicornis, Sphendononema guildingii, Scutigera coleoptrata, and Dendrothereua linceci exhibit the least diagnostic coxae in our dataset. Thereuopoda longicornis populations sampled from different parts of East and Southeast Asia were significantly discriminated from each other, suggesting that, in this case, extensive synonymy may be obscuring diagnosable inter-species coxal shape differences.