GRAZER TRAITS, COMPETITION, AND CARBON SOURCES TO A HEADWATER-STREAM FOOD WEB.We investigated the effect of grazing by a dominant invertebrate grazer (the caddisfly <em>Glossosoma penitum</em>) on the energy sources used by other consumers in a headwater-stream food web. Stable isotope studies in small, forested streams in northern California have shown that <em>G. penitum</em> larvae derive most of their carbon from algae, despite low algal standing crops. We hypothesized that the caddisfly competes with other primary consumers (including mayflies) for algal food and increases their reliance on terrestrial detritus. Because <em>Glossosoma</em> are abundant and defended from predators by stone cases, their consumption of algal energy may reduce its transfer up the food chain. We removed <em>Glossosoma</em> (natural densities >1000 caddisflies/m<sup>2</sup>) from five (4 m<sup>2</sup>) stream sections during the summer of 2000 and measured responses of algae, invertebrate primary consumers, and invertebrate predators. The treatment reduced <em>Glossosoma</em> biomass by 80–90%. We observed a doubling in chlorophyll <em>a</em> per area in sections with reduced <em>Glossosoma</em> abundance and aggregative increases in the biomass of undefended primary consumers. Heptageniid mayfly larvae consumed more algae (as measured by stable carbon isotope ratios and gut content analysis) in caddisfly removal plots at the end of the 60-day experiment, although not after one month. We did not see isotopic evidence of increased algal carbon in invertebrate predators, however. Patterns of caddisfly and mayfly diets in the surrounding watershed suggested that mayfly diets are variable and include algae and detrital carbon in variable proportions, but scraping caddisflies consume primarily algae. Caddisfly and mayfly diets are more similar in larger, more productive streams where the mayflies assimilate more algae. Isotopic analysis, in combination with measurements of macroinvertebrate abundance and biomass in unmanipulated plots, suggested that a substantial portion of the invertebrate community (>50% of biomass) was supported, at least partially, by local algal carbon during midsummer. These data suggest that algae may be more important to community dynamics in headwater streams than their relatively low productivity would suggest. Through their high densities and relative invulnerability to predation, armored grazers may also affect community structure and flow of algal and detrital carbon in headwater streams.