ATMOSPHERIC CO2 AND O3 ALTER THE FLOW OF 15N IN DEVELOPING FOREST ECOSYSTEMS.Anthropogenic O<sub>3</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub>-induced declines in soil N availability could counteract greater plant growth in a CO<sub>2</sub>-enriched atmosphere, thereby reducing net primary productivity (NPP) and the potential of terrestrial ecosystems to sequester anthropogenic CO<sub>2</sub>. Presently, it is uncertain how increasing atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> will alter plant N demand and the acquisition of soil N by plants as well as the microbial supply of N from soil organic matter. To address this uncertainty, we initiated an ecosystem-level <sup>15</sup>N tracer experiment at the Rhinelander (Wisconsin, USA) free air CO<sub>2</sub>-O<sub>3</sub> enrichment (FACE) facility to understand how projected increases in atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> alter the distribution and flow of N in developing northern temperate forests. Tracer amounts of <sup>15</sup>NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> were applied to the forest floor of developing <em>Populus tremuloides</em> and <em>P. tremuloides–Betula papyrifera</em> communities that have been exposed to factorial CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> treatments for seven years. One year after isotope addition, both forest communities exposed to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> obtained greater amounts of <sup>15</sup>N (29%) and N (40%) from soil, despite no change in soil N availability or plant N-use efficiency. As such, elevated CO<sub>2</sub> increased the ability of plants to exploit soil for N, through the development of a larger root system. Conversely, elevated O<sub>3</sub> decreased the amount of <sup>15</sup>N (−15%) and N (−29%) in both communities, a response resulting from lower rates of photosynthesis, decreases in growth, and smaller root systems that acquired less soil N. Neither CO<sub>2</sub> nor O<sub>3</sub> altered the amount of N or <sup>15</sup>N recovery in the forest floor, microbial biomass, or soil organic matter. Moreover, we observed no interaction between CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> on the amount of N or <sup>15</sup>N in any ecosystem pool, suggesting that O<sub>3</sub> could exert a negative effect regardless of CO<sub>2</sub> concentration. In a CO<sub>2</sub>-enriched atmosphere, greater belowground growth and a more thorough exploitation of soil for growth-limiting N is an important mechanism sustaining the enhancement of NPP in developing forests (0–8 years following establishment). However, as CO<sub>2</sub> accumulates in the Earth's atmosphere, future O<sub>3</sub> concentrations threaten to diminish the enhancement of plant growth, decrease plant N acquisition, and lessen the storage of anthropogenic C in temperate forests.