Seasonal variation in carbon accumulation by a high latitude forest ecosystemThis study is concerned with interactions between a boreal forest ecosystem and the atmosphere, measured in an old-growth muskeg ecosystem (predominantly black spruce Picea mariana) in the BOREAS Southern study area (SSA), Saskatchewan, Canada, during 1996. We focus on efforts to understand the net ecosystem exchange of CO2 in terms of the sub-component fluxes operating within the ecosystem. The component fluxes of primary interest are photosynthesis, respiration and evapotranspiration of foliage, and the efflux of CO2 from the forest floor. Woody biomass respiration is also considered. Methodologies were developed to study these fluxes on a continuous basis. An "open" system gas exchange chamber for measuring soil CO2 efflux was designed that eliminated the major problems that have been associated with this methodology in the past. The system was used to investigate temporal and spatial variation in soil CO2 efflux at the field site. A scheme that integrated this temporal and spatial variation was used to estimate the CO2 efflux from the forest floor for an entire year. Seasonally, soil CO2 efflux varied between low, but positive, rates before the springtime thaw and after the winter freeze, to rates as high as 14 mu mol m(-2) s(-1) in late summer. The total carbon efflux from the soil during the measurement period varied from point to point between 152 and 1310 g (C) m(-2) yr(-1), the total soil carbon efflux for the whole ecosystem over the measurement period was estimated to be 790 g (C) m(-2) yr(-1). A "branch bag" methodology for studying the gas exchange of whole tree branches was developed and operated for an entire growing season. Daily maximum photosynthetic rates were zero at the beginning and end of the year and reached a maximum of approximate to 6 mu mol m(-2) s(-1). Night-time respiration reached a maximum rate of approximate to 0.8 mu mol g(-1) s(-1). Total daytime carbon uptake during the measurement period ranged from 12.6 to 22.6 mol m(-2) (leaf area) yr(-1) for individual branches and total night-time loss ranged from 1.98 to 2.27 mol kg(-1) (dry weight) yr(-1). Total net photosynthesis for the canopy during the measurement period was estimated to be 919 g (C) m(-2) (ground area) yr(-1). Above-ground autotrophic respiration in woody tissue during the measurement period was estimated to be 89 g (C) m(-2) y(-1). In 1996, the estimated net carbon uptake during the measurement period for the ecosystem was 222 g (C) m(-2) yr(-1). This was the small difference between a large photosynthetic influx and a large respiratory efflux. The carbon source/sink strength of this ecosystem is thus very sensitive to changes in environmental conditions, and the boreal region may be the location of a large positive feedback on global climate change.