Influence of precipitation on demographics of northern bobwhites in southern TexasNorthern bobwhite (Colinus virginianus) populations in southwestern rangelands are influenced by precipitation; populations increase during relatively wet periods and decrease during drought. Understanding the demographic responses of bobwhites to fluctuations in precipitation might provide a basis for identifying mechanisms responsible for the phenomenon. We compared 10 population variables (bobwhite survival, nesting-season length, nest success, hen success, percent hens nesting and renesting, nesting rate, percent juveniles in fall harvest sample (Nov-Feb), clutch size, and egg hatchability) between a dry (Sep 2000–Aug 2001; 51 cm precipitation) and wet period (Sep 2002–Aug 2003; 93 cm precipitation) in Brooks County, Texas. We monitored radiomarked bob-whites on 3 sites during the dry (n=263 bobwhites) and wet period (n=191 bobwhites) to obtain estimates of survival and reproductive effort. Bobwhite survival curves differed between the dry period (0.30±0.04; ŜS±SE, n=102 bobwhites) and wet period (0.60± 0.06; n=71 bobwhites; P ≤ 0.001) during fall-winter (Sep-Feb). A lower proportion of hens nested during the dry period (95% CI: 52.6±22.5 %; n=19 hens) compared to the wet period (100%; n=15 hens). Of hens that nested, the dry period exhibited a lower nesting rate (95% CI: 1.2±0.3 nests/hen) compared to the wet period (95% CI: 2.3±0.5 nests/hen). The dry period also experienced a shorter nesting season (69 days) compared to wet period (159 days). Lastly, percent juveniles (Nov-Feb) was lower during the dry period (95% CI: 69.3±0.3 %; n=740 harvested bobwhites) compared to wet period (95% CI: 78.3±2.1%; n=1,415 harvested bobwhites). Our field study highlights 4 demographic variables (i.e., survival, percentage of hens nesting, nesting rate, and nesting-season length) that warrant further research to identify causal factors responsible for the boom-and-bust phenomenon in bobwhites. Further, our data suggest that drought negatively impacts bobwhite reproductive effort such that harvest should be reduced or ceased during drought (e.g., <50 cm annual precipitation).