Long-Term Dynamics of Production, Respiration, and Net CO2 Exchange in Two Sagebrush-Steppe Ecosystems.We present a synthesis of long-term measurements of CO<sub>2</sub> exchange in 2 US Intermountain West sagebrush-steppe ecosystems. The locations near Burns, Oregon (1995-2001), and Dubois, Idaho (1996-2001), are part of the AgriFlux Network of the Agricultural Research Service, United States Department of Agriculture. Measurements of net ecosystem CO<sub>2</sub> exchange (<em>F</em><sub><em>c</em></sub>) during the growing season were continuously recorded at flux towers using the Bowen ratio-energy balance technique. Data were partitioned into gross primary productivity (<em>P</em><sub><em>g</em></sub>) and ecosystem respiration (<em>R</em><sub><em>e</em></sub>) using the light-response function method. Wintertime fluxes were measured during 1999/2000 and 2000/2001 and used to model fluxes in other winters. Comparison of daytime respiration derived from light-response analysis with nighttime tower measurements showed close correlation, with daytime respiration being on the average higher than nighttime respiration. Maxima of <em>P</em><sub><em>g</em></sub> and <em>R</em><sub><em>e</em></sub> at Burns were both 20 g CO<sub>2</sub>·m<sup>−2</sup>·d<sup>−1</sup> in 1998. Maxima of <em>P</em><sub><em>g</em></sub> and <em>R</em><sub><em>e</em></sub> at Dubois were 37 and 35 g CO<sub>2</sub>·m<sup>−2</sup>·d<sup>−1</sup>, respectively, in 1997. Mean annual gross primary production at Burns was 1 111 (range 475-1 715) g CO<sub>2</sub>·m<sup>−2</sup>·y<sup>−1</sup> or about 30% lower than that at Dubois (1 602, range 963-2 162 g CO<sub>2</sub>·m<sup>−2</sup>·y<sup>−1</sup>). Across the years, both ecosystems were net sinks for atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> with a mean net ecosystem CO<sub>2</sub> exchange of 82 g CO<sub>2</sub>·m<sup>−2</sup>·y<sup>−1</sup> at Burns and 253 g CO<sub>2</sub>·m<sup>−2</sup>·y<sup>−1</sup> at Dubois, but on a yearly basis either site could be a C sink or source, mostly depending on precipitation timing and amount. Total annual precipitation is not a good predictor of carbon sequestration across sites. Our results suggest that <em>F</em><sub><em>c</em></sub> should be partitioned into <em>P</em><sub><em>g</em></sub> and <em>R</em><sub><em>e</em></sub> components to allow prediction of seasonal and yearly dynamics of CO<sub>2</sub> fluxes.