Use of Long-Term Monitoring Data to Evaluate Benzene, MTBE, and TBA Plume Behavior in Groundwater at Retail Gasoline SitesAbstractLong-term groundwater monitoring data for 48 retail gasoline sites were analyzed to define the characteristics of affected groundwater plumes containing benzene, methyl tert-butyl ether (MTBE), and tert-butyl alcohol (TBA). Results of this analysis were used to determine the observed range and statistical distribution of current plume lengths, plume stability conditions, constituent concentration trends and attenuation rates, and the remediation timeframe for this population of sites. The goal of this evaluation was to characterize plume behavior as observed across a variety of hydrogeologic settings, on the basis of detailed groundwater monitoring records, rather than to define the site-specific factors controlling plume behavior. The results indicate that MTBE plumes in groundwater underlying a majority of these underground storage tank sites that were monitored for five years or longer (1) have significantly diminished in concentration over time, (2) are comparable in length to benzene plumes, (3) are, like benzene plumes, principally stable or shrinking in size and concentration, and (4) are on track to achieve remedial goals within a timeframe comparable to or faster than that of benzene plumes. At these same sites, TBA plumes were found to be comparable to benzene and MTBE plumes in terms of plume length. However, whereas most TBA plumes are also stable or shrinking, the percentage of TBA plumes that are currently stable or shrinking (68%) is less than that for benzene plumes (95%) or MTBE plumes (90%), likely reflecting the temporary build-up of TBA concentrations in groundwater attributable to methyl tert-butyl ether (MTBE) biodegradation. Nevertheless, overall trends for TBA concentrations in groundwater indicate that TBA is attenuating at rates comparable to benzene and MTBE and can be expected to meet applicable remediation goals in a similar timeframe as the other gasoline constituents.