Estimating Siberian timber volume using MODIS and ICESat/GLASGeosciences Laser Altimeter System (GLAS) space LiDAR data are used to attribute a MODerate resolution Imaging Spectrometer (MODIS) 500 m land cover classification of a 10° latitude by 12° longitude study area in south-central Siberia. Timber volume estimates are generated for 16 forest classes, i.e., four forest cover types×four canopy density classes, across this 811,414 km2 area and compared with a ground-based regional volume estimate. Two regional GLAS/MODIS timber volume products, one considering only those pulses falling on slopes ≤10° and one utilizing all GLAS pulses regardless of slope, are generated. Using a two-phase(GLAS-ground plot) sampling design, GLAS/MODIS volumes average 163.4±11.8 m3/ha across all 16 forest classes based on GLAS pulses on slopes ≤10° and 171.9±12.4 m3/ha considering GLAS shots on all slopes. The increase in regional GLAS volume per-hectare estimates as a function of increasing slope most likely illustrate the effects of vertical waveform expansion due to the convolution of topography with the forest canopy response. A comparable, independent, ground-based estimate is 146 m3/ha [Shepashenko, D., Shvidenko, A., and Nilsson, S. (1998). Phytomass (live biomass) and carbon of Siberian forests. Biomass and Bioenergy, 14, 21–31], a difference of 11.9% and 17.7% for GLAS shots on slopes ≤10° and all GLAS shots regardless of slope, respectively. A ground-based estimate of total volume for the entire study area, 7.46×109 m3, is derived using Shepashenko et al.'s per-hectare volume estimate in conjunction with forest area derived from a 1990 forest map [Grasia, M.G. (ed.). (1990). Forest Map of USSR. Soyuzgiproleskhoz, Moscow, RU. Scale: 1:2,500,000]. The comparable GLAS/MODIS estimate is 7.38×109 m3, a difference of less than 1.1%. Results indicate that GLAS data can be used to attribute digital land cover maps to estimate forest resources over subcontinental areas encompassing hundreds of thousands of square kilometers.