Effects of Mycorrhizae and Nontarget Organisms on Restoration of a Seasonal Tropical Forest in Quintana Roo, Mexico: Factors Limiting Tree Establishment.We initiated a study of the effects of mycorrhizal fungal community composition on the restoration of tropical dry seasonal forest trees. Tree seedlings were planted in a severely burned experimental site (1995 fire) during the growing season of 1998 at the El Ed&eacute;n Ecological Reserve, in north Quintana Roo, Mexico. Seedlings of <em>Leucaena leucocephala</em>, <em>Guazuma ulmifolia</em>, <em>Caesalpinia violacea</em>, <em>Piscidia piscipula</em>, <em>Gliricidia sepium</em>, and <em>Cochlospermum vitifolium</em> were germinated in steam-sterilized soil and either remained uninoculated (nonmycorrhizal at transplanting) or were inoculated with mycorrhizal fungi in soils from early-seral (recently burned) or late-seral (mature forest) inoculum. Inoculum from the early-seral soil was largely <em>Glomus</em> spp., whereas a diverse community of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi were reintroduced from the mature forest including species of <em>Scutellospora</em>, <em>Gigaspora</em>, <em>Glomus</em>, Sclerocystis, and <em>Acaulospora</em>. Plants grew better when associated with the mature forest inoculum, unlike a previous experiment in which plants grew taller with the early-seral inoculum. Reasons for the different responses include a less-intense burn resulting in more residual organic matter. In addition to mycorrhizal responses, plants were severely affected by deer browsing. One tree species, <em>C. vitifolium</em> found in the region but not in the reserve, was eliminated by a resident fungal facultative pathogen. Several practical conclusions for restoration can be made. The common nursery practice of soil sterilization may be detrimental because it eliminates beneficial mycorrhizal fungi; species not native to the site may not survive because they may not be adapted to the local pathogens; and herbivory can be severe depending on the landscape context of the restoration.