Organic matter stabilization in a Xanthic Ferralsol of the central Amazon as affected by single trees: chemical characterization of density, aggregate, and particle size fractionsNot only the amount of organic carbon in soil is important for soil organic matter (SOM) stability, but also its physical and chemical properties. The appropriate technique for the assessment of SOM dynamics can vary between soil types, and information about this is lacking for Ferralsols of the central Amazon basin. First, this work identified SOM pools which are sensitive to land-use changes on the terra firme in the central Amazon. In a second step, the effects of single trees on SOM properties were evaluated in a mixed tree crop plantation in comparison to secondary and primary forest sites. Thus, the processes of organic matter stabilization could be studied in the highly aggregated soils. A combination of aggregate and density fractionation was found to be most suitable for physical SOM characterization. The particulate organic matter (POM, density less than 1.6 Mg m−3) varied by one order of magnitude between sites and could be used as a sensitive indicator of land-use changes. Aggregate stability was not related to SOM contents or bulk SOM properties. The incorporation of plant material into stable SOM, however, was enhanced by aggregation. Among aggregate separates, the fraction, 0.25–0.5 mm, showed single-tree effects the most. SOM replenishment was higher under tree species with low quality litter, i.e. high C-to-N and polyphenol-to-N ratios. High quality litter from a leguminous ground cover, however, showed low soil nitrogen and carbon replenishment but increased nitrogen concentrations in light fractions. Litter with a high quality may improve soil nitrogen availability but not amounts of total SOM, which could only be shown for low quality litter. The results indicate the importance of aggregation and POM dynamics for SOM stabilization in the studied Xanthic Ferralsols of the central Amazon basin.