Initial cultivation of a temperate-region soil immediately accelerates aggregate turnover and CO2 and N2O fluxes.The immediate effects of tillage on protected soil C and N pools and on trace gas emissions from soils at precultivation levels of native C remain largely unknown. We measured the response to cultivation of CO<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O emissions and associated environmental factors in a previously uncultivated U.S. Midwest Alfisol with C concentrations that were indistinguishable from those in adjacent late successional forests on the same soil type (3.2%). Within 2 days of initial cultivation in 2002, tillage significantly (<em>P</em>=0.001, <em>n</em>=4) increased CO<sub>2</sub> fluxes from 91 to 196 mg CO<sub>2</sub>-C m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup> and within the first 30 days higher fluxes because of cultivation were responsible for losses of 85 g CO<sub>2</sub>-C m<sup>-;2</sup>. Additional daily C losses were sustained during a second and third year of cultivation of the same plots at rates of 1.9 and 1.0 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> day<sup>-;1</sup>, respectively. Associated with the CO<sub>2</sub> responses were increased soil temperature, substantially reduced soil aggregate size (mean weight diameter decreased 35% within 60 days), and a reduction in the proportion of intraaggregate, physically protected light fraction organic matter. Nitrous oxide fluxes in cultivated plots increased 7.7-fold in 2002, 3.1-fold in 2003, and 6.7-fold in 2004 and were associated with increased soil NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-;</sup> concentrations, which approached 15 &mu;g N g<sup>-;1</sup>. Decreased plant N uptake immediately after tillage, plus increased mineralization rates and fivefold greater nitrifier enzyme activity, likely contributed to increased NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-;</sup> concentrations. Our results demonstrate that initial cultivation of a soil at precultivation levels of native soil C immediately destabilizes physical and microbial processes related to C and N retention in soils and accelerates trace gas fluxes. Policies designed to promote long-term C sequestration may thus need to protect soils from even occasional cultivation in order to preserve sequestered C.