Soil organic matter pools and carbon-protection mechanisms in aggregate classes influenced by surface liming in a no-till systemThe stabilisation of soil organic matter (SOM) is the result of the simultaneous action of three mechanisms: chemical stabilisation, biochemical stabilisation and physical protection. The objectives of this study were (i) to evaluate carbon-protection mechanisms in different SOM pools in soil aggregates and (ii) to identify the association of Ca2 + with total organic carbon (TOC) under the influence of surface liming in a medium-textured Oxisol in a long-term experiment under no-till system (NTS) in southern Brazil (25° 10′ S, 50° 05′ W). The treatments consisted of application of zero or 6 tons ha− 1 of dolomitic lime on the soil surface in 1993 and a reapplication of zero or 3 tons ha− 1 of dolomitic lime in 2000 to plots with or without previous lime application. Soil samples collected at depths of 0–2.5, 2.5–5, 5–10 and 10–20 cm were separated into seven aggregate classes. In each of these classes, TOC, particulate organic carbon (POC) and mineral-associated organic carbon (MAOC) were analysed. The 8–19 mm sized aggregates from the 0–2.5 cm layer were assessed by energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDS) for the elemental analysis of carbon (C) and calcium (Ca). The liming caused an accumulation of TOC in the aggregates, mainly at a depth of 0–2.5 cm. The aggregates from soils treated with lime had a higher mean weight diameter (MWD) that resulted in the accumulation of TOC, especially in the 8–19 mm aggregate class, that was linear and closely related with C input (R2 = 0.99). The proportion of large aggregates in the treatments with lime was closely correlated with the TOC content of the whole sample. The largest dose of lime (9 tons ha− 1) resulted in higher TOC, POC and MAOC values, mainly in the 8–19 mm aggregate class. The elemental analyses for C and Ca revealed similar spectra between them for the surface-liming treatments in the clay fraction found in the centres of the 8–19 mm aggregates. The surface application of lime to NT fields provided greater stability and protection of the intra-aggregate C, presumably due to Ca2 + acting as a cationic bridge between OC and the kaolinite in the clay fraction.