1-Aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid oxidase reaction mechanism and putative post-translational activities of the ACCO proteinACC oxidase (Malus. domestica ACCO1) catalyzes the final step in the biosynthesis of the plant hormone ethylene. ACCO converts 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid(ACC) to ethylene, cyanide, carbon dioxide and water in the presence of ferrous ion, oxygen, ascorbic acid and bicarbonate. Cyanide, a product of the reaction, activates ACCO. Site-directed mutagenesis investigations revealed binding sites for ACC, bicarbonate and ascorbic acid to include; Arg175, Arg244, Ser246, Lys158, Lys292, Arg299 and Phe300. ACCO may be involved in the ethylene signal transduction pathway not directly linked to the ACCO reaction through post-translational modifications. ACCO is subject to auto-phosphorylaton in vitro and promotes phosphorylation of some apple fruit proteins in a ripening-dependent manner. 1-Aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) oxidase (ACCO) catalyses the final step in ethylene biosynthesis converting ACC to ethylene, cyanide, CO2, dehydroascorbate and water with inputs of Fe(II), ascorbate, bicarbonate (as activators) and oxygen. Cyanide activates ACCO. A ‘nest’ comprising several positively charged amino acid residues from the C-terminal α-helix 11 along with Lys158 and Arg299 are proposed as binding sites for ascorbate and bicarbonate to coordinately activate the ACCO reaction. The binding sites for ACC, bicarbonate and ascorbic acid for Malus domestica ACCO1 include Arg175, Arg244, Ser246, Lys158, Lys292, Arg299 and Phe300. Glutamate 297, Phe300 and Glu301 in α-helix 11 are also important for the ACCO reaction. Our proposed reaction pathway incorporates cyanide as an ACCO/Fe(II) ligand after reaction turnover. The cyanide ligand is likely displaced upon binding of ACC and ascorbate to provide a binding site for oxygen. We propose that ACCO may be involved in the ethylene signal transduction pathway not directly linked to the ACCO reaction. ACC oxidase has significant homology with Lycopersicon esculentum cysteine protease LeCp, which functions as a protease and as a regulator of 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid synthase (Acs2) gene expression. ACC oxidase may play a similar role in signal transduction after post-translational processing. ACC oxidase becomes inactivated by fragmentation and apparently has intrinsic protease and transpeptidase activity. ACC oxidase contains several amino acid sequence motifs for putative protein–protein interactions, phosphokinases and cysteine protease. ACC oxidase is subject to autophosphorylaton in vitro and promotes phosphorylation of some apple fruit proteins in a ripening-dependent manner.