Digital mapping for cost-effective and accurate prediction of the depth and carbon stocks in Indonesian peatlandsTropical peatlands have an important role in the global carbon cycle. In order to quantify carbon stock for peatland management and conservation, the knowledge of the spatial distribution of peat and its depth is essential. This paper proposed a cost-effective and accurate methodology for mapping peat depth and carbon stocks in Indonesia. The method, based on the scorpan spatial soil prediction function framework, was tested in Ogan Komering Ilir, South Sumatra and Katingan, Central Kalimantan. A peat hydrological unit, where a peatland is bounded by at least two rivers, is defined as the mapping area or extent. Peat depth is modelled as a function of topography and spatial position. Four machine learning models were evaluated to model and map peat depth: Cubist regression tree, Random Forests (RF), Quantile Regression Forests (QRF) and Artificial Neural Network (ANN). Covariates representing topography and spatial position were derived from the 1 arc-second digital elevation model (DEM) of the Shuttle Radar Topography Mission (SRTM) (resolution of 30.7 m). The spatial models were calibrated from field observations. For model calibration and uncertainty analysis, the k-fold cross validation approach was used. Three models: Cubist, Random Forests, and Quantile Regression Forests models showed excellent accuracies of peat depth prediction for both areas where the coefficient of determination values range from 0.67 to 0.92 and root mean squared error (RMSE) values range from 0.6 to 1.1 m. ANN showed inferior results. In addition, QRF and Cubist showed the best account of the uncertainty of prediction, in terms of percentage of observations that fall within the defined 90% confidence interval. In terms of the best predictor, elevation comes first. Using the spatial prediction functions, peat depth maps along with their 90% confidence interval were generated. The estimated mean carbon stock for Ogan Komering Ilir is 0.474 Gt and for Katingan is 0.123 Gt. Our estimate for Ogan Komering Ilir is twice larger than a previous study because we mapped the peatland hydrological unit, while the previous study only delineated peat domes. Finally, we recommend a sampling method for peat depth mapping using numerical stratification of elevation to cover both the geographical and covariate space. We expect that the combination of an improved sampling strategy, machine learning models, and kriging will increase the accuracy of peat depth mapping.