Micro-topographic patterns unravel controls of soil water and temperature on soil respiration in three Siberian tundra systemsSpatial and temporal patterns of soil respiration rates and controlling factors were investigated in three wet arctic tundra systems. In situ summer season carbon dioxide fluxes were measured across a range of micro-topographic positions in tussock tundra, wet sedge tundra, and low-centre polygonal tundra, at two different latitudes on the Taimyr Peninsular, central Siberia. Measurements were carried out by means of a multi-channel gas exchange system operating in continuous-flow mode. Measured soil respiration rates ranged from 0.1 g CO2-C m(-2) d(-1) to 3.9 g CO2-C m(-2) d(-1) and rate differences between neighbouring sites in the micro-topography (microsites) were larger than those observed between different tundra systems. Statistical analysis identified position of the water table and soil temperature at shallow depths to be common controls of soil respiration rates across all microsites, with each of these two factors explaining high proportions of the observed variations. Modelling of the response of soil respiration to soil temperature and water table for individual microsites revealed systematic differences in the response to the controlling factors between wet and drier microsites. Wet microsites - with a water table position close to the soil surface during most of the summer - showed large soil respiration rate changes with fluctuations of the water table compared to drier microsites. Wet microsites also showed consistently higher temperature sensitivity and a steeper increase of temperature, sensitivity with decreasing temperatures than drier sites. Overall, Q(10) values ranged from 1.2 to 3.4. The concept of substrate availability for determining temperature sensitivity is applied to reconcile these systematic differences. The results highlight that soil respiration rates in wet tundra are foremost controlled by water table and only secondarily by soil temperature. Wet sites have a larger potential for changes in soil respiration rates under changing environmental conditions, compared to drier sites. It is concluded that understanding and forecasting gaseous carbon losses from arctic tundra soils and its implication for ecosystem-scale CO2 fluxes and soil organic matter dynamics require good knowledge about temporal and spatial patterns of soil water conditions. The water status of tundra soils can serve as a control on the temperature sensitivity of soil respiration. (C) 2008 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.