Seed bank dynamics of the desert cactus Opuntia rastrera in two habitats from the Chihuahuan DesertIn desert environments the main input to the seed bank of many succulents is the seed rain through zoochory while high levels of granivory by rodents, birds and ants are the main cause of subsequent losses. In the patchy environment of arid lands the characteristics of both processes may vary between habitats causing differences in the recruitment of new genets. To test this hypothesis we used populations of the desert cactus Opuntia rastrera which has different recruitment rates in the two adjacent habitats where it grows. In Opuntia-dominated scrublands (nopaleras, density ca. 4,000 plants/ha) 1 seedling out of 7,000,000 seeds establish, whereas in grasslands (density ca. 100 plants/ha) this ratio is 1:20,000. From 1996 until 1998 the seed rain, seed removal by granivores and seed abundance in the soil were monitored in both habitats. Results showed striking differences in the dynamics of the seed bank of both habitats. Seed rain was 8.5 times bigger in nopaleras than in grasslands. In nopaleras most seeds were removed by rodents while the quantities of seeds removed by rodents, birds and ants in grasslands were similar. One year after dispersal (the time necessary to break seed dormancy) only 6% of original nopalera seeds and 12% of grassland seeds remained. After germination trials only 1% (ca. 15,000 seeds/ha) and 2% (ca. 2,500 seeds/ha) respectively were viable. These differences in the effective seed bank (6 times bigger in nopaleras) can not explain the differences in genet recruitment (which is several orders of magnitude bigger in grasslands). Apparently the between habitat difference in nurse plant availability and in rodent density (which inflict a strong hervibory upon seedlings) can explain the differences in genet recruitment. It is speculated that this between habitat difference in genet recruitment suggests that the species evolved in less extreme environments (e. g. grasslands) than desert scrublands which, in turn, are colonised due to the singular ability of O. rastrera for vegetative propagation.