Effective population sizes and migration rates in fragmented populations of an endangered insect (Coenagrion mercuriale: Odonata).<ol><li>Effective population sizes (<em>N</em><sub>e</sub>) and migration rates (<em>m</em>) are critical evolutionary parameters that impact on population survival and determine the relative influence of selection and genetic drift. While the parameter <em>m</em> is well-studied in animal populations, <em>N</em><sub>e</sub> remains challenging to measure and consequently is only rarely estimated, particularly in insect taxa.</li><li>We used demographic and genetic methods to estimate <em>N</em><sub>e</sub> and <em>m</em> in a fragmented population of the endangered damselfly <em>Coenagrion mercuriale</em> to better understand the contrast between genetic and field estimates of these parameters and also to identify the spatial scale over which populations may become locally adapted.</li><li>We found a contrast between demographic- and genetic-based estimates of these parameters, with the former apparently providing overestimates of <em>N</em><sub>e</sub>, owing to substantial underestimation of the variance in reproductive success, and the latter overestimating <em>m</em>, because spatial genetic structure is weak.</li><li>The overall <em>N</em><sub>e</sub> of sites within the population network at Beaulieu Heath, the largest <em>C. mercuriale</em> site in the UK, was estimated to vary between approximately 60 and 2700.</li><li>While <em>N</em><sub>e</sub> was not correlated with either the total numbers of adults (<em>N</em>) or the area of habitat, this parameter was always less than <em>N</em>, because of substantial variance in reproductive success. The ratio <em>N</em><sub>e</sub>/<em>N</em> varied between 0·006 and 0·42 and was generally larger in smaller populations, possibly representing some 'genetic compensation'.</li><li>From a simple genetic model and these data on <em>N</em><sub>e</sub> and <em>m</em>, it seems that populations of <em>C. mercuriale</em> have the potential to respond to localized spatial variation in selection and this would need to be considered for future genetic management of this endangered species.</li></ol>