Basal rates of soil respiration are correlated with photosynthesis in a mixed temperate forest.Many field studies have demonstrated that soil temperature explains most of the temporal variation in soil respiration (<em>SR</em>). However, there is increasing evidence to suggest that <em>SR</em> is also influenced by current, or recent, photosynthate. Accordingly, seasonal changes in <em>SR</em> nominally attributed to temperature may, in part, be due to seasonality in photosynthesis. Within a mixed coniferous-deciduous temperate forest, we measured <em>SR</em> and used the process model SECRETS to test whether seasonal changes in photosynthesis influence seasonal differences in <em>SR</em>. Measurements were made in six adjacent plots (from pure evergreen to pure deciduous) that exhibited a gradient in the seasonality of photosynthesis. Within all six plots, we found strong correlations between the basal rate of <em>SR</em> (<em>BR</em>; defined as the <em>SR</em> at 10°C) and modeled photosynthesis (i.e. gross primary productivity; <em>GPP</em>). Moreover, we observed larger seasonal changes in <em>BR</em> in those plots that exhibited larger seasonal changes in photosynthesis, as compared with plots with smaller changes in photosynthesis. This is relevant because estimates of the <em>Q</em><sub>10</sub> of <em>SR</em> (<em>Q</em><sub>10</sub> is the relative change in a process rate per temperature change of 10°C) typically assume a constant <em>BR</em>. Our results therefore support the hypothesis that differences in the apparent <em>Q</em><sub>10</sub> of <em>SR</em> (apparent <em>Q</em><sub>10</sub>=<em>Q</em><sub>10</sub> derived from field measurements of <em>SR</em> and temperature) among studies may, in large part, be related to seasonal differences in photosynthesis. We suggest that variation in stand structure and species composition and, thus, in the photosynthetic signatures, induce different seasonal changes in <em>BR</em> via differences in the belowground supply of labile carbon. If these seasonal changes in <em>BR</em> are not properly accounted for, fitted apparent <em>Q</em><sub>10</sub> values may not express the temperature response of respiratory processes in the soil.