TEMPORAL PARTITIONING: AN EXPERIMENT WITH TWO SPECIES OF SPINY MICE.We studied temporal partitioning between two spiny mouse species that coexist in hot rocky deserts in the Middle East: nocturnal common spiny mice (<em>Acomys cahirinus</em>) and diurnally active golden spiny mice (<em>A. russatus</em>). Although <em>A. russatus</em> is diurnally active, it retains the physical activity and body temperature rhythms of nocturnal mammals. We studied the two species in four 1000-m<sup>2</sup> enclosures at Ein Gedi, Israel: two experimental enclosures with <em>A. russatus</em> kept alone, and two controls with individuals of both species kept together. We monitored activity with Sherman traps and by studying foraging microhabitat use and efficiency using giving-up densities (GUDs) in food trays. The trays contained broken sunflower seeds mixed in local soil and placed in three microhabitats: under boulders, between boulders, and in the open. Trapping revealed that, in the absence of <em>A. cahirinus</em>, the usually diurnal <em>A. russatus</em> was active both day and night. However, during the day <em>A. russatus</em> still foraged in significantly more patches and to significantly lower GUDs than during the night. Both species, but in particular <em>A. russatus</em>, preferred to forage in the boulder habitat. Spiny mice foraged in the same number of trays in the under- and between-boulder microhabitats, but to lower GUDs in the under-boulder microhabitat, both during the day (<em>A. russatus</em>) and during the night (both species). The nocturnal <em>A. cahirinus</em> exploited more patches with greater efficiency than did <em>A. russatus</em> either during the day or during the night. This result suggests that foraging trade-offs that give each species a competitive advantage along some portion of the resource axis cannot be a mechanism of nocturnal coexistence between the two species. Perhaps this is why <em>A. russatus</em> resorts to diurnal activity in this hot rocky desert and why the otherwise rare mechanism of temporal partitioning occurs for these species.