Vegetative Characteristics of Recently Reforested Bottomlands in the Lower Cache River Watershed, Illinois, U.S.A.Interest in restoring native ecosystems is resulting in conversion of marginal agricultural lands to bottomland hardwood-dominated forests in the midwestern and midsouthern United States. Growing stock for these efforts typically consists of planted oak (<em>Quercus</em> spp.) and volunteer vegetation. Reports of mixed reforestation success and the lack of post-establishment tree growth data prompted this evaluation of vegetation characteristics of 5- to 7-year-old operational restorations in the Lower Cache River Watershed in southernmost Illinois, U.S.A. <em>Fraxinus pennsylvanica</em> (green ash), <em>Acer negundo</em> (box-elder), and <em>Liquidambar styraciflua</em> (sweetgum) together comprised 77% of all tree stems observed. Full stocking of overstory tree species can be expected to produce a closed canopy stand within 160 m of a forested edge, due primarily to the abundance of rapidly growing volunteer-origin trees. Planted oaks contributed minimally to total tree stocking but were present in sufficient numbers to eventually improve wildlife habitat, and therefore satisfied restoration objectives. Oak height was 23% greater when in the presence of a non-oak tree species. Herbaceous cover was dominated by <em>Solidago gigantea</em> (late goldenrod) and <em>Juncus</em> spp. (rushes). <em>Solidago gigantea</em> was associated with poor growth and low density of non-oak stems, whereas <em>Juncus dudleyi</em> (Dudley's rush) was associated with taller non-oak stems. These results suggest that the presence of volunteer-origin trees is crucial for the creation of full stand stocking that will result in rapid development of a closed canopy forest. Improved success of future reforestation efforts will require more intensive methods to establish adequate stocking beyond 160 m of a forest edge. Methods described here could be adapted for agricultural field to forest restorations in other regions to predict critical distances from volunteer seed sources within which supplemental planting would be unnecessary to meet tree stocking objectives.