Epibiontic communities on the freshwater shrimp Caridina ensifera (Crustacea, Decapoda, Atyidae) from Lake Poso (Sulawesi, Indonesia)The epibiont communities of the freshwater shrimp Caridina ensifera, endemic to Lake Poso (Sulawesi, Indonesia), were analysed for the first time based on their morphological and biometrical characteristics and taxonomic position. Seven ciliated protozoans and a rotifer were examined: three suctorian ciliate protozoan species (Acineta sulawesiensis, Podophrya maupasi, and Spelaeophrya polypoides), three peritrichs (Zoothamnium intermedium, Vorticella globosa, and Cothurnia compressa), a haptorid (Amphileptus fusidens), and the rotifer species Embata laticeps. A mean number of 314.6 epibionts was found per shrimp specimen. The distribution of the epibiont species on the surface of the basibiont was recorded, to allow calculation of the density on the different colonized individuals of C. ensifera and on each anatomical unit of the shrimp. The most abundant species, Zoothamnium intermedium and Acineta sulawesiensis, were also the ones most widely distributed. The statistical analysis showed that Zoothamnium, Acineta, Podophrya, and Embata were the epibiont genera most widely distributed on the basibiont, and the pairs of epibiont genera Zoothamnium–Embata, Podophrya–Acineta, Spelaeophrya–Amphileptus, and Cothurnia–Vorticella followed a similar pattern of distribution. There was a significant difference between the distribution patterns of the different epibiont species on the shrimp. The analysis of the densities of the epibionts throughout the longitudinal axis of the shrimp showed a gradient from the anterior to the posterior end of the body, and a significantly different distribution of each epibiont species. Their colonization follows a certain pattern of behaviour, the species occupying the available substratum, with particular requirements of each functional group, but with a trend resulting in equilibrium among species and groups, compensating for diversity and density. The possible adaptations of the epibionts, as well as the colonization patterns are discussed.