The wettability of ash from burned vegetation and its relationship to Mediterranean plant species type, burn severity and total organic carbon contentImmediately following a wildfire, a layer of ash and charred material typically covers the ground. This layer will gradually be reduced, being redistributed by rainfall, wind or animals, by partial dissolution and by incorporation into the soil. Ash can increase or decrease the post-fire runoff and erosion response, depending upon the soil and ash properties and the ash thickness. One aspect of ash that has remained unknown and which may affect the variability in the hydrological response of the burned soil is its wettability. This study examines the wettability of ash using the Water Drop Penetration Time (WDPT) test, its relationship with total organic carbon (TOC) content and colour, and its effects when incorporated into the soil. Ash samples (n = 48) were taken from five wildfires in the Mediterranean basin encompassing a range of burn severities. Additional ash material was generated from exposing plant leaves (Rosmarinus officinalis, Pinus halepensis and Quercus coccifera) to specific temperatures in a muffle furnace (200–700 °C). Selected laboratory ash types were also mixed with wettable and water repellent soil material to assess their effect on soil wettability.  Over 30% of ash samples from the wildfire sites exhibited water repellency (WR), with WDPT levels ranging from low to extreme. This variability appears to be related to differences in fire severity, combustion completeness of the biomass, vegetation type and subsequent rainfall events. The laboratory-generated ash exhibited a greater frequency and persistence of water repellency at lower furnace temperatures (200–300 °C), with ash from R. officinalis being generally less water repellent than that derived from the other two species. The water repellency levels of ash correlated well with TOC (r = 0.80), whereas neither of these parameters correlated very well with ash colour (r = 0.57 for TOC and r = 0.59 for WR). This suggests that ash colour, which is widely used as a parameter in classifying burn severity in the field, may not necessarily be a very accurate indicator. Adding water repellent ash to wettable soil induced WR, whereas the addition of wettable ash to water repellent soil had the opposite effect. A wetting–drying cycle can reduce the water repellency of a soil–ash mixture. There were substantial differences between wildfire- and laboratory-generated ash in terms of organic carbon content and colour, suggesting that the combustion conditions in a furnace may not adequately represent those in wildfires.  In contrast to what is generally assumed, our findings demonstrate that ash from vegetation fires can be water repellent. This is likely to have implications for runoff responses and nutrient fluxes not only when ash is present on the ground surface, but also following its redistribution and incorporation into the soil.