Partitioning net ecosystem carbon exchange and the carbon isotopic disequilibrium in a subalpine forest.We investigate the utility of an improved isotopic method to partition the net ecosystem exchange of CO<sub>2</sub> (<em>F</em>) into net photosynthesis (<em>F</em><sub>A</sub>) and nonfoliar respiration (<em>F</em><sub>R</sub>). Measurements of <em>F</em> and the carbon isotopic content in air at a high-elevation coniferous forest (the Niwot Ridge AmeriFlux site) were used to partition <em>F</em> into <em>F</em><sub>A</sub> and <em>F</em><sub>R</sub>. Isotopically partitioned fluxes were then compared with an independent flux partitioning method that estimated gross photosynthesis (GEE) and total ecosystem respiration (TER) based on statistical regressions of night-time <em>F</em> and air temperature. We compared the estimates of <em>F</em><sub>A</sub> and <em>F</em><sub>R</sub> with expected canopy physiological relationships with light (photosynthetically active radiation) and air temperature. Estimates of <em>F</em><sub>A</sub> and GEE were dependent on light as expected, and TER, but not <em>F</em><sub>R</sub>, exhibited the expected dependence on temperature. Estimates of the isotopic disequilibrium <b><em>D</em></b>, or the difference between the isotopic signatures of net photosynthesis (<em>&delta;</em><sub>A</sub>, mean value -;24.6&permil;) and ecosystem respiration (<em>&delta;</em><sub>R</sub>, mean value -;25.1&permil;) were generally positive (<em>&delta;</em><sub>A</sub><em>>&delta;</em><sub>R</sub>). The sign of <b><em>D</em></b> observed here is inconsistent with many other studies. The key parameters of the improved isotopic flux partitioning method presented here are ecosystem scale mesophyll conductance (<em>g</em><sub>m</sub>) and maximal vegetative stomatal conductance (<em>g</em><sub>cmax</sub>). The sensitivity analyses of <em>F</em><sub>A</sub>, <em>F</em><sub>R</sub>, and <b><em>D</em></b> to <em>g</em><sub>cmax</sub> indicated a critical value of <em>g</em><sub>cmax</sub> (0.15 mol m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>) above which estimates of <em>F</em><sub>A</sub> and <em>F</em><sub>R</sub> became larger in magnitude relative to GEE and TER. The value of <b><em>D</em></b> decreased with increasing values of <em>g</em><sub>m</sub> and <em>g</em><sub>cmax</sub>, but was still positive across all values of <em>g</em><sub>m</sub> and <em>g</em><sub>cmax</sub>. We conclude that the characterization of canopy-scale mesophyll and stomatal conductances are important for further progress with the isotope partitioning method, and to confirm our anomalous isotopic disequilibrium findings.