POTENTIAL FOR SUCCESSIONAL THEORY TO GUIDE RESTORATION OF INVASIVE-PLANT-DOMINATED RANGELAND.Ecologists are searching for models, frameworks, and principles that provide a bridge between theory and the practice of restoration. Successional management has been proposed as a useful model for managing and restoring invasive-plant-dominated rangeland because it provides a framework in which ecological processes can be manipulated by managers to achieve a desired plant community. Successional management identifies three general causes of succession (site availability [disturbance], species availability [colonization], and species performance) and suggests that managers address the ecological process influencing each general cause in a coordinated fashion to direct plant community dynamics. We tested successional management using various techniques to restore invasive-weed-dominated rangeland. Our hypothesis was that successively modifying the factors influencing the causes of succession in an integrated fashion would favor the establishment and abundance of native grasses over singularly applied treatments. Thus, we anticipated that the majority of responses to multiple treatments would be explained by higher order interactions, especially in the final year of the study (2004). To test this hypothesis, we used a model system within a <em>Festuca campestris/Pseudoroegneria spicata</em> habitat among pothole wetlands dominated by <em>Centaurea maculosa</em> and <em>Potentilla recta</em>, two invasive species. We used three herbicide treatments (none, 2,4-D, and picloram) to influence species performance; two seeding methods (imprinting, i.e., creating a small depression and broadcasting, and no-till drilling) to influence disturbance; three seeding rates (977, 1322, and 1557 seeds/m<sup>2</sup>) to influence colonization; and two cover crop treatments (with and without <em>Triticum aestivum</em>) to influence soil N and favor native grasses. Treatments were factorially arranged and replicated four times in a randomized complete block design in 2001 and sampled in 2002 and 2004. As predicted, plant response to treatments was dominated by two- and three-way interactions in 2004. The highest seeding rate (colonization) combined with no-till drilling (disturbance) produced the highest native grass density in 2002. These effects persisted into 2004 for <em>P. spicata</em>, but not for <em>F. campestris</em> or <em>F. idahoensis</em>. Combining picloram with no-till drill seeding also produced a high density of <em>P. spicata</em>. Drill seeding at 977 seeds/m<sup>2</sup> favored <em>F. idahoensis</em> density<em>,</em> while no-till drilling at 1322 seeds/m<sup>2</sup> favored its biomass in 2004. <em>F. idahoensis</em> established well after drill seeding with a cover crop and applying 2,4-D. Herbicides reduced native forb density and/or biomass, with early season forbs being more sensitive to picloram and summer forbs being more sensitive to 2,4-D. Herbicides increased exotic grasses' density and biomass but had no effect on native grasses. In most cases, integrating treatments that addressed multiple causes of succession favored a desired plant community. Thus, we accomplished our goal of using successional management to direct plant communities toward native desired species, but the treatments used did not improve species richness. Since naturally occurring native forbs did not respond favorably to any treatment combination, ecological restoration using successional management may best be thought of as an iterative procedure where various components and processes of the system are methodically repaired or replaced over time.