Tree cover and height estimation in the Fennoscandian tundra–taiga transition zone using multiangular MISR dataThe tundra–taiga transition zone stretches around the northern hemisphere separating boreal forest to the south from treeless tundra to the north. Tree cover and height are important variables to characterize this vegetation transition. Accurate continuous fields of tree cover and height would enable the delineation of the forest extent according to different criterion and provide useful data for change detection of this climatically sensitive ecotone. This study examined if multiangular remote sensing data has potential to improve the accuracy of the tree cover and height estimates in relation to nadir-view data. The satellite data consisted of Multi-angle Imaging SpectroRadiometer (MISR) data at 275 m and 1.1 km resolutions. The study area was located in the Fennoscandian tundra–taiga transition zone, in northernmost Finland. The continuous fields of tree cover and height were estimated using neural networks, which were trained and assessed by high-resolution biotope inventory data. The spectral–angular data together produced lower estimation errors than single band nadir, multispectral nadir or single band multiangular data alone. RMSE of the tree cover estimates reduced from 7.8% (relative RMSE 67.4%) to 6.5% (56.1%) at 275 m resolution, and from 5.4% (49.2%) to 4.1% (36.9%) at 1.1 km resolution, when multispectral nadir data were used together with multiangular data. RMSE of the tree height estimates reduced from 2.3 m (44.3%) to 2.0 m (37.6%) and from 1.8 m (35.4%) to 1.3 m (25.4%), respectively. The largest estimation errors occurred in mires and in areas of dense shrub cover, but the use of multiangular data also reduced estimation errors in these areas. The results suggest that directional information has potential to improve the tree cover and height estimates, and hence the accuracy of the land cover change detection in the tundra–taiga transition zone.