Introduced European rabbit as main prey of the native carnivore culpeo fox (Lycalopex culpaeus) in disturbed ecosystems of central ChileThis study describes food habits of the culpeo fox (Lycalopex culpaeus) by scat analysis in two hills considered Priority Conservation Sites of the Mediterranean Region of central Chile, one of the most disturbed and modified ecosystems in the country. The results showed that foxes from both sites consume the introduced European rabbit (Oryctolagus cuniculus) as primary prey and native small mammals as secondary prey. This is the first record of feeding habits of the culpeo fox in central Chile that reports a higher consumption of European rabbit over pooled native small mammals. The reason for this result, as well as the higher trophic niche breadth and trophic niche diversity found in culpeo fox populations from the less disturbed hill, might be due to anthropogenic impacts on the study sites. However, to validate this claim, further studies on prey availability and human impact are required. The culpeo fox can have an important role in controlling pests such as the European rabbit; therefore, a more extensive study of this issue can bring important information for the conservation and management of natural areas of central Chile that show high human impact.Este estudio describe los h√°bitos alimentarios del zorro culpeo (Lycalopex culpaeus) en dos cerros considerados ‚ÄúSitios Prioritarios de Conservaci√≥n‚Ä de la eco-regi√≥n mediterr√°nea de Chile central, el cual es una de las zonas m√°s intervenidas y modificadas del pa√≠s. Los resultados encontrados muestran que los zorros de ambos cerros consumen como presa primaria al conejo europeo (Oryctolagus cuniculus) y a los peque√±os mam√≠feros nativos como presa secundaria. Este es el primer registro de la dieta del zorro culpeo en Chile central que reporta un mayor consumo de conejo europeo por sobre el consumo de peque√±os mam√≠feros nativos en su conjunto. La raz√≥n de este resultado, adem√°s de la mayor amplitud y diversidad de nicho tr√≥fico encontrado en la poblaci√≥n de zorro culpeo en el cerro menos intervenido, podr√≠a deberse al impacto antropog√©nico en los sitios de estudios. Sin embargo, para validar esta afirmaci√≥n se necesitan estudios sobre disponibilidad de presas e impacto humano. El zorro culpeo puede tener un papel importante en el control de plagas como el conejo europeo, por lo cual se requiere un estudio m√°s acabado de esta tem√°tica, lo cual puede brindar informaci√≥n importante para la conservaci√≥n y manejo de √°reas naturales de Chile central que presenten un alto impacto antropog√©nico.