Contrasting responses to drought of forest floor CO2 efflux in a Loblolly pine plantation and a nearby Oak-Hickory forest.Forest floor CO<sub>2</sub> efflux (<em>F</em><sub>ff</sub>) depends on vegetation type, climate, and soil physical properties. We assessed the effects of biological factors on <em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> by comparing a maturing pine plantation (PP) and a nearby mature Oak-Hickory-type hardwood forest (HW). <em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> was measured continuously with soil chambers connected to an IRGA during 2001-2002. At both sites, <em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> depended on soil temperature at 5 cm (<em>T</em><sub>5</sub>) when soil was moist (soil moisture, <em>&theta;</em>>0.20 m<sup>3</sup> m<sup>-;3</sup>), and on both <em>T</em><sub>5</sub> and <em>&theta;</em> when soil was drier. A model (<em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> (<em>T</em><sub>5</sub>, <em>&theta;</em>)) explained ≥92% of the variation in the daily mean <em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> at both sites. Higher radiation reaching the ground during the leafless period, and a thinner litter layer because of faster decomposition, probably caused higher soil temperature at HW compared with PP. The annual <em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> was estimated at 1330 and 1464 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup> for a year with mild drought (2001) at PP and HW, respectively, and 1231 and 1557 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup> for a year with severe drought (2002). In the wetter year, higher soil temperature and moisture at HW compared with PP compensated for the negative effect on <em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> of the response to these variables resulting in similar annual <em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> at both stands. In the drier year, however, the response to soil temperature and moisture was more similar at the two stands causing the difference in the state variables to impel a higher <em>F</em><sub>ff</sub> at HW. A simple mass balance indicated that in the wetter year, C in the litter-soil system was at steady state at HW, and was accruing at PP. However, HW was probably losing C from the mineral soil during the severe drought year of 2002, while PP was accumulating C at a lower rate because of a loss of C from the litter layer. Such contrasting behavior of two forest types in close proximity might frustrate attempts to estimate regional carbon (C) fluxes and net C exchange.