Land-use/cover change effects and carbon controls on volcanic soil profiles in highland temperate forestsThe stabilization of SOM by Al–humus complexes and non-crystalline minerals is a key issue to explain the soil-C variability and the biogeochemical processes that determine the fate of soil C following land-use/cover change (LUCC) in volcanic landscapes. In an altitudinal gradient of volcanic soils (2550–3500 masl), we quantified the total soil C (CT) concentrations and stocks in soil pits sampled by genetic horizons. We performed analyses at landscape and local scales in order to identify and integrate the underlying environmental controls on CT and the effects of LUCC. We selected four sites, two on the upper piedmont, one on the lower mountain slope and one on the middle mountain slope at Cofre de Perote volcano (eastern central Mexico) where temperate forests are the natural vegetation. At each site we selected three to five units of use/cover as a chronosequence of the LUCC pathways. In each soil horizon chemical characteristics (i.e. N, C/N ratio, pH, exchangeable bases) were determined and mineralogical properties were estimated from selective Al, Fe and Si oxalate and pyrophosphate extractions (i.e. the Alp/Alo ratio, the active Al related to non-crystalline minerals as Alo − Alp, the allophane concentration, and the non-crystalline Al and Fe minerals as Alo + 1/2Feo). At landscape scale, the Al–humus complexes were strongly related to the CT concentration in topsoil (A horizons) but this relationship decreased with depth. In turn, the non-crystalline minerals and the C/N ratio explained the variability of the CT concentrations in C horizons. At local scale, CT concentrations and stocks were depleted after conversion of forest to agriculture in Vitric Andosols at the upper piedmont but this was not observed in Silandic Andosols. However, in Vitric Andosols the reduction of the CT stocks is partially recovered throughout the regeneration/reforestation processes. The results suggest that the lower vulnerability of Silandic Andosols than Vitric Andosols to changes in the CT after LUCC is due to the higher levels of SOM stabilized by Al–humus complexes and non-crystalline minerals in the Silandic soils. Furthermore, the importance of the allophane to explain the CT stocks in the Silandic Andosols of the middle slopes suggests that the CT stabilized by this mineral fraction in the subsoil adds an important fraction of the CT to the estimates of the stocks.