Effects of different sensors, flying altitudes, and pulse repetition frequencies on forest canopy metrics and biophysical stand properties derived from small-footprint airborne laser dataCanopy height distributions were created from small-footprint airborne laser scanner (ALS) data collected over 40 field sample plots with size 1000 m2 located in mature conifer forest. ALS data were collected with two different instruments, i.e., the ALTM 1233 and ALTM 3100 laser scanners (Optech Inc.). The ALTM 1233 data were acquired at a flying altitude of 1200 m and a pulse repetition frequency (PRF) of 33 kHz. Three different acquisitions were carried out with ALTM 3100, i.e., (1) a flying altitude of 1100 m and a PRF of 50 kHz, (2) a flying altitude of 1100 m and a PRF of 100 kHz, and (3) a flying altitude of 2000 m and a PRF of 50 kHz. Height percentiles, mean and maximum height values, coefficients of variation of the heights, and canopy density at different height intervals above the ground were derived from the four different ALS datasets and for single+first and last echoes of the ALS data separately. The ALS-derived height- and density variables were assessed in pair-wise comparisons to evaluate the effects of (a) instrument, (b) flying altitude, and (c) PRF. A systematic shift in height values of up to 0.3 m between sensors when the first echoes were compared was demonstrated. Also the density-related variables differed significantly between the two instruments. Comparisons of flying altitudes and PRFs revealed upwards shifted canopy height distributions for the highest flying altitude (2000 m) and the lowest PRF (50 kHz). The distribution of echoes on different echo categories, i.e., single and multiple (first and last) echoes, differed significantly between acquisitions. The proportion of multiple echoes decreased with increasing flying altitude and PRF. Different echo categories have different properties since it is likely that single echoes tend to occur in the densest parts of the tree crowns, i.e., near the apex where the concentration of biological matter is highest and distance to the ground is largest. To assess the influence of instrument, flying altitude, and PRF on biophysical properties derived from ALS data, regression analysis was carried out to relate ALS-derived metrics to mean tree height (hL) and timber volume (V). Cross validation revealed only minor differences in precision for the different ALS acquisitions, but systematic differences between acquisitions of up to 2.5% for hL and 10.7% for V were found when comparing data from different acquisitions.