SOIL DEGRADATION SLOWS GROWTH AND INHIBITS JASMONATE-INDUCED RESISTANCE IN ARTEMISIA VULGARIS.German reunification closed factories that produced point-source emissions and, in so doing, provided ecologists with well-defined pollution gradients with which to study the effects of plant stress on induced resistance against herbivores. We characterized a gradient of severely degraded soil from the dust emissions of a former fertilizer factory and selected three sites along this gradient to study the interaction of pollution stress and herbivore resistance in a single maternal lineage of <em>Artemisia vulgaris</em> that had colonized these disturbed habitats. We measured <em>A. vulgaris</em> growth, reproductive success, and inducible herbivore resistance by eliciting plants at each site with a quantitative methyl jasmonate (MeJA) treatment, and measured the reproductive success of two native herbivores, the aphid <em>Macrosiphoniella artemisiae</em> (in the field) and the grasshopper <em>Chorthippus mollis</em> (in the laboratory). Soil heavy metals and phosphate contents decreased with distance from the former factory, while cation exchange capacity and nitrogen content, as well as <em>A. vulgaris</em> growth and seed germination (measured in both field and laboratory assays) increased, demonstrating a plant stress that is mediated by soil degradation. MeJA elicitation decreased <em>A. vulgaris</em> growth and seed production and the reproductive success of the two insect herbivores. MeJA-induced herbivore resistance waned in plants grown on degraded soils and was correlated with changes in concentrations of leaf secondary metabolites of which chlorogenic acid, which increased dramatically in MeJA-induced plants grown on moderately degraded soil but not in plants from heavily degraded soil, was representative. We conclude that herbivore-induced resistance is constrained in slow-growing plants on degraded soils and that the jasmonate cascade likely mediates plant responses to both types of environmental stresses. A central role for the jasmonate cascade in mediating plant responses to both abiotic and biotic stresses provides a mechanistic understanding of the plant vigor hypothesis.