Genecology and Seed Zones for Indian Ricegrass Collected in the Southwestern United StatesIndian ricegrass (Achnatherum hymenoides &lsqb;Roemer & J.A. Schultes] Barkworth) is a widely distributed, highly desirable native species in desert ecosystems in the western United States. Yet there are no studies linking genetic variation in Indian ricegrass with climate across major areas of its natural distribution. In this study, seeds from 106 collection locations from the southwestern United States were established in common gardens and four phenological traits (Phen; such as blooming date), six production traits (Pro; such as dry weight), and eight morphology traits (Morph; such as leaf dimensions) were measured in 2007 and 2008. Analyses of variance revealed that all basic garden traits differed among source locations (P &spilt; 0.01), indicating widespread genetic variation. Within Phen, Pro, and Morph categories, canonical correlation was completed between basic garden traits and source location temperature and precipitation. This resulted in six significant (P &spilt; 0.01) canonical variates (Phen 1, Pro 1 and 2, and Morph 1, 2, and 3) representing each category of traits. Linear correlations (r &spigt; ± 0.25, P &spilt; 0.01) consistently linked monthly temperature at collection locations with Phen 1, Pro 1, and Morph 1. For precipitation, however, correlations were more dependent on month, with the strongest correlations during the spring developmental period. Using regression models between traits and climate, a map with 12 seed zones was developed representing much of the southwestern United States. This generally distinguished genetic variation between cooler and warmer regions, usually separating more northern, higher elevation areas from more southern, lower elevation areas. The correspondence between climate and genetic variation suggested climate-driven differences in natural selection, likely leading to adaptation. The seed zone map is recommended to guide and broaden germplasm collection and utilization for Indian ricegrass restoration.