Diet of the Red-backed Hawk (Buteo polyosoma) in two environmentally contrasting areas of PatagoniaWe studied the Red-backed Hawk (Buteo polyosoma) diet by pellet analysis in two areas, the Monumento Natural Bosques Petrificados (MNBP) and Junín de los Andes, located in southern and northwestern Argentinean Patagonia respectively. These areas have different values of primary production mainly due to the differences in mean annual precipitation, being higher in Junín de los Andes. Diets were dominated by mammals in both areas (68.3% and 61% of occurrences). Rodents represented the greatest proportion (66.5%) of prey numbers in MNBP. They represented 92.6% of the biomass. Arthropods were also consumed with a relatively high occurrence (21.4%). In Junín de los Andes, rodents were an important prey (57.1%) but represented only 29.6% of the consumed biomass. In contrast, the introduced European hare (Lepus europaeus) was not frequently consumed (13.5%) but comprised 59.3% of prey biomass. Reptiles were a frequent item, consumed at 25.2% of total prey. The diet of the Red-backed Hawk was significantly different between MNBP and Junín de los Andes. The wider food niche breadth of the Red-backed Hawk in Junín de los Andes was likely attributable to the more even distribution of prey categories. Additionally, a functional response toward European hare consumption was observed, with a higher consumption of this prey at Junín de los Andes. Estudiamos la dieta del Aguilucho común (Buteo polyosoma) por medio del análisis de egagrópilas, en dos áreas: el Monumento Natural Bosques Petrificados (MNBP) y Junín de los Andes, situadas respectivamente en el sur y noroeste de la Patagonia Argentina. La productividad primaria es diferente en ambas áreas, debido principalmente a la cantidad de precipitaciones, que son mayores en Junín de los Andes. Los mamíferos fueron las presas más importantes en la dieta del Aguilucho en ambas áreas (68.3% y 61.0% de ocurrencias). La proporción de roedores en el MNBP fue alta (66.5%), representando el 92.6% de la biomasa total consumida. Otro ítem importante fueron los artrópodos con una ocurrencia del 21.34%. En Junín de los Andes, los roedores fueron también presas importantes en la dieta del Aguilucho común (57.1%), pero representaron solamente 29.6% de la biomasa total consumida. Por el contrario, la liebre europea (Lepus europaeus), una presa introducida, fue consumida con una frecuencia menor (13.5%) pero constituyó el 59.3% de la biomasa total. Los reptiles fueron frecuentemente consumidos (25.2%). En concordancia, la dieta del Aguilucho común fue significativamente diferente entre el MNBP y Junín de los Andes. La mayor amplitud del nicho trófico del Aguilucho común en Junín de los Andes podría ser atribuida a la mayor equidad en la distribución de las categorías presa. Adicionalmente, se observó una respuesta funcional hacia el consumo de liebre europea, siendo mayor en Junín de los Andes.