Facilitating grassland diversification using the hemiparasitic plant Rhinanthus minor.<ol><li>Species-rich grasslands are of high conservation value because of the diverse floral and faunal assemblages they support. Intensive agriculture has resulted in the large-scale loss and fragmentation of this habitat throughout the UK and Europe.</li><li>Diversification of species-poor grasslands has proved to be problematical due to seed limitation, lack of microsites for germination and competition from established species.</li><li>Studies of semi-natural grasslands in Britain and Europe suggest that the presence of hemiparasitic angiosperms of the genus <em>Rhinanthus</em> is correlated with local decreases in productivity and an associated increase in species richness.</li><li>In 1998 a randomized block experiment was established to examine: (i) the practicality of introducing <em>Rhinanthus minor</em> into a productive grassland from seed; (ii) the rate of establishment and colonization of the introduced populations; and (iii) the relationship between the frequency of the parasite and the establishment and persistence of introduced forb species.</li><li>Establishment of <em>Rhinanthus</em> was less likely at the lowest sowing rate (0·1 kg ha<sup>-;1</sup>) and population growth was initially slow compared with the higher seed rates (0·5 and 2·5 kg ha<sup>-;1</sup>). After the first year, populations grew rapidly and colonized the unsown plots, so that after 4 years there was little difference in <em>Rhinanthus</em> frequency between treatments.</li><li>In October 2000, 2 years after sowing <em>Rhinanthus</em>, a native wildflower seed mixture was oversown into a number of the treatments at 5 kg ha<sup>-;1</sup>. The mixture comprised 10 forbs of which nine species were previously not present in the grassland. All forbs established with up to seven species m<sup>-;2</sup>. This resulted in an increase in mean richness of sown species of 0·8 to 2·2 m<sup>-;2</sup> and in a cumulative richness per plot of 1·4 to 5·8 m<sup>-;2</sup>.</li><li>In both 2001 and 2002 there was a strong, inverse relationship between the frequency of <em>Rhinanthus</em> and sward height. In 2002, there was evidence of a threshold frequency of the hemiparasite above which there was a significant reduction in grassland productivity.</li><li>The frequency of <em>Rhinanthus</em> in 2001 had a significant beneficial effect on the persistence of seven of the 10 sown forbs in the following year. This probably reflects a reduction in competition from the established grassland species at the vulnerable seedling stage, together with death of the hemiparasite leading to a higher number of gaps for colonization.</li><li><em>Synthesis and applications.</em> The introduction of <em>R. minor</em> is a practical management tool to facilitate the colonization of species-poor, productive grasslands by desirable species. This is achieved by the hemiparasite modifying the competitive relationships between the component species, and increasing establishment and survival of introduced species. This species has a potentially central role in determining the structure and dynamics of grassland communities.</li></ol>