Structure and hydrology of mounds of the imported fire ants in the southeastern United StatesImported fire ants comprise two introduced species which build large mounds at high densities throughout the southeastern United States. They represent a new soil-forming factor for these soils. A study was conducted to quantify the channel network geometry, clod density, aggregate stability, and micromorphology of the mounds on three texturally different soils, and examine the moisture relationships in the mounds. The channels averaged 0.6 cm wide in mounds on a sandy loam and a silt loam, and 1.0 cm wide in a mound on a clay soil. Channels occupied 39% of the horizontal cross-sectional area in the mound on the sandy loam and 55% in the mounds on the silt loam and the clay. The interchannel matrix of the mound assembled by the ants consists of a porous, bridged-pellet framework which is separated from the channels by a thin (<1 mm thick), semi-coherent lining. At the exterior of the mound, this lining forms the underside of the crust of the mound, which is only a few millimeters thick. The aggregates created by the ants do not differ significantly (α=0.05) in bulk density or aggregate stability from those of the undisturbed topsoil, with the exception of aggregates from the crust of the mound, which are up to 38% less dense and up to 82% less stable than the adjacent soil aggregates. The fragile crust allows more infiltration than the surrounding soil. Moisture contents are up to 170% greater in the mound than in the adjacent soil shortly after rainfall. Infiltrating water rapidly drains from the mound and can be stored in the channels below the mound as indicated by the occurrence of free water below mounds at 120, 81 and 46 cm deep, while no free water was present in the adjacent pedons. The mound dries quickly to moisture contents as much as 82%, lower than those of adjacent pedons as a result of this rapid drainage. As colonies relocate their mounds over time, entire landscapes may be exposed to the greater leaching of the pedogenic regime of the mound, and soils may inherit new macropores and soil aggregates.