Revision of the Agrilus occipitalis species–group (Coleoptera, Buprestidae, Agrilini)Abstract The Agrilus occipitalis species–group is redefined and diagnosed. Two species from this group, Agrilus auriventris Saunders, 1873 and Agrilus occipitalis (Eschscholtz, 1822), are known as the serious pests of cultivated Citrus trees. Overall twenty-three taxa are included in the Agrilus occipitalis species–group. A complete list of references, type material, species examined and distribution is given for each taxon. The host plants, adult occurrence and altitude range is cited for most taxa. Habitus of all taxa and aedeagi of available males are pictured. Images of primary type specimens are provided. A character state matrix table for diagnostic characters is given for all taxa to facilitate their determination. The following new taxonomic and nomenclatural acts are proposed. New species:eight new species are described: Agrilus mucidus sp. n., Agrilus nebulosus sp. n., Agrilus picturatus sp. n., Agrilus pluvius sp. n., Agrilus pseudoambiguus sp. n., Agrilus tesselatus sp. n., Agrilus trepanatus sp. n. and Agrilus umrongso sp. n. Proposed synonyms: eight synonyms are proposed: celebicola Obenberger, 1924, syn. n. (synonym of occipitalis Eschscholtz, 1822); connexus Kerremans, 1900, syn. n. (synonym of occipitalis Eschscholtz, 1822); cupricauda Saunders, 1867 syn. n. (synonym of occipitalis Eschscholtz, 1822); evinadus Gory & Laporte, 1839, syn. n. (synonym of occipitalis Eschscholtz, 1822); nirius Obenberger, 1924 syn. reconfirmed (synonym of occipitalis Eschscholtz, 1822); oblatus Kerremans, 1900, syn. n. (synonym of occipitalis Eschscholtz, 1822); samoensis Blair, 1928, syn. n. (synonym of auriventris Saunders, 1873); tebinganus Obenberger, 1924, syn. n. (synonym of occipitalis Eschscholtz, 1822). New lectotype designations: six lectotypes are designated: Agrilus celebicola Obenberger, 1924; Agrilus cupricauda Saunders, 1867; Agrilus korenskyi Obenberger, 1923; Agrilus kurandae Obenberger, 1923; Agrilus nirius Obenberger, 1924; Agrilus nitidus Kerremans, 1898.