Beetle (Insecta, Coleoptera) assemblage in a Southern Brazilian restinga: effects of anthropogenic disturbance and vegetation complexityRestinga is a term used to describe a mosaic of vegetation that occurs in predominantly coastal sandy plains, with physiognomies that range from creeping herbs to forests. In this paper we investigate how the beetle assemblage in a restinga habitat responded to anthropogenic disturbance and vegetation complexity. During four seasons in 2008 and 2009, we sampled beetles using pitfall traps at 10 stations along Pântano do Sul Beach, Santa Catarina Island, Brazil. We compared these beetle assemblages to parameters of anthropogenic disturbance and vegetation complexity at each sampling site. The species composition among the beetle assemblages was considerably different and showed high beta diversity. Disturbed vegetation sites had higher diversity and species richness than most of the undisturbed sites. Although correlations were generally weak, the species of Elateridae were positively correlated with disturbance. These results indicate that restinga vegetation heterogeneity and Coleoptera diversity are related and thus strengthen the importance of chance in beetle distribution across the beach. Despite the low level of endemism in restingas, species found in this habitat should be of greater concern for environmental policies involving Atlantic Forest preservation due to their high diversity. Restinga é um termo usado para descrever uma vegetação em forma de mosaico que ocorre em planícies predominantemente arenosas, com fisionomias que variam de ervas rasteiras a florestas. Neste artigo nós investigamos se a comunidade de besouros apresenta resposta à antropização e à complexidade da vegetação em ambientes de restinga. Os besouros foram amostrados durante quatro estações usando armadilhas do tipo pitfall em dez pontos amostrais na Praia do Pântano do Sul, Ilha de Santa Catarina, Brasil. Também foram medidos parâmetros da antropização e da complexidade da vegetação, usando três transectos para a antropização e um transecto com dez quadrados para a vegetação, em cada ponto amostral. Foram calculadas medidas ecológicas para a comunidade de besouros e as comunidades encontradas em cada ponto amostral e estação do ano foram comparadas. Também correlacionamos os dados ecológicos dos besouros com as medidas ambientais. A similaridade encontrada para as comunidades de besouros foi baixa, e os pontos antropizados apresentaram maior diversidade e riqueza de espécies que a maioria dos pontos não-antropizados. As correlações foram, em geral, fracas, mas Elateridae apresentou correlação positiva com a antropização. A heterogeneidade das restingas e a diversidade de Coleoptera podem ter fortalecido a importância do acaso na distribuição dos besouros ao longo da praia. Apesar do baixo grau de endemismo da restinga, espécies encontradas nestes habitats deveriam receber maior atenção em políticas públicas para a conservação da Mata Atlântica, devido à sua alta diversidade e plasticidade.