NITROGEN CYCLING IN TROPICAL PLANTATION FORESTS: POTENTIAL CONTROLS ON NITROGEN RETENTION.The establishment and management of tropical plantations has the potential to significantly alter patterns in nitrogen (N) cycling relative to old-growth tropical forests, which are generally characterized by high N availability and large fluxes of nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O), an important greenhouse gas. We used <sup>15</sup>N tracer additions to examine the effects of plantation establishment and management on gross N-cycling rates, N retention via microbial assimilation and dissimilatory nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup>) reduction to ammonium (NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>) (DNRA), and N losses via N<sub>2</sub>O emissions. In general, plantations had lower rates of N cycling and increased potential for N losses compared to old-growth forests, but there were few differences between very short (one-year) rotation and 10-yr-old uncut plantations. Gross N mineralization declined by almost 50% in the plantations compared to the old-growth forests, and much of the mineralized N was nitrified at all sites. Gross nitrification rates were more variable and did not differ between old-growth forests and unfertilized plantations; however, fertilization increased gross nitrification by a factor of 6 in short-rotation forests, signaling a potential mechanism for increased N losses via leaching and gaseous emissions. Old-growth forests had significantly higher microbial biomass N and NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> assimilation rates. No microbial N assimilation was measured in the plantation soils, nor was there evidence of gross NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> immobilization from estimates of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup> consumption and nitrification. Plantations and old-growth forests had similar DNRA rates (0.23 μg·g<sup>−1</sup>·d<sup>−1</sup>), which retains N in the ecosystem, and plantations had lower N<sub>2</sub>O emissions. Nitrous oxide fluxes from plantations were highly sensitive to reducing conditions, highlighting the potential for high rates of N<sub>2</sub>O losses. Our results show that plantation establishment can decrease rates of N cycling, but once forests are converted to plantations, internal N-cycling pathways and N<sub>2</sub>O fluxes are relatively resistant to disturbance associated with short rotation length.