Assessment of forest structure with airborne LiDAR and the effects of platform altitudeAirborne scanning LiDAR is a spatial technology increasingly used for forestry and environmental applications. However, the accuracy and coverage of LiDAR observations is highly dependent on both the extrinsic specifications of the LiDAR survey as well as the intrinsic effects such as the underlying forest structure. Extrinsic parameters which are set as part of the LiDAR survey include platform altitude, scan angle (half max. angle off nadir), and beam cross sectional diameter at the reflecting surface (referred to as footprint size). In this paper we investigate the effect of a number of these extrinsic parameters, including three different platform altitudes (1000, 2000, and 3000 m), two scan angles at 1000 m (10° and 15° half max. angle off nadir), and three footprint sizes (0.2, 0.4, and 0.6 m). The comparison was undertaken in eucalypt forests at three sites, varying in vegetation structure and topography within the Wedding Bells State Forest, Coffs Harbour, Australia. Results at the plot scale (40×90 m areas) indicate that tree heights computed from the 1000 m LiDAR data set (10° half max. angle off nadir) are well correlated with maximum plot heights (difference <3 m) and field measured canopy volume (r2>0.75, p<0.001). Using normalised canopy height profiles (CHP) derived for sites, from data recorded at each altitude, we observed no significant difference between the relative distribution of LiDAR returns, indicating that platform altitude and footprint size have not had a major influence on CHP estimation. Interestingly, comparisons of first and last returns for individual pulses at increasing altitudes identified progressively fewer discrete first/last pulse combinations with more than 70% of pulses recorded as a single return at the highest altitude (3000 m). A possible hypothesis is that greater platform altitude and footprint size reduces the intensity of laser beam incident on a given surface area thus decreasing the probability of recording a last return above the noise threshold. Furthermore, tree scale analysis found a positive relationship between platform altitude and the underestimation of crown area and crown volume. The implications of this work for forest management are: (i) platform altitudes as high as 3000 m can be used to quantify the vertical distribution of phyto-elements, (ii) higher platform altitudes record a lower proportion of first/last return combinations that will further reduce the number of points available for forest structural assessment and development of digital elevation models, and (iii) for discrete LiDAR data, increasing platform altitude will record a lower frequency of returns per crown, resulting in larger underestimates of individual tree crown area and volume if standard algorithms are applied.