Influence of halophytic hosts on their parasites—the case of Plicosepalus acaciaeParasitic plants obtain nutrients, carbohydrates, ions and water from their host plants and develop special morphological features to survive on the living tissue of other plants. We investigated the mistletoe Psilocephalus acaciae on halophytic and non-halophytic hosts in the Arava Valley. When P. acaciae was parasitic on halophytic hosts, ions were transported by the transpiration stream in the parasite. Chloride and sodium induced the development of leaf succulence in the parasite. Increasing succulence is a morphological adaptation by the mistletoe to the increasing salt stress on halophytic hosts. Halophytes develop various morphological and physiological traits that enable them to grow successfully on saline substrates. Parasitic plants on halophytic hosts may also encounter salt stress. We investigated the mistletoe Plicosepalus acaciae (syn: Loranthus acacia; Loranthaceae), which occurs on 5 halophytic and at least 10 non-halophytic hosts in the Southern Arava Valley (Israel). Plicosepalus acaciae is a common parasite north of Eilat to the Dead Sea area and in the Jordan Valley. Morphological and physiological responses of P. acaciae to salinity were investigated by comparison of plants on halophytic with those on non-halophytic hosts. Ion patterns of different host–parasite associations were determined as was the development of leaf succulence at different growth stages. The leaf water content of P. acaciae increased and leaves developed succulence when growing on halophytic hosts, especially on Tamarix species, where leaf water content was three times higher than that on non-halophytic hosts and the leaf volume increased four to five times. The reason for increased succulence was a higher ion concentration of, and osmotic adjustment with, Na+ and Cl−. Plicosepalus acaciae showed a high morphological and ecophysiological plasticity, enabling it to cope with salt stress, and can be classified as a facultative eu-halophyte, which increases its halo-succulence according to the host. Host–parasite associations are a model system for the investigation of halophytes under different salt stress conditions.