Condition-specific competition between invasive Argentine ants and Australian Iridomyrmex.<ol><li>Biotic interactions and abiotic suitability are often emphasized as factors influencing invasion success. Here we examine how these factors might interact to affect the competitive performance of invasive Argentine ants (<em>Linepithema humile</em>) in Western Australia.</li><li>In standardized bait surveys Argentine ants controlled twice as many baits in the morning (ground temperatures: 18-25 °C) compared to the number they controlled in the afternoon (ground temperatures: 30-40 °C). Moreover, Argentine ants displaced native ants from baits only in the morning and were, in turn, displaced by native ants only in the afternoon.</li><li>We used a factorial field experiment to test the relative importance of interspecific competition (±) and ground temperature variation [warm (25 °C)/hot (33 °C)] as determinants of competitive performance among established colonies of Argentine ants and two species of native <em>Iridomyrmex</em> (<em>I. bicknelli</em> and <em>I. rufoniger suchieri</em>).</li><li>We observed a condition-specific competitive asymmetry between <em>I. bicknelli</em> and <em>L. humile</em>. In the absence of each other as competitors, these two species responded to ground temperature variation in an opposite manner. <em>I. bicknelli</em> foraged more actively when ground temperatures were hot, whereas <em>L. humile</em> foraged more actively when ground temperatures were warm. In competition with <em>I. bicknelli</em>, Argentine ants monopolized two-thirds of all baits but controlled more than twice the number of baits under warm conditions than under hot conditions. <em>Iridomyrmex bicknelli</em> dominated 22% of all baits but did so primarily when conditions were hot.</li><li><em>Linepithema humile</em> and <em>I. r. suchieri</em> responded to abiotic variation in a qualitatively similar manner. Both species foraged less actively when ground temperatures were hot than when ground temperatures were warm, but <em>L. humile</em> showed stronger declines when ground temperatures were hot than did <em>I. r. suchieri</em>. In competition with <em>I. r. suchieri</em>, Argentine ants again monopolized two-thirds of all baits.</li><li>Our findings suggest that physical conditions unsuitable for <em>L. humile</em> may combine with interspecific competition from native ants that are more tolerant to hot, dry conditions to reduce the extent to which natural areas in Australia become invaded.</li></ol>