Carbon storage and flux in aboveground vegetation and soil of sixty-year old secondary natural forest and large leafed mahogany (Swietenia macrophylla King) plantation in Mt. Makiling, PhilippinesThis study was conducted in Mt. Makiling Forest Reserve (MFR), Luzon, Philippines to compare the carbon cycle pattern according to regeneration method by analyzing the carbon storage and flux of a large leafed mahogany (Swietenia macrophylla King) plantation and a secondary natural forest. The total carbon storage in aboveground biomass, litter layer and soil of the secondary forest stand was 313.12 Mg C/ha, which was 1.7 times larger than the carbon storage of the large leafed mahogany plantation (185.28 Mg C/ha). The stocks of carbon in the aboveground biomass and soil were higher in the secondary forest stand than in the large leafed mahogany plantation. The carbon content in litter layer was higher in the large leafed mahogany plantation than in the secondary forest stand. The soil carbon storage in the secondary forest stand and large leafed mahogany plantation at a depth from 0 similar to 60 cm was 82.25 and 69.04 Mg C/ha, respectively. The higher soil carbon stock in the secondary forest stand was due to the soil carbon stock in the 0 similar to 20 cm depth. The litter production in the dry season was higher in the large leafed mahogany plantation (4.23 Mg C/ha) than in the secondary forest stand (2.90 Mg C/ha) because of the high weight of the fruit. The litter production in the wet season was higher in the secondary forest stand than in the large leafed mahogany plantation because of the high mass of leaves and branches. The dry and wet season soil respiration difference between the control and trenching treatment was higher in the large leafed mahogany plantation than in the secondary forest stand The soil temperature decreased from wet season to dry season. The temperature difference between the large leafed mahogany plantation and secondary forest stand was higher in the dry season. The high carbon emission from the secondary forest stand was due to the:high soil respiration and high bacteria count. In this study, two important types of tropical vegetation, large leafed mahogany plantation and secondary forest stand, showed differences in carbon storage and seasonal, annual carbon flux patterns. The differences will feed back on the carbon and nutrient cycling in this tropical ecosystem in Mt. Makiling, Luzon, Philippines.