Assessment of water quality in Lake Garda (Italy) using HyperionFor testing the integration of the remote sensing related technologies into the water quality monitoring programs of Lake Garda (the largest Italian lake), the spatial and spectral resolutions of Hyperion and the capability of physics-based approaches were considered highly suitable. Hyperion data were acquired on 22nd July 2003 and water quality was assessed (i) defining a bio-optical model, (ii) converting the Hyperion at-sensor radiances into subsurface irradiance reflectances, and (iii) adopting a bio-optical model inversion technique. The bio-optical model was parameterised using specific inherent optical properties of the lake and light field variables derived from a radiative transfer numerical model. A MODTRAN-based atmospheric correction code, complemented with an air/water interface correction was used to convert Hyperion at-sensor radiances into subsurface irradiance reflectance values. These reflectance values were comparable to in situ reflectance spectra measured during the Hyperion overpass, except at longer wavelengths (beyond 700 nm), where reflectance values were contaminated by severe atmospheric adjacency effects. Chlorophyll-a and tripton concentrations were retrieved by inverting two Hyperion bands selected using a sensitivity analysis applied to the bio-optical model. The sensitivity analysis indicated that the assessment of coloured dissolved organic matter was not achievable in this study due to the limited coloured dissolved organic matter concentration range of the lake, resulting in reflectance differences below the environmental measurement noise of Hyperion. The chlorophyll-a and tripton image-products were compared to in situ data collected during the Hyperion overpass, both by traditional sampling techniques (8 points) and by continuous flow-through systems (32 km). For chlorophyll-a the correlation coefficient between in situ point stations and Hyperion-inferred concentrations was 0.77 (data range from 1.30 to 2.16 mg m−3). The Hyperion-derived chlorophyll-a concentrations also match most of the flow-through transect data. For tripton, the validation was constrained by variable re-suspension phenomena. The correlation coefficient between in situ point stations and Hyperion-derived concentrations increased from 0.48 to 0.75 (data range from 0.95 to 2.13 g m−3) if the sampling data from the re-suspension zone was avoided. The comparison of Hyperion-derived tripton concentrations and flow-through transect data exhibited a similar mismatch. The results of this research suggest further studies to address compatibilities of validation methods for water body features with a high rate of change, and to reduce the contamination by atmospheric adjacency effects on Hyperion data at longer wavelengths in Alpine environment. The transferability of the presented method to other sensors and the ability to assess water quality independent from in situ water quality data, suggest that management relevant applications for Lake Garda (and other subalpine lakes) could be supported by remote sensing.