Effect of natural atmospheric CO2 fertilization suggested by open-grown white spruce in a dry environment.Evidence of an atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>-fertilization effect on radial growth rates was uncovered for open-grown white spruce in a mixed-grass prairie of southwestern Manitoba, Canada. Consistent upward trends of the residuals from dendroclimatic models indicated a decreased ability for climatic parameters to predict radial growth. Despite that a similar amount (61%) of the total variation in radial growth index was explained by climate for both young and old trees, residuals from young trees for the period of 1955-1999 demonstrated a stronger upward trend (<em>R</em><sup>2</sup>=0.551, <em>P</em><0.0001) than old trees for the period of 1900-1996 (<em>R</em><sup>2</sup>=0.020, <em>P</em>=0.167). Similar to young trees, the residuals from the early growth period (1900-1929) of old trees also demonstrated a stronger upward trend (<em>R</em><sup>2</sup>=0.480, <em>P</em><0.0001) than the period of 1900-1996. Likewise, a comparable period (1970-1999) of young trees also demonstrated a stronger upward trend (<em>R</em><sup>2</sup>=0.619, <em>P</em><0.0001) than the early growth period (1900-1929) of old trees. In addition, postdrought growth response was much stronger for young trees (1970-1999) compared with old trees at the same development stage (1900-1929) (<em>P</em>=0.011) or within the same time period (1970-1999) (<em>P</em>=0.014). There was no difference (<em>P</em>=0.221) in drought recovery between the early (1900-1929) period and the late (1970-1999) period within old trees. Together, our results suggest that (1) open-grown white spruce trees improved their growth with time at the early developmental stage, and (2) at the same developmental stage, a greater growth response occurred in the late period when atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, and the rate of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> increase were both relatively high. While it is impossible to rule out other factors, these results are consistent with expectations for CO<sub>2</sub>-fertilization effects.