               The effects of dataset length and mast seeding on the demography of               Frasera speciosa               , a long-lived monocarpic plant             Frasera speciosa (Gentianaceae) is a long-lived monocarpic plant with mast seeding, a type of plant whose demography is rarely studied. Using a 35-year dataset from an ongoing study, we described the population dynamics of F. speciosa using matrix projection models, addressed how many years of data are needed to estimate population growth and elasticity values consistently, and examined the effects of mast seeding on demographic parameter estimates. Our results indicated that our population is likely stable, with the annual population growth rate near one (λ = 0.969, λs = 0.967 with 95% CI = 0.923–1.013). Mean generation time was 40 years and the mean estimated lifespan was 6.86 years with a high variance of 181.8 years for individuals starting in the seedling stage, consistent with observations of very long-lived individuals in the field. Elasticity values were highest for the transitions representing stasis and lowest for reproduction. For dataset length, 15 years of data yielded lambda estimates that were within 1% of the long-term estimate, but 20 years of data were needed to yield lambdas with confidence intervals that consistently overlap one. Although mast seeding is generally defined using the inter-annual variation in seed production per unit area, stochastic lambdas were not correlated with this measure of reproduction but instead correlated with per capita dormant seed production and per capita recruit production. Mean survival rate was also positively correlated with stochastic lambda estimates, despite the necessary increase in mortality in years with high reproduction. Our results indicated that the demography of F. speciosa is similar to that of other long-lived monocarps without mast seeding, that long datasets may be needed to capture the variation in demographic rates even for stable populations, and that life history stages with low elasticity values can still be very important to population growth. 