Growth and phenology of mature temperate forest trees in elevated CO2.Are mature forest trees carbon limited at current CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations? Will 'mid-life', 35 m tall deciduous trees grow faster in a CO<sub>2</sub>-enriched atmosphere? To answer these questions we exposed ca. 100-year-old temperate forest trees at the Swiss Canopy Crane site near Basel, Switzerland to a ca. 540 ppm CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere using web-FACE technology. Here, we report growth responses to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> for 11 tall trees (compared with 32 controls) of five species during the initial four treatment years. Tested across all trees, there was no CO<sub>2</sub> effect on stem basal area (BA) increment (neither when tested per year nor cumulatively for 4 years). In fact, the 4th year means were almost identical for the two groups. Stem growth data were standardized by pretreatment growth (5 years) in order to account for a priori individual differences in vigor. Although this experiment was not designed to test species specific effects, one species, the common European beech, <em>Fagus sylvatica</em>, showed a significant growth enhancement in the first year, which reoccurred during a centennial drought in the third year. None of the other dominant species (<em>Quercus petraea</em>, <em>Carpinus betulus</em>) showed a growth response to CO<sub>2</sub> in any of the 4 years or for all years together. The inclusion or exclusion of single individuals of <em>Prunus avium</em> and <em>Tilia platyphyllos</em> did not change the picture. In elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, lateral branching in terminal shoots was higher in <em>Fagus</em> in 2002, when shoots developed from buds that were formed during the first season of CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (2001), but there was no effect in later years and no change in lateral branching in any of the other species. In <em>Quercus</em>, there was a steady stimulation of leading shoot length in high-CO<sub>2</sub> trees. Phenological variables (bud break, leaf fall, leaf duration) were highly species specific and were not affected by elevated CO<sub>2</sub> in any consistent way. Our 4-year data set reflects a very dynamic and species-specific response of tree growth to a step change in CO<sub>2</sub> supply. Stem growth after 4 years of exposure does not support the notion that mature forest trees will accrete wood biomass at faster rates in a future CO<sub>2</sub>-enriched atmosphere.