Why does the Common Ground Dove (Columbina passerina) colonize Caribbean islands but the PlainBreasted Ground Dove (C. minuta) does not?Columbina passerina and C. minuta (Aves, Columbidae) are two Neotropical species of Ground Doves with similar morphology, behavior and natural history. However, they exhibit notably different distributions on Caribbean islands. While C. passerina is found on a majority of them, C. minuta is restricted in the Caribbean to Trinidad. We hypothesized that an explanation for this extreme difference in ranges is due to differences in at least three traits often associated with successful island colonization: morphological structures that promote long flight efficiency, dietary plasticity and water requirements. We tested the first factor by comparing several wing measurements and the other two factors with experiments on wildcaught birds in controlled conditions. We did not find significant differences in wing measures. However, C. passerina showed greater dietary plasticity, a wider diet breadth and lower daily water requirements than C. minuta. Keeping in mind that island colonization success may be shaped by many variables, we concluded that the success of C. passerina maintaining populations on so many Caribbean islands is at least partially explained by its ability to survive in environments with unpredictable food changes and severe fresh water limitations as usually found on some Caribbean islands. Resumen Columbina passerina y C. minuta son dos especies neotropicales de tortolitas muy similares en morfolog铆a, comportamiento e historia natural. Sin embargo, muestran notables diferencias en su distribuci贸n en las islas del Caribe. Mientras que C. passerina se encuentra en la mayor铆a de ellas, C. minuta se restringe a Trinidad. Sugerimos que una explicaci贸n para este extremo contraste en la distribuci贸n a lo largo de las islas del Caribe se debe, al menos, a diferencias en tres caracter铆sticas asociadas con la colonizaci贸n exitosa de las islas: morfolog铆a asociada a vuelos a larga distancia, la plasticidad dietaria y requerimientos de agua. Para probar el primer factor se tomaron medidas del ala en ambas especies, y para los otros dos factores se realizaron experimentos en cautiverio. No se encontraron diferencias significativas en las medidas del ala. Sin embargo C. passerina mostr贸 una mayor plasticidad dietaria, un mayor ancho de dieta y menores requerimientos de agua que C. minuta. Teniendo en cuenta que una colonizaci贸n exitosa de las islas esta determinada por muchas variables, concluimos que el 茅xito de C. passerina en mantener poblaciones en tantas islas del Caribe, se debe al menos parcialmente a su habilidad para sobrevivir en ambientes con cambios impredecibles en los recursos y limitaciones en las fuentes de agua, condiciones t铆picas de muchas islas del Caribe.