Differential drought tolerance in tree populations from contrasting elevationsTo investigate the differential drought tolerance between populations of Pinus tabuliformis from high-elevation (HP) and low-elevation (LP), seedlings of these two populations were subjected to a gradual depletion of soil water availability with a series of traits related to growth and water use efficiency being measured. From our results, we found that all the measured variables from the HP were affected less by drought compared to those of the LP, and most aspects of the HP were canalized against drought stress. We thus drew a conclusion that the two populations responded differentially to drought stress with the HP showing higher drought tolerance than the LP. To predict the ecological consequences of climate change for a widely distributed tree species, it is essential to develop a deep understanding of the ecophysiological responses of populations from contrasting climates to varied soil water availabilities. In the present study, we focused on Pinus tabuliformis, one of the most economically and ecologically important tree species in China. In a greenhouse experiment, we exposed trees from high-elevation (HP) and low-elevation (LP) populations to low (80 % of field capacity, FC), mild (60 % FC), moderate (40 % FC) and severe (20 % FC) water stresses. Leaf gas exchange, biomass production and allocation, as well as water-use efficiency, were measured during the experiment. Increasing soil water stress clearly decreased the relative growth rate (RGR), total dry mass (TDM), light-saturated photosynthetic rate (Asat), stomatal conductance (gs), total water use (TWU) and whole-plant water-use efficiency (WUEWP). In contrast, intrinsic water-use efficiency (WUEi) and carbon isotope composition (δ13C) both increased significantly with increasing soil water stress for both populations. Only in the LP did the root/shoot ratio (R/S ratio) significantly increase when the water stress increased. A strong positive correlation between Asat and gs coupled with a reduced intercellular CO2 concentration (Ci) probably suggested that stomatal limitations were the main cause of the decreased Asat. However, all the measured variables from the HP were affected less by drought compared with those of the LP, and most aspects of the HP were canalized against drought stress, which was reflected by the relatively higher RGR, TDM and WUEWP. Overall, the results suggest that the two populations responded differentially to drought stress with the HP showing higher drought tolerance than the LP, which was reflected by its faster seedling growth rate and more efficient water use under drought conditions.