Induced resistance in groundnut by jasmonic acid and salicylic acid through alteration of trichome density and oviposition by Helicoverpa armigera (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)Jasmonic acid (JA) and salicylic acid (SA) play an important role in activating plant defensive responses against insect pests. In these experiments, trichome density increased in groundnut plants by the pretreatment of JA and SA; however, JA induced significantly greater number of trichomes than SA. Moreover, JA activated antixenosis for oviposition by H. armigera. Insect resistant genotypes (ICGV 86699, ICGV 86031, ICG 2271 and ICG 1697) showed stronger response than the JL 24 (susceptible check). These results show that pre-treatment with JA not only resulted in greater trichome density in groundnut plants, but also conferred antixenosis for oviposition by H. armigera. Jasmonic acid (JA) and salicylic acid (SA) are important phytohormones involved in plant resistance against insect herbivory and pathogen infection. Application of JA and SA induces several defensive traits in plants. Here we investigated the effect of JA and SA on trichome density in five groundnut genotypes [ICGV 86699, ICGV 86031, ICG 2271, ICG 1697 (resistant) and JL 24 (susceptible)]. The effect of JA- and SA-induced resistance on the oviposition behaviour of Helicoverpa armigera on different groundnut genotypes was also studied. Pre-treatment with JA increased numbers of trichomes in the insect-resistant genotypes, ICGV 86699, ICGV 86031, ICG 2271, and ICG 1697. The induction was greater at 10 days after treatment. Jasmonic acid- and SA-treated plants showed a substantial effect on the oviposition behaviour of H. armigera. Jasmonic acid application and herbivory reduced the number of eggs laid by H. armigera in all the groundnut genotypes tested. However, a greater reduction was recorded on plants pre-treated with JA. More egg laying was recorded in JL 24 in all the treatments as compared to the insect-resistant genotypes. These results suggested that pre-treatment with JA increased trichome density in groundnut plants, which conferred antixenosis for oviposition by H. armigera.