Contribution of natural and anthropogenic aerosols to optical properties and radiative effects over an urban locationA method to determine the contribution of natural and anthropogenic aerosol species to aerosol radiative forcing using surface-based, columnar and vertical profile measurements, optical properties and radiative transfer models is outlined. Aerosol optical properties and radiative fluxes measured during 2008 over Ahmedabad, an urban city located in western India are utilized. Mid-visible aerosol optical depth (AOD) does not show a strong seasonal variation, while α, the Ångström exponent, exhibits significant seasonal variation. α is higher during winter and post-monsoon, when fine mode aerosols are dominant, while α is lower during pre-monsoon and monsoon, when coarse mode aerosols are abundant. The contribution of mineral dust to the total aerosol mass is higher than 55% as the study location is in a semi-arid region. Natural aerosols (mineral dust and sea salt) dominate the aerosol mass concentration, while anthropogenic aerosols (water soluble aerosols and black carbon) dominate the aerosol optical depth. The percentage contribution of black carbon to the net atmospheric forcing is larger than 65% throughout the year, corroborating that black carbon aerosol is a strong contributor to global warming on regional scales. Black carbon aerosols contribute 50% or more to the aerosol radiative forcing at the surface, thus, significantly contributing to solar dimming. The large atmospheric warming and the surface forcing due to black carbon aerosols can influence the hydrological cycle. Results emphasize that aerosol radiative forcing is governed more by aerosol optical properties (aerosol optical depth and single scattering albedo) rather than their mass, and there exists no linear relation between mass, optical depth and radiative effects of different aerosol species. These results and the relationship can be used to delineate the anthropogenic influence of aerosols from their natural counterpart, because anthropogenic aerosols in the fine mode (lower mass) give rise to higher AOD, lower SSA, higher aerosol radiative forcing, while natural aerosols which are in the coarse mode (higher mass) give rise to lower AOD, higher SSA and lower aerosol radiative forcing.