Carbonate, organic and clay fractions determine metal bioavailability in periurban calcareous agricultural soils in the Mediterranean areaA set of periurban calcareous agricultural Mediterranean soils, with a natural gradient in the content and composition of organic matter (OM), was spiked with a mixture of Cd, Cu, Pb and Zn at two levels – designated Tt1 and Tt2 – within the limit values proposed by the current European legislation and incubated for ≤ 12 months. We conducted bioassay experiments with romaine and iceberg varieties of lettuce (Lactuca sativa L.). Metal bioavailability patterns were evaluated as a function of soil constituents and extractable metals.  Metal contamination produced a decrease in plant biomass (up to 50%) and nutrient imbalance. The redundancy analysis showed that the carbonate, OM and fine mineral fractions account for up to 85% of the variance in metal bioavailability patterns in lettuce plants. Carbonate and fine mineral fractions were negatively related to Cd and Zn bioavailability in plants respectively. Organic matter explained Cu and Pb bioavailability, although patterns varied between plant tissues according to their organic composition. The labile fraction limited metal absorption of Pb by roots at the Tt2 level and Cu at both levels, but Cu and Pb translocation was enhanced at both levels. There were significant correlations between metals in leaves and metals extracted with both neutral salts and complexing agents. The high rate of metal translocation and the considerable influence of soil properties may indicate that the limiting values of metals in soils proposed by the current European legislation should be revised in the case of multi-component systems, and/or be established according to the soil characteristics.  Abbreviations DTPA, diethylene triamine pentaacetic acid; TEA, triethanolamine; EDTA, ethylene diamine tetra-acetic acid; LMWOA, low molecular weight organic acids; ECC, equivalent CaCO3; CEC, cation exchange capacity; TOC, total organic C; OM, organic matter; LPI, labile pool I of organic matter; LPII, labile pool II of organic matter; RP, recalcitrant pool of organic matter; AAS, atomic absorption spectroscopy; XRD, X-ray diffraction; TI, tolerance index; TF, translocation factor; ANOVA, Analysis of Variance; SPSS, Statistical Package for the Social Sciences; RDA, redundancy analysis; CANOCO, Canonical Community Ordination