New earthworm species of the genus Pheretima (Clitellata: Megascolecidae) from Mountain Province, PhilippinesSix new species of the genus Pheretima are described from Mt. Amuyao and Mt. Lamagan, near Barlig, Mountain Province, the Philippines: Pheretima tanudanensis sp. nov., Pheretima amuyaoensis sp. nov., Pheretima salcedoi sp. nov., Pheretima lamaganensis sp. nov., Pheretima julkai sp. nov., and Pheretima barligensis sp. nov. Pheretima tanudanensis sp. nov. has spermathecal pores in 6/7, 0.18–0.22 circumference ventrally apart, copulatory bursae openings 0.21–0.22 circumference apart, intestinal origin in XVI, and non-muscular spermathecal ducts. Pheretima amuyaoensis sp. nov. and Pheretima salcedoi sp. nov. have spermathecal pores in 5/6–6/7, a condition not previously known in the genus. Pheretima amuyaoensis sp. nov. has ventral spermathecal pores 0.23–0.24 circumference apart, copulatory bursae openings 0.23 circumference apart, and the intestinal origin in XVI. Pheretima salcedoi sp. nov. has ventral spermathecal pores 0.21–0.29 circumference apart, copulatory bursae openings 0.18–0.20 circumference apart, and the intestinal origin in XV. Pheretima lamaganensis sp. nov. and Pheretima julkai sp. nov. belong to the dubia group in Sims and Easton with three pairs of spermathecal pores in 6/7–8/9. Pheretima lamaganensis sp. nov. is a small-bodied worm with more setae in VII than in XX, two pairs of spermathecae in VII, one pair of spermathecae in VIII, ventral spermathecal pores 0.27–0.28 circumference apart and copulatory bursae openings 0.21–0.22 circumference apart. Pheretima julkai sp. nov. has two pairs of spermathecae in VII, one pair of spermathecae in VIII, ventral spermathecal pores 0.20–0.23 circumference apart and copulatory bursae openings 0.18–0.20 circumference apart, typhlosole lacking. One new earthworm, Pheretima barligensis sp. nov. belongs to the darnleiensis group with four pairs of spermathecal pores in 5/6–8/9, and has ventral spermathecal pores 0.16–0.22 circumference apart, copulatory bursae openings 0.19–0.22 circumference apart, an intestinal origin in XVI, and septa 8/9–9/10 present.