Rhizospheric and heterotrophic components of soil respiration in six Chinese temperate forestsPartitioning soil respiration (<em>R</em><sub>S</sub>) into heterotrophic (<em>R</em><sub>H</sub>) and rhizospheric (<em>R</em><sub>R</sub>) components is an important step for understanding and modeling carbon cycling in forest ecosystems, but few studies on <em>R</em><sub>R</sub> and <em>R</em><sub>H</sub> exist in Chinese temperate forests. In this study, we used a trenching plot approach to partition <em>R</em><sub>S</sub> in six temperate forests in northeastern China. Our specific objectives were to (1) examine seasonal patterns of soil surface CO<sub>2</sub> fluxes from trenched (<em>R</em><sub>T</sub>) and untrenched plots (<em>R</em><sub>UT</sub>) of these forests; (2) quantify annual fluxes of <em>R</em><sub>S</sub> components and their relative contributions in the forest ecosystems; and (3) examine effects of plot trenching on measurements of <em>R</em><sub>S</sub> and related environmental factors. The <em>R</em><sub>T</sub> maximized in early growing season, but the difference between <em>R</em><sub>UT</sub> and <em>R</em><sub>T</sub> peaked in later summer. The annual fluxes of <em>R</em><sub>H</sub> and <em>R</em><sub>R</sub> varied with forest types. The estimated values of <em>R</em><sub>H</sub> for the Korean pine (<em>Pinus koraiensis</em> Sieb. et Zucc.), Dahurian larch (<em>Larix gmelinii</em> Rupr.), aspen-birch (<em>Populous davidiana</em> Dode and <em>Betula platyphylla</em> Suk.), hardwood (<em>Fraxinus mandshurica</em> Rupr., <em>Juglans mandshurica</em> Maxim. and <em>Phellodendron amurense</em> Rupr.), Mongolian oak (<em>Quercus mongolica</em> Fisch.) and mixed deciduous (no dominant tree species) forests averaged 89, 196, 187, 245, 261 and 301 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>, respectively; those of <em>R</em><sub>R</sub> averaged 424, 209, 628, 538, 524 and 483 g C m<sup>-;2</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>, correspondingly; calculated contribution of <em>R</em><sub>R</sub> to <em>R</em><sub>S</sub> (<em>RC</em>) varied from 52% in the larch forest to 83% in the pine forest. The annual flux of <em>R</em><sub>R</sub> was strongly correlated to biomass of roots <0.5 cm in diameter, while that of <em>R</em><sub>H</sub> was weakly correlated to soil organic carbon concentration at A horizon. We concluded that vegetation type and associated carbon metabolisms of temperate forests should be considered in assessing and modeling <em>R</em><sub>S</sub> components. The significant impacts of changed soil physical environments and substrate availability by plot trenching should be appropriately tackled in analyzing and interpreting measurements of <em>R</em><sub>S</sub> components.