Evaluating the Impact of the Spatial Distribution of Land Management Practices on Water Erosion: Case Study of a Mediterranean CatchmentAbstractThe spatial distribution of land management practices (LMPs), such as the use of vegetated filters, may have a strong impact on their efficiency in trapping sediments and pollutants. Distributed water erosion models help managers, planners, and policymakers optimize the efficiency of these LMPs regarding their location relative to water and sediment pathways. In this work, the authors analyzed the impact of the spatial distribution of LMPs using an existing distributed model and sensitivity analysis procedures. The distributed model that was used is a distributed single-event physically based water erosion model developed to calculate erosion rates and sediment flow for small (less than 10  km2) agricultural catchments. To measure the impact of the spatial distribution of LMPs, the authors developed a stochastic model that generates LMP locations over the entire catchment. The stochastic model has three input parameters: the density of LMPs, their downslope/upslope location probability, and the probability density function shape controller. Because of its ability to account for the cross effects between parameters, the variance-based Sobol method was used to calculate the sensitivity of the soil loss ratio of a typical Mediterranean agricultural catchment (Roujan, southern France) to the LMP location model parameters. Three measurement points (two subcatchment outlets and the main outlet) were used to examine the spatially distributed effects of the LMP locations. The simulation results indicated that 70% of the variation of the net erosion is explained by variations in LMP density for the main outlet catchment, making LMP density the most sensitive parameter. However, the total Sobol sensitivity indices indicate a strong interaction among the three parameters when the density values are low (few LMPs are applied). Thus, although the density of the LMPs is the most sensitive parameter, their location may influence their global trapping efficiency in (real) cases where few LMPs are applied.