ANNUAL SOIL RESPIRATION CYCLE IN A BEECH FOREST AT MONTE TABURNO ITALY CAMPANIAN APENNINES IN RELATION TO PRINCIPAL ECOLOGICAL FACTORSSoil respiration measurements taken from Sept. 1972 to Nov. 1973, in a beech forest of Monte Taburno in the Campania Appennines [Italy] (41.degree.05'00" N, 12.degree.27'08" E) are presented. The site of the experiment is located at an altitude of 1100 m, on a southern slope, 25% step. The luxuriant stand, with rich undergrowth, consists of 90 yr old Fagus sylvatica L. The vegetation grouping belongs to Aquifolio Fagetum Gentile. The soil is a brown earth. The regional climate is characterized by copious rainfall from Oct. to March. The 40 yr mean annual rainfall for the closest (10 km S) meteorological station (Montevergine) is 2165.8 mm. The 80 yr mean annual temperature is 7.9.degree. C. Monthly mean temperature varies from -0.3.degree. in Jan. to 17.1.degree. C in Aug. Evolution of CO2 from the entire profile of the forest floor and from the soil after removal of the litter layer was measured, twice a month, by the inverted-box method over a 24 h period, using 4 replicate tins. Along with soil respiration, temperature and relative humidity in the surface air at 10 cm, and soil temperature at 5 cm depth, were recorded. Moisture content of the soil was determined before and after each run. Daily mean temperatures agree well with those of Montevergine. Variation pattern of soil water content, mostly higher as 70%, corresponds with rainfall height. Seasonal variations of CO2 evolution from exposed soil and from entire profile are quite similar, while respiration values of undisturbed soil are significantly higher as those of the soil without litter layer. The lowest respiration rates (38 mg/m2 per h) were measured in winter; the highest (200 mg/m2 per h) in summer. Soil respiration is set in relation with soil temperature and moisture. A correlation was found between the rate of CO2 evolution from the litter free soil and the mean daily soil temperature at 5 cm depth (r = 0.72; P < 0.001). A temperature increase of 10.degree. C determines a 2-fold increase of soil metabolism. A negative high correlation (r = -0.68; P < 0.001) exists between soil moisture (5 cm depth) and the rates of CO2 evolution from the soil. A humidity increase of 10 g H2O/100 g dry soil causes a 20 mg decrease of CO2 evolution rate. The calculated annual release of 553.03 liters/m2 is equivalent to the CO2 released by complete oxidation of 0.790 kg dry matter. In the literature higher values are available for a beech forest in Denmark. Although the latter are considered too high, the reason for the relatively low CO2 evolution rates in the beech forest of Monte Taburno is the high soil moisture during most of the year as indicated by the high negative correlation between water content and soil respiration.