Interactions among tree-line conifers: differential effects of pine on spruce and larch<ol><li>Plant-plant interactions are increasingly considered as complex phenomena involving both negative and positive components. Within a community, the relative importance of these components is probably species-specific and may also vary among life-history stages and along environmental gradients.</li><li>We used the tree line of the north-eastern Calcareous Alps of Austria, composed of shrubby <em>Pinus mugo</em> and upright <em>Picea abies</em> and <em>Larix decidua</em>, as a simple system in which to investigate these interactions. We focused on the largely unknown effects of pines on spruce and larch, rather than on <em>P. mugo</em>, which is known to be competitively displaced by the two tree species.</li><li>We used regression models on observational data to analyse the responses of the trees to a gradient of pine cover in terms of recruitment, growth, fecundity and browsing damage, and to determine whether effects involved both competitive and facilitative components, if they depended on the life-history stage of the trees and if they were species-specific.</li><li>We detected a pronounced negative effect of pine cover on recruitment and growth of both spruce and larch, whereas seed production was unaffected. Larch turned out to be more sensitive to pine competition: its recruitment and growth are superior to that of spruce in open habitats but this advantage vanishes in dense pine thickets.</li><li>Contrary to expectations, the effects of pine cover on growth rates of spruce and larch did not depend on the life-history stage of the trees.</li><li>Pine cover is a major determinant of browsing damage for both spruce and larch, indicating that it does have a positive effect in providing shelter against herbivores.</li><li>The differential effects of pines on spruce and larch are likely to favour spruce at the expense of larch in realizing potential habitat expansion as a result of climate change. Disregarding the complex details of plant-plant interactions may thus result in unrealistic predictions of species responses to environmental changes.</li></ol>