Contribution of different proton sources to pedogenetic soil acidification in forested ecosystems in JapanThe contribution of different proton sources to pedogenetic soil acidification was evaluated for three Japanese forest soils, i.e. ando soil, podzolic soil and brown forest soil in relation to the respective soil forming processes. Soil acidification rate and net proton generation were quantified based on the theory of proton budget for the respective soil horizon compartments (mainly the O, A and B horizons) by measuring fluxes of solutes entering and leaving the soil horizon compartment and vegetation uptake. Protons were produced by the dissociation of organic acids and nitrification in the O horizon and then consumed by adsorption and decomposition of organic acids and nitrate uptake by vegetation in deeper soil horizons at all plots. Excess uptake of cation over anion by vegetation was highest among proton sources in the whole soil compartment at all plots. Pedogenetic soil acidification was considered to include cation leaching from surface soil horizons due to proton generation by the dissociation of organic acids and nitrification and subsequent cation excess accumulation in wood in the growth stage of forests. In ando soil, andosolization resulted from the low contribution of net proton generation by the dissociation of organic acids as well as a lower soil acidification rate and complete acid neutralization. Dissolved organic carbon (DOC) fluxes in ando soil were lower than those in podzolic soil and brown forest soil due to high adsorption capacity of amorphous materials. In podzolic soil, podzolization resulted from intensive acidification in the O horizon, which derived from net proton generation by the dissociation of organic acids and nitrification as well as cation excess uptake by vegetation due to concentrated fine root biomass in the O horizon, and subsequent high proton efflux to subsoil. The high fluxes of DOC and Al leached from surface soil horizons were considered to contribute to eluviation of Al from surface soil and illuviation in subsoil in podzolic soil. In brown forest soil, brunification resulted from a lower DOC flux from the O horizon due to high decomposition and adsorption by oxides, where podzolization was weakened by high acid neutralization. Thus, the three representative processes involved in the pedogenesis of Japanese forest soils were well characterized by quantification of the respective proton-generating and consuming processes in each soil horizon.