SYNTHESIS OF A SIX-YEAR STUDY OF CALCAREOUS GRASSLAND RESPONSES TO IN SITU CO2 ENRICHMENT.We exposed species-rich temperate calcareous grassland to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> (600 μL/L) for six growing seasons and studied carbon (C) and nutrient (nitrogen [N] and phosphorus [P]) cycling, water relations, and plant community structure and diversity. CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment stimulated leaf- and ecosystem-level daytime CO<sub>2</sub> uptake and increased plant community productivity; relative CO<sub>2</sub> effects on aboveground biomass were predicted with <em>r</em> <−0.98 (<em>r</em><sup>2</sup> > 0.95) by precipitation prior to biomass harvests. The underlying mechanisms were water savings due to reduced leaf conductance under elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, allowing for more growth in this temporarily water-limited ecosystem; this effect was more important in dry years. At the plant-species level, no effects of [CO<sub>2</sub>] were found except for the subdominant sedges <em>Carex flacca</em> and <em>C. caryophyllea</em>, which responded positively to elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, mainly due to increased soil moisture. Bryophytes also responded to CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment for the same reason. At a more aggregate level, elevated CO<sub>2</sub> increased species evenness (but not richness). Community productivity was N-limited; legumes derived >90% of their N from atmospheric N<sub>2</sub>, but did not respond to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> because they were limited by low P availability. This ultimately also prevented larger community-level responses to elevated CO<sub>2</sub> because eventually extra legume N would have been transferred to nonlegumes, resulting in extra biomass. Higher biomass in elevated CO<sub>2</sub> was attained by increasing C:N and C:P ratios; total N and P in plant biomass remained unaffected by [CO<sub>2</sub>]. N retention, legume dinitrogen fixation (both assessed with <sup>15</sup>N), and microbial net N immobilization did not change. Based on our findings, our main conclusions are: (1) The effect of elevated CO<sub>2</sub> is mainly indirect via effects on the hydrological cycle in this water-limited ecosystem; (2) the C cycle responds more than mineral nutrient cycles; (3) low available P ultimately limited community productivity and responses to CO<sub>2</sub>, and this limitation may not be atypical for many natural ecosystems in which N inventories often are controlled by biologically available P; and (4) that interactions with variable environmental conditions critically co-determine CO<sub>2</sub> responses, which contrasts with greenhouse studies and emphasizes the importance of field studies in predicting long-term effects of increasing [CO<sub>2</sub>] on natural ecosystems.