Diet of the Rufous‚Älegged Owl (Strix rufipes, Strigiformes) in an Andean Nothofagus‚ÄìAraucaria forest, southern ChileWe quantified the diet of the Rufous‚Älegged Owl (Strix rufipes) by analyzing 40 pellets collected during the austral autumn 2001, 2003 and 2004 in an Andean Nothofagus‚ÄìAraucaria forest, southern Chile. Five small mammal species, two passerine birds, insects of two orders, four scorpions and a snail were identified in the pellets. Although insects were the most numerous prey (72.4% of all prey items), small mammals constituted most of the biomass (89.2%). The arboreal small mammals Dromiciops gliroides and Irenomys tarsalis were the most frequently consumed prey (10.4% and 6.3% of all individuals; 37.7% and 28% of total biomass, respectively). The scansorial Oligoryzomys longicaudatus accounted for almost 3% of all items and 7% of total biomass. Terrestrial small mammals accounted for only 1% of all individual prey and 3.6% of total biomass. Our results were similar to those reported for Rufous‚Älegged Owls inhabiting Valdivian rainforests, which suggest that this owl species is conservative in its food habits throughout the southern temperate forest, hunting mostly arboreal and scansorial small mammals. Resumen La dieta del conc√≥n (Strix rufipes) fue cuantificada sobre la base de 40 regurgitados colectados durante los oto√±os de 2001, 2003 y 2004 en un bosque andino de Nothofagus‚ÄìAraucaria en el sur de Chile. Cinco especies de micromam√≠feros, dos aves paserinas, dos √≥rdenes de insectos, cuatro escorpiones y un caracol fueron identificados en los regurgitados. Aunque los insectos fueron las presas m√°s numerosas (72.4% de todas las presas individuales), los micromam√≠feros constituyeron la mayor parte de la biomasa (89.2%). Los micromam√≠feros arbor√≠colas Dromiciops gliroides e Irenomys tarsalis fueron las presas m√°s consumidas (10.4% y 6.3% de todas las presas; 37.7% y 28% de la biomasa total, respectivamente). Oligoryzomys longicaudatus, un roedor trepador, constituy√≥ casi el 3% de todas las presas y 7% de la biomasa total. Los micromam√≠feros terrestres alcanzaron s√≥lo el 1% de todas las presas y 3.6% de la biomasa total. Nuestros resultados fueron similares con aquellos documentados para concones que habitan el bosque Valdiviano del sur de Chile, sugiriendo que la especie es conservadora en sus h√°bitos tr√≥ficos a lo largo del bosque templado austral, cazando principalmente micromam√≠feros arbor√≠colas y trepadores.