Population genetics of purple saxifrage (Saxifraga oppositifolia) in the high Arctic archipelago of SvalbardUsing DNA markers and sequencing we investigated patterns of genetic variability in purple saxifrage, Saxifraga oppositifolia in the isolated Arctic Svalbard archipelago. Purple saxifrage is a circumpolar, ecologically and morphologically variable species with a wide range of habitats. Population genetic structures showed that both genetic variation and differentiation levels are modest, outcrossing is the main mating system, and dispersal and gene flow are important, likely accountable to strong winds and human and animal vectors. Different growth habits (compact, trailing and intermediate) did not possess distinct genetic composition. We investigated patterns of genetic variability in Saxifraga oppositifolia in the isolated Arctic Svalbard archipelago. The genetic analysis included genotyping using nine polymorphic microsatellite markers and sequencing of the nuclear internal transcribed spacer region. Among populations, mean allele numbers per microsatellite locus ranged from 2.0 to 2.6, and 9 % of alleles were unique. Observed (HO) and expected (HE) heterozygosities averaged 0.522 and 0.445, respectively. Typically negative but non-significant FIS values (mean −0.173) were found in S. oppositifolia populations. FST values were relatively low (mean 0.123). The Bayesian structure analysis provided additional information on population genetic structures. Seven out of 11 studied populations, including populations located both near each other and far apart (distances 5–210 km), showed relatively homogeneous clustering patterns, while one population located on a slope in the main settlement of Longyearbyen possessed a unique genetic structure. The Mantel test proved that there is no significant correlation between genetic and geographical distances. Different growth habits (compact, trailing and intermediate) did not possess distinct genetic compositions based on microsatellite variation. Internal transcribed spacer sequencing revealed 12 polymorphic sites. Among 24 sequenced Svalbard samples, eight haplotypes were detected, none shared by the mainland samples. Population genetic structures of S. oppositifolia in Svalbard show that both genetic variation and differentiation levels are modest, outcrossing is the main mating system, and dispersal and gene flow are important, probably attributable to strong winds and human and animal vectors.