Relative importance of phenotypic trait matching and species' abundances in determining plant–avian seed dispersal interactions in a small insular communityIn this paper the authors take advantage of the simplicity of an insular community to evaluate the relative importance of species' phenotypic traits and species' abundance in determining fruit-avian disperser interactions, at both network and pairwise interaction levels. The authors innovatively include fruit nutrient compounds in fruit-avian network analyses. Although the best way to predict plant-avian interactions was based on both phenotypic traits and species abundance, the most important factor to explain these mutualistic interactions was fruit-beak size overlap, followed by species abundance and fruit nutrient compounds. This work will encourage further studies to look for similar patterns in more species-rich communities. Network theory has provided a general way to understand mutualistic plant–animal interactions at the community level. However, the mechanisms responsible for interaction patterns remain controversial. In this study we use a combination of statistical models and probability matrices to evaluate the relative importance of species morphological and nutritional (phenotypic) traits and species abundance in determining interactions between fleshy-fruited plants and birds that disperse their seeds. The models included variables associated with species abundance, a suite of variables associated with phenotypic traits (fruit diameter, bird bill width, fruit nutrient compounds), and the species identity of the avian disperser. Results show that both phenotypic traits and species abundance are important determinants of pairwise interactions. However, when considered separately, fruit diameter and bill width were more important in determining seed dispersal interactions. The effect of fruit compounds was less substantial and only important when considered together with abundance-related variables and/or the factor ‘animal species’.