Arthropod Food Web Restoration Following Removal Of An Invasive Wetland Plant.ration of habitats impacted by invasive plants is becoming an increasingly important tool in the management of native biodiversity, though most studies do not go beyond monitoring the abundance of particular taxonomic groups, such as the return of native vegetation. Yet, the reestablishment of trophic interactions among organisms in restored habitats is equally important if we are to monitor and understand how ecosystems recover. This study examined whether food web interactions among arthropods (as inferred by abundance of naturally occurring stable isotopes of C [δ<sup>13</sup>C] and N [δ<sup>15</sup>N]) were reestablished in the restoration of a coastal <em>Spartina alterniflora</em> salt marsh that had been invaded by <em>Phragmites australis</em>.<br><br>From patterns of C and N stable isotopes we infer that trophic interactions among arthropods in the native salt marsh habitats are characterized by reliance on the dominant marsh plant <em>Spartina</em> as a basal resource. Herbivores such as delphacid planthoppers and mirid bugs have isotope signatures characteristic of <em>Spartina</em>, and predatory arthropods such as dolicopodid flies and spiders likewise have δ<sup>13</sup>C and δ<sup>15</sup>N signatures typical of <em>Spartina</em>-derived resources (approximately −13‰ and 10‰, respectively). Stable isotope patterns also suggest that the invasion of <em>Phragmites</em> into salt marshes and displacement of <em>Spartina</em> significantly alter arthropod food web interactions. Arthropods in <em>Phragmites</em>-dominated sites have δ<sup>13</sup>C isotope values between −18‰ and −20‰, suggesting reliance on detritus and/or benthic microalgae as basal resources and not on <em>Phragmites</em>, which has a δ<sup>13</sup>C approximately −26‰. Since most <em>Phragmites</em> herbivores are either feeding internally or are rare transients from nearby <em>Spartina</em>, these resources do not provide significant prey resources for other arthropod consumers. Rather, predator isotope signatures in the invaded habitats indicate dependence on detritus/algae as basal resources instead of the dominant vegetation. The reestablishment of <em>Spartina</em> after removal of <em>Phragmites</em>, however, not only returned species assemblages typical of reference (uninvaded) <em>Spartina</em>, but stable isotope signatures suggest that the trophic interactions among the arthropods were also similar in reestablished habitats. Specifically, both herbivores and predators showed characteristic <em>Spartina</em> signatures, suggesting the return of the original grazer-based food web structure in the restored habitats.