Collision avoidance by migrating raptors encountering a new electric power transmission lineAvian collisions with overhead power lines are of conservation concern, particularly in migration corridors. We studied potential collisions where an existing power line supported by towers 20–25 m tall was replaced by the Susquehanna-Roseland line (S-R line), a new line with towers 55–60 m tall. The S-R line crosses Kittatinny Ridge, a corridor for raptors migrating south through New Jersey and Pennsylvania, USA. We hypothesized that the S-R line, which on Kittatinny Ridge includes markers designed to increase its visibility to birds, would cause migrating raptors to react in 1 of 3 ways: (1) to not alter flight elevation, but to pass safely through the S-R wire zone; (2) to not alter flight elevation, and to not pass safely through the wire zone, leading to collisions; or (3) to alter flight elevation and to pass safely above or below the S-R wire zone. To evaluate these hypotheses, we recorded the flight elevations of migrating raptors in 2013 before construction of the S-R line and in 2014 postconstruction. Preconstruction, we recorded 3,698 raptor crossings. Most raptors (72%) crossed above the anticipated S-R wire zone. Some (24%) passed through the anticipated S-R wire zone, and a few (4%) passed below the anticipated S-R wire zone. Postconstruction, we recorded 4,482 crossings. Most raptors (92%) crossed above the S-R wire zone. A few passed through (5%) or below (3%) the S-R wire zone. Postconstruction, raptors responded to the new line by flying higher than they had when traversing the previous line. We did not observe any collisions. Altered flight elevations and the absence of observed collisions supported hypothesis 3. If similar patterns occur at other lines that cross diurnal migration corridors along ridges, then future monitoring may be better focused on potentially riskier settings, such as areas where migrating birds do not have deflected winds to assist with gaining elevation.