Soil-atmospheric exchange of CO2, CH4, and N2O in three subtropical forest ecosystems in southern ChinaThe magnitude, temporal, and spatial patterns of soil-atmospheric greenhouse gas (hereafter referred to as GHG) exchanges in forests near the Tropic of Cancer are still highly uncertain. To contribute towards an improvement of actual estimates, soil-atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub>, and N<sub>2</sub>O fluxes were measured in three successional subtropical forests at the Dinghushan Nature Reserve (hereafter referred to as DNR) in southern China. Soils in DNR forests behaved as N<sub>2</sub>O sources and CH<sub>4</sub> sinks. Annual mean CO<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O, and CH<sub>4</sub> fluxes (mean±SD) were 7.7±4.6 Mg CO<sub>2</sub>-C ha<sup>-;1</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>, 3.2±1.2 kg N<sub>2</sub>O-N ha<sup>-;1</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>, and 3.4±0.9 kg CH<sub>4</sub>-C ha<sup>-;1</sup> yr<sup>-;1</sup>, respectively. The climate was warm and wet from April through September 2003 (the hot-humid season) and became cool and dry from October 2003 through March 2004 (the cool-dry season). The seasonality of soil CO<sub>2</sub> emission coincided with the seasonal climate pattern, with high CO<sub>2</sub> emission rates in the hot-humid season and low rates in the cool-dry season. In contrast, seasonal patterns of CH<sub>4</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O fluxes were not clear, although higher CH<sub>4</sub> uptake rates were often observed in the cool-dry season and higher N<sub>2</sub>O emission rates were often observed in the hot-humid season. GHG fluxes measured at these three sites showed a clear increasing trend with the progressive succession. If this trend is representative at the regional scale, CO<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O emissions and CH<sub>4</sub> uptake in southern China may increase in the future in light of the projected change in forest age structure. Removal of surface litter reduced soil CO<sub>2</sub> effluxes by 17-44% in the three forests but had no significant effect on CH<sub>4</sub> absorption and N<sub>2</sub>O emission rates. This suggests that microbial CH<sub>4</sub> uptake and N<sub>2</sub>O production was mainly related to the mineral soil rather than in the surface litter layer.