Growth of in vitro Oncidesa plantlets cultured under cold cathode fluorescent lamps with super-elevated CO2 enrichmentHow can one increase the biomass of plants, particularly orchids, in an effective way? Photoautotrophic micropropagation is an effective means of increasing the biomass of Oncidesa orchids. Using 10,000 µmol mol−1 CO2 and a photosynthetic photon flux density of 60 µmol m−2 s−1, the number of leaves and roots and shoot and root fresh and dry weights could be considerably increased, but only when cultured on Kyoto medium rather than Vacin and Went medium. Super-elevated CO2 enrichment and growth under cold cathode fluorescent lamps can positively affect the efficiency and quality of commercial production of clonal Oncidesa plantlets. As interest in how to increase biomass production through biotechnological means gains traction, focus is turning towards the use of photoautotrophic micropropagation under elevated levels of carbon dioxide (CO2) to maximize plant growth and productivity. The effect of super-elevated CO2 with cold cathode fluorescent lamps (CCFLs) on the photoautotrophic growth of Oncidesa in vitro has been studied using a gas-permeable film culture vessel, the ‘Vitron’. The growth of Oncidesa (formerly Oncidesa Gower Ramsey ‘U-1’) plantlets on Vacin and Went (VW) medium was stimulated by 10 000 μmol mol−1 CO2. In particular, increasing the photosynthetic photon flux density (PPFD) from 45 to 60 μmol m−2 s−1 under 10 000 μmol mol−1 CO2 in the growth chamber remarkably increased the number of leaves and roots, and shoot and root fresh and dry weights compared with plantlets under the same level of CO2 under low PPFD (45 μmol m−2 s−1). However, there was a remarkable decrease in photosynthetic capacity, and chlorosis and browning of leaves. In stark contrast, plantlets grown on Kyoto medium at 10 000 μmol mol−1 CO2 under high PPFD had a higher photosynthetic rate than plantlets grown on VW medium, and no chlorosis or browning was observed. Furthermore, shoot growth was remarkably enhanced. Therefore, super-elevated CO2 (10 000 μmol mol−1) enrichment and growth under CCFLs can positively affect the efficiency and quality of commercial production of clonal Oncidesa plantlets.