Oxygen effects on methane production and oxidation in humid tropical forest soils.We investigated the effects of oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) concentration on methane (CH<sub>4</sub>) production and oxidation in two humid tropical forests that differ in long-term, time-averaged soil O<sub>2</sub> concentrations. We identified sources and sinks of CH<sub>4</sub> through the analysis of soil gas concentrations, surface emissions, and carbon isotope measurements. Isotope mass balance models were used to calculate the fraction of CH<sub>4</sub> oxidized <em>in situ</em>. Complementary laboratory experiments were conducted to determine the effects of O<sub>2</sub> concentration on gross and net rates of methanogenesis. Field and laboratory experiments indicated that high levels of CH<sub>4</sub> production occurred in soils that contained between 9±1.1% and 19±0.2% O<sub>2</sub>. For example, we observed CH<sub>4</sub> concentrations in excess of 3% in soils with 9±1.1% O<sub>2</sub>. CH<sub>4</sub> emissions from the lower O<sub>2</sub> sites were high (22-101 nmol CH<sub>4</sub> m<sup>-;2</sup> s<sup>-;1</sup>), and were equal in magnitude to CH<sub>4</sub> emissions from natural wetlands. During peak periods of CH<sub>4</sub> efflux, carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) emissions became enriched in <sup>13</sup>C because of high methanogenic activity. Gross CH<sub>4</sub> production was probably greater than flux measurements indicated, as isotope mass balance calculations suggested that 48-78% of the CH<sub>4</sub> produced was oxidized prior to atmospheric egress. O<sub>2</sub> availability influenced CH<sub>4</sub> oxidation more strongly than methanogenesis. Gross CH<sub>4</sub> production was relatively insensitive to O<sub>2</sub> concentrations in laboratory experiments. In contrast, methanotrophic bacteria oxidized a greater fraction of total CH<sub>4</sub> production with increasing O<sub>2</sub> concentration, shifting the <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C composition of CH<sub>4</sub> to values that were more positive. Isotopic measurements suggested that CO<sub>2</sub> was an important source of carbon for methanogenesis in humid forests. The <em>&delta;</em><sup>13</sup>C value of methanogenesis was between -;84&permil; and -;98&permil;, which is well within the range of CH<sub>4</sub> produced from CO<sub>2</sub> reduction, and considerably more depleted in <sup>13</sup>C than CH<sub>4</sub> formed from acetate.