Photosynthesis, carboxylation and leaf nitrogen responses of 16 species to elevated pCO2 across four free-air CO2 enrichment experiments in forest, grassland and desert.The magnitude of changes in carboxylation capacity in dominant plant species under long-term elevated CO<sub>2</sub> exposure (elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub>) directly impacts ecosystem CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation from the atmosphere. We analyzed field CO<sub>2</sub> response curves of 16 C<sub>3</sub> species of different plant growth forms in favorable growth conditions in four free-air CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment (FACE) experiments in a pine and deciduous forest, a grassland and a desert. Among species and across herb, tree and shrub growth forms there were significant enhancements in CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation (<em>A</em>) by +40±5% in elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> (49.5-57.1 Pa), although there were also significant reductions in photosynthetic capacity in elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> in some species. Photosynthesis at a common <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> (<em>A</em><sub>a</sub>) was significantly reduced in five species growing under elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub>, while leaf carboxylation capacity (<em>V</em><sub>cmax</sub>) was significantly reduced by elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> in seven species (change of -;19±3% among these species) across different growth forms and FACE sites. Adjustments in <em>V</em><sub>cmax</sub> with elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> were associated with changes in leaf N among species, and occurred in species with the highest leaf N. Elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> treatment did not affect the mass-based relationships between <em>A</em> or <em>V</em><sub>cmax</sub> and N, which differed among herbs, trees and shrubs. Thus, effects of elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> on leaf C assimilation and carboxylation capacity occurred largely through changes in leaf N, rather than through elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> effects on the relationships themselves. Maintenance of leaf carboxylation capacity among species in elevated <em>pC</em><sub>a</sub> at these sites depends on maintenance of canopy N stocks, with leaf N depletion associated with photosynthetic capacity adjustments. Since CO<sub>2</sub> responses can only be measured experimentally on a small number of species, understanding elevated CO<sub>2</sub> effects on canopy <em>N</em><sub>m</sub> and <em>N</em><sub>a</sub> will greatly contribute to an ability to model responses of leaf photosynthesis to atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> in different species and plant growth forms.