Soil respiration in broad-leaved and Korean pine forest ecosystems, Changbai mountain, ChinaThe emission of carbon from soils to the atmosphere occurs primarily in the form Of CO2 as the result of soil respiration. Increased storage of carbon in soil could help offset further anthropogenic emissions of CO2, whereas a release from soil could significantly exacerbate the increase of atmospheric CO2 and reinforce the greenhouse-warming effect. Because of the enormous carbon storage in soils, even a small change in soil respiration will be equal to or even exceed the annual CO2 input into the atmosphere from land use changes or burning of mineral fuels. Thus, changes in soil respiration can have a significant positive or negative impact on atmospheric CO2 concentrations and therefore affect climate change. Controlling soil respiration potentially can abate increases in atmospheric CO2 concentrations. To understand the soil respiration dynamics of the broadleaved and Korean pine forests at Changbai Mountain, and to provide a scientific basis for quantitatively assessing carbon source/sink relationships, soil respiration in broad-leaved and Korean pine forests at Changbai Mountain was measured using a static closed chamber method. The results indicated that the diurnal dynamics of soil respiration presented a single-peaked curve with the maximum occurring around 18: 00. The seasonal dynamics of soil respiration also showed a single-peaked curve with the maximum occurring in July during the growing season. The mean soil respiration rates during the growing season were 0. 22 gC . m(-2) . h(-1) in June, 0.32 gC . m(-2) . h(-1) in July, 0. 23 gC . m(-2) . h(-1) in August, and 0. 13 gC . m(-2) . h(-1) in September. Increasing temperatures would accelerate the soil respiration rate. Compared to air temperatures, soil temperatures more precisely reflect the dynamics of soil respiration. More soil water in a certain range would improve soil respiration rates, but excessive water in soil would restrain soil respiration rates and decrease CO2 emission rates from the broad-leaved and Korean pine forests.