Primitive nest architecture and small monogynous colonies in basal Attini inhabiting sandy beaches of southern BrazilThe species Mycetophylax conformis, M. simplex and Cyphomyrmex morschi, all belonging to the basal Attini, occur exclusively on beaches along the Atlantic shores of South America. In Brazil C. morschi colonies were found sympatrically with the two Mycetophylax species which, however, had no overlap in their geographic distribution. We recorded species‚Äspecific nesting site preferences resulting in a zonal colonization of dune and restinga areas, with distinct preferences in microhabitat choice. After excavating subterraneous nests, we were able to describe details of nest architecture, especially with regard to the number and position of the fungus chambers. The nest structure is similar in all species, but the colony size differed with the highest number of workers in M. simplex. All nests were headed by a single mated queen. First attempts were undertaken to maintain colonies under laboratory conditions. Resumo As esp√©cies Mycetophylax conformis, M. simplex e Cyphomyrmex morschi fazem parte do grupo dos Attini basais e ocorrem exclusivamente em praias do Atl√¢ntico na Am√©rica do Sul. No Brasil C. morschi ocorre simpatricamente com as esp√©cies de Mycetophylax, mas as duas esp√©cies de Mycetophylax n√£o tem uma sobreposi√ß√£o na sua distribui√ß√£o geogr√°fica. Tamb√©m detectamos prefer√™ncias espec√≠ficas na escolha da √°rea da nidifica√ß√£o o que resulta em uma coloniza√ß√£o zonal das dunas e restingas com prefer√™ncias distintas na escolha do microhabitat. Com escava√ß√µes cuidadosas de um n√∫mero representativo de ninhos obtivemos detalhes sobre a arquitetura, em especial o n√∫mero e posi√ß√£o das c√¢maras de fungo. A estrutura subterr√¢nea dos ninhos √© similar nas esp√©cies estudadas mas o tamanho da popula√ß√£o difere entre as esp√©cies com o maior n√∫mero de oper√°rias em M. simplex. Todas as col√¥nias tem uma rainha que copulou apenas uma √∫nica vez. Primeiras tentativas de manuten√ß√£o de col√¥nias no laborat√≥rio foram feitas.