Field Studies and Modeling Exploring Mean and Maximum Water Age Association to Water Quality in a Drinking Water Distribution NetworkAbstractThis paper presents the findings of an investigation into predicted/modeled water age and the associated quality characteristics within a UK drinking water distribution network to determine if there is a discernable link. The hydraulic and water quality software Aquis was used to identify water volumes of different ages, generated by localized demand patterns in pipes that are in close proximity to one another. The pipe network studied was small spatially, of a single material, and had a consistent demand attributable to serving predominately light industry, but with interesting hydraulic patterns involving loops and mixing of water volumes, and some long retention times. Field work was undertaken to obtain water quality samples from five network locations identified as containing a broad range of calculated water age. The samples were analyzed for standard regulated parameters by a UK Accreditation Service (UKAS) [formerly known as the National Measurement Accreditation Service (NAMAS)] accredited water laboratory in line with UK water industry standard quality assurance practice. The water sample analytical results were examined to test how a number of physical, chemical, and bacteriological parameters related to the calculated water age at each sample point. Heterotrophic plate counts were used as the indicator of general bacteriological water quality. A limited association between the calculated water mean age and quality parameters was observed. Further investigations, taking into account mixing of different aged water volumes and the maximum age contributions to the mean age at each sample location, produced some association. The work demonstrated that mean age is not a sufficient guide to general water quality in this small network area. Mixing effects, and maximum age volume contributions, need to be taken into account if a more comprehensive understanding of water quality is to be obtained.