The effect of biocrusts on evaporation from sand dunes in the Negev DesertDictating the length of time during which water is available, evaporation plays a cardinal role in ecosystem ecology and structure. This is especially so in arid and semi arid zones, where precipitation is highly limited. Covering the surface with a distinct 1–10 cm thick layer, biocrusts (called also biological soil crusts or microbiotic crusts) may affect the evaporation rate and hence the water loss of the underlying parent material. Owing to their wide occurrence in arid and semi arid regions, examination of their impact upon the evaporation rate of the underlying soil is of special importance.  The evaporation of water from sand covered by four types of cyanobacterial crusts and one moss-dominated crust in the Negev Desert was examined along with bare sand. The crusts and sand were subjected to wetting by rain and sprinkling (in Petri dishes and within 25 cm diameter plots), and the crust and subcrust temperatures and moisture content were measured. In addition the albedo of the crusts was also measured. Whereas thick and high-biomass crusts tended to retain higher amounts of water in the Petri dishes, they were found to increase subsurface temperatures (by up to 3.9 °C at 5 cm depth) under field conditions, subsequently decreasing the 0–10 cm moisture content. Moisture content at the crusted plots was significantly lower than that of non-crusted plot, with crusted plots having an evaporation rate of 1.24–1.57 (with average of 1.38) times higher than the bare sand. These findings were supported by field measurements under natural rain precipitation. In both cases, the field data under sprinkling and rain precipitation showed that the non-crusted surfaces retained their available moisture at the upper 10 cm of the soil profile for 5–7 days longer than that of the crusted surfaces. The findings may explain contradictory data published in the literature regarding field and lab experiments, and may point to the negative effect that biocrusts may have upon the soil water budget and hence on water availability for higher plants.