TRANSPIRATION AND HYDRAULIC STRATEGIES IN A PIÑON–JUNIPER WOODLAND.Anthropogenic climate change is likely to alter the patterns of moisture availability globally. The consequences of these changes on species distributions and ecosystem function are largely unknown, but possibly predictable based on key ecophysiological differences among currently coexisting species. In this study, we examined the environmental and biological controls on transpiration from a piñon–juniper (<em>Pinus edulis</em>–<em>Juniperus osteosperma</em>) woodland in southern Utah, USA. The potential for climate-change-associated shifts in moisture inputs could play a critical role in influencing the relative vulnerabilities of piñons and junipers to drought and affecting management decisions regarding the persistence of this dominant landscape type in the Intermountain West. We aimed to assess the sensitivity of this woodland to seasonal variations in moisture and to mechanistically explain the hydraulic strategies of <em>P. edulis</em> and <em>J. osteosperma</em> through the use of a hydraulic transport model. Transpiration from the woodland was highly sensitive to variations in seasonal moisture inputs. There were two distinct seasonal pulses of transpiration: a reliable spring pulse supplied by winter-derived precipitation, and a highly variable summer pulse supplied by monsoonal precipitation. Transpiration of <em>P. edulis</em> and <em>J. osteosperma</em> was well predicted by a mechanistic hydraulic transport model (<em>R</em><sup>2</sup> = 0.83 and 0.92, respectively). Our hydraulic model indicated that isohydric regulation of water potential in <em>P. edulis</em> minimized xylem cavitation during drought, which facilitated drought recovery (94% of pre-drought water uptake) but came at the cost of cessation of gas exchange for potentially extended periods. In contrast, the anisohydric <em>J. osteosperma</em> was able to maintain gas exchange at lower water potentials than <em>P. edulis</em> but experienced greater cavitation over the drought and showed a lesser degree of post-drought recovery (55% of pre-drought uptake). As a result, these species should be differentially affected by shifts in the frequency, duration, and intensity of drought. Our results highlight the sensitivity of this woodland type to potential climate-change-associated shifts in seasonal moisture patterns and demonstrate the utility of mechanistic hydraulic models in explaining differential responses of coexisting species to drought.