A Biodiversity Assessment of Bats (Chiroptera) in a Tropical Lowland Rainforest of Central Amazonia, Including Methodological and Conservation ConsiderationsIn our study of bat diversity in the Amazon Basin, we captured bats in undisturbed continuous forest and in forest fragments at the Biological Dynamics of Forest Fragments Project (BDFFP) near Manaus, Brazil, from January 1996 until July 1999. We recorded 72 species of bats in a sample of more than 7700 individuals caught during 29,900 mistnet hours in terra-firme forest. Species accumulation curves and mathematical estimates of species numbers based on the number of species captured with standardized methodology suggest that we sampled about 95% of the entire expected bat fauna of the area, including aerial insectivorous bats. Our results are similar to those of other mistnetting inventories of Amazonian bat assemblages in terms of species composition and number of species per bat family. Some species considered widespread in Central Amazonia and expected at our study site were not recorded. We interpret their absence as effects of sampling bias and of local ecological conditions. We know from acoustic monitoring (i.e., identification of bats by their echolocation calls) that our mistnet data are incomplete for aerial insectivorous species. We conclude that the development of comprehensive inventories of key vertebrate taxa such as bats derived from a combination of several standardized sampling procedures is essential to develop meaningful, conservation-oriented plans for land-use and management of protected areas. Resumo Em nosso estudo sobre diversidade de morcegos na Bacia Amazônica, nós capturamos morcegos em floresta contínua não perturbada e em fragmentos florestais no Projeto Dinâmica Biológica de Fragmentos Florestais (PDBFF), próximo à Manaus, Brazil, de Janeiro de 1996 até Julho de 1999. Nós registramos 72 espécies de morcegos capturando cerca de 7700 indivíduos em 29,900 horas de captura em áreas de terra-firme. As curvas de acumulação e modelos matemáticos baseados no número de espécies capturadas com metodologia estandartizada indicam que nós registramos cerca de 95% da fauna esperada para a área, incluindo as capturas de espécies de morcegos aéreos insetívoros. Nossos resultados são equivalentes a outros inventários baseados em redes de captura de morcegos na Amazônia, em termos de composição de espécies e em número de espécies para cada família de morcegos. Algumas espécies consideradas como uniformemente distribuídas na região Amazônica e que deveriam também ocorrer na nossa área de estudo não foram coletadas. Nós interpretamos a ausência de espécies esperadas como um efeito de limitações na metodologia e devido a condições ecológicas locais. Sabemos por monitoramento acústico (identificação de morcegos através dos sinais de ecolocação), que nossos dados de redes de captura estão incompletos para morcegos insetívoros aéreos. Nós concluímos que o desenvolvimento de inventários de grupos chave, como morcegos, com a combinação de vários métodos de amostragem estandardizados é essencial para o desenvolvimento de planos conservationistas significativos no uso da terra e no controle de áreas protegidas.