Methyl bromide emissions to the atmosphere from temperate woodland ecosystems.The environmental importance of methyl bromide (CH<sub>3</sub>Br) arises from its contribution to stratospheric ozone loss processes and, as a consequence, its emissions from anthropogenic sources are subject to the Montreal Protocol. A better understanding of the natural budget of CH<sub>3</sub>Br is required for assessing the benefit of anthropogenic emission reductions and for understanding any potential effects of environmental change on global CH<sub>3</sub>Br concentrations. Measurements of CH<sub>3</sub>Br flux in temperate woodland ecosystems, in particular, are very sparse, yet these cover a large fraction of terrestrial land surface. Results presented here from 18 months of field measurements of CH<sub>3</sub>Br fluxes in four static flux chambers in a woodland in Scotland and from enclosures of rotting wood and deciduous and coniferous leaf litter suggest net emissions from temperate woodlands. Net CH<sub>3</sub>Br fluxes in the woodland varied between the chambers, fluctuating between net uptake and net emissions (-;73 to 279 ng m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup> across 161 individual measurements), and with no strong seasonality, but with time-averaged net emission overall [27±57 (1 SD)] ng m<sup>-;2</sup> h<sup>-;1</sup>]. This work demonstrates that scale-up needs to be based on sufficient individual measurements to provide a reasonably constrained estimate of the long-term mean. Mean (±1 SD) net CH<sub>3</sub>Br emissions from deciduous and coniferous leaf litter were 43 (±33) ng kg<sup>-;1</sup> (dry weight) h<sup>-;1</sup> and 80 (±37) ng kg<sup>-;1</sup> (dry weight) h<sup>-;1</sup>, respectively, and &sim;1-2 ng kg<sup>-;1</sup> (fresh weight) h<sup>-;1</sup> from rotting woody litter. Despite the intrinsic variability, data obtained here consistently point to the conclusion that the temperate forest soil/litter ecosystem is a net source of CH<sub>3</sub>Br to the atmosphere.