Belowground carbon pools and processes in different age stands of Douglas-firForest floor material and soil organic matter may act as both a source and a sink in global CO2 cycles. Thus, the ecosystem processes controlling these pools are central to understanding the transfers of carbon (C) between the atmosphere and terrestrial systems. To examine these ecosystem processes, the effect of stand age on temporal carbon source-sink relationships was examined in 20-year-old, 40-year-old and old-growth stands of Douglas-fir (Pseudotsuga menziesii (Mirb.) Franco) in the Cascade Mountains of south-central Washington State. Belowground C and nitrogen (N) storage and soil respiration were measured. In addition, nylon mesh bags containing homogenized soils from each site were buried at the respective sites to quantify root ingrowth and potential C sequestration and loss. The sites supporting the 20- and 40-year-old stands had soil C stores reflecting the C contributions from logging residue, coarse woody debris and stumps left after harvest. Because the N-fixer red alder (Alnus rubra Bong.) comprised 33% of the 40-year-old stand, this site had significantly greater concentrations and pools of N in the forest floor than sites without red alder. This N-rich site had consistently lower soil CO2 efflux rates during the growing season than the sites supporting the 20-year-old and old-growth stands. Estimated annual soil C efflux was 1367, 883 and 1194 g m(-2) for the sites supporting the 20-, 40- and old-growth stands, respectively. These values are higher than previously reported values. Root ingrowth was significantly less in the 40-year-old stand than in the 20-year-old stand, and both young stands showed markedly less fine root growth than the old-growth stand. At the sites supporting the young stands, C and N were lost from the soil bags, whereas there was an increase in C and N in the soil bags at the site supporting the old-growth stand. The fine root growth and soil respiration data support the hypothesis that belowground C allocation decreases with increasing fertility. Quantification of the source-sink relationship of soil C at the three stands based on litterfall, relative root ingrowth and soil respiration measurements was compromised because of significant CO2 flux from decaying organic matter in the young stands.