Prevalence of monodominant vigorous tree populations in the tropics: herbivory pressure on Tabebuia species in very different habitats.<ol><li>We have studied the reproductive performance, early establishment and insect herbivory in two <em>Tabebuia</em> species found in contrasting distant habitats. <em>Tabebuia ochracea</em> and <em>T. aurea</em> are sympatric in the cerrado (Brazilian savanna), whereas <em>T. aurea</em> also colonizes floodplains in the wetlands of the 'Pantanal Matogrossense' as large monodominant stands, but is sparsely distributed in the cerrado.</li><li>We test the hypothesis that <em>T. aurea</em> has a more vigorous genotype in the Pantanal than in the cerrado, which may be due to a lower negative selection caused by insect herbivory, positive selection for better soil conditions and an increased growth in the face of stochastic flooding. In addition, we predict that <em>T. ochracea</em> is better adapted to withstand higher herbivory rates than <em>T. aurea</em>, and is thus more successful in the cerrado.</li><li>Kruskal-Wallis analysis and Wilcoxon paired-sample tests were used to compare adult tree reproductive traits. A reciprocal transplant experiment, combined with a glasshouse experiment, was used to investigate herbivory on half-sib seed families found in each habitat.</li><li>Over a 2-year period, <em>T. ochracea</em> had the higher investment in flower and seed production, which compensated for lower germination rates. However, in the Pantanal, <em>T. aurea</em> had the greatest conversion of flowers to fruit.</li><li>Fewer seeds of <em>T. aurea</em> survived and germinated in the cerrado than in the Pantanal, but seedlings from the Pantanal grew faster than those from the cerrado. The growth rate of <em>T. ochracea</em> was approximately four times lower than that of <em>T. aurea</em>.</li><li>Herbivory on seedlings was lower in the Pantanal than in the cerrado. Although seedlings of <em>T. aurea</em> from the Pantanal suffered the highest rates of herbivory in the cerrado, they survived equally to seedling genotypes from the cerrado. <em>Tabebuia aurea</em> had a higher mortality in both the cerrado and under controlled environmental conditions.</li><li>Faster growth rates may evolve when favourable abiotic conditions prevail. Although herbivores may promote habitat specialization by restricting colonization of poor soil environments by fast-growing species, herbivory pressure may select for tree genotypes with conservative growth rates in newly colonized habitats with poor soil conditions and intense herbivory.</li></ol>