Geoffroy's cats at the northern limit of their range: activity patterns and density estimates from camera trapping in Bolivian dry forestsWe used camera traps to survey Geoffroy's cats, Oncifelis geoffroyi, at six dry forest sites in Bolivia. Cumulative activity patterns across all sites are principally nocturnal though the species is active by day in both summer and winter. At two sites the number of captures and recaptures was sufficient to estimate abundance using the software Capture, and in turn a population density of 9‚Äì40 per 100¬†km2 for the two sites. Geoffroy's cats are present in all dry forest types surveyed: Chaco savannas, Chaco dry forest, Chaco transitional forest, Chaco‚ÄChiquitano transitional forest, Chaco‚ÄCerrado transitional forest and Chiquitano dry forest. They are most abundant at the driest site, the only one with grassland formations and where ocelots are absent. Camera trapping records tend to be more numerous in the dry season, suggesting seasonal changes in behavior and habitat use. Resumen Empleamos trampas‚Äc√°mara para muestrear Oncifelis geoffroyi en seis sitios ubicados en bosques secos de Bolivia. El patr√≥n de actividad en todos los sitios es principalmente nocturno, pero la especie puede estar activa de d√≠a en verano como en invierno. En dos sitios tuvimos suficiente capturas y recapturas para estimar abundancia usando el programa Capture, y luego una densidad poblacional de 9‚Äì40/100¬†km2 para los dos sitios. Oncifelis geoffroyi est√° presente en todas los tipos de bosques secos muestreados: sabanas chaque√±as, bosque seco chaque√±o, bosque transicional chaque√±o, bosque transicional Chaco‚ÄChiquitano, bosque transitional Chaco‚ÄCerrado, y bosque seco Chiquitano. Es m√°s abundante en el sitio con menor precipitaci√≥n, el √∫nico sitio con formaciones de pampas y donde es ausente Leopardus pardalis. Se tiene m√°s registros con trampas‚Äc√°mara en la √©poca seca, sugiriendo cambios estacionales en comportamiento y uso de h√°bitat.