Assessment of soil losses by ephemeral gully erosion using high-altitude (stereo) aerial photographsThe objective of this study is to explore in a critical way the potential of high-altitude (stereo) aerial photographs for the assessment of ephemeral gully erosion rates. On 28 May 1995, an intensive rainfall event (30 mm h−1 during 30 min, return period = 3 years) occurred in central Belgium. Ephemeral gullies formed within an area of 218 ha (study area 1) were mapped and measured both in the field and by high-altitude aerial photos taken at the same time. Comparison of these two methods shows that if only one of the two surveying techniques had been used, only 75 per cent of the total ephemeral gully length would have been detected, so that the combination of aerial and field data leads, in fact, to the best possible determination of total gully length within the selected area. A correction factor (C) is proposed, so that the results of an ephemeral gully erosion survey based on high-altitude (stereo) aerial photos can be adjusted for the undetected gullies.  Next, a sequential series of high-altitude stereo aerial photographs, taken in six different years, was analysed in order to determine ephemeral gully erosion rates in three selected study areas (study areas 2, 3 and 4). Selection criteria were chosen so that these three areas were similar to study area 1 and representative for the cultivated areas in central Belgium where intense soil erosion regularly occurs. Ephemeral gullies were mapped and their total length was measured from the aerial photos. Using a mean gully cross-section of 0·2635 m2 (determined in study area 1), the average eroded volume is 1·89 m3 ha−1 in six months for study area 1, 0·86 m3 ha−1 in six months for area 2, 1·44 m3 ha−1 in six months for area 3, and 2·37 m3 ha−1 in six months for area 4. According to the correction factor (C), these mean ephemeral gully erosion volumes have to be increased by 44 per cent. The ephemeral gully erosion rates based on high-altitude stereo aerial photos, correspond well with the results of other surveys carried out in the Belgian loess belt.