Temporal and spatial dynamics of long-distance Conyza canadensis seed dispersal.<ol><li>Glyphosate-resistant <em>Conyza canadensis</em> populations now infest more than 44 000 ha of arable land in eastern USA, only 5 years after the first resistant population was reported. Seed dispersal, the expansive use of glyphosate and the lack of tillage are all factors contributing to this high invasion speed.</li><li>Seed collected from deliberately established <em>C. canadensis</em> source populations were found at the furthest seed traps in our empirical studies, providing one of the most complete dispersal kernels for studying long-distance dispersal. The results indicate that seed regularly disperses at least 500 m from source populations. While a relatively small number of seeds moves long distances, 99% of the seed was found within 100 m of the source.</li><li>Empirical and mechanistic models were fitted to the data to predict the dispersal in the prevailing wind direction. Both models underestimated seed deposition beyond 200 m but the mechanistic model provided a better fit to the data (lower Akaike information criterion). A two-dimensional analysis examined the correlation between angular directions of wind and seed movement. All trials were anisotropic but only the cumulative wind and seed direction were significantly correlated (<em>P</em> &lt; 0·05).</li><li>The empirical model was used to explore the effect of increasing source strength, which would be expected as an infestation of glyphosate-resistant <em>C. canadensis</em> expands on a producer's farm. At infestation levels consistent with a heavy infestation in a 5-ha field, seed dispersed further than 1·5 km, easily affecting 10s to 100s of surrounding farms.</li><li><em>Synthesis and applications</em>. Emigration of <em>C. canadensis</em> seed, from a source farm to adjacent farms, means that population dynamics and weed management are dependent on both intra- and interfield dispersal phenomena. Wind-dispersed plants challenge the common practice of single field management as a viable management option for herbicide-resistant weeds. Farms coupled by seed dispersal require proactive management practices by every producer to prevent and minimize the development of glyphosate-resistant infestations of undesirable and alien plants.</li></ol>