Mapping tree and shrub leaf area indices in an ombrotrophic peatland through multiple endmember spectral unmixingLeaf area index (LAI) is an important parameter used by most process-oriented ecosystem models. LAI of forest ecosystems has routinely been mapped using spectral vegetation indices (SVI) derived from remote sensing imagery. The application of SVI-based approaches to map LAI in peatlands presents a challenge, mainly due to peatlands characteristic multi-layer canopy comprising shrubs and open, discontinuous tree canopies underlain by a continuous ground cover of different moss species, which reduces the greenness contrast between the canopy and the background.Our goal is to develop a methodology to map tree and shrub LAI in peatlands and similar ecosystems based on multiple endmember spectral mixture analysis (MESMA). This new mapping method is validated using LAI field measurements from a precipitation-fed (ombrotrophic) peatland near Ottawa, Ontario, Canada. We demonstrate first that three commonly applied SVI are not suitable for tree and shrub LAI mapping in ombrotrophic peatlands. Secondly, we demonstrate for a three-endmember model the limitations of traditional linear spectral mixture analysis (SMA) due to the unique and widely varying spectral characteristics of Sphagnum mosses, which are significantly different from vascular plants. Next, by using a geometric-optical radiative transfer model, we determine the nature of the equation describing the empirical relationship between shadow fraction and tree LAI using nonlinear ordinary least square (OLS) regression. We then apply this equation to describe the empirical relationships between shadow and shrub fractions obtained from mixture decomposition with SMA and MESMA, respectively, and tree and shrub LAI, respectively. Less accurate fractions obtained from SMA result in weaker relationships between shadow fraction and tree LAI (R2=0.61) and shrub fraction and shrub LAI (R2=0.49) compared to the same relationships based on fractions obtained from MESMA with R2=0.75 and R2=0.68, respectively. Cross-validation of tree LAI (R2=0.74; RMSE=0.48) and shrub LAI (R2=0.68; RMSE=0.42) maps using fractions from MESMA shows the suitability of this approach for mapping tree and shrub LAI in ombrotrophic peatlands. The ability to account for a spectrally varying, unique Sphagnum moss ground cover during mixture decomposition and a two layer canopy is particularly important.