Consolidated horizons in soils formed in aeolian deposits in southland, New ZealandThe morphology of consolidated horizons in three soil series formed in aeolian parent material is described. The soils are classified as Otama series (Psammentic Hapludalf), formed in near-source aeolian deposits, Crookston series (Aquic Dystrochrept) at intermediate sites, and Waikoikoi series (Typic and Aquic Fragiochrepts) at distal sites. All three soils have a consolidated horizon with clay illuviation features, bulk density of 1.6 t/m3 or more, and total porosity 42% or less. The soils of the Waikoikoi series have a fragipan as defined in Soil Taxonomy. Macro- and micromorphological evidence suggests that the rate of accumulation of aeolian parent materials of the soils has governed the degree of disruption of consolidated horizons. In soils of the Otama series two consolidated horizons have formed but pores and clay skins in the deeper horizon have escaped significant disruption. We suggest that this is because later aeolian deposits at this near-source accumulation site have provided a protective layer. In soils of the Waikoikoi series, by contrast, physical disruption of the soil fabric during accumulation of the aeolian parent material has been much greater, probably because rates of accumulation were slower. Consequently, pores are discontinuous and limit water and root penetration, and the consolidated horizon meets fragipan criteria. Soils of the Crookston series have less evidence of disruption of the consolidated horizon and have properties intermediate between Otama and Waikoikoi series. Phosphorus chemistry supports the conclusion that Waikoikoi and Crookston consolidated horizons were exposed to weathering for longer than the deeper consolidated horizon of Otama series. The study indicates that fragipans in the soils studied are formed by disruption of the fabric of a consolidated horizon. Such distruption is most likely to occur at distal sites where aeolian accession rates have been slow, and the physical and biogenic fabric of the consolidated horizon has not been insulated from disruptive effects by later accumulation of aeolian deposits.