Systematics of the parasitic wasp genus Oxyscelio Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), Part I: Indo-Malayan and Palearctic faunaAbstract The Indo-Malayan and Palearctic species of Oxyscelio (Hymenoptera: Platygastridae s.l.) are revised. A total of 90 species are recognized as valid, 19 of which are redescribed - Oxyscelio acutiventris (Kieffer), Oxyscelio brevinervis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio carinatus (Kieffer), Oxyscelio ceylonensis (Dodd), Oxyscelio consobrinus (Kieffer), Oxyscelio crassicornis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio cupularis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio dorsalis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio excavatus (Kieffer), Oxyscelio flavipennis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio florus Kononova, Oxyscelio foveatus Kieffer, Oxyscelio kiefferi Dodd, Oxyscelio magnus (Kieffer), Oxyscelio marginalis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio naraws Kozlov & Lê, Oxyscelio perpensus Kononova, Oxyscelio rugosus (Kieffer) and Oxyscelio spinosiceps (Kieffer), and 71 which are described as new - Oxyscelio aclavae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio amrichae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio anguli Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio angustifrons Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio angustinubbin Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio arcus Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio arvi Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio asperi Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio aureamediocritas Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio bipunctuum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio brevidentis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio caesitas Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio capilli Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio capitis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio cavinetrion Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio chimaerae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio codae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio convergens Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio cordis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio crateris Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio crebritas Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio crustum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio cuculli Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio cyrtomesos Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio dasymesos Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio dasynoton Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio dermatoglyphes Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio doumao Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio fistulae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio flabellae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio flaviventris Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio fodiens Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio fossarum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio fossularum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio genae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio granorum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio granuli Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio greenacus Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio halmaherae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio intermedietas Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio jaune Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio jugi Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio kramatos Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio labis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio lacunae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio latinubbin Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio latitudinis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio limae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio longiventris Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio mesiodentis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio mollitia Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio nasolabii Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio nodorum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio noduli Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio nubbin Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio obsidiani Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio ogive Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio operimenti Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio peludo Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio planocarinae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio praecipitis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio reflectens Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio regionis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio sinuum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio spinae Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio striarum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio tecti Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio unguis Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio vadorum Burks, sp. n., Oxyscelio vittae Burks, sp. n. and Oxyscelio zeuctomesos. Neotypes are designated for nine species, including the type species O. foveatus Kieffer, Oxyscelio brevinervis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio bifurcatus (Kieffer), Oxyscelio frontalis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio crassicornis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio cupularis (Kieffer), Oxyscelio foveatus Kieffer, Oxyscelio kiefferi Dodd, Oxyscelio magnus (Kieffer) and Oxyscelio marginalis (Kieffer). Oxyscelio bifurcatus (Kieffer) syn. n. and Oxyscelio frontalis (Kieffer) syn. n. are synonymized under Oxyscelio consobrinus (Kieffer). The fauna is divided into 13 species groups, with six species unplaced to a group. A phylogenetic analysis employing 73 morphological characters did not find most of these groups to be monophyletic, but they are retained to aid in specimen identification. Potential biogeographical patterns are discussed, including regional variation in surface sculpture and a morphological link between Sri Lankan and Australian species.